<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.163.2291</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Discovery of the genus 
                    <italic>Meggoleus</italic> Townes, 1971 (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Tersilochinae) in Peru, with the description of two new species</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Alvarado</surname>
                        <given-names>Mabel</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:969AA574-A398-4087-BCF9-98CB8ABDC91F</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Division of Entomology, Natural History Museum, and Department of Ecology &amp; Evolutionary Biology, 1501 Crestline Drive – Suite 140, University of Kansas, Lawrence, Kansas, 66045, USA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Departamento de Entomología, Museo de Historia Natural, Av. Arenales 1256 Jesús María, Lima 14, Perú
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Mabel Alvarado (<email xlink:type="simple">malvarado@ku.edu</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: G. Broad</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>9</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>163</issue>
            <fpage>83</fpage>
            <lpage>90</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>27</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>16</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Mabel Alvarado</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:A7F0DD64-A7CC-4652-A68F-E428C2D3ADED</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Townes, 1971 (<tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Tersilochinae</tp:taxon-name>) currently comprises two species, one from Brazil and one from Gabon. The genus is recorded from Peru for the first time, with a range extension of the type species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus spirator</tp:taxon-name></italic> Townes, 1971, and the discovery of two new species – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus fuscatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus pampahermosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n</bold>. A key to the world’s species is provided.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name></kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>Peru</kwd>
                <kwd>Neotropical region</kwd>
                <kwd>South America</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Tersilochinae</tp:taxon-name> is a cosmopolitan ichneumonid subfamily that is most species-rich in the Holarctic region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Yu et al. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Khalaim 2007</xref>). Only the Palaearctic fauna has been studied moderately well, the majority of non-Palaearctic species are still undescribed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Khalaim and Sheng 2009</xref>). The Neotropical fauna of <tp:taxon-name>Tersilochinae</tp:taxon-name> is poorly known <!--PageBreak-->and includes only four genera, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allophrys</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Barycnemis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Stethantyx</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and with 13 described species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Yu et al. 2005</xref>). This is the first record of <tp:taxon-name>Tersilochinae</tp:taxon-name> for Peru.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Townes, 1971 is a small, tropical genus known until now from only two species. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus spirator</tp:taxon-name></italic> Townes, 1971, the type species, was described from Curitiba, Southern Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Townes 1971</xref>), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus townesi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khalaim, 2007 is known only from Gabon in equatorial Africa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Khalaim 2007</xref>). The genus was also recorded from Costa Rica but not assigned to species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Gauld 1991</xref>).</p>
            <p>The majority of <tp:taxon-name>Tersilochinae</tp:taxon-name> are koinobiont endoparasitoids of beetle larvae, mainly <tp:taxon-name>Curculionidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomelidae</tp:taxon-name>, and <tp:taxon-name>Nitidulidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Khalaim 2011</xref>), but nothing is known of the biology of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <p>The aim of this paper is to describe two new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Peru and document a range extension for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus spirator</tp:taxon-name></italic> to this country. A key to the world’s species is also provided.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods">
            <title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>This work is based on material of the San Marcos University Natural History Museum, Peru (MUSM). A paratype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus spirator</tp:taxon-name></italic> deposited in the American Entomological Institute, Gainesville, Florida (AEIC) was examined. Specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus townesi</tp:taxon-name></italic> were not examined since the original description was sufficient; this species has a distinct morphology with the epicnemial carina reaching the midline of the anterior margin of the mesopleuron and the first metasomal segment without glymmae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Khalaim 2007</xref>). I present below a key to females of the four species; males were not included because only the male of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus townesi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known.</p>
            <p>Morphological terminology and the format for descriptions generally follow those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Gauld (1991)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Khalaim (2011)</xref>. Photomicrographs were prepared using a Nikon D1x digital camera attached to an Infinity K-2 long-distance microscopic lens. Specimens studied herein are deposited in San Marcos Natural History Museum, Peru (MUSM) and the Division of Entomology, University of Kansas Natural History Museum (SEMC).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics">
            <title>Systematics</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Meggoleus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Townes, 1971</tp:taxon-authority>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>The genus is characterized by the labium prolonged into a tongue that is about 0.33 as long as the height of head; antenna with 15 flagellomeres; foveate groove on mesopleuron almost straight, inclined 45° from horizontal; propodeum moderately long with a narrow median longitudinal carina or basal keel between the base of the propodeum and transverse carina; fore wing vein 2<italic>m-cu</italic> postfurcal, pretarsal claws<!--PageBreak--> long, not pectinate; thyridial depression much longer than wide. The Afrotropical species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus townesi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, differs from the Neotropical species in that the epicnemial carina reaches the anterior margin of the mesopleuron near its midlength (in Neotropical species the epicnemial carina reaches dorsally almost to the subtegular ridge) and the first tergite lacks a glymma in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus townesi</tp:taxon-name></italic> but is present in all known Neotropical species. However, the most striking feature of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the exceptionally large (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Townes 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Khalaim 2007</xref>) and rounded propodeal spiracle a character not known among other ichneumonids.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">fuscatus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3CFA76C6-DD61-45AA-851D-A81A5E9D65F4</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Meggoleus_fuscatus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Alvarado</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">6</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype">
                    <title>Holotype.</title>
                    <p>♀ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>), PERU: JU [Junín], Chanchamayo, S.N. Pampa Hermosa, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">10°59'52.7&quot;S, 75°25'34.3&quot;W</named-content>, 1757 m. 23–31.v.2011, Malaise [trap]. M. Alvarado (MUSM).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes">
                    <title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p>4♀♀, same data as holotype (MUSM); 2♀♀, same data as holotype, but Pan trap (SEMC); 1♀, same locality and collector as holotype, but <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">75°25'35.9&quot;W, 10°59'51.8&quot;S</named-content>, 1940 m, 23–31.v.2011, Pan trap. M. Alvarado (MUSM); 1♀, same locality and collector as holotype, but <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">10°59'48.9&quot;S, 75°25'35.3&quot;W</named-content>, 1593 m, 23–31.v.2011, Pan trap (MUSM).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comparison">
                    <title>Comparison.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus fuscatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from other Peruvian species by the long foveate groove almost reaching the epicnemial carina anteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>) and darker body coloration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">6</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>♀: Body length 3.9 mm (without ovipositor); fore wing length 3.6 mm. Lateral ocellus separated from eye by ca. 2.5–2.7× ocellar diameter. Flagellum of antenna filiform, short, with 15 flagellomeres; flagellomeres elongate, first flagellomere 3–4x as long as centrally broad; penultimate flagellomere 1.6–1.7× as long as centrally broad; all flagellomeres covered by short hairs, in addition to apical long bristles. Malar space as long as basal mandibular width. Clypeus broad, usually smooth on lower part, granulate and punctate on upper part. Mandible punctate basally, upper tooth much longer than lower tooth. Face, frons, vertex and occiput finely granulate and usually finely punctate (punctures sometimes indistinct because of granulation). Temple finely and sparsely punctate, smooth between punctures; temporal orbits smooth without setae. Mesoscutum entirely granulate, indistinctly punctate; notaulus weak; mesopleuron almost smooth and punctate; epicnemial carina reaching to subalar prominence; foveate groove elongate, almost reaching to epicnemial carina, oblique, with some transverse wrinkles; metapleuron finely punctate. Propodeum with basal keel distinct, 0.75–1.0× as long as apical area; spiracle round and large, separated from pleural carina; apical area elongate, acute anteriorly, with apical longitudinal carinae reaching transverse carina anteriorly, alutaceous and coarsely punctate; dorsolateral areas usually <!--PageBreak-->smooth with fine, sparse punctures. Fore wing with vein 2<italic>m-cu</italic> unpigmented anteriorly. Tibial spurs weakly curved; pretarsal claws long, not pectinate. Metasoma with tergite I moderately slender, 3.9–4.3× as long as posteriorly broad, in dorsal view polished with a row of setae in lateral part of tergite, over lateromedian longitudinal carina, extending from base of segment to dorsad spiracle, and with some sparse setae on posterior area; tergite 2 smooth, 2.1–2.3× as long as basal broad; thyridial depression distinctly elongate, about 1.5 times as long as wide; tergites 3–6 similarly sculptured; spiracle of tergite 1 large, separation between spiracles at most 1.9–2.0× spiracle diameter (maximum diameter measured between external margins of carina round spiracle); ovipositor short, upcurved, with shallow dorsal depression near apex, without teeth.</p>
                    <p>Head black except palpi, clypeus, and mandible yellowish, and malar space, scape, and pedicel reddish. Mesosoma predominantly black, sometimes partly with reddish tinge, particularly on pronotum and mesopleuron; legs yellowish except dorsum of metafemur, mesotibia, metatibia, and meso- and metatarsomeres brown. Wing membranes hyaline and weakly infuscate; pterostigma dark brown. Metasoma with segment 1 and dorsum of tergites 2–4 dark brown; remainder of metasoma yellowish.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–3.</label>
                        <caption><p>Lateral habitus of Neotropical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. <bold>1</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus pampahermosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype female <bold>2</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus spirator</tp:taxon-name></italic> Townes, paratype female <bold>3</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus fuscatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype female.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-163-083-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific epithet is the Latin term <italic>fuscatus</italic>, meaning “darkened”, in reference to the darker body coloration of the species, compared to the other Neotropical species.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pampahermosensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:DA3BD80D-41E8-4710-85E6-82846B6DAEAB</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Meggoleus_pampahermosensis</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Alvarado</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">4, 8</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype">
                    <title>Holotype.</title>
                    <p>♀, PERU: JU [Junín], Chanchamayo, SN Pampa Hermosa, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">10°59'48.9&quot;S, 75°25'35.3&quot;W</named-content>, 1593 m, 23–31.v.2011, FIT [Flight Interception Trap], M. Alvarado (MUSM).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes">
                    <title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p>3♀♀, same data as holotype (MUSM); 1♀, same data as holotype, but Pan trap (SEMC); 1♀, same data as holotype, but light trap (SEMC); 1♀, same locality and collector as holotype, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">10°59'52.7&quot;S, 75°25'34.3&quot;W</named-content>, 1757 m, 23–31.v.2011, Pan trap (MUSM).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comparison">
                    <title>Comparison.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus pampahermosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> most closely resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus spirator</tp:taxon-name></italic> in that the foveate groove is short, and in general body coloration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">4</xref>). However, the new species differs in having the first metasomal segment with the spiracles smaller, more widely spaced, and in a more lateral position (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>♀: Body length 3.6 mm (without ovipositor); fore wing length 3.2 mm. Lateral ocellus separated from eye by ca. 1.6–1.8× ocellar diameter. Fagellum of antenna filiform, short, with 15 flagellomeres; flagellomeres elongate, first flagellomere 2.3–2.7× as long as centrally broad; penultimate flagellomere 1.3–1.4× as long as centrally broad; all flagellomeres covered by short hairs, in addition to apical long bristles. Malar space 0.7–0.8× as long as basal mandibular width. Clypeus broad, usually smooth on lower part, granulate and punctate on upper part. Mandible punctate basally, upper tooth much longer than lower tooth. Face, frons, vertex and occiput finely granulate and usually finely punctate (punctures sometimes indistinct because of granulation). Temple finely and sparsely punctate, smooth between puntures; temporal orbits smooth without setae. Mesoscutum entirely granulate, indistinctly punctate; notaulus weak; mesopleuron almost smooth and punctate; epicnemial carina reaching to subalar prominence; foveate groove short, oblique, scrobiculate; metapleuron finely punctate. Propodeum with basal keel distinct, 0.7–0.8× as long as apical area; spiracle round and large, separated from pleural carina; apical area elongate, acute anteriorly, with apical longitudinal carinae reaching transverse carina anteriorly, alutaceous and coarsely punctate; dorsolateral areas usually smooth with fine, sparse punctures. Fore wing with vein 2<italic>m-cu</italic> unpigmented anteriorly. Tibial spurs weakly curved; pretarsal claws long, not pectinate. Metasoma with tergite 1 moderately slender, 3.1–3.2× as long as posteriorly broad, in dorsal view polished with a row of setae in lateral part of tergite, over lateromedian longitudinal carina, extending from base of segment to dorsad spiracle, and with some sparse setae on posterior area; tergite 2 smooth, 1.6–1.8× as long as basal broad; thyridial depression distinctly elongate, about 1.5× as long as wide; tergites 3–6 similarly sculptured; spiracle of tergite 1 large, separation between spiracles at most 1.8–1.9× spiracle diameter (maximum diameter measured between external margins of carina around spiracle); ovipositor short, upcurved, with shallow dorsal depression near apex, without teeth.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->Head black except for palpi, clypeus, mandible, malar space, scape, and pedicel reddish. Mesosoma black except for pronotum, pleura, and sterna reddish; legs generally yellowish except base of pro- and mesotibiae, apex of metafemur, metatibia (with darker spots at base and apex), and metatarsus brown. Wing membranes generally hyaline and weakly infuscate; pterostigma dark brown. Metasoma with segment 1, dorsum of tergite 2, and basal parts of tergites 2–5 brown; remainder of metasoma yellowish.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 4–8.</label>
                        <caption><p>Details of Neotropical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. <bold>4</bold> Lateral view of mesosoma of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus pampahermosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype female <bold>5</bold> Lateral view of mesosoma of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus spirator</tp:taxon-name></italic> Townes, paratype female <bold>6</bold> Lateral view of mesosoma of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus fuscatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype female <bold>7</bold> Dorsal view of first metasomal tergite of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus spirator</tp:taxon-name></italic>, female <bold>8</bold> Dorsal view of first metasomal tergite of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus pampahermosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype female.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-163-083-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific epithet is based on the type locality of Pampa Hermosa.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">spirator</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Meggoleus_spirator</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Townes, 1971</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">5, 7</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>BRAZIL: 1♀ (Paratype), Campina Grande nr. [near] Curitiba, Feb. 12, 1966, H. &amp; M. Townes (AEIC). PERU: 1♀, MD [Madre de Dios], Reserva Comunal Amarakaeri, Qda Pinquiri, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">70°51'33.96&quot;W, 12°55'29.98&quot;S</named-content>, 421 m, 03–04.vi.2011, Malaise. [trap] B. Medina y L. Huerto (MUSM).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to species of Meggoleus (females only)">
                    <title>Key to species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (females only)</title>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epicnemial carina reaching anterior margin of mesopleuron near its midlength; first tergite without glymma (Afrotropical region)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus townesi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khalaim</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epicnemial carina reaching subalar prominence; first tergite with glymma (Neotropical region)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foveate groove on mesopleuron long, almost reaching to epicnemial carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>); metasoma brownish black to black, except pronotum reddish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus fuscatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foveate groove short (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 4, 5</xref>); metasoma laterally and ventrally reddish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 4, 5</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spiracle of tergite 1 large; separation between spiracles at most 1.1–1.2x spiracle diameter (maximum diameter measured between external margins of carina round spiracle), spiracles mostly located on dorsal part of tergite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus spirator</tp:taxon-name></italic> Townes</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spiracle of tergite 1 moderate sized; separation between spiracles 1.8–1.9× spiracle diameter, spiracles mostly located on lateral part of tergite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Meggoleus pampahermosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>I am grateful to Dave Wahl (AEIC) for permitting examination of Townes’s paratype, and Caroline S. Chaboo (SEMC) for advice and support during this work. Andre<!--PageBreak-->y Khalaim and Anu Veijalainen read the submitted manuscript and returned very useful suggestions, corrections, and information. San Marcos University (Lima, Peru) provided financial support for the field work (project No. 111001161), while research permits were issued by the Ministry of Environment (Peru). This is a contribution of the Division of Entomology, University of Kansas Natural History Museum.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> The Ichneumonidae of Costa Rica 1, Introduction, keys to subfamilies, and keys to the species of the lower pimpliform subfamilies: Rhyssinae, Pimplinae, Poemeniinae, Acaenitinae and Cylloceriinae.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute </source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>589</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalaim</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> First records of <italic>Meggoleus</italic>, <italic>Heterocola</italic> and <italic>Phradis</italic> (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae: Tersilochinae) from the Afrotropical region, with description of four new species.</article-title> <source>African Invertebrates </source> <volume>48</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalaim</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Tersilochinae of South, Southeast and East Asia, excluding Mongolia and Japan (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae).</article-title> <source>Zoosystematica Rossica </source> <volume>20</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>96</fpage>-<lpage>148</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalaim</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheng</surname> <given-names>M-L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Review of the Tersilochinae (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae) of China, with description of four new species.</article-title> <source>Zookeys </source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>81</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.14.141" xlink:type="simple">10.3897/zookeys.14.141</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Townes</surname> <given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<article-title> The genera of Ichneumonidae, Part 4.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>372</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Achterberg</surname> <given-names>Kv</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horstmann</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> World Ichneumonoidea 2004. In: Yu DS (Ed) Taxapad 2005 Data Base.</source> [http://www.taxapad.com]</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>