<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.77.936</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                Review of the European Greenomyia Brunetti (Diptera, Mycetophilidae) with new descriptions of females
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Kurina</surname>
                        <given-names>Olavi</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
								</contrib>		
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Hedmark</surname>
                        <given-names>Kjell</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Karström</surname>
                        <given-names>Mats</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Kjærandsen</surname>
                        <given-names>Jostein</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
								</contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>Institute of Agricultural and Environmental Sciences, Estonian University of Life Sciences, Riia st 181, 51014 Tartu, Estonia</label></aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>Kungsfågelvägen 1C, S- 79432 Orsa, Sweden</label></aff>
                    <aff id="A3"><label>Älvvägen 4, S-96030 Vuollerim, Sweden</label></aff>
                    <aff id="A4"><label>Department of Biology, Museum of Zoology, Lund University, Helgonavägen 3, S-223 62 Lund, Sweden</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Olavi Kurina (<email xlink:type="simple">olavi.kurina@emu.ee</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Chris Thompson</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>26</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>77</issue>
            <fpage>31</fpage>
            <lpage>50</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>12</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>13</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Olavi Kurina, Kjell Hedmark, Mats Karström, Jostein Kjærandsen</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The females of the four continental <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> Brunetti species in Europe are associated with the males, diagnosed and keyed, providing the first association and description of the females of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> Zaitzev, 1994 and <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name> Zaitzev, 1982. Colour photographs of their habitus and line drawings of their female terminalia are provided. <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> Laštovka &amp; Matile, 1974 is found to be a senior synonym of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia theresae</tp:taxon-name> Matile, 2002. <bold>syn. n.</bold> The diagnostic characters used to distinguish between <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name> Ostroverkhova in keys did not hold up to a closer scrutiny and leave the status of <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name> as separate genus questionable.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Mycetophilidae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Greenomyia</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Neoclastobasis</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>fungus gnats</kwd>
                <kwd>systematics</kwd>
                <kwd>identification key</kwd>
                <kwd>synonymy</kwd>
                <kwd>Europe</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> Brunetti was erected to distinguish a single oriental species, <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia nigricoxa</tp:taxon-name> Brunetti, 1912. Since then several species (mainly Holarctic) have been described and new combinations proposed. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Laštovka and Matile (1974)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Chandler and Ribeiro (1995)</xref> characterised the genus and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Matile (2002)</xref> provided a key to all 11 worldspecies of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name>. Species of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> are mostly dark coloured medium-sized fungus gnats with a typical wing venation similar to that of <tp:taxon-name>Leia</tp:taxon-name> <!--PageBreak-->Meigen, 1818 and allied genera where R1 is notably shorter than the long and nearly horizontally aligned crossvein <italic>rm</italic>. Further diagnostic characters include the lateral ocelli being well separated from the eye margins and all veins reaching the wing margin (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Søli et al. 2000</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Edwards (1925)</xref> introduced the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Leiini</tp:taxon-name> for <tp:taxon-name>Leia</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> and a number of other genera with an intermediate position between the subfamilies <tp:taxon-name>Sciophilinae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Mycetophilinae</tp:taxon-name>. Later the tribe has sometimes been given subfamily status (see review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Gammelmo 2004</xref>), but recent morphological and molecular studies have questioned its monophyly (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Amorim and Rindal 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Rindal et al. 2009</xref>). <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> appears most closely related to the genus <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name> Ostroverkhova, 1970, a genus that includes two eastern Palaearctic (<tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis sibirica</tp:taxon-name> Ostroverkhova, 1970 and <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis kamijoi</tp:taxon-name> Sasakawa, 1964) and one European species (<tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis draskovitsae</tp:taxon-name> Matile, 1978). The genus <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name> is diagnosed by a prolonged apical palpal segment, the veins M2 and CuA1 terminating before the wing margin, and distinctive terminalia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Ostroverkhova 1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Matile 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Zaitzev 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Søli et al. 2000</xref>).</p>
            <p>Species of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> are not frequently encountered in Europe and apart from the widespread <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> Laštovka &amp; Matile, 1974 (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bechev 1989</xref>; Ševčik and Martinovský 1999; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Plassmann 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Caspers 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Kurina 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Chandler 2010</xref>), they are generally thought of as quite rare. A revitalized focus on fungus gnats the last two decades, however, has yielded a number of new records and five species are now reported from Europe: viz. <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> Zaitzev, 1994, <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> (Winnertz, 1863), <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia lucida</tp:taxon-name> (Becker, 1908), <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> (= <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia theresae</tp:taxon-name> Matile, 2002, syn. n.), and <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name> Zaitzev, 1982 (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 29</xref> for published records, except <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia lucida</tp:taxon-name>, which is endemic to the Canary Islands).</p>
            <p>While the males of most <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> species are adequately illustrated and keyed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Zaitzev 1982</xref>, 1994; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Laštovka and Matile 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Chandler and Ribeiro 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Matile 2002</xref>) the females of several species remain to be properly diagnosed and described. The current communication was initiated by the finding of three <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> species from two localities 1 km apart in Vuollerim, Lule Lappmark in northern Sweden (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Kjærandsen et al. 2007</xref>). The material gave us the opportunity to associate and describe females of two species for the first time. The shifted focus to females further revealed that the generic characters separating <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name> from <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> do not hold, and highlights a need to re-evaluate their status as separate genera.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Material and collections from a wide range of Palaearctic sources were studied. The collecting methods, if known, are referred to in case by each specimen in the studied material section below. The following codens obtained from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Evenhuis (2009)</xref> are used for depositories:</p>
            <p><abbrev>Coll. Hedmark<def> <p>Private collection of Kjell Hedmark, Orsa, Sweden.</p></def></abbrev></p>
            <p><abbrev>Coll. Selin<def> <p>Private collection of Allan Selin, Tallinn, Estonia.</p></def></abbrev></p>
            <p><abbrev>EIHU<def> <p>Hokkaido University Museum, Sapporo, Japan.<!--PageBreak--></p></def></abbrev></p>
            <p><abbrev>IZBE<def> <p>Institute of Agricultural and Environmental Sciences, Estonian University of Life Sciences (former Institute of Zoology and Botany), Tartu, Estonia.</p></def></abbrev></p>
            <p><abbrev>MNHN<def> <p>Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris, France.</p></def></abbrev></p>
            <p><abbrev>MZLU<def> <p>Museum of Zoology, Lund University, Lund, Sweden.</p></def></abbrev></p>
            <p><abbrev>ZIN<def> <p>Zoological Institute of Russian Academy of Sciences, St. Petersburg, Russia.</p></def></abbrev></p>
            <p><abbrev>ZMHB<def> <p>Museum für Naturkunde Humbolt-Universität zu Berlin, Germany.</p></def></abbrev></p>
            <p><abbrev>ZSM<def> <p>Zoologische Staatssammlung in München, Germany</p></def></abbrev></p>
            <p>Three of four species were photographed and figured based on material collected in Vuollerim (Sweden), while illustrations of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> were based on Greek material. The terminalia were detached and cleared in a solution of KOH, followed by neutralization in acetic acid and washing in distilled water or in alcohol. The remaining chitinous parts were inserted into glycerine for detailed study, including illustration, and thereafter preserved as glycerine preparations in polyethylene micro vials. Habitus and wing photos were taken of specimens in alcohol, using a Canon 7D camera fitted with a Canon MP-E65 (F2.8 1–5 ×) lens. Illustrations of the terminalia were prepared using a U-DA drawing tube attached to a Olympus CX31 compound microscope. Terminalia are figured in three different positions: laterally, dorsally and ventrally. Sternite VIII was detached and figured separately to better expose the shape of hypoproct and gonapophysis IX. The preservation method of the studied specimens is indicated in the material section for each species. We used a 70–80 % solution of ethanol for alcohol preservation and the chemical method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Vockeroth (1966)</xref> for dry-mounting from alcohol. Slide mounting in Euparal followed the method described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Kurina (2008b)</xref>. Morphological terminology follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Søli (1997)</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics"><title>Systematics</title>
            <sec sec-type="Key to females of European Greenomyia species"><title>Key to females of European Greenomyia species</title>
                <p>Compiled from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Zaitzev (1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">1994</xref>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Chandler and Ribeiro (1995)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Matile (2002)</xref> and original data.</p>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing hyaline (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 12</xref>). Coxae yellow, femora and tibiae yellow, only hind femur brown in apical fourth. Mesonotum yellow with three fused longitudinal brown stripes. Cercus one segmented. Sternite VIII with three apical incisions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 28</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name> Zaitzev, 1982</td>
                            </tr>
														
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing with apical or preapical dark band. Mesonotum dark brown to black. Coxae yellow or blackish. Cercus one- or two-segmented. Sternite VIII with single central incision apically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 25–27</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
														
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing tip darkened on about apical third (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 11</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            </tr>
														
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing with preapical dark band leaving tip hyaline (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 9–10</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
														
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mid and hind coxae brown to black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>). Cercus clearly two-segmented</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> Laštovka &amp; Matile, 1974</td>
                            </tr>
														
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All coxae yellow or slightly darkened basally</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia lucida</tp:taxon-name> (Becker, 1908) [Endemic to the Canary Islands, not seen]</td>
                            </tr>
														
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Last palpal segment elongated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>). C terminating distinctly before apex of wing, making R5 straight to slightly sinuate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>). Cercus two-segmented but segments partly fused (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 14</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">18</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> (Winnertz, 1863)</td>
                            </tr>
														
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Last palpal segment not elongated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>). C terminating almost at apex of wing, making R5 distinctly arched (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 9</xref>). Cercus one-segmented (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 13</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">17</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> Zaitzev, 1994</td>
                            </tr>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="The species"><title>The species</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">baikalica</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Zaitzev, 1994</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">5</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">9</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">13</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">17</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">21</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">25</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material studied"><title>Material studied:</title>
                    <p> <bold>SWEDEN.</bold> 1♀, Lu. Jokkmokk, Vuollerim, Bomyrberget, in forest 135 m.a.s.l., Malaise trap, 16.–18.VIII.2006 (K. Hedmark leg.) [IZBE, mounted from alcohol]; 1♀, Lu. Jokkmokk, Vuollerim, Bomyrberget, 135 m.a.s.l., Malaise trap, 18.–24.VIII.2007 (K. Hedmark leg.) [MZLU, in alcohol]. <bold>FINLAND.</bold> 1♂, Kn. Sotkamo, Urpovaara, window trap N2, 26.VIII.–11.IX.1997 (M. Kuussaari leg.) [IZBE, on pin].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnostic characters"><title>Diagnostic characters.</title>
                    <p> Female. Thorax blackish, abdomen brown. Legs yellow, cx3 with small dark markings basally. All trochanters yellow, with small black apicoventral spots. Tibiae with dense brown setae. Scape and pedicel dark yellow, first flagellomere basally yellowish, rest of flagellum brown. Mouthparts pale yellow. Apical palpal segment 1.4–1.6 (n=2) times as long as penultimate segment. Wing with narrow preapical brownish band, gradually tapering towards hind margin. C terminating almost at apex of wing, R5 distinctly arched (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 9</xref>). Medial and cubital veins both reach wing margin, CuA1 basally obsolete, brownish shade along posterior margin of CuA2. Terminalia brown, cercus one-segmented, yellow apically. Tergite IX larger than tergite VIII. Gonapophysis IX visible in lateral view, with wide pear-shaped medial incision apically. Sternite VIII deeply incised apicomedially and moderately emarginated basally.</p>
                    <p>Male. Coloration and other non-terminal characters including palpi similar to female. Apical palpal segment is 1.4 (n=1) times as long as penultimate segment.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 1–4.</label>
                        <caption><p>Habitus photos of European <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> females. <bold>1</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>2</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>3</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>4</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name>.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-077-031-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 5–8.</label>
                        <caption><p>Head and palpi of European <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> females, lateral view. <bold>5</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>6</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>7</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>8</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name>. Last palpal segment is indicated by a red arrow.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-077-031-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Zaitzev (1994)</xref> described this species from Siberian material (Buryat Republic). Subsequently only a few specimens have been recorded from Norway, Sweden, Finland and Russian Karelia (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Kjærandsen et al. 2007</xref>; Fig. 29). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Zaitzev (1994)</xref> figured the male terminalia whereas the female terminalia have not been figured earlier. Using the key by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Zaitzev (1994)</xref> the studied females run to <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> and they are also morphologically conspecific with material of both sexes collected simultaneously<!--PageBreak--> in Russian Karelia (A. Polevoi, pers. comm.). The studied female specimens were collected in a boggy forest stand within a small (9 ha) protected remnant of semi-natural, mixed forest.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">borealis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Winnertz, 1863)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">6</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">10</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">14</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">18</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">22</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">26</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material studied"><title>Material studied:</title>
                    <p> <bold>SWEDEN</bold>. 2♂♂, SK, Lund and Lund, Abusa, undated (J. W. Zetterstedt leg.) [MZLU, on pins]; 1♀, ÖG, Valdemarsvik, Snäckevarp (Snäckehvarps <!--PageBreak-->gästgifvaregård 1 km NE Gryt), 11 Aug 1825 (C. Stenhammar leg.) [MZLU, on pin]; 1♀, Lu. Jokkmokk, Vuollerim, in a garden, 105 m.a.s.l., Malaise trap, 8.–15.VIII.2008 (K. Hedmark and M. Karström leg.) [IZBE, mounted from alcohol]; <bold>ESTONIA.</bold> 1♂, Nigula NR, Haavapeaksi, sweeping, 12.VII.1998 (O. Kurina leg.) [IZBE, on pin]; 1♀, Tartu Marja 14, on window 21.VIII.2008 (O. Kurina leg.) [IZBE, on pin]. <bold>GREECE.</bold> 1♂ 2♀♀, Central Macedonia, Kerkini lakes area, village Vironia, Ramna site, 41°17'42.5"N, 023°11'33.1"E, 750 m.a.s.l., Malaise trap, 7.–13.VII.2008 (G. Ramel leg.) [IZBE, mounted from alcohol]; 1♂, Central Macedonia, Kerkini lakes area, village Vironia, Beabies site, 41°19'15.4"N, 023°13'39.6"E, 1150 m.a.s.l., Malaise trap, 21.–27.VII.2008 (G. Ramel leg.) [IZBE, mounted from alcohol]; 1♂ Central Macedonia, Kerkini lakes area, village Neo Petritsi, Midway site, 41°18'49.8"N, 023°16'35.6"E,<!--PageBreak--> 750 m.a.s.l., Malaise trap, 23.–29.VI.2008 (G. Ramel leg.) [IZBE, mounted from alcohol]. <bold>KAZAKHSTAN.</bold> 1♀, Alma-Ata, 13.–16.VI. 1824 (Kuzin leg.) [ZIN, on pin].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnostic characters"><title>Diagnostic characters.</title>
                    <p> Female. Thorax brown to blackish. Abdomen entirely brown or first two segments slightly lighter. Legs pale to yellow, except cx2 and cx3 with dark markings basally and apically, all trochanters brown and f3 brown, with lateral parts lighter to yellow. Tibiae with dense brown setae. Scape and pedicel dark yellow, flagellomeres brown. Mouthparts yellow. Apical palpal segment 5.0–5.4 (n=4) times as long as penultimate segment. Wing with broad preapical brownish band, reaching hind margin but gradually paler. C terminating distinctly before apex of wing, R5 straight to slightly sinuate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 10</xref>). M2 and CuA1 <!--PageBreak-->not reaching wing margin, CuA1 basally obsolete or very weak. Terminalia brown; cercus yellow, two-segmented, apical segment small and partly fused with basal segment. Gonapophysis IX well sclerotized apically, visible in lateral view and with well developed narrow apical incision. Tergite VIII equal in size but slightly wider than tergite IX. Sternite VIII with medial incision apically and well emarginated basally.</p>
                    <p>Male. Coloration and other non-terminal characters including palpi similar to female. Apical palpal segment is 4.7–5.7 (n=4) times as long as penultimate segment.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 9–12.</label>
                        <caption><p>Wings of European <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> females. <bold>9</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>10</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>11</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>12</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name>.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-077-031-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 13–16.</label>
                        <caption><p>Female terminalia of European <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> species, lateral view. <bold>13</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>14</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>15</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>16</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name>. cerc = cercus; gp = gonapophysis; hyp = hypoproct; st = sternite; tg = tergite.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-077-031-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 17–20.</label>
                        <caption><p>Female terminalia of European <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> species, dorsal view. <bold>17</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>18</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>19</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>20</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name>.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-077-031-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 21–24.</label>
                        <caption><p>Female terminalia of European <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> species, ventral view, sternite VIII detached. <bold>21</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>22</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>23</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>24</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name>.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-077-031-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 25–28.</label>
                        <caption><p>Female terminalia of European <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> species, ventral view of sternite VIII. <bold>25</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>26</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>27</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> <bold>28</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name>.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-077-031-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p> While studying the Swedish specimen from Vuollerim, it ran by the first attempt using the key by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Zaitzev (1994)</xref> to <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name> because of the extra long last palpal segment and M2 and CuA1 not reaching the wing margin. The colouration of the studied specimen is, however, different and female terminalia lack strong spines on sternite VIII, being typical to all of the described <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name> species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Zaitzev 1982</xref>; JK and OK <italic>pers. obs.</italic> of <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis kamijoi</tp:taxon-name>: 5♂♂ 2♀♀, South Korea, Sanan, I-li-Keumsan, [MNHN], 1♂ 3♀♀, Japan, Hokkaido, Sapporo [EIHU, MZLU]; <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis draskovicae</tp:taxon-name>: paratypes, 1♂ 1♀ in MNHN, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Matile 1978</xref>). The discovery<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> of a <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> female, with similar size and coloration as the male of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> in the same Malaise trap sample from northern Greece (Kerkini Lake area) allowed a safe association of the sexes. The females from Sweden, Estonia and Kazakhstan were further found to be conspecific with the Greek material of both sexes. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Chandler et al. (2006)</xref>, a male specimen from Greek mainland (Vikos Aoos National Park) has mainly yellow coxae, while other European specimens of <!--PageBreak--><tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> have mainly dark coxae. This may represent an intraspecific variation, however, all specimens studied during the current investigation have coxae whitish yellow. The above-mentioned Estonian specimen represents the first record of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> from the country. The female specimen from Vuollerim was collected in the same garden as <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name>. <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> was previously known only with two 19th century findings from southern Sweden.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">mongolica</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Laštovka et Matile, 1974</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 3</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">7</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">11</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">15</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">19</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">23</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">27</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia theresae</tp:taxon-name><comment> Matile, 2002, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia theresae</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Kurina 2008a</xref>: 255, 270.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material studied"><title>Type material studied:</title>
                    <p> <bold>Paratype</bold> ♂ of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name>: <bold>MONGOLIA.</bold> Central aimak, Tosgoni ovoo, 5–10 km N von Ulan-Baator, 1500–1700 m a.s.l., Exp. Dr. Z. Kaszab 1967 nr. 926, 19–24 Jul 1967 (Z. Kaszab leg.) [MNHN, JKJ-SPM-011843, on pin]</p>
                    <p><bold>Holotype</bold> ♂ of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia theresae</tp:taxon-name>: <bold>ITALY.</bold> Aosta, Champlong, Dessus, 1000 m a.s.l., “courant sur Feuille de Frêne - 2m -”, 26 Aug 1997 (L. Matile leg.) [MNHN, JKJ-SPM-011844, on pin].</p>
                    <p>Other material studied: <bold>SWEDEN.</bold> 1♂, SÖ, Stockholm, Skarpnäck, Skarpa by, 13.VII.-4.X.2003 (B. Viklund leg.) [MZLU, in alcohol]. <bold>GERMANY.</bold> 1♂, D. Oberpfals, NM Main-Donau-Kanal (Proj. Warncke), 12.IX.–5.X.1988 (S. Blank leg.) [No. 30132 in ZSM, in alcohol]. <bold>RUSSIA.</bold> 2♂♂ 3♀♀, Nikolsk-Ussur, 29.VII.1926 (Kuznetzov leg.) [ZIN, on pins]. <bold>ESTONIA.</bold> 1♀, Kääriku, 5.X.1985 (H. Remm leg.) [IZBE, on pin]; 1♀, Luunja, 20.X.1996, on the house wall (O. Kurina leg.) [IZBE, on pin]; 6♂♂ 3♀♀, Karilatsi near Tartu, bait traps, 19.–28.VIII.2005 and 04.–25.IX.2005 (T. Tammaru leg.) [IZBE, on pins]. <bold>HUNGARY.</bold> 38♂♂ 3♀♀, 10 km S Eger, 47°49'11"N, 020°21'37"E, 20 Aug 1989 (R. Danielsson leg.) [MZLU, on pins]. <bold>ITALY.</bold> 1♂, Aosta valley, Verrayes, Promellian, 1200 m.a.s.l., sweeping, 17.VI.2007 (V. Soon leg.) [IZBE, on pin]; 1♀, Siena, 6.V.2007 (A. Selin leg.) [Coll. Selin, on pin]; 3♂♂, Trentino-Alto Adige, Prov. Bolzano, Parco Nationale dello Stelvia, Sulden Valley near Schmelz southwest of Prad, 46°36'42.1"N, 010°34'35.6"E, 940 m.a.s.l., 5.IX.–14.X.2005 (J. Ziegler and C. Lange leg.) [1♂ in ZMHB, 2♂♂ in IZBE, mounted from alcohol]. <bold>GREECE.</bold> 1♂ 2♀♀, Central Macedonia, Kerkini lakes area, village Vironia, Beabies site, 41°19'15.4"N, 023°13'39.6"E, 1150 m.a.s.l., Malaise trap, 30.VI.–6.VII.2008 (G. Ramel leg.) [IZBE, mounted from alcohol]; 6♀♀, Central Macedonia, Kerkini lakes area, village Vironia, Ramna site, 41°17'42.5"N, 023°11'33.1"E, 750 m.a.s.l., Malaise trap, 23.–29.VI.2008 (G. Ramel leg.) [IZBE, mounted from alcohol].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnostic characters"><title>Diagnostic characters.</title>
                    <p> Female. Thorax dark brown to blackish. Abdomen entirely blackish brown or first three segments slightly paler laterally. cx1 entirely yellow or darkened in basal half, cx2 and cx3 entirely dark brown to black. Fore trochanter yellow basally, brown apically. Mid and hind trochanters brown. f1 and f2 yellow, f3 yellow with brown apical fifth. Tibiae yellow, apically slightly darkened, with dense brown setae. Scape, pedicel and flagellomeres brown. Mouthparts pale yellow. Apical palpal segment 1.8–2.2 (n=5) times as long as penultimate segment. Wing tip shaded on about apical third, with darkened area along fore margin. All veins reach wing margin, M2 sometimes basally obsolete or very weak, A1 ending close to, sometimes fused into base of CuA2. Terminalia brown. Cercus distinctly two-segmented, apical segment small, ovate. Gonapophysis IX membranous, widely protruding apically, not visible <!--PageBreak-->in lateral view. Tergite VIII larger than tergite IX. Sternite VIII apically with shallow medial incision, moderately emarginated basally.</p>
                    <p>Male. Coloration and other non-terminal characters including palpi similar to female. Apical palpal segment is 1.7–2.1 (n=5) times as long as penultimate segment.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p> This species was originally described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Laštovka and Matile (1974)</xref> based on Mongolian material and subsequently widely recorded in Europe. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Chandler (2005)</xref> did not include <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> in the European list and assigned all records to <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia theresae</tp:taxon-name>, a species described from northern Italy by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Matile (2002)</xref>. Careful comparisons of type material of both species at MNHN in Paris (independently undertaken by two of the authors, OK and JK; the holotype of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> deposited in the Hungarian Natural History Museum was not available for the study) did not indicate any substantial differences in their male terminalia. The minor diagnostic characters as indicated in the original description and illustrations by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Matile (2002)</xref> are liable to different angles of views only. Consequently we have come to the conclusion that <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia theresae</tp:taxon-name> at present state of knowledge must be treated as a junior synonym of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> and that all published records in Europe should rather be associated with the latter. In addition to the studied type material, we also compared the terminalia of female specimens from the Russian Far East, Estonia and northern Greece without finding any reliable differences. Moreover, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Papp (2000)</xref> confirmed conspecificity when he compared central European material from Hungary with the Mongolian type material. Male terminalia are figured by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Laštovka and Matile (1974)</xref> and subsequently by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Matile (2002)</xref>, while female terminalia have previously been figured by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Zaitzev (1982)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Kurina (1997)</xref>. Our association of males and females are based on multiple simultaneous findings in trap samples (see above) that agrees with previous descriptions of the female. In the Pre-Balkan mountain range in Bulgaria, the species has been collected in xerotermic oak forest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bechev 2000</xref>). The species was quite common in samples taken in a bait trap, operated on the basis of a mixture of fermenting sugar and red wine, in southern Estonia (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kurina 2006</xref>). The above-mentioned specimens from Greece are the first records from the country.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Zaitzev, 1982</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 4</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">8</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">12</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">16</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">20</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">24</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">28</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material studied"><title>Type material studied:</title>
                    <p> <bold>Holotype</bold> ♂, <bold>RUSSIA.</bold> Primorskiy Terr., Santaheza, 07.VII.1927 (A. Stackelberg leg.) [ZIN, on pin].</p>
                    <p>Other material studied: <bold>SWEDEN.</bold> 4 ♀♀, Lu. Jokkmokk, Vuollerim, in garden, 105 m.a.s.l., Malaise trap, 11.VIII.–19.IX.2003 (K. Hedmark and M. Karström leg.); 1♂, the same locality, Malaise trap 11.–19.VIII.2004; 25♂♂ 15♀♀, the same locality, Malaise trap 11.VIII.–7.X.2005; 11♂♂ 4♀♀, the same locality, Malaise trap 11.VIII.–22.IX.2006; 18♂♂ 14♀♀, the same locality, yellow pan-trap VII–08.X.2006; 17♂♂ 7♀♀, the same locality, yellow pan-trap 16.VI.–20.VII.2007; 14♂♂ 4♀♀, the same<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> locality, Malaise trap 12.VIII.–28.IX.2007; 9♂♂ 3♀♀, the same locality, window trap VI–11.IX.2007; 4♂♂ 1♀, the same locality, Malaise trap 13.–27.VI.2008; 1♀, the same locality, yellow pan-trap 19.VI.2008; 1♂, the same locality, window trap 1.VI.–1.VII.2008. In total 153 specimens: 100♂♂ 53♀♀, [most in Coll. Hedmark, some in IZBE and MZLU, most of the material preserved in alcohol, while some specimens are mounted from alcohol to pins or slide mounted].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnostic characters"><title>Diagnostic characters.</title>
                    <p> Female.Thorax bi-coloured; mesonotum yellow with variably developed black thoracic stripes; pronotum and propleuron yellow, other pleural parts brown to blackish. Abdominal sternites I-IV entirely yellow or slightly brownish; tergites of first four segments bi-coloured: basally yellow, apically brown (in a few occasions first four tergites entirely brown). Legs all yellow except dark brown band on apical fourth of hind femur. Tibiae densely covered with brown setulae. Scape, pedicel, and 3–5 flagellomeres yellow, rest of flagellum light brown. Mouthparts yellow. Apical palpal segment 4.1–4.4 (n=5) times as long as penultimate segment. Wing hyaline with slight yellowish tinge, all veins reach wing margin, M1 and CuA2 basally obsolete or very weak. Terminalia brown, cercus one-segmented, apically yellow. Gonapophysis IX membranous, subsquare with shallow incision apically, not visible in lateral view. Tergite VIII wider than tergite IX. Sternite VIII medially with deep and narrow incision, lateral incisions more shallow.</p>
                    <p>Male. Coloration and other non-terminal characters similar to female. The apical palpal segment is 4–5 (n=5) times as long as penultimate segment.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p> Besides its peculiar distribution (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 29</xref>), <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name> is unique among the four studied species in having vivid yellowish colouration and hyaline wings. It was described from South Primorje in the Russian Far East (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Zaitzev 1982</xref>) and has subsequently been recorded only from two semi-urban localities in the Nordic region: the single locality in Swedish Lapland (present material, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Kjærandsen et al. 2007</xref>) and from one locality in the capital of Norway, Oslo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Søli and Kjærandsen 2008</xref>). Eight years of collecting (2002–2009) with Malaise traps, yellow pan-traps and window traps near a compost in the garden of one of the authors (MK) yielded 153 <!--PageBreak-->specimens, indicating rise and decline of a small population. None was collected in the first and the last year, while four in 2003, one in 2004, 40 in 2005, 47 in 2006, 54 in 2007 and seven in 2008. The flight activity lasted almost the whole vegetation season, from the middle of June (in 2007) to the beginning of October (in 2004). A garden compost is the supposed microhabitat for this population of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name> and its origin should be somewhere in the surroundings. A close potential natural habitat could be the Vuollerim ravine a few hundred meters away. Waste from picked forest fungi might be another possibility<bold>.</bold></p>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figure 29.</label>
                        <caption><p>Known records of European <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> species. <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> (black squares): <bold>4</bold> original data <bold>5</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Polevoi 2000</xref> (marked with a question mark) <bold>7</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Chandler 2005</xref> <bold>9</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Chandler 2005</xref> <bold>10</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Kjærandsen et al. 2007</xref>, original data <bold>12</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Lackschewitz 1937</xref> <bold>13</bold> original data from two localities <bold>16</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Winnertz 1863</xref> <bold>17</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Chandler 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">2005</xref> (doubtful) <bold>22</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Ševčík and Košel 2009</xref> <bold>26</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Ševčík and Papp 2001</xref> <bold>29</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Chandler et al. 2006</xref> <bold>30</bold> original data <bold>32</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Zaitzev 1982</xref>, 1994 <bold>33</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Zaitzev 1982</xref>, 1994 <bold>38</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Zaitzev 1982</xref>, 1994. <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> (green squares): <bold>3</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gammelmo and Søli 2006</xref> <bold>4</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Kjærandsen et al. 2007</xref> <bold>5</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Polevoi 2000</xref> (three different localities) <bold>6</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Polevoi 2001</xref> <bold>34</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Zaitzev 1994</xref> <bold>35</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Zaitzev 1994</xref>. <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia mongolica</tp:taxon-name> (blue squares): <bold>2</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Søli et al. 2009</xref> <bold>8</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Chandler 2010</xref> (seven different localities) <bold>11</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Kjærandsen et al. 2007</xref> <bold>14</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Kurina 1997</xref> <bold>15</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Zaitzev 1994</xref> <bold>17</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Matile 2002</xref> (as <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia theresae</tp:taxon-name>) <bold>18</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Matile 2002</xref> (as <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia theresae</tp:taxon-name>) <bold>19</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Caspers 1996</xref> <bold>20</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Kurina 2008a</xref> (as <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia theresae</tp:taxon-name>) <bold>21</bold> original data <bold>22</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Martinovský and Ševčik 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Martinovský and Barták 2000</xref> <bold>23</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Plassmann 1996</xref> <bold>24</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Matile 2002</xref> (as <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia theresae</tp:taxon-name>) <bold>25</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Ševčík and Martinovský 1999</xref> <bold>27</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Papp 2000</xref> (several different localities), original data <bold>28</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bechev 1989</xref> <bold>30</bold> original data <bold>36</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Laštovka and Matile 1974</xref> <bold>37</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Zaitzev 1982</xref>, 1994 <bold>40</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Zaitzev 1982</xref>, 1994. <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name> (red squares): <bold>1</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Søli and Kjærandsen 2008</xref> <bold>4</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Kjærandsen et al. 2007</xref> <bold>39</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Zaitzev 1982</xref>, 1994.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-077-031-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Species descriptions of fungus gnats are largely based and depending on characters in the male terminalia. Females are often ignored in taxonomic reviews and only a few generic reviews cover all or the majority of associated females (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Søli 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Martinsen and Søli 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Kjærandsen 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">2009</xref>). Still, females usually have distinctive yet less pronounced characters in their terminalia. In the case of the few European <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> species we found it fairly easy to safely associate the females based on body characters such as colouration patterns, wing shape and venation details shared between the sexes, and the associations were further strengthened by co-occurrence in multiple trap samples.</p>
            <p>Our study of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> revealed that the diagnostic characters used to distinguish <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name> in keys (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Søli et al. 2000</xref>) does not hold up to a closer scrutiny, especially when both sexes are considered. Both sexes of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> havewings where M2 and CuA1 end slightly before the wing margin, and both sexes of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name> have prolonged apical segment of their palps. These characters are akin to those used to diagnose <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name>. Yet, although the three known species of <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name> are very similar to <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> in general appearance they show distinctive features in their terminalia that separate them from <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name>. In <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> the dorsal branch of the male gonostylus always has two distinct combs of blunt spines on an otherwise bare inner surface. In <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name> the entire inner surface is covered with short blunt setae and a single row of larger spines is situated basally. Females of <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name> have a few short and strong spines along the apical margin of sternite VIII, which are never found in <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name>. We think <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Neoclastobasis</tp:taxon-name> may prove to be monophyletic sistertaxa, but pending genetic studies and a better definition of the entire <tp:taxon-name>Leiini</tp:taxon-name> clade we leave the question whether they deserve to retain their status as separate genera or could be joined into one. In the meantime separating the two genera must rest entirely on differences in their terminalia as described above.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>OK was funded by grant 7558 of the Estonian Science Foundation, JK by the Swedish Taxonomy Initiative. We are grateful to the European Commission’s Research Infrastructure for funding the study visits to MNHN via the SYNTHESYS programme (FR-TAF-956 for JK and FR-TAF-5005 for OK). We are much obliged to the curators M. Baylac (MNHN), C. Daugeron (MNHN), E. Nartshuk (ZIN), W. Schacht (ZSM) and J. Ziegler (ZMHB) for the opportunity to work with the collections and for loans of material. A. Polevoi (Petrozavodsk, Russia), in addition to valuable comments and information, is thanked for assistance in determining the first specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia stackelbergi</tp:taxon-name> and for providing a male of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia baikalica</tp:taxon-name> for study. A. Selin (Tallinn, Estonia), J. Jakovlev (Vantaa, Finland) and G. Ramel (Kerkini, Greece) helped with material for study. Lars Hedström (Uppsala, Sweden) is acknowledged for help with interpreting an old specimen label of <tp:taxon-name>Greenomyia borealis</tp:taxon-name>. Peter Kerr (Sacramento, USA) and an anonymous reviewer are thanked for their comments and suggestions on the manuscript.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Amorim</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rindal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of the Mycetophiliformia, with proposal of the subfamilies Heterotrichinae, Ohakuneinae, and Chiletrichinae for the Rangomaramidae (Diptera, Bibionomorpha).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1535</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> New species Mycetophiloidea (Diptera) for Bulgarian fauna. III</article-title>. <source>Travaux Scientifiques d’Universite de Plovdiv, Biologie</source> <volume>27</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>. [in Bulgarian]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Seasonal activity and vertical distribution of fungus gnats (Diptera: Sciaroidea, excluding Sciaridae) in the western and the central parts of Stara Planina ridge (Bulgaria).</article-title> <source>Travaux Scientifiques d’Universite de Plovdiv, Animalia</source> <volume>36</volume> (<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1908</year>)<article-title> Dipteren der Kanarischen Inseln.</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen aus dem Zoologischen Museum in Berlin,</source> <volume>1908</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>180</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunetti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>)<article-title> The Fauna of British India, including Ceylon and Burma</article-title>. <source>Diptera Nematosera (Excluding Chironomidae and Culicidae)</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>581</lpage> pp., pls. I-XII.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Caspers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title>Fundort Schöngeising, Oberbayern Die Pilzmücken (Diptera Sciaroidea: Bolitophilidae, Diadocidiidae, Ditomyiidae, Keroplatidae, Mycetophilidae).</article-title> <source>Entomofauna</source> <volume>17</volume> (<issue>25</issue>):<fpage>385</fpage>-<lpage>396</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> 20. Mycetophilidae</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Merz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bächli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haenni </surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonseth</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Fauna Helvetica 1. Diptera-Checklist</source>. <publisher-name>Schweizerische Entomologische Gesellschaft</publisher-name>, <fpage>113</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Fauna Europaea: Mycetophilidae</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Fauna Europaea: Diptera, Nematocera. Fauna Europaea, version 1.2</source>. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.faunaeur.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.faunaeur.org</ext-link> [accessed 21.I.2010]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Fungus Gnats Recording Scheme. Newsletter 4.</article-title> <source>Dipterists Forum, Spring</source> <volume>2010</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caspers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> The fungus gnats (Diptera: Bolitophilidae, Diadocidiidae, Ditomyiidae, Keroplatidae and Mycetophilidae) of Greece, its islands and Cyprus.</article-title> <source>Studia Dipterologica</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>314</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title>The Sciaroidea (Diptera) (excluding Sciaridae) of the Atlantic Islands (Canary Islands, Madeira and the Azores)</article-title>. <source>Boletim do Museu Municipal do Funchal (Historia Natural), Suplemento No. 3</source>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1925</year>)<article-title> British Fungus-Gnats (Diptera, Mycerophilidae). With a revised Generic Classification of the Family.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the Entomological Society of London</source> <volume>73</volume> (<issue>1924</issue>):<fpage>505</fpage>-<lpage>670</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Evenhuis</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> The insect and spider collections of the world website</source>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hbs.bishopmuseum.org/codens/" xlink:type="simple">http://hbs.bishopmuseum.org/codens/</ext-link> [accessed 13.II.2010]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gammelmo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title>. Classification of Mycetophilidae (Diptera, Sciaroidea).</article-title> <source>Norwegian Journal of Entomology</source> <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gammelmo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Søli</surname><given-names>GEE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title>Norwegian fungus gnats of the family Mycetophilidae (Diptera, Nematocera).</article-title> <source>Norwegian Journal of Entomology</source> <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjærandsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Review of fungus gnats of the genus <italic>Tarnania</italic> Tuomikoski, with a phylogeny of the <italic>Rymosia</italic> s. l. genus group (Diptera: Mycetophilidae).</article-title> <source>Insect Systematics and Evolution</source> <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>-<lpage>148</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjærandsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> The genus <italic>Pseudexechia</italic> Tuomikoski re-characterized, with a review of European species (Diptera: Mycetophiliae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2056</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjærandsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedmark</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurina</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polevoi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Økland</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Götmark</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Annotated checklist of fungus gnats from Sweden (Diptera: Bolitophilidae, Diadocidiidae, Ditomyiidae, Keroplatidae and Mycetophiliae)</article-title>. <source>Insect Systematics and Evolution Supplement No. 6</source>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurina</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> <italic>Greenomyia mongolica</italic> Lastovka et Matile, 1974 (Diptera, Mycetophilidae) found in Estonia.</article-title> <source>An international Journal of Dipterological Research</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurina</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> A review of Estonian wood gnats (Diptera: Anisopodidae).</article-title> <source>Sahlbergia</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurina</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008a</year>)<article-title> Sciaroidea excl. Sciaridae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziegler J (Ed) Diptera</surname><given-names>Stelviana</given-names></name></person-group>. <issue-title> A dipterological perspective on a changing alpine landscape. Volume 1. Studia Dipterologica.</issue-title> <source>Supplements</source> <volume>16</volume> :<fpage>245</fpage>-<lpage>293</lpage>..</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurina</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008b</year>)<article-title> <italic>Cluzobra matilei</italic> sp. n. from French Guyana, with notes on congeners (Diptera: Mycetophilidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1874</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lackschewitz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1937</year>)<article-title> Die Fungivoriden des Ost baltischen Gebietes. Arbeiten des Naturforscher Verein zu Riga (N.F.</article-title> <source>)</source> <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Laštovka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matile</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<article-title> Mycetophilidae (Diptera) de Mongolie</article-title>. <source>Acta Zoologica Academiae Scientiarum Hungaricae</source> <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1/2</issue>): <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Søli</surname><given-names>GEE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Description of females of three species of <italic>Ectrepesthoneura</italic> Enderlein (Diptera, Mycetophilidae).</article-title> <source>Norwegian Journal of Entomology</source> <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>-<lpage>147</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinovský</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ševčik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> Bolitophilidae, Diadocidiidae, Ditomyiidae, Keroplatidae, Macroceridae, Mycetophilidae</article-title>. <source>Folia Facultatis Scientiarum Naturalium Universitatis Masarykianae Brunensis Biologia</source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinovský</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barták</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Mycetophilidae. In Barták M, Vaňhara J (Eds) Diptera in an industrially affected region (North-Western Bohemia, Bílina and Duchcov environs) I.</article-title> <source>Folia Facultatis Scientiarum Naturalium Universitatis Masarykianae Brunensis, Biologia</source> <volume>104</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Matile</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>)<article-title> Description d’un <italic>Neoclastobasis</italic> noveau de Hongrie et remarques sur divers Leiini (Diptera: Mycetophilidae)</article-title>. <source>Folia Entomologica Hungarica, S. N.</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>172</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Matile</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Notes sur le genre <italic>Greenomyia</italic> Brunetti et description d’une espece nouvelle des Alpes et des Apennins (Diptera: Mycetophilidae).</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société Entomologique de France (Nouvelle série)</source> <volume>38</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Meigen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1818</year>)<source> Systematische Beschreibung der bekannten europäischen zweiflügeligen Insekten</source>. Vol <volume>1</volume>, <publisher-name>Aachen</publisher-name>, xxxvi + <lpage>333</lpage>pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ostroverkhova</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> New data on Siberian fungus Gnats (Diptera, Mycetophilidae)</article-title>. <source>Entomologicheskoe Obozrenie</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>. [In Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Pediciidae, Bolitophilidae, Keroplatidae, Mycetophilidae and Dixidae: genera and species new to Hungary (Diptera).</article-title> <source>Folia Entomologica Hungarica</source> <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>231</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Plassmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Zur Kenntnis der Pilzmückenfauna Österreichs (Diptera: Nematocera: Mycetophilidae)</article-title>. <source>Mitteilungen des internationalen Entomologischen Vereins</source> <volume>21</volume> (<issue>3/4</issue>): <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Polevoi</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<source> Fungus gnats (Diptera: Bolitophilidae, Ditomyiidae, Keroplatidae, Diadocidiidae, Mycetophilidae) of Karelia</source>. <publisher-loc>Petrozavodsk</publisher-loc>, <lpage>84</lpage>pp. [In Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Polevoi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> The study of forest Diptera fauna in Koitajoki area</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hokkanen</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Diversity studies in Koitajoki area (North Karelian Biosphere Reserve, Ilomantsi, Finland</source>). <publisher-name>Metsähallitus</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Vantaa</publisher-loc>, <fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rindal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Søli</surname><given-names>GEE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachmann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> On the systematics of the fungus gnat subfamily Mycetophilinae (Diptera): a combined morphological and molecular approach.</article-title> <source>Journal of Zoological Systematics and Evolutionary Research</source> <volume>47</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>227</fpage>-<lpage>233</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasakawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<article-title> Japanese Mycetophilidae V. Descriptions of three new species.</article-title> <source>Akitu</source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Søli</surname><given-names>GEE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> On the morphology and phylogeny of Mycetophilidae, with a revision of <italic>Coelosia</italic> Winnertz (Diptera, Sciaroidea).</article-title> <source>Entomologica Scandinavica Supplement</source> <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>139</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Søli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjærandsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Additions to the Norwegian fauna of fungus gnats (Diptera, Mycetophilidae).</article-title> <source>Norwegian Journal of Entomology</source> <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Søli</surname><given-names>GEE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vockeroth</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matile</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> A.4. Families of Sciaroidea</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darvas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Contribution to a Manual of Palaearctic Diptera. Appendix</source>. <publisher-name>Science Herald</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Budapest</publisher-loc>, <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Søli</surname><given-names>GEE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rindal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen L</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> New records of fungus gnats for Norway (Diptera: Mycetophilidae).</article-title> <source>Norwegian Journal of Entomology</source> <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ševčík</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Košel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Mycetophilidae Newman, 1834</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jedlička</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kúdela</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stloukalová</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Checklist of Diptera of the Czech Republic and Slovakia. Electronic version 2</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zoology.fns.uniba.sk/diptera2009" xlink:type="simple">http://zoology.fns.uniba.sk/diptera2009</ext-link> [accessed 07.II.2010]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ševčík</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinovský</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Faunistic records. Keroplatidae, Mycetophilidae</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jedlička</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Dipterologica bohemoslovaca</source>. Vol. 9. <publisher-name>Slovak Entomological Society</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Bratislava</publisher-loc>, <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B44"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ševčík</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Bolitophilidae and Mycetophilidae (Diptera): genera and species new to Hungary.</article-title> <source>Folia Entomologica Hungarica</source> <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>-<lpage>229</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B45"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vockeroth</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1966</year>)<article-title> A method of mounting insects from alcohol.</article-title> <source>The Canadian Entomologist</source> <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B46"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Winnertz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1863</year>)<article-title> Beitrag zu einer Monographie der Pilzmücken</article-title>. <source>Verhandlungen der Zoologisch-Botanischen Gesellschaft in Wien</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>637</fpage>–<lpage>964</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B47"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaitzev</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<article-title> <italic>Greenomyia</italic> and <italic>Neoclastobasis</italic>. Fungus gnats (Diptera, Mycetophilidae) of the USSR</article-title>. <source>Vestnik Zoologii</source> <volume>1982</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. [in Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B48"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaitzev</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<source> Fungus gnats of the fauna of Russia and adjacent regions. Part 1</source>. <publisher-loc>Moscow</publisher-loc>, <lpage>288</lpage>. [in Russian, with English summary]</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>