<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.302.5261</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new Ingolfiellid (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Ingolfiellidae) from an anchialine pool on Abd al Kuri Island, Socotra Archipelago, Yemen</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Iannilli</surname>
                        <given-names>Valentina</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:73E6D417-5CD1-4749-989E-BF336E24AE16</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Vonk</surname>
                        <given-names>Ronald</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:A12CE9EA-80D0-4AF2-83D1-70A87EC56A93</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>ENEA, Technical Unit of Sustainable Management of Agro-Ecosystems, C.R. Casaccia via Anguillarese 301, 00123 Rome, Italy
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Museo Civico di Storia Naturale di Verona, Lungadige Porta Vittoria, 9, I-37129 – Verona, Italy
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Naturalis Biodiversity Center, Darwinweg 2, P.O. Box 9517, 2300 RA Leiden, The Netherlands
            </aff>
            <aff id="A4">
                <label>4</label>Institute for Biodiversity and Ecosystem Dynamics, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam 1098 XH, The Netherlands
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Ronald Vonk (<email xlink:type="simple">ronald.vonk@naturalis.nl</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: C. O. Coleman</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>20</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>302</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>12</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>15</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2013</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>15</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2013</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Valentina Iannilli, Ronald Vonk</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:6F033BB9-B120-412A-957B-0EA64874CD47</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella arganoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> from Abd al Kuri Island in the Arabian Sea is described from two specimens, a male and a female. The western shore of the Indian Ocean was hitherto a vacant spot in the distribution of circumtropical shallow marine interstitial ingolfiellids and therefore the location of the new species fills a meaningful gap in the geography of the family. Morphologically, the new species shows close affinities with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella xarifae</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Maldives.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>meiofauna</kwd>
                <kwd>subterranean thalassoid amphipods</kwd>
                <kwd>beach environment</kwd>
                <kwd>mesopsammon</kwd>
                <kwd>Arabian Sea</kwd>
                <!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>During sampling of aquatic fauna from the Socotra Archipelago conducted by Roberto Argano and co-workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Taiti and Ferrara 2004</xref>), two specimens of a new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella</tp:taxon-name></italic> were found in the mesopsammon of an anchialine pool on Abd al Kuri Island (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a, b</xref>). Anchialine water bodies are well known to offer a great potential of unique species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Becking et al. 2011</xref> and references herein). Ingolfiellid amphipods are sporadically found and are confined to fresh, brackish, and marine ground- and cave waters, and even ocean floor habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Ruffo 1950</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Spooner 1959</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">1960</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Vonk and Schram 2003</xref>). They are seldom observed in great numbers and the specimens from the small island of Abd al Kuri are no exception to this rule; only two specimens were found. Their discovery points to a long-awaited geographic link in the chain of locality records in this group, as they bridge a gap in the so often presumed Tethys distribution. Until now, no ingolfiellid has been reported between the coasts of Greece in the west and the beaches of the Maldives in the east – a stretch well over 6000 km.</p>
            <p>The late Sandro Ruffo, curator of the natural history museum of Verona, started the work on the two specimens from Abd al Kuri, helped by one of us (V.I.), but did not finish it because he was not confident about the status of a new species based on so little material and the presence of only few available distinctive morphological characters. A few years later we decided to take up this work and bring it to fruition because it provides relevant new information on the geographic range of ingolfiellids and on new combinations of character states as shown by these specimens from an anchialine environment in the Arabian Sea.</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p><bold>a</bold> Abd al Kuri, beach, with gully in foreground, scoured in the sand by rainwater during the wet season (photograph taken while standing at the collection site by R. Argano). Pointed hills on the white beach sand are <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ocypode</tp:taxon-name></italic> crab burrows <bold>b</bold> position of Abd al Kuri Island (red color) in the Arabian Sea.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-302-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The two specimens were collected on a beach on the north coast of Abd al Kuri Island, Republic of Yemen, (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">12°11.988'N, 52°15.943'E</named-content>), close to a little village called Bait <!--PageBreak-->Eesa. Sampling was done with a micro-creel in coarse sand at the bottom of a pool in an otherwise dry wadi, running as a slight depression to the sea (pers. comm. R. Argano). The approximate position of the pool with unknown salinity from which the ingolfiellids were collected on 7 February 2000 is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <sec sec-type="Order AMPHIPODA Latreille, 1802">
                <title>Order <tp:taxon-name>AMPHIPODA</tp:taxon-name> Latreille, 1802
                Suborder <tp:taxon-name>INGOLFIELLIDEA</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1903
                Family <tp:taxon-name>Ingofiellidae</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1903
                Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hansen, 1903</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ingolfiella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">arganoi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:807BB2C1-62F5-4930-A55B-74AF21C033EB</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Ingolfiella_arganoi</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">–5</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Two specimens: one male <bold>holotype</bold>, 1.4 mm, dissected and mounted in Faure’s liquid on slide MSNVRCr nr. 434; one preparatory female <bold>paratype</bold> on two slides MSNVRCr nr. 470 in Museo di Storia Naturale di Verona, Italy.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Lateral lobes on frontal margin of head developed. Maxillule, basal endite (= outer lobe) left and right with asymmetrical seta. Gnathopods 1 and 2 carpochelate with oblique palm, dactyli with a serrated inner margin with four teeth. Female with extra palmar margin robust seta. Oöstegites on pereiopod 3 and 4, with three regularly placed small button-like processes. Gills present on P3-5. Dactylus of P3 and P4 with slender trifid unguis; P5-7 with thicker bifid unguis, not clearly separated from dactylus. Pleopods 1-3 subtrapezoidal and similar, except first pleopod in male which is flexed and has a broadened tip. Uropod 1 with inner ramus about 1.5 times as long as outer ramus; uropod 2 peduncle without basofacial spine and with two diagonal rows of sturdy rectangular setae, three rows in female, individual setae mostly bifid but with some of them trifid at the tip.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The new species is named after Roberto Argano (University of Rome “la Sapienza”) who collected the specimens and gave them to the Verona Museum for study.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Body</italic> elongate, without coloration, all segments laterally compressed. <italic>Head</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>) with lateral margin rounded; lateral or ‘ocular lobes’ present on frontal margin, well developed, suboval. <italic>Pleonites</italic> I-III with diffusely developed posteriorly rounded epimeral plates adorned with simple seta, a superficial marginal edge slightly visible. <italic>Urosomite</italic> III subcilindrical, slightly longer than deep, enclosing base of telson and uropod III.</p>
                        <p><italic>Antennule</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>), peduncular article slightly shorter than head; article ratio 1:0,42:0,42; flagellum of 4 articles, half the length, articles 2-4 with 1 aesthetasc; accessory flagellum slightly shorter than flagellar articles 1+2, three articles.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak--><italic>Antenna</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>) subequal in length to antennule; flagellum of 5 articles, slightly shorter than half the length of peduncle, the last article bearing one aesthetasc (antenna drawn by S. Ruffo but not present in mounted slides).</p>
                        <p><italic>Mandibles</italic> with non-triturative molar process, spiniform. Left mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5d</xref>) with broad incisor, right mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5c</xref>) with fine serrations on lacinia and molar process margin.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak--><italic>Maxillule</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5a, e</xref>) coxal endite (= inner lobe) with 3 simple setae; basal endite (= outer lobe) with six robust setae of which the second one on the medial side has four teeth in the left maxillule and three teeth in the right one. Endopod (= palp) two-segmented, distal segment with two setae.</p>
                        <p><italic>Maxilla</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5b</xref>) with short, equally long plates, each bearing four distal setae.</p>
                        <p><italic>Maxilliped</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5f</xref>) basal endite slender, with one simple seta; ischium with two setae; merus and carpus without setae; propodus with one seta; dactylus with one lateral robust seta and distally two long setae, unguis not discernible.</p>
                        <p><italic>Oöstegites</italic> on pereiopods III-IV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3d, e</xref>), suboval, without setae and with 3 button-like processes.</p>
                        <p>Coxal gills on pereiopods III-V.</p>
                        <p><italic>Gnathopod I</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b</xref>) carpo-subchelate, palm strongly oblique, carpus 2.4 times as long as wide, palm margin smooth, not serrated, and with three short, bifid flagellate setae along lateral side of margin, and one simple seta on palm angle in male. In female two of such setae of which one placed closer to the row of three bifid setae. Just posterior to the palmar angle seta is a broad triangular spine on the medial side in the male, and three spines in the female: two smaller ones and a larger, more pointed one. Dactylus with four long spines along posterior margin and thin setules or grooves at the base of the unguis.</p>
                        <p><italic>Gnathopod II</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2c, d</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3c</xref>) Carpo-subchelate, palm oblique, carpus stronger than in gnathopod I, subtrapezoidal, carpal index = 4.6, palm angle defined by one large seta and one smaller spine in female (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>), one seta in male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2c, d</xref>), and with triangular tooth proximal to the palmar angle seta, palm margin with irregular serrations; propodus strong with lobe on lateral side ending in a setule, less pronounced in female; dactylus with four strong teeth enforced with thick margins on lateral side and a groove or bundled setules at the base of the unguis.</p>
                        <p><italic>Pereipods III</italic>-<italic>IV</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3d, e</xref>) with two distal setae on dactylus at the base of the unguis, and three distal setae on propodus, one of them long and apically bifid, unguis apically trifid. Oöstegites with in both pereiopods regularly placed series of 3 button-like processes.</p>
                        <p><italic>Pereiopods V – VII</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4a,b, c</xref>) progressively longer towards P7; basis of P5 broad, that of P7 slender; carpus of P5 with two long and stout distal setae, others shorter; carpus of P7 with broad, curved and modified comb setae; merus of P7 with long distal seta; dactyli with two small setae distally; unguis bifid.</p>
                        <p><italic>Pleopods I-III</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>) subtrapezoidal, without setae. Pleopod I in male deformed or broadened distally.</p>
                        <p><italic>Uropod</italic> I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2e</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4e</xref>) male: protopod with one seta and a row of fine setules on anterolateral margin; exopod with very feeble segment suture and one seta placed at two-thirds the length; endopod with terminal row of spines and four long setae laterally. In female protopod with three setae; endopod with six long setae laterally.</p>
                        <p><italic>Uropod</italic> II (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4d</xref>), protopod with two oblique comb rows in male, and three in female; setae of rows more or less rectangular with bifid or trifid, or even comb-like tips; endopod slightly longer than exopod, sharper, and with four setae.</p>
                        <p><italic>Uropod</italic> III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>) short, 2 segmented, with one ramus, protopod with 2 distal setae, ramus short with 1 distal seta.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Telson (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>) globose, with 1 pair of long dorsal setae.</p>
                        <p>Differences between male and female: gnathopods without extra palmar seta in male, and uropod II without a third comb row in male. Pleopod I in the male has a broadened tip.</p>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 2.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella arganoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype 1.4 mm. <bold>a</bold> habitus, male 1.4 mm <bold>b</bold> left gnathopod I, lateral <bold>c</bold> right gnathopod II, lateral <bold>d</bold> left gnathopod II, medial <bold>e</bold> right uropod I, lateral.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-302-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 3.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella arganoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype 1.4 mm. <bold>a</bold> right uropod II, lateral; female paratype 1.5 mm. <bold>b</bold> right gnathopod I, lateral <bold>c</bold> right gnathopod II, lateral <bold>d</bold> right pereiopod III, lateral <bold>e</bold> right pereiopod IV, lateral.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-302-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 4.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella arganoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female paratype. <bold>a</bold> pereiopod V <bold>b</bold> pereiopod VI <bold>c</bold> pereiopod VII <bold>d</bold> right uropod II, medial <bold>e</bold> left uropod I, lateral.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-302-001-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 5.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella arganoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female paratype. <bold>a</bold> left maxillule <bold>b</bold> maxilla <bold>c</bold> right mandible <bold>d</bold> left mandible <bold>e</bold> right maxillule <bold>f</bold> right maxilliped.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-302-001-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella arganoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. shares most morphological character states with a species found 2500 km southeastward across the Indian Ocean, on the Maldives, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella xarifae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Ruffo, 1966), from washed-out broken coral pieces (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Favites</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.). Species ranges of stygobionts have not been reported to exceed such large distances in the past and molecular work on cryptic lineage diversity of populations of groundwater crustaceans have even diminished existing ranges to distances of less than 1000 km (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Trontelj et al. 2009</xref>).</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->For now, five clear morphological differences justify the designation of a new species that also is geographically quite far away from its nearest congeners. These differences can be observed in the four spines on the medial margin of the propodus of gnathopod I – three spines in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella xarifae</tp:taxon-name></italic>; subtrapezoidal carpus of gnathopod 2 – elongate oval in <italic>xarifae</italic>; palmar index of gnathopod 2 is 4.6 – against 6.4 in xarifae; palm of gnathopod 2 strongly serrate – almost smooth in <italic>xarifae</italic>; pereiopod VII with specialized, combed, robust setae distally on carpus – not present in <italic>xarifae</italic>.</p>
                        <p>The differences in the placement, form and number of setae have shown to be quite consistent in the case of the poorly setose ingolfiellids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Vonk and Sanchez 1991</xref>). The spines and setae that have remained, are perhaps critically functional due to selective reductive factors in the underground environment.</p>
                        <p>The oöstegites have 3 small button-like processes. The same character was described in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella alba</tp:taxon-name></italic> Iannilli et al., 2008, where also three small button-like processes are present, but here from P3 to P5. Re-examination of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella xarifae</tp:taxon-name></italic> typus by Sandro Ruffo and V.I. allowed them to observe also on the oöstegites of this species the button-like processes, as described for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella alba</tp:taxon-name></italic>.Something similar was described in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metaingolfiella mirabilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ruffo, 1969, although the processes were smaller and more numerous. These structures are probably present in other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella</tp:taxon-name></italic> species but have yet to be observed and described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Iannilli et al., 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Stock (1979)</xref> observed in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella quadridentata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Stock, 1979, that oöstegites found on P3 and P4 were: “curved, truncate at tip, provided with 3 apical teeth, but without setae.”</p>
                        <p>In other amphipods with preparatory females (females in a moult stage in between two brooding periods), these structures are sometimes present on the oöstegites (pers. comm. D. Jaume). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Slattery (1985)</xref> mentions the development of oöstegites in infaunal amphipod families of <tp:taxon-name>Phoxocephalidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Haustoriidae</tp:taxon-name> undergoing three stages of development: buds (of the oostegite itself), preparatory (moderately long oöstegites with some setae), and mature (long oöstegites, curved, and setose to form a brood-carrying pouch or marsupium). If the buttons, that occur in threesomes on the oöstegites of pereiopods III and IV in <!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella arganoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, can be observed in other ingolfiellids as being present at the same time with setae this might prove their precursory role. On the other hand, in contradiction to these observations, are our studies of abundant material of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella alba</tp:taxon-name></italic>, that shows this character. The material consists of several individuals collected in different years (from 1992 to 2004) and in different months of the year. We could verify that the structure is always the same, namely the presence of only three button-like processes, and we did not find setae on the oöstegites. So an interpretation of these structures being preparatory setae seems not convincing for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella</tp:taxon-name></italic> species.</p>
                        <p>In agreement with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Ruffo and Vigna Taglianti 1989</xref> the new species could be placed in the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tethydiella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Vonk and Schram (2003)</xref>, basing their phylogeny on more characters, did not use the splitting of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiella</tp:taxon-name></italic> into genus and subgenera as several taxa are poorly described when compared to recent taxonomic descriptions and only few species have both sexes well known.</p>
                        <p>However, the species-groups in sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Ruffo (1970)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Ruffo and Vigna Taglianti (1989)</xref> may still be of practical taxonomic use and the geographical location as well as the morphological diagnosis fits the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tethydiella</tp:taxon-name></italic> group. Of course, more detailed biogeographic data are required to reconstruct the history of the actual distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiellidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Iannilli et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Subterranean thalassoid crustaceans of the region">
            <title>Subterranean thalassoid crustaceans of the region</title>
            <p>The present discovery represents the westernmost record of ingolfiellids in the Indo-Pacific Oceans. The Red Sea shores, Gulf of Aden, and the shores of the Arabian sea are relatively unknown areas for stygobiont and marine interstitial crustaceans. Geographically it is an interesting region as it forms the corridor between the better known Mediterranean and south east Asian/Australian stygofaunas. Sampling by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Stock and Nijssen (1965)</xref> on Entedebir Island in the southern Red Sea revealed the presence of the circumtropical marine groundwater amphipod genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psammogammarus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Vonk and Stock 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Vonk 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Van der Ham and Vonk 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Tomikawa et al. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Vonk et al. 2011</xref>), suggesting the possible occurrence of the usual inhabitants of the present coastal groundwater biotope. In this respect also <italic><tp:taxon-name>Angeliera xarifae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Siewing, 1959 can be mentioned. This is a microparasellid isopod, sampled from coastal groundwater of Abd al Kuri during the Xarifa expedition of 1957 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Wallace and Zahir 2007</xref>). In 2005 Iannilli et al. described the bogidiellid amphipod <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nubigidiella theresiae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, from a freshwater well at Bin Aissa, on Abd al Kuri Island. Until 2005 the only amphipod species known from the subterranean waters of Socotra was <italic><tp:taxon-name>Indoweckelia superstes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Holsinger &amp; Ruffo, 2002, from a water well on the main island of Socotra. These are mainly freshwater subterranean amphipods with well investigated marine affinities. Recently the coastal aquifer waters of Oman showed to contain <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metacrangonyx</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Jaume &amp; Vonk, 2012), a stygobiont amphipod with proven marine origins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bauzà-Ribot et al. 2012</xref>), distributed in marine and freshwaters from the Caribbean to its current eastern border, the Indian Ocean. On Socotra and Abd al Kuri new cyclopoid copepods were described from brackish wells and caves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Mirabdullaev et al. 2002</xref>) showing the island’s isolated status. The first inland, freshwater ingolfiellid of the region, as well as those from deep marine sediments, are still to be discovered.</p>
            <!--PageBreak-->
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We thank Leonardo Latella and Roberta Salmaso (Museo Civico di Storia Naturale, Verona) for help and access to the crustacean collection; Traudl Krapp (Zoologisches Forschungsmuseum Alexander Koenig, Bonn) for her indispensable work on amphipod identifications and cataloguing in the Verona collection; Damiá Jaume (Institut Mediterrani d’Estudis Avanzats, Mallorca) for his comments on peracarid development and taxonomy; Bert Hoeksema (Naturalis Biodiversity Center, Leiden) for close reading; Kees van den Berg (Naturalis Biodiversity Center, Leiden) for new microscopy tools and assistance; and Roberto Argano (University La Sapienza, Rome) for donating his expedition specimens. We dedicate this study, in the warmest remembrance, to the late Sandro Ruffo. The work at the Verona museum by RV was supported by Naturalis bench fee grants of 2011 and 2012.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauzà-Ribot</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juan</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nardi</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oromí</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pons</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaume</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Mitogenomic phylogenetic analysis supports continental-scale vicariance in subterranean thalassoid crustaceans.</article-title> <source>Current Biology</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>2069</fpage>-<lpage>2074</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2012.09.012" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.cub.2012.09.012</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Becking</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Renema</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santodomingo</surname> <given-names>NK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeksema</surname> <given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuti</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Voogd</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Recently discovered landlocked basins in Indonesia reveal high habitat diversity in anchialine systems.</article-title> <source>Hydrobiologia</source> <volume>677</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>105</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10750-011-0742-0" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10750-011-0742-0</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holsinger</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruffo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title><italic>Indoweckelia superstes</italic> n. gen. sp. n. from the subterranean waters of Socotra Island: the first weckeliid amphipod crustacean (Hadziidae) found in the Indo-West Pacific region.</article-title> <source>Bolletino del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale di Verona, Botanica, Zoologia</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Iannilli</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berera</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottarelli</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Description of the first marine interstitial ingolfiellid from Philippines, <italic>Ingolfiella alba</italic> sp. n., with some remarks on the systematic of the genus (Amphipoda: Ingolfiellidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1675</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Iannilli</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruffo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holsinger</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>Nubigidiella theresiae</italic> sp. n. from Abd al Kuri Island, Yemen (Crustacea Amphipoda, Bogidiellidae), with description of a new maxillipedal structure.</article-title> <source>Bollettino del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale di Verona</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaume</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vonk</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Discovery of <italic>Metacrangonyx</italic> in inland groundwaters of Oman (Amphipoda: Gammaridea: Metacrangonyctidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>3335</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirabdullaev</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Damme</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumont</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Freshwater cyclopoids (Crustacea: Copepoda) from the Socotra Archipelago, Yemen, with description of a new species of <italic>Bryocyclops</italic>.</article-title> <source>Fauna of Arabia</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>-<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruffo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1950</year>) <article-title>Considerazione sulla posizione sistematica e sulla distribuzione geografica degli Ingolfiellidi.</article-title> <source>Bollettino dei Musei di Zoologia ed Anatomia Comparata della Reale Università di Torino</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruffo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1966</year>) <article-title><italic>Ingolfiella xarifae</italic> (Crustacea, Amphipoda) nuova specie dell’Oceano Indico.</article-title> <source>Memorie del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale Verona</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>182</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruffo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>) <article-title>Studi sui crostacei anfipodi LXIII: Descrizione di <italic>Metaingolfiella mirabilis</italic> n. gen. sp. n. (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Metaingolfiellidae fam. nova) delle acque sotterranee del Salento nell’Italia meridionale.</article-title> <source>Memorie del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale Verona</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>-<lpage>260</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruffo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>) <source>Considérations à propos de la systématique et de la biogéographie de Ingolfielles (Crustacea Amphipoda). Livre centenaire Emile G. Racovitza: 223–230.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruffo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigna</surname> <given-names>Taglianti A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Description of a new cavernicolous <italic>Ingolfiella</italic> species from Sardinia, with remarks on the systematics of the genus.</article-title> <source>Annali del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale Genova</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>261</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Siewing</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>) <article-title><italic>Angeliera xarifae</italic>, ein neuer Isopode aus dem Küstengrundwasser der Insel Abd-el-Kuri (Golf von Aden).</article-title> <source>Zoologischer Anzeiger</source> <volume>163</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>-<lpage>370</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Slattery</surname> <given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Life histories of infaunal amphipods from subtidal sands of Monterey Bay, California.</article-title> <source>Journal Of Crustacean Biology</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>635</fpage>-<lpage>649</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1548241" xlink:type="simple">10.2307/1548241</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Spooner</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>) <article-title>New members of the British marine bottom fauna.</article-title> <source>Nature</source> <volume>183</volume>: <fpage>1695</fpage>-<lpage>1696</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/1831695b0" xlink:type="simple">10.1038/1831695b0</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Spooner</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1960</year>) <article-title>The occurrence of <italic>Ingolfiella</italic> in the Eddystone shell gravel, with description of a new species. Journal of the Marine Biological Association, U.K.</article-title>  <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>329</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0025315400013357" xlink:type="simple">10.1017/S0025315400013357</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>New data on taxonomy and zoogeography of ingolfiellid Crustacea. Bijdr. Dierk.</article-title>  <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nijssen</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>) <article-title><italic>Eriopisa longiramus</italic> sp. n., a new subterranean amphipod from a Red Sea Island.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the Sea Fisheries Research Station of Israel</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>28</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Taiti</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrara</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The terrestrial Isopoda (Crustacea: Oniscidea) of the Socotra Archipelago.</article-title> <source>Fauna of Arabia</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>-<lpage>325</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomikawa</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kakui</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamasaki</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A new species of <italic>Psammogammarus</italic> (Amphipoda: Melitidae) from Kuchinoerabu Island, Japan, with a note on its feeding habits.</article-title> <source>Zoological Science</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>615</fpage>-<lpage>626</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2108/zsj.27.615" xlink:type="simple">10.2108/zsj.27.615</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Trontelj</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Douady</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fišer</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibert</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorički</surname> <given-names>Š</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefébure</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sket</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zakšek</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>A molecular test for cryptic diversity in ground water: how large are the ranges of macro-stygobionts? Freshwater Biology 54: 727–744.</source> doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2427.2007.01877.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1365-2427.2007.01877.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Van der</surname> <given-names>Ham JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vonk</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A phylogenetic analysis of the <italic>Eriopisa</italic> complex (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Melitidae) and a new species from beach interstitial in Venezuela.</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>779</fpage>-<lpage>796</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222930110108344" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/00222930110108344</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vonk</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title><italic>Psammogammarus stocki</italic> n.sp. (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Melitidae) from beach interstitia on Tenerife.</article-title> <source>Bijdragen tot de Dierkunde</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>271</fpage>-<lpage>276</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vonk</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>A new marine interstitial ingolfiellid (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Ingolfiellidea) from Tenerife and Hierro.</article-title> <source>Hydrobiologia</source> <volume>223</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>-<lpage>299</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF00047646" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/BF00047646</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vonk</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schram</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Ingolfiellidea (Crustacea, Malacostraca, Amphipoda): a phylogenetic and biogeographic analysis.</article-title> <source>Contributions to Zoology</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vonk</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title><italic>Psammogammarus longidactilus</italic> n.sp., a new cave amphipod (Crustacea) and other stygobiont amphipods from Bonaire.</article-title> <source>Stygologia</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>-<lpage>251</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vonk</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeksema</surname> <given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaume</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A new marine interstitial <italic>Psammogammarus</italic> (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Melitidae) from Gura Ici Island, off western Halmahera (North Moluccas, Indonesia), and an overview of the genus.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>73</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.128.1661" xlink:type="simple">10.3897/zookeys.128.1661</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahir</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The “Xarifa” expedition and the atolls of the Maldives, 50 years on.</article-title> <source><italic>Coral Reefs</italic></source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00338-006-0188-4" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00338-006-0188-4</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>