<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.157.1433</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>The adipokinetic hormone family in Chrysomeloidea: structural and functional considerations <xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref>
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Gäde</surname>
                        <given-names>Gerd</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Marco</surname>
                        <given-names>Heather G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Zoology Department, University of Cape Town, Rondebosch, South Africa
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Gerd Gäde (<email xlink:type="simple">gerd.gade@uct.ac.za</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Michael Schmitt</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="other" id="FN1"><p>Contribution to the European Symposium on Chrysomelidae, held August 23, 2010, in Budapest, Hungary</p></fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>21</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>157</issue>
            <fpage>81</fpage>
            <lpage>94</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Gerd Gäde, Heather G. Marco</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The presented work is a hybrid of an overview and an original research paper on peptides belonging to the adipokinetic hormone (AKH) family that are present in the corpora cardiaca of <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomeloidea</tp:taxon-name>. First, we introduce the AKH/red pigment-concentrating hormone (RPCH) peptide family. Second, we collate the available primary sequence data on AKH peptides in <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomelidae</tp:taxon-name>, and we present new sequencing data (from previously unstudied species) obtained by liquid-chromatography coupled with ion trap electrospray ionisation mass spectrometry. Our expanded data set encompasses the primary structure of AKHs from seven species of <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name> and three species of <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomelidae</tp:taxon-name>. All of these species synthesise the octapeptide code-named Peram-CAH-I (pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp amide). Whereas this is the sole AKH peptide in <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomelidae</tp:taxon-name> demonstrate a probable event of AKH gene duplication, thereby giving rise to an additional AKH. This second AKH peptide may be either Emppe-AKH (pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Thr-Pro-Asn-Trp amide) or Peram-CAH-II (pGlu-Leu-Thr-Phe-Thr-Pro-Asn-Trp amide). The peptide distribution and structural data suggest that both families are closely related and that Peram-CAH-I is the ancestral peptide. We hypothesise on the molecular evolution of Emppe-AKH and Peram-CAH-II from the ancestral peptide due to nonsynonymous missense single nucleotide polymorphism in the nucleotide coding sequence of prepro-AKH. Finally, we review the biological significance of the AKH peptides as hyperprolinaemic hormones in <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomeloidea</tp:taxon-name>, i.e. they cause an increase in the circulating concentration of proline. The mobilisation of proline has been demonstrated during flight in both cerambycid and chrysomelid beetles.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Cerambycidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Chrysomelidae</kwd>
                <kwd>adipokinetic hormone</kwd>
                <kwd>structure elucidation</kwd>
                <kwd>mass spectrometry</kwd>
                <kwd>phylogenetic relatedness</kwd>
<!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="1. The adipokinetic hormone (AKH)/red pigment-concentrating hormone (RPCH) family of peptides: general background information"><title>1. The adipokinetic hormone (AKH)/red pigment-concentrating hormone (RPCH) family of peptides: general background information</title>
            <p>Peptides belonging to the AKH/ RPCH family are produced in neurosecretory cells of either the corpora cardiaca (CC) of insects or of the X-organ cells in the eyestalks of decapod crustaceans (see reviews by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Gäde 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Gäde et al. 1997b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Gäde and Marco 2006</xref>). In crustaceans, the classical effect of RPCH is the concentrating movement of pigment granules in integument cells causing a blanching appearance of the whole body (see review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Rao 2001</xref>). In insects, AKHs classically control the mobilisation of fuels for active muscular exertion, such as flight, swimming or running (see reviews by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Gäde 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Gäde and Marco 2009</xref>). Such metabolites can be lipids, carbohydrates or the amino acid proline, and the neuropeptides involved in this action are then generally referred to as adipokinetic (lipid-mobilising), hypertrehalosaemic (increase in the level of the haemolymph sugar, trehalose) or hyperprolinaemic (increase of haemolymph proline levels). After release of the neuropeptides from the CC into the haemolymph during flight for example, they bind to G-protein-coupled receptors, which are known from a limited number of insects to date, and in turn activate either a triacylglycerol lipase or a glycogen phosphorylase in the fat body via diverse second messenger systems (see review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Gäde and Auerswald 2003</xref>). Whereas only two structurally different octapeptides are known from <tp:taxon-name>Crustacea</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Fernlund and Josefsson 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Christie et al. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Marco and Gäde 2010</xref>), about 50 isoforms are known from various insect species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Gäde 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Gäde and Simek 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Marco et al. 2011</xref>). These peptides have the following common structural characteristics: a chain length of 8–10 amino acids, post-translationally modified termini (the N-terminus contains a pyroglutamate residue and the C-terminus is carboxyamidated), at least two aromatic amino acids (at position 4 and 8), a glycine residue at position 9, and largely, but not exclusively, the peptides are uncharged with only 4 of the 50 odd members having a charged asparagine residue at position 7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Gäde 2009</xref>).</p>
            <p>The primary structure of peptides from the AKH/RPCH family have been used as an additional data set to aid in the construction of phylogenies in insect orders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Gäde 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Gäde et al. 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1997</xref>a, 2003a,b; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Gäde and Simek 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Kodrík et al. 2010</xref>). Despite the few character states, these structures supported, for example, a high-level phylogeny for Odonata (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Gäde and Marco 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Gäde et al. 2011</xref>) when used in conjunction with published ideas on Odonata phylogenies (see, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bechly 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Misof 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Ware et al. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Dumont et al. 2010</xref>).</p>
            <p>In the present study we focus on the AKHs from certain beetle families, namely the superfamily <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomeloidea</tp:taxon-name>. Here, we review the previously published data on AKHs in this superfamily and add hitherto unpublished structural data on AKHs of more species from the two subfamilies, <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomelidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name>, with the aim of drawing preliminary conclusions on the putative value of this data set for scientific speculation on relatedness of these families. We also review the current knowledge on the function of AKHs in both subfamilies with respect to the control of substrate availability, especially the amino acid proline.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="2. The AKH/RPCH peptide family in Chrysomeloidea"><title>2. The AKH/RPCH peptide family in <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomeloidea</tp:taxon-name></title>
            <p>The order <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name> constitutes the most species-rich taxon on Earth with approximately 350 000 described species and comprises, therefore, about 40 % of all insect species and about 25 % of all animal species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Hammond 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Grove and Stork 2000</xref>). About 75 % of beetle species are phytophagous and within these “<tp:taxon-name>Phytophaga</tp:taxon-name>” two superfamilies, <tp:taxon-name>Curculionoidea</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomeloidea</tp:taxon-name>, are especially diverse and total about 130 000 species. The <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomeloidea</tp:taxon-name> is usually divided in five families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Crowson 1981</xref>) of which the <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name> (longhorn beetles) and <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomelidae</tp:taxon-name> (leaf beetles) are the most radiated ones with about 35 000 species each. In the current work, we have compiled an AKH data base using seven cerambycid and three chrysomelid species.</p>
            <sec sec-type="2.1. Insects included in the current data set"><title>2.1. Insects included in the current data set</title>
                <p>The cerambycids <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Linnaeus, 1764 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Promeces longipes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier, 1795) were collected in September 2009 and 2010 in the Cedarberg close to Clanwilliam, South Africa, while the eucalyptus borer <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phoracantha recurva</tp:taxon-name></italic> Newman, 1840 was found in the cellar of a house in Cape Town, S. Africa after the purchase and storage of logs from eucalyptus trees which were apparently infested with borer larvae and pupae (2009). The chrysomelid <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina kuesteri</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Helliesen, 1912) was collected at the beginning of November 2007 in a vineyard in Frickenhausen, Germany. The cerambycid <italic><tp:taxon-name>Leptura maculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Poda, 1761 and the chrysomelid <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina fastuosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Scopoli, 1763 were collected in June 2011 in the forest adjacent to the campus of the University of Konstanz in Germany. For collection details of the cerambycids <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis thunbergii</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fåhraeus, 1872, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phryneta spinator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius, 1792) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Morimus funereus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mulsant, 1863, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gäde and Auerswald (2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">2001</xref>), and for the chrysomelid <italic><tp:taxon-name>Leptinotarsa decemlineata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Say, 1824, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Gäde and Kellner (1989)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Gäde (1999)</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="2.2 Structure elucidation and diversity of AKHs"><title>2.2 Structure elucidation and diversity of AKHs</title>
                <p>We followed standard laboratory procedures to identify and obtain the primary structure of AKHs from the CC of <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomeloidea</tp:taxon-name> species. In all cases, the CC were dissected into 80% methanol and extracts were prepared by sonification according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Gäde et al. (1984)</xref>. AKH peptides from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis thunbergii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phryneta spinator</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Leptinotarsa decemlineata</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Morimus funereus</tp:taxon-name></italic> were then purified by reversed-phase high performance liquid chromatography (RP-HPLC) as outlined in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Gäde (1985)</xref> and identified in biological assays; finally, material from active fractions were sequenced by the Edman degradation technique (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Gäde and Kellner 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gäde and Auerswald 2000</xref>).</p>
                <p>For the remaining species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Promeces longipes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phoracantha recurva</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Leptura maculata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina kuesteri</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina fastuosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, peptide material in the CC extracts were analysed directly by <!--PageBreak-->liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry (LC-MS) using a quadropole ion trap mass spectrometer equipped with an electrospray ionisation (ESI) source (instruments and methods as described in detail elsewhere (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Kodrík et al. 2010</xref>). This strategy has been employed successfully for a number of other insect species (see for example <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Gäde et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Gäde and Simek 2010</xref>), and produces clean, easily interpretable data for which only a fraction of gland material is required when compared with enzymatic degradation techniques. For the current study, the mass spectrometry results are exemplarily illustrated from a CC extract of a cerambycid, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>), and of a chrysomelid, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina kuesteri</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"></xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 1.</label>
                    <caption><p> LC-MS analysis of an extract from the corpora cardiaca of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Material from the CC of the cerambycid beetle, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> was extracted with 80% methanol and analysed by LC-MS. <bold>A</bold> The total ion chromatogram <bold>B</bold> A full scan positive electrospray ionisation (ESI) mass spectrum of the peak shown in (<bold>A</bold>) with a retention time of 5.40 min.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-157-081-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <p>The total ion chromatogram of about 0.5 pair equivalent of CC from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> showed one peak of interest at a retention time of 5.40 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>); this peak displays inter alia an ion with highest abundance at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 973.5 for the [M + H]<sup>+</sup> ion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). The primary sequence of the peptide was deduced from the MS<sup>2</sup> spectrum obtained by collision-induced dissociation (CID) of the precursor shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>. The characteristic y-type and b-type product ions, in conjunction with diagnostic ions (i.e. y-NH<sub>3</sub>, y-2NH<sub>3</sub> and b-H<sub>2</sub>O) enabled the assignment of an [M + H]<sup>+</sup> ion as a member of the AKH family (see inset in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Although the alignment of the first two amino acids cannot be inferred from the recorded MS<sup>2</sup> spectrum, we know from the general signature structure of AKHs that pyroglutamate is typically at the N-terminus, which leaves only a valine residue at position two to fill the gap of the measured 99 atomic mass units. Thus, the sequence of the AKH synthesised in the CC of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is assigned as pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp amide which is identical to that of Peram-CAH-I (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Periplaneta americana</tp:taxon-name></italic>-cardioacceleratory hormone-I), which was found for the first time in the cockroach <italic><tp:taxon-name>Periplaneta americana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus, 1758) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Scarborough et al. 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Witten et al. 1984</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 2.</label>
                    <caption><p> The collision-induced dissociation ESI mass spectrum of an AKH peptide in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and its deduced amino acid sequence. The CID MS<sup>2</sup>-ESI spectrum of the ion MH<sup>+</sup> (<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 973.5) in Fig. 1B. The inset shows the assigned peptide sequence (corresponding to that of Peram-CAH-I), together with the theoretical calculated masses for b-type and y-type diagnostic fragment ions which are observed in the MS<sup>2</sup> mass spectrum.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-157-081-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <p>The total ion chromatogram of about 0.8 pair equivalent of CC from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina kuesteri</tp:taxon-name></italic> show three peaks of interest at retention times of 5.02 min (highest abundance), 5.23 min (lowest abundance) and 5.36 min (intermediate abundance) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>); these peaks display ions at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 973.5, 1031.5 and 987.5, respectively for the [M + H]<sup>+</sup> ions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3B-D</xref>). The MS<sup>2</sup> spectra obtained by CID of the respective precursors were recorded. Because the spectrum for [M + H]<sup>+</sup> at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 973.4 was almost identical to the one for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>), the data are not illustrated here, and the underlying AKH was easily assigned as Peram-CAH-I. The MS<sup>2</sup> spectrum for [M + H]<sup>+</sup> at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 987.5 is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>; the interpretation was straightforward, and a peptide with the primary structure of pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Thr-Pro-Asn-Trp amide was assigned, which had previously been found in the CC of the mantid <italic><tp:taxon-name>Empusa pennata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thunberg, 1815) called Emppe-AKH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Gäde 1991</xref>). The third peptide with [M + H]<sup>+</sup> at <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> 1031.5 was assigned as a C-terminal Gly-extended non-amidated form of Peram-CAH-I by its MS<sup>2</sup> spectrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 3.</label>
                    <caption><p> LC-MS analysis of an extract from the corpora cardiaca of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina kuesteri</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Material from the CC of the chrysomelid beetle, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina kuesteri</tp:taxon-name></italic> was extracted with 80% methanol and analysed by LC-MS. (A) The total ion chromatogram. Full scan positive ESI mass spectra of the peaks shown in (<bold>A</bold>) with a retention time of 5.02 min (<bold>B</bold>), 5.23 min (<bold>C</bold>) and 5.36 min (<bold>D</bold>).</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-157-081-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 4.</label>
                    <caption><p> The collision-induced dissociation ESI mass spectrum of an AKH peptide in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina kuesteri</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and its deduced amino acid sequence. The CID MS<sup>2</sup> ESI spectrum of the ion MH<sup>+</sup> at <italic>m</italic>/z 987.5 (see Fig. 3D). The inset shows the sequence of the assigned peptide (corresponding to that of Emppe-AKH), together with the theoretical calculated masses for b-type and y-type diagnostic fragment ions which are observed in the MS<sup>2</sup> mass spectrum.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-157-081-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 5.</label>
                    <caption><p> The collision-induced dissociation ESI mass spectrum of an additional putative AKH peptide in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina kuesteri</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and its deduced amino acid sequence. The CID MS<sup>2</sup> ESI spectrum of the ion MH<sup>+</sup> at <italic>m</italic>/z 1031.5 (see Fig. 3C). The inset shows the sequence of the assigned peptide (corresponding to an intermediate processing form of Peram-CAH-I, i.e. a non-amidated nonapeptide with a Gly residue at position 9). Also shown are the theoretical calculated masses for b-type and y-type diagnostic fragment ions which are observed in the MS<sup>2</sup> mass spectrum.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-157-081-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <p>In the cases detailed above, the assigned amino acid sequence of the native AKHs was confirmed by comparing the retention times, the [M + H]<sup>+</sup> ions and the respective CID-MS<sup>2</sup> spectra with those of the appropriate synthetic peptides; chromatographic and mass spectral properties were always identical (data not shown). For use in such confirmatory studies, synthetic peptides Peram-CAH-I and -II (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Periplaneta americana</tp:taxon-name></italic><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> cardioacceleratory hormone-I and -II) had been purchased from Peninsula Laboratories Inc. (now Bachem Americas Inc., California, USA), while the peptide Emppe-AKH (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Empusa pennata</tp:taxon-name></italic> adipokinetic hormone) had been custom-synthesised by Dr. R. de Milton (Medical School, UCT, South Africa).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="2.3 Primary sequence diversity of AKHs"><title>2.3 Primary sequence diversity of AKHs</title>
                <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> summarises the structural information of AKHs in chrysomeloid beetles known previously from Edman sequencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Gäde and Kellner 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gäde and Auerswald 2000</xref>), and those (hitherto unpublished) that have recently been elucidated by employing direct analysis of the glandular extract via LC-ESI MS. Although mass spectra of AKHs are only shown for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina kuesteri</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the current work, it should be noted that clear sequencing data were obtained for all chrysomeloid beetles studied in this way. Hence, the current study unambiguously identifies AKHs from the two large families of the <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomeloidea</tp:taxon-name> via a combined LC-MS approach in comparison with synthetic peptides. These results are very interesting and revealing. First, all AKH members are octapeptides, no decapeptide has been detected yet in any chrysomeloid beetle. In fact, the only decapeptide member sequenced from ANY beetle species to date is the peptide code-named Declu-CC (pGlu-Leu-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp-Gly-Asn amide; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Decapotoma lunata</tp:taxon-name></italic>-CC) which is biosynthesised in the CC of members of blister beetles (<tp:taxon-name>Meloidae</tp:taxon-name>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Gäde 1995</xref>). Second, all investigated chrysomeloid species contain in their CC the peptide Peram-CAH-I (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). All 7 species of the <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name>, spanning 6 genera, have this peptide as the only AKH member, whereas <!--PageBreak-->the three species of <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomelidae</tp:taxon-name> representing two genera have Peram-CAH-I plus a second AKH peptide (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Interestingly, the two species from the same genus (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina kuesteri</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina fastuosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>) have the same AKH complement. Additionally, what appears to be an incompletely-processed form of Peram-CAH-I is also detected in the CC of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina kuesteri</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). Whether this non-amidated nonapeptide is biologically active, remains to be determined in the future.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Table 1.</label>
                    <caption><p> Adipokinetic hormone sequences in <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomelidae</tp:taxon-name>. Primary sequences of peptides of the adipokinetic hormone family in the corpora cardiaca of various species belonging to the families <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomelidae</tp:taxon-name>.</p></caption>
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Family</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Species</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Amino acid sequence</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Code name of peptide</bold></th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="7" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Phryneta spinator</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peram-CAH-I</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis thunbergii</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peram-CAH-I</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peram-CAH-I</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Promeces longipes</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peram-CAH-I</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Phoracantha recurva</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peram-CAH-I</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Morimus funereus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peram-CAH-I</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Leptura maculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peram-CAH-I</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="6" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Chrysomelidae</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Leptinotarsa decemlineata</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peram-CAH-I</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Leu-Thr-Phe-Thr-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peram-CAH-II</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina kuesteri</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peram-CAH-I</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Thr-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emppe-AKH</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina fastuosa</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Ser-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peram-CAH-I</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGlu-Val-Asn-Phe-Thr-Pro-Asn-Trp amide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emppe-AKH</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>From the data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, it seems that Peram-CAH-I is the ancestral peptide. We propose that the following molecular evolution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>) may have occurred by conservative nucleotide substitutions involving nonsynonymous missense single nucleotide polyphemisms (SNPs) in the DNA:</p>
                <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 6.</label>
                    <caption><p> Putative molecular evolution of adipokinetic peptides in chrysomeloid beetles. A proposed scheme of the molecular evolution of adipokinetic peptides to give rise to the different structures observed in investigated chrysomeloid beetles. The inset shows the genetic code for the respective amino acids involved. Differences in amino acids or code nucleotides are given in bold lettering.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-157-081-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <p>(1)	T in position one of the genetic code for serine (S<sup>5</sup>) in Peram-CAH-I was replaced by A to code for threonine (T<sup>5</sup>) in Emppe-AKH;</p>
                <p>(2)	G in position one of the genetic code for valine (V<sup>2</sup>) in Emppe-AKH was replaced by C to now code for leucine (L<sup>2</sup>) in Pyrap-AKH (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pyrrhocoris apterus</tp:taxon-name></italic>-adipokinetic hormone);</p>
                <p>(3)	A in position two of the genetic code for asparagine (N<sup>3</sup>) in Pyrap-AKH was replaced by C and now codes for threonine (T<sup>3</sup>) in Peram-CAH-II (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
                <p>The proposed scenario outlined above, appears to be the most likely one. An alternative route may have involved the molecular change from Emppe-AKH to Peram-CAH-II via another intermediate peptide where N<sup>3</sup> in Emppe-AKH is first changed to T<sup>3</sup>; we find this to be highly unlikely since none of the 50 completely known AKH structures, to date, has the combination of pGlu-Val-Thr at the N-terminus that is required from such an intermediate AKH.</p>
                <p>The evolutionary steps proposed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> lead to the peptide Pyrap-AKH, which exists in certain heteropteran and homopteran bugs, in a pamphagid grasshopper and in the red flour beetle, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tribolium castaneum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Herbst, 1797) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Gäde 2009</xref>). In <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomelidae</tp:taxon-name>, however, this peptide has not yet been detected. With more chrysomelid beetles to be investigated for their complement of AKH peptides, the proposed hypothesis can be proven or refuted in the future. We would like to emphasise that AKH structures cannot be used as a sole tool for investigation into the phylogenies of <tp:taxon-name>Chrysomelidae</tp:taxon-name>. Phylogenies have been carried out based on morphological and molecular data (for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Duckett et al. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Gomez-Zurita et al. 2007</xref>) and these two pillars will certainly continue to be central in future investigations, with peptide structure and complement used in a supportive context.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="2.4. Functional significance of AKH peptides"><title>2.4. Functional significance of AKH peptides</title>
                <p>Previously, we conducted two sets of experiments to determine which substrate is mobilised by the secretion of an AKH in chrysomeloid beetles.</p>
                <p>In the first set of experiments, we injected the cerambycid beetles, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis thunbergii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phryneta spinator</tp:taxon-name></italic>, with their own CC extract or a low dose of the identified peptide,<!--PageBreak--> Peram-CAH-I, in a synthetic form and measured the concentration of total lipids, total carbohydrates and proline in the haemolymph before injection and 90 min thereafter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gäde and Auerswald 2000</xref>). In both beetles the crude CC extract, as well as the synthetic Peram-CAH-I peptide had a hypertrehalosaemic and hyperprolinaemic effect, i.e. significant increases in the concentration of carbohydrates and proline were measured. In the chrysomelid, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Leptinotarsa decemlineata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, it was shown that injection of conspecific CC extract had a hypertrehalosaemic effect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Gäde and Scheid 1986</xref>) and injection of low doses of synthetic endogenous peptides, Peram-CAH-I and -II, caused a significant increase in the proline concentration in the haemolymph (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Gäde 1999</xref>).</p>
                <p><!--PageBreak-->In the second set of experiments we examined the effect of active flight on substrate levels in the haemolymph of chrysomeloid beetles. In this set-up, the beetles were tethered to a flight mill that was modified to allow lift-generating flight; after a 1 min period of such active flying, the beetle was detached from the mill and kept at rest. In both cerambycid species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceroplesis thunbergii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phryneta spinator</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a small but significant decrease in the concentration of carbohydrates was measured in the haemolymph upon 1 min of flight; there was, however no changes measured in the levels of total lipids. In contrast, the proline concentration in these cerambycid species diminished by 20 to 30 % upon 1 min of flight; following an hour of rest subsequent to a short period of active flight, however, the proline concentration returned to pre-flight levels in the haemolymph (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gäde and Auerswald 2000</xref>). In the chrysomelid beetle, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Leptinotarsa decemlineata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Gäde, 1999), we note very similar results, i.e. a decrease in the circulating proline concentration upon 1 min of flight and subsequent restoration of the pre-flight proline level (at rest) within 1 h of rest after the flight episode. The data indicate that AKH peptides are released during flight, which initiate substrate mobilisation for use by the active muscle tissue. During the restorative phase (resting after flight), the flight muscles are no longer active and, consequently, there is a build-up of the substrates in the haemolymph that were released from stored sources in the fat body (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Gäde 2004</xref>).</p>
                <p>Based on these earlier investigations with chrysomeloid species, we have, thus, shown that proline is used in conjunction with carbohydrates as metabolic fuel to power flight activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Gäde 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gäde and Auerswald 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Gäde and Auerswald 2002</xref>). The pathway that involves proline, ultimately relies on the activation of a lipase which is necessary to provide acetyl-CoA units for the formation of proline from alanine (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Gäde and Auerswald 2003</xref>). This critical step in the process of supplying proline for metabolic use is under the regulatory control of members of the AKH family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Gäde and Auerswald 2003</xref>). We have, however, no information on the respective role played by multiple AKH peptides in fuel mobilisation in an individual insect, e.g. do both AKHs have the same potency and same action in chrysomelid beetles? Further, does the conserved AKH (Peram-CAH-I) in cerambycid beetles hint at a conserved receptor structure? It still remains a biological curiosity as to why certain groups of insects have AKH gene duplication and others not. In conclusion, many more questions remain open in insect studies that may be addressed by additional investigations at different phylogenetic and physiological levels.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>This study was funded in part by grants from the National Research Foundation (Pretoria, South Africa; grants FA2007021300002 and IFR2008071500048 to GG) and the University of Cape Town Research Council (grants to GG and HGM). We are indebted to P. Simek (Ceske Budejovice, Czech Republic) for contributing the mass spectrometric measurements and A. Bellmann (Bremen, Germany) for identifying the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysolina</tp:taxon-name></italic> species, as well as H. Martz and D. Gustav (Konstanz, Germany) for help with collecting and identifying beetle species in Konstanz.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechly</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<source> Morphologische Untersuchungen an Flügelgeäder der rezenten Libellen und deren Stammgruppenvertreter (Insecta: Pterygota: Odonata) unter besonderer Berücksichtigung der Phylogenetischen Systematik und des Grundplanes der Odonata. Petalura 2 (Special Volume): 1–402.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cashman</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stemmler</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Identification of putative crustacean neuropeptides using <italic>in silico</italic> analyses of publicly accessible expressed sequence tags.</article-title> <source>General and Comparative Endocrinology </source> <volume>156</volume>: <fpage>246</fpage>-<lpage>264</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ygcen.2008.01.018" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/j.ygcen.2008.01.018</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Crowson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<source> The Biology of the Coleoptera. Academic Press, New York.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Duckett</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjer</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Relationships among the subfamilies of Chrysomelidae inferred from small subunit ribosomal DNA and morphology, with special emphasis on the relationship among the flea beetles and the Galerucinae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jolivet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santiago-Blay</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>New Developments in the Biology of Chrysomelidae.</issue-title> <source>SPB Academic Publishing, The Hague</source>: <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumont</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vierstraete</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanfleteren</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> A molecular phylogeny of the Odonata (Insecta).</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology </source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>6</fpage>-<lpage>18</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3113.2009.00489.x" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1111/j.1365-3113.2009.00489.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernlund</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Josefsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Crustacean colour change hormone: amino acid sequence and chemical synthesis.</article-title> <source>Science </source> <volume>177</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>175</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.177.4044.173" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1126/science.177.4044.173</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Isolation of the hypertrehalosaemic factors I and II from the corpus cardiacum of the Indian stick insect, <italic>Carausius morosus</italic>, by reversed-phase high-performance liquid chromatography, and amino acid composition of factor II.</article-title> <source>Biological Chemistry Hoppe-Seyler </source> <volume>366</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>-<lpage>199</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1515/bchm3.1985.366.1.195" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1515/bchm3.1985.366.1.195</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> The hypertrehalosaemic peptides of cockroaches: a phylogenetic study.</article-title> <source>General and Comparative Endocrinology </source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>-<lpage>300</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0016-6480(89)90082-8" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/0016-6480(89)90082-8</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> The adipokinetic neuropeptide of Mantodea: sequence elucidation and evolutionary relationships.</article-title> <source>Biological Chemistry Hoppe-Seyler </source> <volume>372</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>201</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1515/bchm3.1991.372.1.193" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1515/bchm3.1991.372.1.193</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> Isolation and identification of AKH/RPCH family peptides in blister beetles (Meloidae).</article-title> <source>Physiological Entomology </source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3032.1995.tb00799.x" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1111/j.1365-3032.1995.tb00799.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> The explosion of structural information on insect neuropeptides.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Herz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steglich</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title> Progress in the Chemistry of Organic Natural Products.</issue-title> <source>Springer-Verlag, Wien, </source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Control of proline as flight substrate in long-horned and leaf beetles by AKH/RPCH neuropeptides.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roubos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wendelaar Bonga</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaudry</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Loof</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Recent Developments in Comparative Endocrinology and Neurobiology.</issue-title> <source>Shaker Publishing, Maastricht</source>: <fpage>308</fpage>-<lpage>310</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Regulation of intermediary metabolism and water balance of insects by neuropeptides.</article-title> <source>Annual Reviews of Entomology </source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Peptides of the adipokinetic hormone/ red pigment-concentrating hormone family. A new take on biodiversity.</article-title> <source>Trends in Comparative Endocrinology and Neurobiology Annual New York Academy of Science </source> <volume>1163</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Auerswald</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Flight substrates and their regulation by a member of the AKH/RPCH family of neuropeptides in Cerambycidae.</article-title> <source>Journal of Insect Physiology </source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1567</fpage>-<lpage>1576</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Auerswald</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Neurohormonal control of proline metabolism in beetles.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Goos</surname><given-names>HJTh</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rastogi</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaudry</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierantoni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Perspective in Comparative Endocrinology: Unity and Diversity.</issue-title> <source>Monduzzi Editore S.p.A., Italy</source>: <fpage>443</fpage>-<lpage>453</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Auerswald</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Beetles’ choice - proline for energy output. Control by AKHs.</article-title> <source>Comparative Biochemistry and Physiology B </source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>-<lpage>128</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S1096-4959(01)00541-3" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/S1096-4959(01)00541-3</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Auerswald</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Mode of action of neuropeptides from the adipokinetic hormone family.</article-title> <source>General and Comparative Endocrinology </source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0016-6480(03)00159-X" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/S0016-6480(03)00159-X</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Auerswald</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Šimek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kodrik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003a</year>)<article-title> Red pigment-concentrating hormone is not limited to crustaceans.</article-title> <source>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications </source> <volume>309</volume>: <fpage>967</fpage>-<lpage>973</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bbrc.2003.08.107" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/j.bbrc.2003.08.107</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grandcolas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kellner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997a</year>)<article-title> Structural data on hypertrehalosaemic neuropeptides from <italic>Cryptocercus punctulatus</italic> and <italic>Therea petiveriana</italic>: how do they fit into the phylogeny of cockroaches?</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society London B.</source> <volume>264</volume>: <fpage>763</fpage>-<lpage>768</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.1997.0108" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1098/rspb.1997.0108</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldsworthy</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kegel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Single step purification of locust adipokinetic hormones I and II by reversed-phase high-performance liquid chromatography and the amino-acid composition of the hormone II.</article-title> <source>Hoppe Seyler’s Zeitschrift für physiologische Chemie </source> <volume>365</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>-<lpage>398</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1515/bchm2.1984.365.1.393" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1515/bchm2.1984.365.1.393</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spring</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997b</year>)<article-title> Hormonal regulation in insects: facts, gaps and future directions.</article-title> <source>Physiological Reviews</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>963</fpage>-<lpage>1032</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kellner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> The metabolic neuropeptides of the corpus cardiacum from the potato beetle and the American cockroach are identical.</article-title> <source>Peptides </source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1287</fpage>-<lpage>1289</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0196-9781(89)90023-5" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/0196-9781(89)90023-5</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> The adipokinetic hormones of Odonata: a phylogenetic approach.</article-title> <source>Journal of Insect Physiology </source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>-<lpage>341</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jinsphys.2004.12.011" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/j.jinsphys.2004.12.011</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> The invertebrate AKH/RPCH family.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kastin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>The Handbook of Biologically Active Peptides.</issue-title> <source>Elsevier, Amsterdam</source>: <fpage>189</fpage>-<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Peptides of the adipokinetic hormone/red pigment-concentrating hormone family with special emphasis on Caelifera: primary sequences and functional considerations contrasting grasshoppers and locusts.</article-title> <source>General and Comparative Endocrinology </source> <volume>162</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ygcen.2008.06.007" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/j.ygcen.2008.06.007</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desutter-Grandcolas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003b</year>)<article-title> A phylogenetic analysis of the adipokinetic neuropeptides of Ensifera.</article-title> <source>Physiological Entomology </source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>-<lpage>289</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3032.2003.00344.x" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1111/j.1365-3032.2003.00344.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beeching</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<source> Molecular evolution of peptides of the AKH/RPCH family. In: Davey KG, Peter RE, Tobe SS (Eds) Perspectives in Comparative Endocrinology, National Research Council of Canada, Ottawa, 119–128.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> A comparative study on the isolation of adipokinetic and hypertrehalosaemic factors from insect corpora cardiaca.</article-title> <source>Physiological Entomology </source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>157</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3032.1986.tb00401.x" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1111/j.1365-3032.1986.tb00401.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> A novel member of the adipokinetic peptide family in a “living fossil”, the ice crawler <italic>Galloisiana yuasai</italic>, is the first identified neuropeptide from the order Grylloblattodea.</article-title> <source>Peptides </source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>372</fpage>-<lpage>376</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.peptides.2009.10.016" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/j.peptides.2009.10.016</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fescemyer</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Adipokinetic hormones provide inference for the phylogeny of Odonata.</article-title> <source>Journal of Insect Physiology </source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>174</fpage>-<lpage>178</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jinsphys.2010.11.002" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/j.jinsphys.2010.11.002</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> The first identified neuropeptide in the insect order Megaloptera: A novel member of the adipokinetic hormone family in the alderfly <italic>Sialis lutaria</italic>.</article-title> <source>Peptides </source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>477</fpage>-<lpage>482</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.peptides.2008.07.022" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/j.peptides.2008.07.022</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Zurita</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopliku</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> Recalibrated tree of leaf beetles (Chrysomelidae) indicates independent diversification of angiosperms and their insect herbivores. PLoS ONE 2 (4): e360. </source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0000360" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0000360</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grove</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stork</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> An inordinate fondness for beetles.</article-title> <source>Invertebrate Taxonomy </source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>733</fpage>-<lpage>739</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/IT00023" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1071/IT00023</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Species inventory.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Groombridge</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed.</role>). <issue-title>Global Diversity, Status of the Earth’s Living Resources.</issue-title> <source>Chapman and Hall, London</source>: <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kodrík</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Šimek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Socha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Štys</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> The adipokinetic hormones of Heteroptera: a comparative study.</article-title> <source>Physiological Entomology</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>-<lpage>127</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3032.2009.00717.x" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1111/j.1365-3032.2009.00717.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Biological activity of the predicted red pigment-concentrating hormone of <italic>Daphnia pulex</italic> in a crustacean and an insect.</article-title> <source>General and Comparative Endocrinology </source> <volume>166</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ygcen.2009.08.002" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/j.ygcen.2009.08.002</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Šimek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gäde</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> The first decapeptide adipokinetic hormone (AKH) in Heteroptera: a novel AKH from a South African saucer bug, <italic>Laccocoris spurcus</italic> (Naucoridae, Laccocorinae).</article-title> <source>Peptides </source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>454</fpage>-<lpage>460</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.peptides.2010.10.015" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/j.peptides.2010.10.015</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Misof</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Diversity of Anisoptera (Odonata): inferring speciation processes from patterns of morphological diversity.</article-title> <source>Zoology </source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>365</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1078/0944-2006-00076" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1078/0944-2006-00076</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Crustacean pigmentary-effector hormones: chemistry and functions of RPCH, PDH, and related peptides.</article-title> <source>American Zoologist </source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>364</fpage>-<lpage>379</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1668/0003-1569(2001)041[0364:CPEHCA]2.0.CO;2" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1668/0003-1569(2001)041[0364:CPEHCA]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Scarborough</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalish</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McEnroe</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schooley</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Isolation and primary structure of two peptides with cardioacceleratory and hyperglycemic activity from the corpora cardiaca of <italic>Periplaneta americana</italic>.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA </source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>5575</fpage>-<lpage>5579</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.81.17.5575" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1073/pnas.81.17.5575</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ware</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>May</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of the higher Libelluloidea (Anisoptera: Odonata): an exploration of the most speciose superfamily of dragonflies.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogeny and Evolution </source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>-<lpage>310</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2007.05.027" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/j.ympev.2007.05.027</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Witten</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Shea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemling</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinehart</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Structures of two cockroach neuropeptides assigned by fast atom bombardment mass spectrometry.</article-title> <source>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications </source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>350</fpage>-<lpage>358</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0006-291X(84)91560-2" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/0006-291X(84)91560-2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>