<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.92.1036</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new species of Leucothoid Amphipod, <italic>Anamixis bananarama</italic>, sp. n., from Shallow Coral Reefs in French Polynesia (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Leucothoidae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>James Darwin</surname> 
                        <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:44494135-041B-452C-8CDA-A20FF412930C</uri></contrib>           
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Krapp-Schickel</surname> 
                        <given-names>Traudl</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:E1B1DCCF-04CB-4B1A-A69B-A7C25EC95A38</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Nova Oceanographic Center, Dania, Florida, USA</aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Forschungsmuseum A. Koenig, Bonn, Germany</aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: James Darwin Thomas (<email xlink:type="simple">thomasjd@nova.edu</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Charles Oliver Coleman</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
            	    <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>28</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>92</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>8</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>31</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>9</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>James Darwin Thomas, Traudl Krapp-Schickel</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:A1FD8DA7-C01B-4B5E-9AEF-041990BDE8A1</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Both leucomorph and anamorph developmental stages of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, are illustrated and described from shallow back reef environments of Moorea, French Polynesia. Distinguished by vestigial first gnathopods that persist in post-transformational adult males, this is the second species in the genus to exhibit this unusual character. In other features such as coxae and second gnathopods <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> resembles other Pacific Plate endemics of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis</tp:taxon-name></italic> known from the region. Specific host association is not documented but suspected to be small calcareous asconoid sponges associated with coral rubble.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Amphipod</kwd>
                <kwd>Leucothoidae</kwd>
                <kwd>sponge</kwd>
                <kwd>Coral reefs</kwd>
                <kwd>French Polynesia</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Leucothoid amphipods are of interest for their unusual ecology as commensal inhabitants of sessile invertebrates such as sponges, sea squirts, and bivalves. Obligate commensal species have evolved highly characteristic and unusual morphologies and feeding strategies as <!--PageBreak-->a consequence of their way of life, including eusocial structure, a condition once thought limited to insects and naked mole rats. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Duffy (1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2003</xref>) first documented eusocial behavior in marine sponge-inhabiting snapping shrimp. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Thomas (1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">1997</xref>) documented eusociality and communal living in highly derived tropical leucothoids in the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Thiel (1999)</xref> reported on nest guarding in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Leucothoe spinicarpa</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Florida, USA. Because of their cryptic lifestyle and need for specialized collecting methods, leucothoid diversity has been vastly underrepresented in museum collections. Specialized <italic>in-situ</italic> underwater collecting techniques pioneered by the first author are beginning to reveal the extent of leucothoid diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Thomas 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Thomas and Klebba 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">White and Thomas 2010</xref>). The 22 species in genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Stebbing, 1897, are primarily tropical – warm temperate in distribution. Their greatest diversity is in the Pacific with 14 species, followed by the Indian Ocean with five species, and the Caribbean Sea and Western Atlantic with four species. Further specialized collecting of host and symbiont will undoubtedly significantly expand the addition of new taxa in the <tp:taxon-name>Leucothoidae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Thomas and Barnard (1983)</xref> announced the transformation of males of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Leucothoides pottsi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, originally belonging to <tp:taxon-name>Leucothoidae</tp:taxon-name> Dana, 1852, into hyperadult males of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis hanseni</tp:taxon-name></italic> belonging to <tp:taxon-name>Anamixidae</tp:taxon-name> Stebbing, 1897 [now <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis cavatura</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thomas, 1997)], but avoided synymymising the two families. In 2000, Lowry and colleagues merged the <tp:taxon-name>Anamixidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Leucothoidae</tp:taxon-name> (Lowry et al, 2000). With the addition of both anamorph and leucomorph descriptions in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. this proposed familial restructuring now comprises 139 species in six genera: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Stebbing, 1897 (22 spp.); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nepanamixis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thomas, 1997 (4 spp.); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranamixis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schellenberg, 1938 (13 spp.); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Leucothoe</tp:taxon-name></italic> Leach, 1814 (96 spp.); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Leucothoella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schellenberg, 1928 (2 spp.); and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paraleucothoe</tp:taxon-name></italic> Stebbing, 1899 (2 spp.). A full taxonomic database for the <tp:taxon-name>Leucothoidae</tp:taxon-name> with hyperlinks to illustrations is available (Thomas, 1999) at: http://www.nova.edu/ocean/jthomas/Current_Leucothoidae_7_09.pdf</p>
            <p>In a study of leucothoids from Florida and Belize reefs, the first author and graduate students documented 43 invertebrate host species for Caribbean leucothoids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Thomas and Klebba 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">2007</xref>). These results combined with the recent addition of Lizard Island (Australia) species of leucothoids underscore the high level of undiscovered leucothoid diversity and illustrate how specialized field collecting can lead to new taxonomic discovery. Despite current taxonomic limitations, the <tp:taxon-name>Leucothoidae</tp:taxon-name> remain objects of intense interest due to their intriguing ecology, endocommensal lifestyle, and emerging biogeographic patterns.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
            <p>Specimens were collected by snorkeling and SCUBA. Rubble and other shallow algal substrates were isolated <italic>in-situ</italic> and processed by elutriation. In the lab juvenile (leucomorph) and adult males (anamorphs) were separated and photographed using AutoMontage©. Specimens were fixed in 100% ETOH for molecular analysis and in 2% buffered formalin for dissection and illustration. Type material is deposited in the<!--PageBreak--> collections of the Florida Museum of Natural History in Gainesville, Florida with the prefix “UF” for museum numbers.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Anamixis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">bananarama</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C57C627F-D2F5-48CD-94C9-5868B6144F96</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Anamixis_bananarama</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"/>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                    <p><italic>Holotype</italic>, Anamorph male “A”, 2.34mm, UF 26542, <italic>Paratype</italic>, leucomorph female “B”, 2.10mm; UF 26543; Cook’s Bay, Moorea, French Polynesia, J.D. Thomas collector, 4 December 2009, JDT Moorea 09–4 (South-17.48220:West-149.82530). Wash of backreef rubble, 1–2m. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Additional paratypes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, female leucomorphs (7 specimens), UF 26544, Cook’s Bay, Moorea, French Polynesia, J.D. Thomas collector, 11 December 2009, JDT-Moorea 09–10 (South 17.59205:West-149.835211) coral rubble, coralgal sand, and coral heads, 2–3m.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Additional material"><title>Additional material.</title>
                    <p>Hans-Georg Mueller collector; 27 February to 6 March 1988, shallow reef, Bora Bora.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Terminal anamorph males: Eyes with 7 scattered ommatidia; gnathopod 1 greatly reduced, shriveled, persisting in post-transformational stages. Gnathopod 2, basis greatly elongated, narrow; carpus elongate, apically blunt, with reduced setal tufts on medial margin; propodus with sparse mediofacial setal row. Telson elongate for genus, 1.72 times longer than wide.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Head margin broadly rounded, lacking any defining processes; ventral keel, anterior margin rounded, with small midapical indentation; eyes reduced, consisting of 7 scattered ommatidial facets. Antenna 1, ratio of segments 1–3, 43:33:28, peduncle segment 1 and 2 with 3 and 2 plumose setae respectively; flagellum 6-articulate, articles 3–6 with aesthetascs. Antenna 2, flagellum short, 4-articulate. Maxilliped, inner plates fused, apically produced, apical margin with small concave excavation; outer plates lacking inner lobes; palp article 4, 1.36 times length of article 3. Pereonite 1 with small lateral locking ridge.</p>
                    <p>Gnathopod 1, coxa greatly reduced, apically bifid; remainder of appendage a small bud, articles 2–5 extremely reduced and shriveled. Gnathopod 2, coxa extending deeper than coxa 3–4, distal margin evenly rounded, bearing 10 mediodistal submarginal setules; basis thin, elongate; carpus slightly curved, blunt, reaching 85 percent of propodus, with 6 medial clusters of setae: 2:(2+3):(3+3):(4+1):3:1, distal margin with 5 small submarginal setules; propodus with single row of 7 mediofacial feeding setae, extending 43 percent of propodus length, posterior margin smooth with 3 submarginal setae, anterior margin with 2 prominent apically truncate processes; dactyl straight, inner surface smooth with paired setae on small process near apex, reaching 83 percent on propodus.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->Pereopod 3, coxa smaller than 4, rounded ventrally, anterior and posterior margins straight; remainder of pereopods unremarkable. Pereopod 4, coxa slightly larger than 3, posterior margin slightly expanded, remainder of peropod similar to pereopod 3. Pereopods 5–6, coxae bilobed; pereopod 7, coxa entire. Epimera normal for genus. Uropods 1–2, outer rami shortened, approximately 40 percent of inner ramus. Uropod<!--PageBreak--> 3, outer ramus 40 percent of inner ramus, outer and inner rami with 1 and 2 marginal spines respectively. Telson 1.70 times longer than wide, with 2 apical setae.</p>
                    <p><bold>Leucomorph.</bold> Description of female leucomorph. Head, anterior margin rounded, smooth, eyes consisting of 7 scattered ommatidial facets. Antenna 1, ratio of segments 1–3, 33:26:23; flagellum 5-articulate, articles 4 and 5 with aesthetascs. Antenna <!--PageBreak-->2, flagellum short, 5-articulate. Gnathopod 1, coxa moderately reduced, extending to ventral margin of head, apically bifid; carpus shorter than propodus, with two apical recurved spines, anterior margin bare; propodus, posterior margin finely serrate, bearing a thick recurved apical seta. Gnathopod 2, anterior margin of coxa broadly rounded, ventral margin slightly produced, posteroventral corner with small cusp, posterior margin straight; propodus, palm angle transverse, palmar margin defined by series of concavities and processes, corner of palm defined by distinct cusp; dactyl reaching to end of palm. Telson 1.72 times longer than wide, with 2 apical setae.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype, anamorph male male ”A”, 2.34 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-092-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., paratype, leucomorph female “B”, 2.10mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-092-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 3.</label> 
                        <caption><p>AutoMontage Z-stacked photograph of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype, anamorph male male ”A”, 2.34 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-092-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>This species is named for the long recurved carpal lobe on the second gnathopod that resembles the shape of a banana.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Relationships"><title>Relationships.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> shares it closest affinity with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis jebbi</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Madang Lagoon, Papua New Guinea, (Thomas, 1997), with both species having 7 ommatidial facets in both leucomorph and anamorph stages, and a reduced, vestigial first gnathopod in the post transformational anamorph stage. The second gnathopod of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis jebbi</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the elongate basis, the more blunt and less<!--PageBreak--> setose carpus, and reduced mediofacial setal row (7 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic>; 14 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis jebbi</tp:taxon-name></italic>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> exhibits an elongated telson typical of ratios found in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nepanamixis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thomas, 1997). Both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis jebbi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> show transitional characters placing them in a clade by themselves with the elongate telson of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> placing it nearer to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nepanamixis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in this regard. The telson of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> at 1.70 times longer than wide exceeds that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis jebbi</tp:taxon-name></italic> at 1.32 and approaches the telson ratios typical of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nepanamixis</tp:taxon-name></italic> at 1.8–2.0 times longer than wide.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>Color in life and in freshly collected and preserved material of both leucomorph and anamorph stages are pale translucent pink. There is faint thin reddish banding on posterior thoracic and abdominal segments. Eyes are red. Ovigerous females contain an average of 7–10 yellow eggs in the marsupium.</p>
                    <p>The vestigial first gnathopods found in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis bananarama</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anamixis jebbi</tp:taxon-name></italic> are persistent morphologies in post transformational anamorphs in both taxa. A number of specimens were examined by the first author to ensure these were not transitional transformational features as reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Thomas (1997)</xref> in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranamixis clarkae</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Seychelles Islands. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranamixis clarkae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, transformational anamorphs exhibit small shrunken vestiges of gnathopod 1 which are lost in subsequent molts. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Ren (2006)</xref> described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranamixis vestigium</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the South China Sea, illustrating similar reduced first gnathopods. In all other aspects <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranamixis vestigium</tp:taxon-name></italic> resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranamixis misakiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Thomas (1997)</xref> from Japan and examination of a series of anamorph specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranamixis vestigium</tp:taxon-name></italic> is needed to resolve whether these vestigial first gnathopods persist in post-transformational molts.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Habitat"><title>Habitat.</title>
                    <p>Specific habitat/host undocumented but assumed to be small asconoid calcareous sponges in protected rubble habitats in backreef environments.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Moorea and Bora Bora, French Polynesia, Pacific Ocean. 1–3m.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>The first author was supported by the BioCode project with support from the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation and a President’s Faculty Research Grant from Nova Southeastern University. The first author was assisted in the field by Kristine White and Sharein El Tourky. Photographer David Littschwager, on assignment in Moorea for National Geographic Magazine, helped render color photographs of the type specimen in AutoMontage©. Colleagues Oliver Coleman and Alan Myers provided editorial improvements to the draft manuscript.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Eusociality in a coral-reef shrimp.</article-title> <source>Nature</source> <volume>381</volume>:<fpage>512</fpage>-<lpage>514</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/381512a0" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1038/381512a0</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> The ecology and evolution of eusociality in sponge-dwelling shrimp.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Higashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Genes, behavior, and evolution in social insects.</source> <publisher-name>University of Hokkaido Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Sapporo</publisher-loc>, <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>254</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> Fauna Sinica, Invertebrata, volume 41, Crustacea, Amphipoda, Gammaridea (i).</source> <publisher-name>Science Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Bejing</publisher-loc>, 588 pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Host-use and population demographics of the ascidian-dwelling amphipod <italic>Leucothoe spinicarpa</italic> : indication for extended parental care and advanced social behaviour.</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History</source> <volume>1999</volume> (<issue>33</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>206</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/002229399300371" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1080/002229399300371</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Systematics and Phylogeny of the commensal amphipod family Anamixidae (Crustacea: Amphipoda).</article-title> <source>Records of the Australian Museum</source>, Volume <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>, figures 1–27–187.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> Biological monitoring and tropical biodiversity in marine environments: a critique with recommendations, and comments on the use of amphipods as bioindicators.</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History,</source> <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>795</fpage>-<lpage>806</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222939300770481" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1080/00222939300770481</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> Transformation of the <italic>Leucothoides</italic> morph to the <italic>Anamixis</italic> morph (Amphipoda).</article-title> <source>Journal of Crustacean Biology</source> <volume>3</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>154</fpage>-<lpage>157</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1547860" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.2307/1547860</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klebba</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> New species and host associations of commensal leucothoid amphipods from coral reefs in Florida and Belize (Crustacea: Amphipoda).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1494</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>, 27 figures.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klebba</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Studies of commensal leucothoid amphipods: two new sponge-inhabiting species from south Florida and the western Caribbean.</article-title> <source>Journal of Crustacean Biology</source> <volume>26</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1651/C-2624.1" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1651/C-2624.1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Leucothoidae. In: Lowry JK, Myers AA (Eds) Amphipoda of the Great Barrier Reef, Australia.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2260</volume>:<fpage>494</fpage>-<lpage>555</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>