<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.149.1516</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>The Lepidoptera of White Sands National Monument, Otero County, New Mexico, USA 2. Rediscovery and description of 
                    <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Grote, 1883) (Noctuidae, Noctuinae, Hadenini)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Metzler</surname>
                        <given-names>Eric H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Forbes</surname>
                        <given-names>Gregory S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Adjunct Curator of Lepidoptera, Michigan State University, P.O. Box 45, Alamogordo, NM 88311–0045 U.S.A.
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>1009 Luna St, Las Cruces, New Mexico 88001 U.S.A.
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Eric H. Metzler (<email xlink:type="simple">metzlere@msu.edu</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Donald Lafontaine </p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>149</issue>
            <fpage>117</fpage>
            <lpage>123</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>13</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>13</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Eric H. Metzler, Gregory S. Forbes</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>In 2006 the U.S. National Park Service initiated a long term study of the <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> at White Sands National Monument, Otero County, New Mexico. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Grote, 1883), previously known only from historical specimens collected in Arizona and New Mexico, was discovered in the Monument in 2007 during the second year of the study. The adult moths and male and female genitalia are illustrated for the first time.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><italic>Sparkia immacula</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>Tularosa Basin</kwd>
                <kwd>biological diversity</kwd>
                <kwd>white gypsum dunes</kwd>
                <kwd>Noctuidae</kwd>
                <kwd>White Sands National Monument</kwd>
                <kwd>New Mexico</kwd>
                <kwd>National Park</kwd>
                <kwd>Otero County</kwd>
                <kwd>Arizona</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>In 2006 the U.S. National Park Service invited the author to initiate a long-term study of the <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> at White Sands National Monument, Otero County, New Mexico. A primary purpose of the study was to compile an inventory of moths in habitats within and immediately adjacent to the white gypsum sand dunes in the Monument.</p>
            <p>White Sands National Monument preserves 285 km<sup>2</sup> (110 mi<sup>2</sup>), or about 40%, of the world’s largest snow-white gypsum dune field. The remainder of the 712 km<sup>2</sup> (275 mi<sup>2</sup>) dune field is under the jurisdiction of the U.S. Army in the White Sands Missile Range. The dune field is located in the northern Chihuahuan Desert in southern New Mexico’s Tularosa Basin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Schneider-Hector 1993</xref>). A complete description of the study site and some of its unique biological resources is in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Metzler et al. (2009)</xref>.</p>
            <p>There is a dearth of research on the invertebrate fauna in the gypsum dune field in the Tularosa Basin of New Mexico. Details of previous research pertinent to insects is given in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Metzler et al. (2009)</xref>.</p>
            <p>In the period extending from 9 February 2007 through 31 December 2010 we identified more than 430 species of <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> (Metzler et al. unpublished data) from the Monument. This is the fourth in a series of papers pertinent to a detailed study of the <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> at White Sands National Monument (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Metzler et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Metzler et al. 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Metzler et al. 2010b</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>More than 250 samples of moths and other night flying insects were collected on 75 different nights in U.S.D.A. type black light traps, and at a black light or a mercury vapor light and sheet, as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Covell (1984)</xref>. A detailed description of the study methods is given in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Metzler et al. (2009)</xref>.</p>
            <p>Genitalia were examined following procedures outlined in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Clarke (1941)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hardwick (1950)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Lafontaine (2004)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Pogue (2002)</xref>. Abdomens were removed from the moths, wetted in 95% ethyl alcohol, and, using a dry bath, they were soaked in 10% KOH for 1.5 hours at 50°C. Genitalia were dissected in 5% ethyl alcohol, stained with Safranin O in 95% ethyl alcohol and Chlorazol Black E in water, dehydrated in 100% ethyl alcohol, cleared in clove oil, rinsed in xylene, and slide mounted in Canada balsam.</p>
            <p>Terminology for elements of wing pattern, morphology, and genital structures follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Forbes (1954)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Lafontaine (2004)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Mikkola et al. (2009)</xref>. Forewing lengths were measured to the nearest ½ mm, from the base to the apex excluding fringe, using a stereo-microscope.</p>
            <p>All specimens collected as part of a long-term study of <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> at White Sands National Monument are deposited in the following collections:</p>
            <p><abbrev>EHM<def><p>	personal collection of Eric H. Metzler, Alamogordo, New Mexico, USA, for subsequent transfer to MSU</p></def></abbrev></p>
            <p><abbrev>MSU<def><p>	Albert J. Cook Arthropod Research Collection, Department of Entomology, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, USA</p></def></abbrev></p>
            <p><abbrev>NMSU<def><p>	New Mexico State University Arthropod Collection, Las Cruces, New Mexico, USA</p></def></abbrev></p><!--PageBreak-->
            <p><abbrev>UNM<def><p>	Museum of Southwestern Biology, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, New Mexico, USA</p></def></abbrev></p>
            <p><abbrev>WHSA<def><p>	White Sands National Monument, New Mexico, USA</p></def></abbrev></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results"><title>Results</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Sparkia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">immacula</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Sparkia_immacula</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Grote, 1883)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">5, 6</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">7</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cea immacula</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Grote 1883b</xref>: 78</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name><comment>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Nye 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Franclemont 1983</xref>.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic> was described from “Arizona.” The male holotype is deposited in the U.S. National Museum, Washington, DC (USNM). The abdomen of the holotype is missing. Another short series of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic>, from Arizona, in the USNM, contains one male, also missing its abdomen.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figs 1–2</xref>) is a pale greenish-yellow noctuid moth without normal transverse markings or spots. The diagnostic features are 1) the pale yellowish-green color, and 2) lack of normal transverse markings and spots. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic> might be mistaken for a species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schinia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hübner, but <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schinia</tp:taxon-name></italic> have spines on the foretibia which are lacking in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic> flies with and is the same size as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichocosmia inornata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Grote 1883a</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figs 3–4</xref>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichocosmia inornata</tp:taxon-name></italic> is pale tan-ochre with faint transverse markings and a faint reniform spot. The frons is slightly rounded out.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–4.</label>
                        <caption><p> <bold>1</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Grote) male <bold>2</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Grote) female <bold>3</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichocosmia inornata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Grote male <bold>4</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichocosmia inornata</tp:taxon-name></italic> 0 female.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-149-117-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Adult male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1</xref>). Head - front bulging, closely scaled, pale yellow and white; vertex scales narrow strap-like, erect, pale yellow and white; labial palpus white and pale yellow, erect, scales strap-like, closely scaled laterally and mesally, longer scales form longer fringe ventrally and shorter fringe dorsally. Haustellum coiled between labial palpi. Antenna filiform, dorsally pale yellow, closely scaled, ventrally setose, naked, brown. Thorax - dorsum pale yellow, scales long hair-like or strap-like; underside white, scales erect long hair-like. Legs pale yellow, closely scaled with long hair-like scales on ventral surface forming a shaggy fringe. Forewing: Length 12.5 mm (variation: 11.4–13.5 mm, mean 12.7 mm, n = 17.) Pale greenish yellow, transverse lines and spots typical of noctuines are absent; fringe pale yellow; underside pale greenish yellow; fringe pale greenish yellow. Hindwing white; fringe white; underside white; fringe white. Abdomen <bold>-</bold> dorsum closely scaled, whitish; underside whitish, closely scaled. Genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 5</xref>): tegumen expanded laterally with lateral lobes, uncus short, setose, spoon shaped; saccus short, U shaped, apex rounded; juxta with high ridge pointed anteriorly; valve tear drop shaped, costa sclerotized, ventral margin membranous, editum sclerotized, larger on right valve than left valve, digitus a sclerotized ridge <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->in a thumb-like projection, sacculus sclerotized, well developed, cucullus moderately developed, corona with many mesally directed setae. Aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 6</xref>) sclerotized, apex with blunt point, vesica membranous, straight, slightly shorter (.9×) than aedeagus, no diverticula, apex with strong cornutus.</p>
                    <p>Adult female (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 2</xref>): similar to male. Forewing length 12.5 - 14 mm, mean 13.1 mm, n = 9. Genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 7</xref>): Papilla analis not sclerotized, setose; posterior apophysis extend anteriorly to posterior margin of eighth segment; anterior apophysis length similar to posterior apophysis; ductus bursa sclerotized at posterior end, else membranous, elongate; corpus bursa oblong with four round signa.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 5–6.</label>
                        <caption><p> <bold>5</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic> male genitalia capsule <bold>6</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic> male genitalia aedeagus.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-149-117-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 7.</label>
                        <caption><p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic> female genitalia.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-149-117-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sparkia immacula</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known from Arizona and New Mexico. Adult flight dates are 20 June through 25 August. The immature stages are unknown.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>The study of <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> at White Sands National Monument is projected to last approximately 10 years.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>The Western National Parks Association, Tucson, Arizona contributed funding for travel for this study of <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> at White Sands National Monument. We are especially grateful for their financial support.</p>
            <p>Several persons, Hildy Reiser, Diane White, Cliff Spencer, and Kevin R. Schneider, from the U.S. National Park Service were instrumental in arranging and promoting this study of the moths at White Sands National Monument. We especially thank David Bustos from White Sands National Monument for his assistance and support of our research. The National Park Service renewed the study for 2007 through 2011. Representatives from research collections provided insect pins, alcohol, identification services, research consultation, and storage space for specimens collected. We thank the following persons for offering support from their respective institutions: David B. Richman (NMSU) Kelly B. Miller, Sandra L. Brantley, and David C. Lightfoot (UNM), Frederick W. Stehr, Anthony I. Cognato, Gary L. Parsons, and Richard W. Merritt (MSU), Charles V. Covell, Jr., Jacqueline Y. Miller, and Thomas C. Emmel (UFL), J. Donald Lafontaine (CNC), Larry Berger Ohio Department of Agriculture, and David G. Furth (USNM). Patricia A. Metzler faithfully accompanied Metzler on his many collecting trips to the Monument, and she accompanied him on several long driving trips to Washington, DC for the purpose of identifying specimens. She contributed financially to the study. We thank Gary Parsons, John W. Brown, Clifford D. Ferris, J. Donald Lafontaine, and two anonymous reviewers for reading the paper and offering valuable suggestion<!--PageBreak-->s.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDunnough</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1911</year>)<article-title> On <italic>Cea immacula</italic> and allied species. Can. Ent.</article-title> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>318</fpage>-<lpage>320</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/Ent43318-9" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.4039/Ent43318-9</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>JFG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1941</year>)<article-title> The preparation of slides of the genitalia of Lepidoptera.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the Brooklyn Entomological Society </source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Covell</surname><given-names>Jr. CV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<source> A Field Guide to Moths of Eastern North America. Virginia Museum of Natural History Special Publication Number 12.</source> <publisher-name>Martinsville</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Virginia</publisher-loc>, <lpage>496</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>WTM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1954</year>)<source> Lepidoptera of New York and Neighboring States, Noctuidae, Part III. Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station Memoir 329.</source> <publisher-name>Ithaca</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <lpage>433</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Franclemont</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<source> Noctuidae. In: Hodges RW, Dominick T, Davis DR, Ferguson DC, Franclemont JG, Munroe EG, Powell JA (1983) Check List of the Lepidoptera of America North of Mexico. E. W. Classey Ltd, London and The Wedge Entomological Research Foundation Washington, xxiv + 284 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grote</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1883a</year>)<article-title> New species and notes on structure of moths and genera.</article-title> <source>The Canadian Entomologist </source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/Ent153-1" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.4039/Ent153-1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grote</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1883b</year>)<article-title> Notes on new species in Mr. Neumoegen’s collection.</article-title> <source>Papilio </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardwick</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1950</year>)<article-title> Preparation of slide mounts of lepidopterous genitalia.</article-title> <source>The Canadian Entomologist </source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>235</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/Ent82231-11" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.4039/Ent82231-11</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafontaine</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<source> The Moths of North America Including Greenland, Fascicle 27.1, Noctuoidea Noctuidae (part) Noctuinae (part – Agrotini).</source> <publisher-name>The Wedge Entomological Research Foundation, Washington</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>DC</publisher-loc>, <lpage>385</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzler</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bustos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> The Lepidoptera of White Sands National Monument, Otero County, New Mexico, USA 1. Two new species of Noctuidae (Lepidoptera, Noctuinae, Agrotini).</article-title> <source>ZooKeys </source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.9.182" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.3897/zookeys.9.182</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzler</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bustos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010a</year>)<source> Moth Studies at White Sands National Monument. In: Greenwald David H (Ed) A Walk Through Time - The Tularosa Basin’s Past, 2009 Tularosa Basin Conference Proceedings. CD-ROM.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzler</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bustos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010b</year>)<article-title> First records, representing major range extensions, of three species of Lepidoptera (Erebidae, Noctuidae, and Lasiocampidae) from New Mexico.</article-title> <source>Southwestern Entomologist </source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>311</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3958/059.035.0309" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.3958/059.035.0309</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikkola</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafontaine</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> The Moths of North America including Greenland Fascicle 26.9 Noctuoidea Noctuidae (part) Xyleninae (part) Apameini (part – <italic>Apamea</italic> group of genera).</source> <publisher-name>The Wedge Entomological Research Foundation, Washington</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>DC</publisher-loc>, <lpage>192</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nye</surname><given-names>IWB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>)<source> The generic names of moths of the world, Volume 1 Noctuoidea (part): Noctuidae, Agaristidae, and Nolidae. London: British Museum (Natural History), 568 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pogue</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> A World revision of the genus <italic>Spodoptera</italic> Guenée (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae).</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the American Entomological Society </source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>202</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider-Hector</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<source> White Sands The History of a National Monument.</source> <publisher-name>The University of New Mexico Press. Albuquerque</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New Mexico</publisher-loc>, <lpage>270</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>