<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.255.3272</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Eleven new species of theridiosomatid spiders from southern China (Araneae, Theridiosomatidae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Zhao</surname>
                        <given-names>Qingyuan</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:37C8117C-D5AE-4900-9FE6-E89AC30554CE</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Li</surname>
                        <given-names>Shuqiang</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:0968F85E-881F-43FD-8E6A-BE570F9E334F</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100101, China
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, China
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Shuqiang Li (<email xlink:type="simple">lisq@ioz.ac.cn</email>)
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: J. Miller</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>27</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>255</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>48</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>23</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>13</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Qingyuan Zhao, Shuqiang Li</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:86859633-2784-4A09-B94E-84AD84537078</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Two new genera of the spider family <tp:taxon-name>Theridiosomatidae</tp:taxon-name>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>gen.n.</bold> with the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Menglunia</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>gen.n.</bold> with the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Menglunia inaffecta</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, are described from Guizhou and Yunnan, China. Nine more new species from Guangxi, Guizhou, Hainan and Yunnan Provinces of southern China are described: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub rastrarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>,<italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub youyiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia nitida</tp:taxon-name></italic><bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia prolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>,<italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius hapalus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma plumaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma triumphalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma vimineum</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma fascia</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> The type specimens are deposited in the Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences in Beijing.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Biodiversity</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>canopy</kwd>
                <kwd>cave</kwd>
                <kwd>leaf litter</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Theridiosomatids are small (usually ≤ 3mm), widely distributed, and cryptozoic spiders, which can be found in damp, dark habitats (litter layer of forest or caves). They can be easily recognized by the presence of a pair of pits on the anterior margin of the sternum near the labial base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9D</xref>), the disproportionately large globular pedipalps (except for genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Menglunia</tp:taxon-name></italic>), and the long dorsal trichobothria on the third and fourth tibia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Coddington 1986</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>The genera of family <tp:taxon-name>Theridiosomatidae</tp:taxon-name> were reviewed and revised by Coddington in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">1986</xref>. Based on cladistic analysis, he recognized 4 subfamilies: <tp:taxon-name>Platoninae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Epeirotypinae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Ogulniinae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Theridiosomatinae</tp:taxon-name>. He also described/redescribed 9 genera and validated 28 species in his paper. Since then, 5 new genera and 25 new species have been discovered worldwide. In <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">2011</xref>, Wunderlich introduced three new theridiosomatid species from Laos and recognized one new subfamily: <tp:taxon-name>Luangnaminae</tp:taxon-name>. He also downgraded <tp:taxon-name>Platoninae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Epeirotypinae</tp:taxon-name>, and <tp:taxon-name>Ogulniinae</tp:taxon-name> to tribal rank based on rare or special characters. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Platnick (2012)</xref>, there are currently 16 genera and 89 species belonging to this family. Three widespread genera including <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wendilgarda</tp:taxon-name></italic>, can be found in China and other Asian countries. The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coddingtonia</tp:taxon-name></italic> was the first genus known only from China. As a monotypic genus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coddingtonia</tp:taxon-name></italic> is distinguished from other theridiosomatids by its distantly-separated spermathecae and long copulatory ducts. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. (2009)</xref> also discovered new species from other six genera, three of which were found in China for the first time. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma dibaiyin</tp:taxon-name></italic> as the second speices and first known male from the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma</tp:taxon-name></italic>, gives us new thoughts about the validation of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma taiwanica</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Zhang &amp; Zhu, 2006). According to the illustrations given by that paper, we found that it resembles several critical features possessed by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> rather than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma</tp:taxon-name></italic>. We have no doubt that it will make more sense if it could be transferred to genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, including two species, was created by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Chen (2010)</xref>. As the second genus endemic to China, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia</tp:taxon-name></italic> is placed in the <tp:taxon-name>Theridiosomatinae</tp:taxon-name> for three synapomorphies it shares with the other members of this subfamily: a row of short bristles on the cymbium at the junction with cymbial lamella, elongated median apophysis with a trough or groove along its upper surface, and singly attached egg sacs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Chen 2010</xref>: figs 12, 13, 30). Two new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Kastia</tp:taxon-name></italic> are described here in this paper, merely on the basis of the female characteristics, further diagnosis will be done when males are collected. To a certain extant, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub</tp:taxon-name></italic> are seemingly closely related, despite the fact <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a few unique features: presence of cymbium apophysis, and stout, overlapped spermathecae, the accuracy or verity of it is still questionable to us, and more study efforts desperately need to be put into this extraordinary genus in the future.
            </p>
            <p>Theridiosomatids in China are mainly found in the southern provinces: Guangxi, Guizhou, Hainan, Taiwan and Yunnan, which is consistent with the tropical and subtropical preferences typical for this family. Some theridiosomatids are associated with caves, which are characterized by stable humidity and temperature. In this paper, we provide descriptions and distribution data for eleven new species collected in Guangxi, Guizhou, Hainan and Yunnan.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
            <title>Method</title>
            <p>Specimens were examined using a LEICA M205 C stereomicroscope. Further details were studied under an Olympus BX51 compound microscope. All illustrations were made using a camera lucida attached to an Olympus BX51 compound microscope, and then inked on ink jet plotter paper. Male and female genitalia were examined and illustrated<!--PageBreak--> after being dissected from the spiders’ bodies. Left pedipalps of male spiders were illustrated, except as otherwise indicated. Vulvae of female were removed and cleared in lactic acid or warm 10% potassium hydroxide (KOH) solution before illustration. All embolic divisions and vulvae were illustrated after being embedded in Arabic gum. Type specimens examined were preserved in 75% ethanol solution. Photos were taken with an Olympus c7070 wide zoom digital camera (7.1 megapixels) mounted on an Olympus SZX12 stereomicroscope. Images from multiple focal planes were combined using Helicon Focus (version 3.10.3) image stacking software. All measurements are given in millimeters. Leg measurements are shown as: total length (femur, patella, tibia, metatarsus, tarsus).</p>
            <p>SEM images were taken using the HITACHI S-3000N at the Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences. Specimens for SEM examination were critical point dried and sputter coated with gold-palladium. Specimens were mounted on copper pedestal using double-sided adhesive tape.</p>
            <p>All type specimens are deposited in the Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences in Beijing.</p>
            <p><bold>Chaetotaxy.</bold> Macrosetae are marked for the dorsal (d), prolateral (p), retrolateral (r), and ventral (v) surfaces of the legs. Metatarsal trichobothrium (Tm) is given as the ratio of the distance between the proximal margin of the metatarsus and the root of the trichobothrium divided by the total length of the metatarsus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Locket and Millidge 1953</xref>) and Tm value for each leg is given as Tm I, Tm II, Tm III, Tm IV respectively.
            </p>
            <p><bold>Abbreviations and conventions.</bold> Abbreviations used in the text are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. References to figures in cited papers are listed in lowercase type (fig.); Figures of this paper are noted with an initial capital (Fig.).
            </p>
            <p>When extra materials are examined and recorded, and the paratype’s collecting information is the same as holotype’s, it will be implied in brackets as [same data as holotype].</p>
        <table-wrap position="float" orientation="portrait" id="T1">
            <label>Table 1.</label>
            <caption><p>List of abbreviations used in the text and figures.</p>
            </caption>
            <table>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="2"><bold>Male pedipalp</bold>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Co</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">conductor</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>E</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">embolus</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>EA</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">embolic apophysis</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MA</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">median apophysis</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PC</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">paracymbium</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>T</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tegulum</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="2"><bold>Vulva</bold>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CD</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Copulatory duct</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>S</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">spermatheca</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="2"><bold>Spinnerets spigot morphology</bold>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AC</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">aciniform gland spigot</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>AG</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">aggregate gland spigot</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ALS</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">anterior lateral spinneret</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CY</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cylindrical gland spigot</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FL</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">flagelliform gland spigot</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MAP</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">major ampullate gland spigot</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>mAP</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">minor ampullate gland spigot </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PI</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">piriform gland spigot</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PLS</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">posterior lateral spinneret</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PMS</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">posterior median spinneret</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>t</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tartipore</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="2"><bold>Institution</bold>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IZCAS</bold>
                        </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences</td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>
        </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <sec sec-type="Key to Theridiosomatidae from southern China">
                <title>Key to <tp:taxon-name>Theridiosomatidae</tp:taxon-name> from southern China</title>
                <p><bold>(</bold>Species known from one sex is marked as ‘m’ or ‘f’ to represent their holotype’s sex ‘male’ or ‘female’; if unmarked, it means they are known from both sexes)
                </p>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior median eyes separated by about their diameter or more (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Figs 20C–D</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior median eyes separated by less than 1/2 their diameter or less (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7C–D</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The turning made by the copulatory ducts bends outwardly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Fig. 20B</xref>). Median apophysis mesally with a projection oriented distoventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19A</xref>). Embolic apophysis long, whip-like (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19C</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius hapalus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The turning made by the copulatory ducts bends inwardly. Median apophysis with apex oriented distodorsally. Embolic apophysis filiform (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: figs 5C, 3D, 4G)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius barbandrewsi</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Males</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16A</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape protruding from beneath the epigynal plate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape protruding from epigyne’s posterior rim (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape less sclerotized, smaller and partially exposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Coddington 1986</xref>: fig. 206)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape more sclerotized, and utterly exposed. Spermathecae juxtaposed. Copulatory ducts rise and curl up to form a blunt-tipped projection at each side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spermathecae juxtaposed, unseparated</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spermathecae separated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Song and Zhu 1994</xref>: fig. 5)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(f) <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wendilgarda assmensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epigyne with a deeper median invagination of the posterior margin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: 11D
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wendilgarda muji</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epigyne with a blunt tip and concave posterior margin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Zhu and Wang 1992</xref>: fig. 3)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wendilgarda sinensis<!--PageBreak--></tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spermathecae distally fused (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spermathecae juxtaposed or overlapped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11B</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape with a central pit on the epigynal plate. Spermathecae long,narrow, form an arcade-shaped conformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7A–B</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub rastrarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape with a semi-transparent distal tip. Spermathecae small, elliptical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9A–B</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(f) <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub youyiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epigyne subtriangular, pointed posteriorly with concave margins so medial part is more acute than lateral part (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 3E)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(f) <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub nemesis</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spermathecae juxtaposed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11B</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spermathecae overlapped at the tip (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Chen 2010</xref>: fig. 6)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epigyne small, with a short, distally spherical scape protruding from posterior margin of epigynal plate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 17A, D, E</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(f) <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia nitida</tp:taxon-name></italic>sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epigyne with a long, apiculate scape protruding perpendicularly (slightly tilted) from posterior margin of epigynal plate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18E–F</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(f) <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia prolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epigyne with an apiculate, approximately triangular scape. Spermathecae potato-like, bulging and stout (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Chen 2010</xref>: fig. 20)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia coddingtoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epigyne with a triangular scape protruding from its posterior rim. Spermathecae peanut-shape stout and simple (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Chen 2010</xref>: fig. 6)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia upperyangtz</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spermathecae separated by less their diameter or juxtaposed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16B</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spermathecae separated by nearly their diameter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 11F)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(f) <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coddingtonia euryopoides</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spermathecae spherical, separated from each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16B</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Menglunia inaffecta</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spermathecae juxtaposed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdomen with silver patches forming curved transverse strip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F29">Figs 29C–D</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdomen without silver patches forming curved transverse strip</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The upper rim of the spermathecae is the same height as the copulatory ducts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 11B)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma didaiyin</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The spermathecae is above the loop made by the copulatory ducts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F29">Fig. 29B</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma fascia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epigyne with a deep atrium, height of opening about one third the width in posterior view (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 3B)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epeirotypus dalong</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atrium absent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 3F) or slit-like (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 13A), height of opening (if visible) much less than one third the width in posterior view
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epigyne with pair of processes arising from posterolateral margin running toward each other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 3H)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(f) <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma shuangbi</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epigyne without pair of processes arising from posterolateral margin</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior margin of epigyne with median longitudinal slit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 9A)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma diwang</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior margin of epigyne without median longitudinal slit, but with a median transverse ridge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Zhang et al. 2006</xref>: fig. 2)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma taiwanica</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embolic apophysis absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embolic apophysis present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tegulum without tuberculate-textured mesal lobe</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tegulum with tuberculate-textured mesal lobe. Median apophysis lightly sclerotized, with fine distoventral projection. Conductor a complex of sclerotized and membranous structure enveloping thick embolus for most of its length (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 2A)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epeirotypus dalong</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embolus long, whip-like, mostly enveloped in conductor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1B–D</xref>). Median apophysis disproportionately large, orienting and stretching along the longitudinal axis of pedipalp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embolus short, stout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 15B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">17B</xref>). Tegulum suboval shaped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15D</xref>). Median apophysis with a short projection oriented distoventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15A</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Menglunia inaffecta</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embolic division simple with one filiform embolic apophysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F28">Fig. 28C</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embolic division complex with more than one embolic apophysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Fig. 24C</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposed embolic apophysis short with a triangular tip, embolus ‘Z’-shaped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F28">Figs 28A–D</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma fascia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposed embolic apophysis long; embolic division with a moderate branching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 10F)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma dibaiyin</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The mesal bristle of the embolic apophysis protruding from beneath the conductor and lying long the mesal side of the conductor itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Coddington 1986</xref>: fig. 198)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The palp without a mesal bristle of apophysis protruding from beneath the conductor and lying long the mesal side of the conductoritself</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conductor with a spear-shaped apophysis, above median apophysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Zhu and Wang 1992</xref>: fig. 7)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wendilgarda sinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conductor without a spear-shaped apophysis. Palpa tibia with one trichobothrium. Median apophysis sclerotized with concave dorsal margin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 12E)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wendilgarda muji</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embolic apophysis with blunt, spatulate processes, without a mesal bristle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Coddington 1986</xref>: fig. 162; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Chen 2010</xref>: fig. 11)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embolic apophysis fragments, filiform, with tips protruding out of conductor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Fig. 24B</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median apophysis elongated and has a trough of groove along its upper surface. Cymbium with apophysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Chen 2010</xref>: figs 26–27)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median apophysis small, triangular and cleft (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6A, D</xref>). Embolic apophysis spatulate arching structure with abruptly acuminated distal ends (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub rastrarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.<!--PageBreak-->
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cymbium apophysis small. Paracymbium with a long spine on the distal end (Chen 2009: fig. 13)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia upperyangze</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cymbium apophysis big, distally crooked. Paracymbium without a long spine (Chen 2009: fig. 27)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia coddingtoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conductor with plumose branching (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 22C</xref>). Median apophysis with a curved lobe attenuates distally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23">Fig. 23A</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(m) <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma plumaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conductor without plumose branching</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two embolic apophysis fragments form a 'V'-shaped conformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Figs 24A–B</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(m) <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma triumphalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">One embolic apophysis fragment forms a beak-shaped conformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F26">Figs 26A–B</xref>). Conductor with a piece of long, pliant apophysis protruding from its ridge and stretching towards median apophysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F26">Figs 26B, D</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(m) <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma vimineum</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <label>Genus</label>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Alaria</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A977D6FD-0DFF-448D-A83D-09193762595F</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Alaria</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                        <title>Type species.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The generic epithet is derived from the Latin ‘alarius’, meaning ‘of wings’, which refers to the two projections of the copulatory ducts at each side, which resembles a pair of wings. Gender is feminine.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>The unique structure of epigyne distinguishes <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> from other theridiosomatids. Like in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wendilgarda</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chthonopes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the scape in female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> protrudes from beneath epigynal plate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Coddington 1986</xref>: figs 206, 213; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Wunderlich 2011</xref>: figs 18d–e), but is utterly exposed, and more sclerotized, like a shield attached to the abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A–B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A–B</xref>). The conformation of the copulatory ducts is similar to that in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius obtectus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Coddington 1986</xref>: fig. 113), but copulatory ducts make one coil before the conjuncture with spermathecae instead a fold (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). The paracymbium in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> is neither a T-shaped lobe as in most thridiosomatids nor a broad apophysis as in <tp:taxon-name>Epeirotypinae</tp:taxon-name>, it is a thick, elongated structure with a small hooked projection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). The long, whip-like embolus in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> resembles embolic apophysis in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Coddington 1986</xref>: figs 100–101, 116, 118), but proportionately much longer and mostly enveloped in conductor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B–D</xref>). The median apophysis of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> is disproportionately large, stretching along the longitudinal axis of pedipalp with two curved, pointed distal ends (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>), which is never seen in any other theridiosomatid genus. Based on the combination of features mentioned above, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> should be recognized as a new genus, and is likely close to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wendilgarda</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chthonopes</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Species">
                        <title>Species.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Alaria</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5EEE5079-3F6D-48CC-84D1-1A26BAD71F78</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Alaria_chengguanensis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: CHINA, Guizhou: Bijie City, Chengguan Town, Xiaohe Village, Xiniu Cave, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">27°21.231'N, 105°17.186'E</named-content>, elevation ca 1515 m, 30 April 2007, J. Liu &amp; Y.C. Lin (IZCAS), 1 male.
                        </p>
                        <p>Paratypes: [same data as holotype] (IZCAS), 13 males, 8 females.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>This specific name chéng guān ( ) refers to its type locality; adjective.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>See diagnosis for genus.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Carapace brownish red, with symmetric dark veins. Sternum yellow with dark brown margins. Legs yellow, dark brown distally at joints, especially tibiae. Abdomen tan with dark grey and silver patches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A–B</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Male pedipalp: Patella with strong sinuous macroseta. Tibia with two trichobothria. Cymbium with small cluster of long setae proximally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>). Paracymbium elongated, curved near base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>). Tegulum smooth. Median apophysis wide, longitudinally grooved, strongly sclerotized, with curved and pointed distal region. Conductor a thick, looped, blade-shaped structure enveloping embolus for most of its length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1B–D</xref>). Embolus long, slim.
                        </p>
                        <p>Vulva: Epigyne with long, tongue-shaped scape protruding from beneath its concaved margin. Scape slightly humped with a small transverse opening at its distal end. Spermathecae juxtaposed. Copulatory ducts rise and curl up to form a blunt-tipped projection at each side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Male (holotype): Total length 2.10, carapace 1.24 long, 1.08 wide, clypeus 0.13, sternum 0.6 long, 0.6 wide, coxae IV separated by two thirds their width. Posterior median eyes separated by half their diameter. Macrosetae: Leg I: femur d 1, patella d 1, tibia d 1, p 1, v 2, r 1, metatarsus p 1, v 1; Leg II: femur d 2, patella d 2, tibia d 1, p 1, v 1, r 1, metatarsus p 1, v 1; Leg III: femur d 3, patella d 1, tibia p 1, v 2, metatarsus d 1, p 1, r 1; Leg IV: femur d 1, tibia p 1, v 1, r 1, metatarsus p 1, v 1, r 1. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.27; Tm II: 0.30; Tm III: 0.84; Tm IV: 0.24. Leg measurements: I 3.98 (1.25, 0.50, 0.85, 0.88, 0.50); II 3.09 (1.00, 0.43, 0.63, 0.63, 0.40); III 2.27 (0.68, 0.35, 0.38, 0.48, 0.38); IV 2.95 (0.93, 0.38, 0.63, 0.63, 0.38).</p>
                        <p>Female (one of paratypes): Total length 2.50, carapace 1.25 long, 1.25 wide, clypeus 0.08, sternum 0.78 long, 0.63 wide, coxae IV separated by 1 time their width. Posterior median eyes separated by half their diameter. Macrosetae as in male. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.21 ; Tm II: 0.25; Tm III: 0.48; Tm IV: 0.27. Leg measurements: I 4.66 (1.05, 0.63, 0.95, 0.95, 0.63); II 3.75 (1.20, 0.55, 0.75, 0.75, 0.50); III 2.48(0.75, 0.33, 0.50, 0.50, 0.40); IV 3.75 (1.25, 0.50, 0.75, 0.75, 0.50).<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 1.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Pedipalp, ventral view <bold>C</bold> Embolic division, dorsal view <bold>D</bold> Pedipalp, retrolateral view. <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>PC</bold> paracymbium; <bold>T</bold> tegulum. Scale bars: <bold>D</bold> as <bold>A</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 2.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype (<bold>C</bold>) and female paratype (<bold>A–B, D</bold>). <bold>A</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>B</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>C</bold> Male, dorsal view <bold>D</bold> Female, dorsal view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>S </bold>spermatheca. Scale bars: <bold>B</bold> as <bold>A</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 3.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., SEM of pedipalp of a male paratype. A Prolateral view, detail showing MA <bold>B</bold> Retrolateral view <bold>C</bold> Retrolateral view, detail showingembolus <bold>D</bold> Retrolateral view, detail showing <bold>PC</bold>. <bold>Co</bold> conductor <bold>E</bold> Embolus; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>PC</bold> paracymbium; <bold>T</bold> tegulum.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 4.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., SEM of a female paratype. <bold>A</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Epigyne, lateral view <bold>C</bold> Spinnerets <bold>D</bold> ALS <bold>E</bold> PMS <bold>F</bold> PLS. <bold>AC</bold> aciniform gland spigot; <bold>AG</bold> aggregate gland spigot; <bold>ALS</bold> anterior lateral spinneret; <bold>CY</bold> cylindrical gland spigot; <bold>MAP</bold> major ampullate gland spigot; <bold>mAP</bold> minor ampullate gland spigot; <bold>n</bold> nubbin; <bold>PI</bold> piriform gland spigot; <bold>PLS</bold> posterior lateral spinneret; <bold>PMS</bold> posterior median spinneret; <bold>t</bold> tartipore.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 5.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype (<bold>A–B</bold>) and female paratype (<bold>C–D</bold>). <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Embolic division, dorsal view <bold>C</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>D</bold> Vulva, dorsal view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>S</bold> spermatheca. Scale bars: <bold>D</bold> as <bold>C</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Genus Baalzebub Coddington, 1986">
                <title>Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub</tp:taxon-name></italic> Coddington, 1986
                </title>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub</tp:taxon-name></italic> Coddington, 1986: 71. Type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub baubo</tp:taxon-name></italic> Coddington, 1986.
                </p>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Baalzebub</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">rastrarius</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7E74FF15-FCE5-45FB-807A-12724669D543</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Baalzebub_rastrarius</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined. </title>
                        <p>Holotype:CHINA, Guizhou: Bijie City, Chengguan Town, Xiaohe Village, Xiniu Cave, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">27°21.231'N, 105°17.186'E</named-content>, elevation ca 1515 m, 30 April 2007, J. Liu &amp; Y.C. Lin (IZCAS), 1 male.
                        </p>
                        <p>Paratypes: [same data as holotype] (IZCAS), 1 male, 7 females. CHINA, Guizhou: Xishui County, Sangmu Town, Tuhe Village, Dongkouwan Cave, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">28°15.679'N, 106°18.355'E</named-content>, elevation ca 1271 m, 16 March 2011, Z.G. Chen &amp; Z.W. Zha (IZCAS), 4 males, 8 females; Dafang County, Wenge Town, Taibai Village, Yelaoda <!--PageBreak-->Cave, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">27°10.869'N, 105°28.289'E</named-content>, elevation ca 1398 m, 12 March 2011, Z.G. Chen &amp; Z.W. Zha (IZCAS), 2 males, 2 females.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The epithet comes from Latin word ‘rastrarius’ which means ‘of a hoe’, referring to the hoe-shaped conductor in prolateral view; adjective.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>The presence of small, cleft median apophysis and blunt, spatulate processes of embolic apophysis in males, and tip-fused spermathecae in females indicates<!--PageBreak--> that this species belongs to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Conductor in males envelopes the entire embolic apophysis (Fig 6A), which is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub albinotatus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, butthe rectangular conductor and the small, pointed cymbium apophysis are different from other described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. Females distinguished by the triangular epigynal plate, similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub baubo</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Coddington 1986</xref>: figs 183, 184), but distinguished by the narrower, arcade-shaped spermathecae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Carapace yellow tan. Sternum yellow with dark orange margins and setae. Legs yellow, dark brown distally at joints, especially tibiae. Abdomen tan with 2–4 rows of dark grey patches, the first two of which are connected by a perpendicular grey patch at midline, and two pairs of small dorsal brown spots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7C–F</xref><!--PageBreak-->).
                        </p>
                        <p>Male pedipalp: Patella with strong sinuous macroseta. Tibia with two trichobothria. Cymbium with a row of short regular bristles at its junction with cymbial lamella. Paracymbium with a long, pointed distal end (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>). Cymbium apophysis small and pointed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>). Median apophysis triangular, strongly sclerotized (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A</xref>). Conductor a sub-rectangular translucent theca covering the complex embolic division and embolic apophysis. Embolic apophysis a spatulate arching structure with abruptly acuminated distal ends (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Vulva: Epigyne with a smooth triangular scape protruding from posterior margin of epigyne plate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7A–B</xref>). A deep pit lies on the epigynal mesal anterior edge. Spermathecae long, narrow, meeting at the tip to form an arcade-shaped structure. Copulatory ducts follow simple curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8D</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Male: Total length 1.75, carapace 0.94 long, 1.09 wide, clypeus 0.25, sternum 0.53 long, 0.56 wide, coxae IV separated by their width. Posterior median eyes separated by less than half their diameter. Macrosetae: Leg I: femur p 1, patella d 1, tibia d 3, r 1; Leg II: femur r 1, patella d 2, tibia d 1, r 1; Leg III: patella d 2, tibia d 1; Leg IV: patella d 2, tibia d 1. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.25; Tm II: 0.29; Tm III: 0.23; Tm IV: 0.26. Leg measurements: I 4.66 (1.50, 0.50, 1.26, 1.00, 0.40); II 3.45 (1.10, 0.40, 0.80, 0.80, 0.35); III 2.50 (0.75, 0.30, 0.50, 0.50, 0.45); IV 3.10 (0.75, 0.60, 0.75, 0.70, 0.30).</p>
                        <p>Female: Total length 2.24, carapace 0.93 long, 0.93 wide, clypeus 0.11, sternum 0.5 long, 0.5 wide, coxae IV separated by their width. Posterior median eyes separated by less than half their diameter. Macrosetae as in male. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.28; Tm II: 0.25; Tm III: 0.45; Tm IV: 0.27. Leg measurements: I 4.17 (1.38, 0.48, 0.98, 0.88, 0.45); II 3.39 (1.10, 0.43, 0.73, 0.75, 0.38); III 2.50 (0.75, 0.35, 0.50, 0.55, 0.35); IV 3.11 (1.00, 0.33, 0.65, 0.75, 0.38).</p>
        <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 6.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub rastrarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Pedipalp, retrolateral view <bold>C</bold> Embolic division, retrolateral view <bold>D</bold> Pedipalp, ventral view. <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>EA</bold> embolic apophysis; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>PC</bold> paracymbium; <bold>T</bold> tegulum. Scale bars: <bold>B</bold> as <bold>A</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 7.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub rastrarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype (<bold>C</bold>) and female paratype (<bold>A–B, D–F</bold>). <bold>A</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>C</bold> Male, dorsal view <bold>D</bold> Female, dorsal view <bold>E</bold> Female, ventral view <bold>F </bold>Female, lateral view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct, <bold>S</bold> spermatheca. Scale bars: <bold>B</bold> as <bold>A, D</bold> as <bold>E</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 8.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub rastrarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype (<bold>A–B</bold>) and female paratype (<bold>C–D</bold>). <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Embolic division, retrolateral view <bold>C</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>D</bold> Vulva, dorsal view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>S</bold> spermatheca. Scale bars: <bold>D</bold> as <bold>C</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Baalzebub</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">youyiensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:791FC4A5-1C1F-4E54-97BA-EEDF7FAFFCA9</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Baalzebub_youyiensis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: CHINA, Guangxi: Pingxiang City, Youyi County, Bantou Village, Niuyan Cave, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">22°05.666'N, 106°45.439'E</named-content>, elevation ca 251 m, 18 January 2011, Z.G. Chen &amp; Z.W. Zha (IZCAS), 1 female.
                        </p>
                        <p>Paratypes: [same data as holotype] (IZCAS), 3 females.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>This specific name formed from the Chinese words for friendship yŏu yì ( ), which is the name of the county where this species was collected; adjective.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Females distinguished from other described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the shape of the semi-transparent scape, which is proportionately shorter and with a blunt tip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A</xref>). Spermathecae, contrasted with narrow, long spermathecae in other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub</tp:taxon-name></italic> species, is relatively shorter and smaller compared to the ovoid loops made by copulatory ducts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9B</xref>)
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Carapace broad, orange. Sternum yellow with dusky margins. Legs yellow, brown from patella to tarsus (except for leg I, which only brown distally at joints). Abdomen beige with irregular light, greenish-grey patches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9C–E</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Vulva: Epigyne with a short, pointed triangular scape with concave lateral margins protruding from posterior margin of epigyne plate, through which dark orange vulva is visible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A</xref>). Scape translucent. Epigyne plate with transverse grooves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A</xref>). Spermathecae small, elliptical, joining each other at the tip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10B</xref>). Copulatory ducts simple, with three coils toward spermathecae.
                        </p>
                        <p>Female: Total length 2.10, carapace 1.00 long, 1.00 wide, clypeus 0.19, sternum 0.53 long, 0.53 wide, coxae IV separated by 1.00 time their width. Posterior median eyes separated by less than half their diameter. Macrosetae: Leg I: femur d 1, p 1, patella d 1, tibia d 2, p 1, r 1; Leg II: patella d 3, tibia d 2, r 1; Leg III: patella d 2, tibia d 2, r 2; Leg IV: patella d 2, tibia d 1. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.20; Tm II: 0.15; Tm III: 0.19; Tm IV: 0.22. Leg measurements: I 3.76 (1.20, 0.40, 0.88, 0.80, 0.48); II 3.2 (1.00, 0.36, 0.72, 0.64, 0.48); III 2.24 (0.72, 0.32, 0.44, 0.45, 0.31); IV 2.92 (1.00, 0.40, 0.60, 0.52, 0.40).</p>
                        <p>Male unknown.</p>
        <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 9.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub youyiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype. <bold>A</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>C </bold>Female, dorsal view <bold>D</bold> Female, ventral view <bold>E</bold> Female, lateral view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>S</bold> spermatheca. Scale bars: <bold>A</bold> as <bold>B, C, D</bold> as <bold>E</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 10.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub youyiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype. <bold>A</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Vulva, dorsal view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>S</bold> spermatheca. Scale bars: <bold>B</bold> as <bold>A</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Genus Karstia Chen, 2010">
                <title>Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chen, 2010
                </title>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chen, 2010: 2. Type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia upperyangtzica</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chen, 2010.
                </p>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Karstia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">nitida</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5ABD3E69-462D-4811-9851-EF178144FE62</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Karstia_nitida</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: CHINA, Guangxi: Hechi City, Hechi County, Laba Village, Shoushui Cave, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">24°41.229'N, 107°52.609'E</named-content>, elevation ca 268 m, 31 March 2011, Z.G. Chen &amp; Z.W. Zha (IZCAS), 1 female.
                        </p>
                        <p>Paratypes: [same data as holotype] (IZCAS), 14 females.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>This specific name comes from the Latin word ‘nitidus’ which means ‘shinning and elegant’, referring to the glossiness of the swollen tip of the epigynal scape; adjective.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Females distinguished by the following combination of characters: the structure of the scape, the stout, overlapped spermathecae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11B</xref>), and the habitus of this species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11C–E</xref>). Spermathecae oval-shaped with vertically longer diameter, slightly detached from each other along their inner margin. The abdomen large, contrasted with distinctly small epigynal area. The scape structure is quite different from other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia</tp:taxon-name></italic> or <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub</tp:taxon-name></italic> species: the tip of scape is swollen and shimmery, and the lateral margins of the plate extend toward the scape tip to form a arm<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->et-shaped conformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11A</xref>). Generic placement tentative pending discovery and examination of the male.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Carapace pale yellow with yellow ocular region. Sternum yellow with tan margins. Legs yellow, brown distally at joints. Abdomen dark grey mottled with white patches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11C–E</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Vulva: Epigyne small, with short, distally spherical scape protruding from posterior margin of epigyne plate. Epigyne plate extends posteriorly, together with scape to form a barbute-shaped conformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12A</xref>). End of scape glossy with black purfle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11A</xref>). Spermathecae peanut-shaped, juxtaposed, slightly detached from each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12B</xref>). Copulatory ducts follow simple rout to form small loops and one turning before connected with spermathecae at the bottom (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12B</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Female: Total length 3.25, carapace 1.38 long, 1.13 wide, clypeus 0.10, sternum 0.70 long, 0.65 wide, coxae IV separated by their width. Posterior median eyes separated by less than half their diameter. Macrosetae: Leg I: femur p 1, r 1, patella d 1, tibia d 2, p 2, v 2, r 1, metatarsus d 1, v 2, r 1; Leg II: femur d 2, patella d 2, tibia d 4, p 1, v2, metatarsus p 1, v 2; Leg III: femur d 1, patella d 2, tibia d 1, v 1, metatarsus d 3; Leg IV: patella d 2, tibia d 1, v 1, r 1, metatarsus d 2. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.23; Tm II: 0.21; Tm III: 0.16; Tm IV 0.22. Leg measurements: I 4.00 (0.56, 0.63, 1.09, 1.09, 0.63); II 4.16 (1.25, 0.50, 0.94, 0.94, 0.53); III 2.98 (0.78, 0.47, 0.63, 0.63, 0.47); IV 3.66 (1.25, 0.38, 0.78, 0.78, 0.47).</p>
                        <p>Male unknown.</p>
        <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 11.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia nitida</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype. <bold>A</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>C</bold> Habitus, dorsal view <bold>D</bold> Habitus, ventral view <bold>E</bold> Habitus, lateral view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct <bold>S</bold> spermatheca. Scale bars: <bold>C, D</bold> as <bold>E</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F12" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 12.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia nitida</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype. <bold>A</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Vulva, dorsal view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct, <bold>S</bold> spermatheca.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g012.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Karstia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">prolata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:38E8200D-E27D-4710-ABEE-FBF657944027</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Karstia_prolata</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 13</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: CHINA, Guangxi: Pingxiang City, Youyi County, Bantou Village, Niuyan Cave, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">22°05.666'N, 106°45.439'E</named-content>, elevation ca 251 m, 18 January 2011, Z.G. Chen &amp; Z.W. Zha (IZCAS), 1 female.
                        </p>
                        <p>Paratypes: [same data as holotype] (IZCAS), 9 females.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific name is derived from the Latin word ‘prolatus’ meaning elongated’, and refers to the extended epigynal scape; adjective.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Females distinguished by the protruding scape and the overlapped, stout spermathecae. The long acute-angled scape protrudes vertically from the posterior epigynal margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 13B, F</xref>), which is different from other known <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub</tp:taxon-name></italic> species.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Relatively large in total body length, compared to other theridiosomatid species. Carapace greenish tan, with brown ocular region. Sternum yellow with dark margins. Femur yellow, brown from patella to tarsus. Abdomen beige with evenly distributed silver spots within dorsal area and 8 or more rows of mesally disrupted greenish grey patches, with a large, wedge-shaped greenish grey patch between epigyne and spinnerets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 13D–E</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Vulva: Epigyne with a long, apiculate scape protruding perpendicularly (slightly tilted) from posterior margin of epigyne plate, flanked by a cluster of long sinuous setae on each side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 13A, E–F</xref>). Two deep grooves occur at the posterior base of epigyne which are likely connected to the copulatory openings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 13B, E</xref>). Tip of<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> scape glossy black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13A</xref>). Spermathecae peanut-shaped, juxtaposed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13C</xref>). Copulatory ducts’ routing simple, half-looped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 13C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14B</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Female: Total length 3.85, carapace 1.92 long, 1.25 wide, clypeus 0.15, sternum 0.63 long, 0.65 wide, coxae IV separated by 2.00 times their width. Posterior median eyes separated by half their diameter. Macrosetae: Leg I: femur d 2, p 1, patella d 2, tibia d 2, p 2, v 1, r 1, metatarsus p 1, v 3, r 1; Leg II: femur d 2, patella d 2, tibia d 1, p 2, v 1, r 1, metatarsus p 1, v 2, r 1; Leg III: femur d 1, v 1, patella d 1, tibia d 1, p 2, v 2, metatarsus d 3; Leg IV: tibia d 2, p 1, metatarsus d 2. Metatarsal trichobothria: <!--PageBreak-->Tm I: 0.13; Tm II: 0.22; Tm III: 0.27; Tm IV: 0.22. Leg measurements: I 6.35 (2.00, 0.75, 1.35, 1.50, 0.75); II 5.25 (1.50, 0.70, 1.10, 1.20, 0.75); III 3.35 (0.95, 0.45, 0.70, 0.75, 0.50); IV 4.60 (1.50, 0.50, 1.00, 1.00, 0.60).</p>
                        <p>Male unknown.</p>
        <fig id="F13" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 13.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia prolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype. <bold>A</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Vulva, posterior view <bold>C</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>D</bold> Habitus, dorsal view <bold>E</bold> Habitus, ventral view <bold>F</bold> Habitus, lateral view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>S</bold> spermatheca. Scale bars: <bold>B</bold> as <bold>A, D, F</bold> as <bold>E</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g013.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F14" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 14.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia prolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype. <bold>A</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Vulva, dorsal view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>S</bold> spermatheca.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g014.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <label>Genus</label>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Menglunia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:272F2972-D45B-4401-AD1E-62ADCB6D498E</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Menglunia</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                        <title>Type species.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Menglunia inaffecta</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The generic epithet refers to the place měng lún ( ) where these specimens were collected. Menglun Town is located at Xishuangbanna in Yunnan province, where tropical rain forest harbors countless species, both vertebrates and invertebrates. Gender is feminine.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Distinguished from other theridiosomatids by the extremely simple, short embolus, and the round, separated spermathecae. The pedipalp in males is an elliptical (slightly rectangular in total), theca-textured, and obscurely circumscribed structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 15A, D</xref>). Conductor is less extensive, and fully covers the embolus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 18A</xref>). The embolus is beak-like, and enveloped in conductor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15B</xref>). Unlike any other theridiosomatid genus, the median apophysis in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Menglunia</tp:taxon-name></italic> is merely a small projection, mildly curved without any sharp tip or trough (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15A</xref>). Spermathecae similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coddingtonia euryopoides</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Luangnam discobulbus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Wunderlich, 2011), but instead of being elliptical and separated by their diameter, they are more rounded and separated by less than half of their diameter. Copulatory duct is shorter and forms a simple loop which is about the same height as spermathecae’s diameter, compared to the big loop and higher-positioned copulatory ducts in <italic>Coddingtonia euryopoides and L. discobulbus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16B</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Species">
                        <title>Species.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Menglunia inaffecta</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Menglunia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">inaffecta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:63DFDE88-8154-412E-B02E-47A71157F286</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Menglunia_inaffecta</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 15</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: CHINA, Yunnan: Menglun Town: Xishuangbanna Botanical Garden, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">21°55.035'N, 101°16.500'E</named-content>, elevation ca 558 m, 22 July 2007, primary tropical seasonal rain forest, searching, G. Zheng (IZCAS), 1 male.
                        </p>
                        <p>Paratypes: [same data as holotype] (IZCAS), 9 males, 9 females.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Its Latin origin ‘inaffectus’ means ‘natural and simple’, which refers to the simplicity of the structure of the male pedipalp; adjective.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>See diagnosis for genus.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Carapace yellow tan. Sternum yellow with greenish brown margins and sparse hairs. Legs thick, yellow. Abdomen beige with small, irregularly-distributed greenish brown spots.</p>
                        <p>Male pedipalp: Patella with erect macroseta. Tibia with one trichobothrium. Paracymbium with a short pointed distal end (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17A</xref>). Tegulum sub-oval. Median <!--PageBreak-->apophysis with a small projection oriented distoventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 15A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18A</xref>). Conductor kidney-shaped, translucent theca. Embolus beak-shaped, stout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 15A–B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">17B</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Vulva: Epigyne with obscure plate margins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 16A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">17A</xref>). Spermathecae round, separated from each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16B</xref>). Copulatory duct short and simple (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16B</xref>).<!--PageBreak-->
                        </p>
                        <p>Male (holotype): Total length 1.00, carapace 0.40 long, 0.44 wide, clypeus 0.05, sternum 0.30 long, 0.25 wide, coxae IV separated by 1.5 times their width. Posterior median eyes separated by less than half their diameter. Macrosetae: Leg I: patella d 2, tibia d 2, p 1; Leg II: patella d 1, tibia d 1, p 1, r 1; Leg III: patella d 2. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.27; Tm II: 0.38; Tm III: 0.36. Leg measurements: I 1.10 (0.31, 0.13, 0.25, 0.23, 0.18); II 0.84 (0.25, 0.06, 0.20, 0.20, 0.13); III 0.66 (0.18, 0.11, 0.13, 0.13, 0.11); IV 0.76 (0.19, 0.13, 0.19, 0.14, 0.11).</p>
                        <p>Female (one of paratypes): Total length 1.00, carapace 0.63 long, 0.48 wide, clypeus 0.05, sternum 0.30 long, 0.30 wide, coxae IV separated by 1.5 times their width. Posterior median eyes separated by less than half their diameter. Macrosetae as in male. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.32; Tm II: 0.38; Tm III: 0.29. Leg measurements: I 1.09 (0.32, 0.20, 0.24, 0.25, 0.18); II 1.02 (0.25, 0.19, 0.23, 0.20, 0.15); III 0.75 (0.19, 0.11, 0.13, 0.18, 0.14); IV 0.91 (0.25, 0.13, 0.21, 0.18, 0.14).</p>
        <fig id="F15" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 15.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Menglunia inaffecta</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Embolic division <bold>C</bold> Pedipalp, ventral view <bold>D</bold> Pedipalp, retrolateral view. <bold>E</bold> embolus; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>PC</bold> paracymbium; <bold>T</bold> tegulum. Scale bars: <bold>A, D</bold> as <bold>C</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g015.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F16" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 16.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Menglunia inaffecta</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype (<bold>C</bold>) and female paratype (<bold>A–B, D–F</bold>). <bold>A</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>C</bold> Male habitus, dorsal view <bold>D</bold> Female habitus , dorsal view <bold>E </bold>Female habitus, ventral view <bold>F</bold> Female habitus, lateral view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct, <bold>S</bold> spermatheca. Scale bars: <bold>A</bold> as <bold>B, E</bold> as <bold>D</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g016.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F17" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 17.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., SEM of male paratype (<bold>A–B</bold>) and female paratype (<bold>C–F</bold>). <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, retrolateral view <bold>B</bold> Pedipalp, retrolateral view, detail showing embolus  <bold>C</bold> Epigyne <bold>D</bold> ALS <bold>E </bold>PMS <bold>F</bold> PLS. <bold>AC</bold> aciniform gland spigot; <bold>AG</bold> aggregate gland spigot; <bold>ALS</bold> anterior lateral spinneret; <bold>CY</bold> cylindrical gland spigot <bold>E</bold> embolus; <bold>FL</bold> flagelliform gland spigot; <bold>MAP</bold> major ampullate gland spigot; <bold>mAP</bold> minor ampullate gland spigot; <bold>PC</bold> paracymbium; <bold>PI</bold> piriform gland spigot; <bold>PLS</bold> posterior lateral spinneret; <bold>PMS</bold> posterior median spinneret; <bold>t</bold> tartipore.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g017.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F18" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 18.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Menglunia inaffecta</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype (<bold>A–B</bold>) and female paratype (<bold>C–D</bold>). <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Embolic division, retrolateral <bold>C</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>D</bold> Vulva, dorsal view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis <bold>S</bold> spermatheca.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g018.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Genus Ogulnius O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1882">
                <title>Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius</tp:taxon-name></italic> O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1882
                </title>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius</tp:taxon-name></italic> O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1882: 432. Type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius obtectus</tp:taxon-name></italic> O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1882.
                </p>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ogulnius</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">hapalus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2CE2BCE0-15BC-488A-A363-872B6BA232F0</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Ogulnius_hapalus</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Figs 19</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">21</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: CHINA, Yunnan: Menglun Town: Xishuangbanna Botanical Garden, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">21°55.035'N, 101°16.500'E</named-content>, elevation ca 558 m, 22 July 2007, primary tropical seasonal rain forest, fogging, G. Zheng (IZCAS), 1 male.
                        </p>
                        <p>Paratypes: [same data as holotype] (IZCAS), 2 males, 6 females.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>This specific name describes the softness and fragility of this species. The Latin origin is ‘hapalus’ meaning ‘delicate and tender’; adjective.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Though lack of one genetic feature, which is fourth legs are longer than the first legs (subequal in females), other generic characteristics of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be seen in this species: tapering whip-like embolic apophysis in males (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19C</xref>), transverse grooves on epigyne in females, separated and juxtaposed posterior median eyes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Coddington 1986</xref>). Males distinguished from other described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius</tp:taxon-name></italic> species by the shape of median apophysis and the proportion of embolic apophysis. The median apophysis in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius hapalus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.is similar to that in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius gloriae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Coddington 1986</xref>: fig. 99): mesally wide, with a projection oriented distoventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19A</xref>). The embolic apophysis is proportionately longer than that in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius barbandrewsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 5F). The Females distinguished by the routing of copulatory ducts and the peanut-shaped spermathecae. The fold made by the copulatory ducts is bending outwardly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Fig. 20B</xref>), instead of in<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->wardly as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius barbandrewsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Miller et al. 1986: fig. 3D). The posterior lip of epigyne in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius hapalus</tp:taxon-name></italic> concave in stead of convex as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius pullus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Brignoli 1981</xref>: fig.1).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Carapace pale yellow. Sternum ivory. Legs pale yellow, semi-transparent. Abdomen pale with soft, translucent cuticle.</p>
                        <p>Male pedipalp: Patella with strong sinuous macroseta. Tibia with one trichobothrium. Paracymbium slim with filiform projection distally. Median apophysis curvy, mesally wide, with apex oriented distoventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Figs 19A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">21A</xref>). Conductor a translucent theca covering about two thirds length of the long filiform embolic apophysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Figs 19C–D</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Vulva: Epigyne with transverse groove and a concave posterior margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Fig. 20A</xref>). Spermathecae peanut-shaped, juxtaposed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Fig. 20B</xref>). Copulatory ducts bend downwardly at top and wide at entrance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Figs 20B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">21B</xref><!--PageBreak-->).
                        </p>
                        <p>Male: Total length 1.00, carapace 0.50 long, 0.40 wide, clypeus 0.09, sternum 0.25 long, 0.25 wide, coxae IV separated by 2.00 times their width. Posterior median eyes separated by 1.5 times their diameter. Macrosetae: Leg I: patella d 1, tibia d 1, p 1; Leg II: patella d 1, tibia d 1; Leg III: patella d 1, tibia d 1; Leg IV: patella d 1, tibia d 1. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.23; Tm II: 0.19; Tm III: 0.27. Leg measurements: I 1.00 (0.30, 0.18, 0.20, 0.20, 0.12); II 0.87 (0.26, 0.12, 0.20, 0.16, 0.13); III 0.57 (0.11, 0.10, 0.11, 0.15, 0.10); IV 0.64 (0.15, 0.10, 0.14, 0.15, 0.10).</p>
                        <p>Female: Total length 1.41, carapace: 0.50 long, 0.44 wide, clypeus 0.23, sternum 0.30 long, 0.25 wide, coxae IV separated by 2.00 times their width. Posterior median eyes separated 1.5 times their diameter. Macrosetae as in male. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.25; Tm II: 0.21; Tm III: 0.27. Leg measurements: I 0.95 (0.20, 0.25, 0.15, 0.20, 0.15); II 0.82 (0.25, 0.12, 0.15, 0.15, 0.15); III 0.62 (0.12, 0.10, 0.15, 0.15, 0.10); IV 0.90 (0.30, 0.15, 0.15, 0.20, 0.10).</p>
        <fig id="F19" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 19.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius hapalus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Pedipalp, ventral view <bold>C</bold> Embolic division, retrolateral view <bold>D</bold> Pedipalp, retrolateral view. <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>EA</bold> embolic apophysis; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis <bold>T</bold> tegulum. Scale bars: <bold>D</bold> as <bold>A, C</bold> as <bold>B</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g019.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F20" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 20.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius hapalus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype (<bold>C</bold>) and female paratype (<bold>A–B, D–F</bold>). <bold>A</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>C</bold> Male habitus, dorsal view <bold>D</bold> Female habitus, dorsal view <bold>E</bold> Female habitus, ventral view <bold>F</bold> Female habitus, lateral view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>S</bold> spermatheca. Scale bars: <bold>B</bold> as <bold>A, D, E</bold> as <bold>F</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g020.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F21" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 21.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius hapalus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype (<bold>A–B</bold>) and female paratype (<bold>C–D</bold>). <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Embolic division, retrolateral view <bold>C</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>D</bold> Vulva, dorsal view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>S</bold> spermatheca.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g021.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Genus Theridiosoma O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1879">
                <title>Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1879
                </title>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1879: 193. Type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma argenteolum</tp:taxon-name></italic> O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1879 (= <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma gemmosum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (L. Koch, 1878)).
                </p>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Theridiosoma</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">plumaria</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:34DDB1DE-B435-4A41-8EF7-A40B43ACC9E0</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Theridiosoma_plumaria</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Figs 22</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23">23</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: CHINA, Hainan: Mt. Jianfengling National Nature Reserve: Tianchi watershed <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">18°44.383'N, 108°51.062'E</named-content>, elevation ca 888 m, 19 July 2007, S. Li (IZCAS), 1 male.
                        </p>
                        <p>Paratype: CHINA: Hainan: Mt. Bawangling National Nature Reserve, 5 kilometers past Dongerjianchazhan, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">19°05.186'N, 109°11.802'E</named-content>, elevation ca 1010 m, 25 July 2007, S. Li (IZCAS), 1 male.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific name was taken from the Latin word ‘plumarius’ which means ‘of feathers’. It refers to the plumose branching of its conductor theca (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Figs 22B–C</xref>); adjective.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Males, similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma gemmosum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (L. Koch) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Coddington 1986</xref>: figs 134, 135), distinguished from any other known male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Asia by the following characters: broader, slightly groovy median apophysis with an acuminated tip, and the exposed branchings of embolic apophysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 22A</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Carapace yellow tan. Sternum yellow with brown margins. Legs yellow. Abdomen tan with sparse silver specks and symmetric dark grey patches.</p>
                        <p>Male pedipalp: Patella with strong macroseta. Tibia with two trichobothria. Paracymbium hooked with pointed distal end. Tegulum large with tuberculate mesal lobe <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Figs 22A, D</xref>). Median apophysis a curved lobe attenuate distally. Conductor a translucent theca covering fragmented embolic apophysis, with plumose branching and erect tip near tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 22B</xref>). Embolic apophysis fragment tips protruding out of the conductor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Figs 22A–C</xref>). Embolic apophysis fragments long, slim (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Figs 22D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23">23B</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Male: Total length 1.60, carapace 0.80 long, 0.80 wide, clypeus 0.20, sternum 0.40 long, 0.40 wide, coxae IV separated by their width. Posterior median eyes separated by less than half their diameter. Macrosetae: Leg I: femur p 1, patella d 1, tibia d 1, p 1, r 1; Leg II: femur r 1, patella d 1, tibia d 1, p 1, r 1; Leg III: patella d 1, tibia p 1, r 1, metatarsus p 1; Leg IV: patella d 2, tibia d 1. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.0.25; Tm II: 0.19. Leg measurements: I 3.16 (0.93, 0.35, 0.75, 0.75, 0.38); II 2.80 (0.88, 0.28, 0.63, 0.63, 0.38); III 1.66 (0.50, 0.18, 0.35, 0.38, 0.25); IV 1.83 (0.50, 0.25, 0.38, 0.45, 0.25).</p>
        <fig id="F22" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 22.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma plumaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Pedipalp, retrolateral view <bold>C</bold> Pedipalp, ventral view <bold>D</bold> Embolic division, retrolateral view. <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>EA</bold> embolic apophysis; MA median apophysis; <bold>T</bold> tegulum. Scale bars: <bold>B, C</bold> as <bold>A</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g022.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F23" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 23.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma plumaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Embolic division, retrolateral view. <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>EA</bold> embolic apophysis; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>T</bold> tegulum.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g023.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
                        <p>Female unknown</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Theridiosoma</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">triumphalis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:958EEF84-677E-4E46-B673-AA78B5FF63E6</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Theridiosoma_triumphalis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Figs 24</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F25">25</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: CHINA, Hainan: Mt. Jianfengling National Nature Reserve: Tianchi watershed, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">18°44.383'N, 108°51.062'E</named-content>, elevation ca 888 m, 19 July 2007, S. Li (IZCAS), 1 male<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific Latin word ‘triumphalis’ meaning ‘of victory’ refers to the 'V'-shaped conformation made by the two embolic apophysis fragments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Figs 24A, B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F25">25B</xref>); adjective.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Males distinguished from other described Asian <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> species by the shape of median apophysis: a small, curved projection with an attenuated tip extending distoventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Fig. 24B</xref>). Embolic apophysis fragmented, similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma caaguara</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Rodrigues and Ott 2005</xref>: figs 4, 5), but different in details: four pieces of different shapes, the longest one with a whip-like tip, the longer one broad, with a blunt end (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Fig. 24C</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Carapace yellow tan. Sternum yellow with dark margins. Legs yellow. Due to poor preservation condition, abdomen too shriveled to make out its original color pattern.</p>
                        <p>Male pedipalp: Patella with strong macroseta. Paracymbium elongate with attenuated tip. Tegulum smooth with tuberculate ventral ridge. Median apophysis curved lobe with attenuated distal end. Conductor translucent theca covering most fragmented embolic apophysis, with a small rough ventral area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Fig. 24A</xref>). Two embolic apophysis fragment tips protruding out of the conductor tip to form a 'V'-shaped conformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Fig. 24B</xref>). Embolic apophysis with four separate sclerotic fragments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Figs 24C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F25">25A</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Male: Total length 1.7, carapace 0.50 long, 0.50 wide, clypeus 0.09, sternum 0.31 long, 0.31 wide, coxae IV separated by their width. Posterior median eyes separated by less than half their diameter. Macrosetae: Leg I: femur r 1, patella d 1, tibia d 1, p 1; Leg II: patella d 1, tibia d 2, p 1; Leg III: tibia p 1; Leg IV: tibia d 1. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.21; Tm II: 0.27; Tm III: 0.20. Leg measurements: I 2.01 (0.63, 0.25, 0.50, 0.38, 0.25); II 1.76 (0.50, 0.25, 0.38, 0.38, 0.25); III 1.33 (0.30, 0.13, 0.15, 0.25, 0.15); IV 1.14 (0.38, 0.13, 0.25, 0.25, 0.13).</p>
        <fig id="F24" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 24.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma triumphalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Right pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Right pedipalp, retrolateral view <bold>C</bold> Embolic division, retrolateral view <bold>D</bold> Right pedipalp, ventral view. <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>EA</bold> embolic apophysis; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>T</bold> tegulum. Scale bars: <bold>B</bold> as <bold>A</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g024.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F25" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 25.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma triumphalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Embolic division, retrolateral view <bold>B</bold> Right pedipalp, prolateral view. <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>EA</bold> embolic apophysis; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>T</bold> tegulum.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g025.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
                        <p>Female unknown</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Theridiosoma</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">vimineum</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7E3616F4-8E17-4E5D-9892-98A2860B8AC3</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Theridiosoma_vimineum</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F26">Figs 26</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F27">27</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: CHINA, Yunnan: Menglun Town: Xingshuangbanna Botanical Garden, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">21°55.428'N, 101°16.441'E</named-content>, elevation ca 598 m, 19–26 May 2007, primary tropical seasonal rain forest, searching, G. Zheng (IZCAS), 1 male.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific name is derived from Latin word ‘vimineus’ meaning ‘pliant’, refers to the long, pliant apophysis that protrudes from the conductor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F26">Fig. 26B</xref>); adjective.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Males similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma semiargentum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Simon) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Coddington 1986</xref>: figs 154, 156), but different in the details of embolic apophysis fragments and the shape of median apophysis. The apophysis protruding from the conductor is longer and slimmer in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma vimineum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, spur on the conductor is absent, and the median apophysis lacks a pointed hook at the tip.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Carapace yellow. Sternum tan with dark margins. Legs yellow. Abdomen tan with light grey spots randomly distributed on the dorsal area.</p>
                        <p>Male pedipalp: Patella with macroseta. Tibia with one trichobothrium. Paracymbium elongate with sharp tip. Tegulum smooth with rough mesal lobe. Median apophysis slightly grooved, semi-transparent at the distal end (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F26">Figs 26B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F27">27B</xref>). Conductor translucent theca with a hooked end oriented proximally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F26">Fig. 26A</xref>). A piece of long, flat embolic apophysis fragment with a attenuated tip protruding from the ridge of conductor and stretching toward median apophysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F26">Figs 26B, D</xref>). Embolic apophysis fragmented into long, slim bristles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F26">Fig. 26C</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Male: Total length 1.75, carapace 0.95 long, 0.50 wide, clypeus 0.19, sternum 1.54 long, 0.35 wide, coxae IV separated by their width. Posterior median eyes separated by their diameter. Macrosetae: Leg I: femur d 1, patella d 2, tibia d 2, p 1; Leg II: patella d 2, tibia d 2, r 1; Leg III: patella d 1, tibia r 2; Leg IV: tibia d 1. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.23; Tm II: 0.20. Leg measurements: I 2.18 (0.68, 0.25, 0.50, 0.50, 0.25); II 1.86 (0.63, 0.20, 0.38, 0.40, 0.25); III 1.03 (0.35, 0.13, 0.15, 0.25, 0.15); IV 1.31 (0.38, 0.18, 0.30, 0.30, 0.15).</p>
                        <p>Female unknown<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
        <fig id="F26" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 26.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma vimineum</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Right pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Right pedipalp, retrolateral view <bold>C</bold> Embolic division of right pedipalp, retrolateral view <bold>D</bold> Right pedipalp, ventral view. <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>EA</bold> embolic apophysis; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>PC</bold> paracymbium; <bold>T</bold> tegulum. Scale bars: <bold>A</bold> as <bold>B</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g026.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F27" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 27.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma vimineum</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Embolic division of right pedipalp, retrolateral view <bold>B</bold> Right pedipalp, prolateral view. <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>EA</bold> embolic apophysis; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>T</bold> tegulum.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g027.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Genus Zoma Saaristo, 1996">
                <title>Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> Saaristo, 1996
                </title>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> Saaristo, 1996: 51. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma zoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> Saaristo, 1996.
                </p>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zoma</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">fascia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4FC78696-B0B2-413F-B8F1-A4FF9D25591F</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zoma_fascia</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F28">Figs 28</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F29"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F30">30</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: CHINA: Hainan: Mt. Bawangling National Nature Reserve, 5 kilometers past Dongerjianchazhan, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">19°05.186'N, 109°11.802'E</named-content>, elevation ca 1010 m, 25 July 2007, S. Li (IZCAS), 1 male.
                        </p>
                        <p>Paratypes: CHINA: Hainan: Mt. Diaoluoshan National Nature Reserve, Diaoluoshan Resort, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">18°43.766'N, 109°51.815'E</named-content>, elevation ca 1010 m, 15 August 2007, <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->S. Li (IZCAS), 1 female; Mt. Jianfengling National Nature Reserve, Huxiaolongyin scenery, on the mountain by the river, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">18°45.159'N, 108°54.604'E</named-content>, elevation ca 900 m, 20 July 2007, S. Li (IZCAS), 1 female; Mt. Limushan Provincial Nature Reserve, Qulinggulinyuan, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">19°10.686'N, 109°44.490'E</named-content>, elevation ca 654 m, 12 August 2007, C.X. Wang (IZCAS), 1 female; [same data as holotype] (IZCAS), 1 female; Mt. Jianfengling National Nature Reserve, east valley of Tianchi, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">18°54.691'N, 108°51.588'E</named-content>, elevation ca 811 m, 17 July 2007, S. Li (IZCAS), 1 female.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific name comes from a Latin word ‘fascia’, which refers to the silver band on its abdomen; nou<!--PageBreak-->n.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Males distinguished by the presence of a filiform embolic apophysis extending beyond the conductor tip and a 'Z'-shaped embolus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F28">Figs 28B, D</xref>). Exposed portion of embolic apophysis is smaller compared to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma didaiyin</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 10F).
                        </p>
                        <p>Female distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma didaiyin</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the mildly convex posterior margin of the epigyne and the higher position of the spermathecae relative to the copulatory ducts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F29">Figs 29A, B</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Carapace brownish yellow in males, brown in females. Sternum yellow with dark brown margins. Legs yellow. Abdomen beige in males, dark grey in females with silver pecks forming a transverse belt.</p>
                        <p>Male pedipalp: Patella with macroseta. Tibia with one trichobothrium. Paracymbium hooked with short, pointed tip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F28">Fig. 28B</xref>). Median apophysis lightly sclerotized, similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma didaiyin</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: fig. 10D). Conductor translucent. Embolic apophysis filiform, with triangular tip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F28">Fig. 28C</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Vulva: Epigyne a flat orange plate with a low median pit. Spermathecae subspherical, juxtaposed. Copulatory ducts follow simple curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F29">Fig. 29A, B</xref>) .
                        </p>
                        <p>Male: Total length 1.52, carapace 0.72 long, 0.60 wide, clypeus 0.14, sternum 0.37 long, 0.31 wide, coxae IV separated by their width. Posterior median eyes separated by less than half their diameter. Macrosetae: Leg I: femur p 1, patella d 1, tibia d <!--PageBreak-->1, p 1, r 1; Leg II: patella d 2, tibia d 3, v 2, r 1; Leg III: patella d 1, tibia d 1; Leg IV: patella d, tibia d 1. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.21; Tm II: 0.20; Tm III: 0.27. Leg measurements: I 2.19 (0.70, 0.25, 0.50, 0.47, 0.27); II 1.99 (0.63, 0.23, 0.44, 0.39, 0.30); III 1.16 (0.31, 0.23, 0.22, 0.23, 0.17); IV 1.45 (0.39, 0.21, 0.31, 0.31, 0.23).</p>
                        <p>Female: Total length 1.80, carapace 0.88 long, 1.00 wide, clypeus 0.18, sternum 0.50 long, 0.30 wide, coxae IV separated by their width. Posterior median eyes separated by less than half their diameter. Macrosetae as in male. Metatarsal trichobothria: Tm I: 0.30; Tm II: 0.19; Tm III: 0.27. Leg measurements: I 2.11 (0.63, 0.31, 0.47, 0.39, 0.31); II 1.97 (0.63, 0.31, 0.39, 0.39, 0.25); III 1.47 (0.47, 0.23, 0.31, 0.25, 0.21); IV 1.16 (0.31, 0.23, 0.23, 0.23, 0.16).</p>
        <fig id="F28" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 28.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma fascia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Pedipalp, retrolateral view <bold>C </bold>Embolic division, retrolateral view <bold>D</bold> Pedipalp, ventral view. <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>EA</bold> embolic apophysis; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>PC</bold> paracymbium; <bold>T</bold> tegulum. Scale bars: <bold>A</bold> as <bold>B</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g028.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F29" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 29.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma fascia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype (<bold>C</bold>) and female paratype (<bold>A–B, D–F</bold>). <bold>A</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>C</bold> Male habitus, dorsal view <bold>D</bold> Female habitus, dorsal view <bold>E</bold> Female habitus, ventral view <bold>F</bold> Female habitus, lateral view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>S</bold> spermatheca. Scale bars: <bold>A</bold> as <bold>B, D, E</bold> as <bold>F</bold>.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g029.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F30" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 30.</label>
            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma fascia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype (<bold>A–B</bold>) and paratype female (<bold>C–D</bold>). <bold>A</bold> Pedipalp, prolateral view <bold>B</bold> Embolic division, retrolateral view <bold>C</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>D</bold> Vulva, dorsal view. <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>Co</bold> conductor; <bold>EA</bold> embolic apophysis; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>S</bold> spermatheca. <bold>T</bold> tegulum.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g030.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
        <fig id="F31" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            <label>Figure 31.</label>
            <caption><p>Locality records for eleven theridiosomatid spider species in China. <bold>1</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alaria chengguanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n., sp. n. <bold>2</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub rastrarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>3</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baalzebub youyiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>4</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia nitida</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>5</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Karstia prolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>6</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Menglunia inaffecta</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n., sp. n. <bold>7</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ogulnius hapalus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>8</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma plumaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>9</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma triumphalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>10</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridiosoma vimineum</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>11</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zoma fascia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-001-g031.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgement</title>
            <p>The manuscript benefited greatly from comments by Jeremy A. Miller (Naturalis Biodiversity Center) and Michael G. Rix (Western Australian Museum). The study was supported by the National Natural Sciences Foundation of China (China National funds for Distinguished Young Scientists-31025023) and the Knowledge Innovation Program of the Chinese Academy of Sciences (KSCX2-EW-Z-8).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brignoli</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<article-title> Spiders from the Philippines IV. A new <italic>Ogulnius</italic> and notes on some other oriented and Japanese Theridiosomatidae (Araneae).</article-title> <source>Acta Arachnologica </source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2476/asjaa.30.9" xlink:type="simple">10.2476/asjaa.30.9</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> <italic>Karstia</italic>, a new genus of troglophilous Theridiosomatid (Araneae, Theridiosomatidae) from Southwestern China.</article-title> <source>Guizhou Science </source> <volume>28</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coddington</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> The genera of the spider family Theridiosomatidae.</article-title> <source>Smithsonian Contributions to Zoology </source> <volume>422</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>96</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5479/si.00810282.422" xlink:type="simple">10.5479/si.00810282.422</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Locket</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Millidge</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1953</year>)<source> British Spiders. Volume 2.</source> <publisher-name>Ray Society</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>449</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griswold</surname> <given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> The symphytognathoid spiders of the Gaoligongshan, Yunnan, China (Araneae, Araneoidea): Systematics and diversity of micro-orbweavers.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys </source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>195</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.11.160-app.C.dt" xlink:type="simple">10.3897/zookeys.11.160-app.C.dt</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> The World Spider Catalog, version 13.0.</source> <publisher-name>American Museum of Natural History</publisher-name>. Online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://research.amnh.org/entomology/soiders/catalog/INTRO1.html" xlink:type="simple">http://research.amnh.org/entomology/soiders/catalog/INTRO1.html</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname> <given-names>ENL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ott</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Aranhas da família Theridiosomatidae: espécie nova e novas ocorrências no Brasil.</article-title> <source>Iheringia, Série Zoologia </source> <volume>95</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>441</fpage>-<lpage>443</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S0073-47212005000400016" xlink:type="simple">10.1590/S0073-47212005000400016</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Saaristo</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Theridiosomatid spiders of the granitic islands of Seychelles.</article-title> <source>Phelsuma</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname> <given-names>DX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> On some species of cave arachnids of China.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>YY</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed.</role>) <source>Sixtieth Anniversary of the Founding of China Zoological Society: Memorial Volume Dedicated to the Hundredth Anniversary of the Birthday of the Late Prof. Sisan Chen (Z. Chen).</source> <publisher-name>China Science and Technology Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>, <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wunderlich</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Extant and fossil spiders (Araneae).</article-title> <source>Beiträge zur Araneologie </source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>427</fpage>-<lpage>444</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>JX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tso</surname> <given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> First record of the family Theridiosomatidae from Taiwan, with description of a new species (Arachnida: Araneae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British Arachnological Society </source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>-<lpage>266</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>WZ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> The spider family Theridiosomatidae first found in China, and with description of a new species (Araneae).</article-title> <source>Acta Arachnologica Sinica </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>14</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>