<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.149.1517</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>The Lepidoptera of White Sands National Monument, Otero County, New Mexico, USA 3. A new species of 
                    <italic>Aleptina</italic> Dyar, 1902 (Lepidoptera, Noctuidae, Amphipyrinae, Psaphidini)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Metzler</surname>
                        <given-names>Eric H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:BBF4EAD8-74F4-455D-B28E-EFA8015EC34C</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Forbes</surname>
                        <given-names>Gregory S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:BA8A85BE-5E04-4649-8DC4-107A40CCA5A5</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Adjunct Curator of Lepidoptera, Michigan State University, P.O. Box 45, Alamogordo, NM 88311-0045 U.S.A.
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>1009 Luna St, Las Cruces, New Mexico 88001 U.S.A.
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Eric H. Metzler (<email xlink:type="simple">metzlere@msu.edu</email>)
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: D. Lafontaine</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>149</issue>
            <fpage>125</fpage>
            <lpage>133</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>15</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>11</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Eric H. Metzler, Gregory S. Forbes</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:09386409-AE9E-4D09-8658-82228D509F4E</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>In 2006 the US National Park Service initiated a long-term study of the <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> at White Sands National Monument, Otero County, New Mexico. <italic>Aleptina arenaria</italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, described here, was discovered in 2008, the second year of the study. The adult moths and male and female genitalia are illustrated.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Tularosa Basin</kwd>
                <kwd>biological diversity</kwd>
                <kwd>white gypsum dunes</kwd>
                <kwd>Noctuidae</kwd>
                <kwd>White Sands National Monument</kwd>
                <kwd>New Mexico</kwd>
                <kwd>National Park</kwd>
                <kwd>Otero County</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The North American genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Dyar (1902)</xref> was revised by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Todd et al. (1984)</xref>. In 2008, 2009, and 2010, adults of an unknown species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina</tp:taxon-name></italic> were collected at White Sands National Monument, New Mexico. No specimens of this species were <!--PageBreak-->known prior to this study of insects at the Monument. The lack of specimens can probably be attributed to a dearth of collecting in the gypsum dunes ecosystem of White Sands National Monument in New Mexico, which is under the jurisdiction of the U.S. National Park Service and the U.S. Army’s White Sands Missile Range.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
            <title>Methods</title>
            <p>More than 250 samples of moths and other night flying insects were collected in U.S.D.A. type black light traps, and at black light, as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Covell (1984)</xref>, sometimes with mercury vapor light, and sheet on more than 75 different nights. A detailed description of the study methods is in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Metzler et al. (2009)</xref>. Genitalia were examined following procedures outlined in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Metzler and Forbes (2011)</xref>. Terminology for elements of wing pattern, morphology, and genital structures follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Todd et al. (1984)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Lafontaine (2004)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Mikkola et al. (2009)</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>All specimens were collected as part of a long-term study of Lepidoptera at White Sands National Monument, and they are deposited in the following collections:</p>
            <p><abbrev>EHM<def><p>	Eric H. Metzler, Alamogordo, NM, for subsequent transfer to MSU</p></def></abbrev>
            </p>
            <p><abbrev>MSU<def><p>	Albert J. Cook Arthropod Research Collection, Department of Entomology, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI</p></def></abbrev>
            </p>
            <p><abbrev>UNM<def><p>	Museum of Southwestern Biology, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM</p></def></abbrev>
            </p>
            <p><abbrev>USNM<def><p>	United States Museum of Natural History (Smithsonian Institution), Washington, DC pending mutual resolution and agreement with the National Park Service regarding specimen deposition.</p></def></abbrev>
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Aleptina</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">arenaria</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B2D5BDEB-3743-4C92-87EE-9899390FA809</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Aleptina_arenaria</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Metzler &amp; Forbes,</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">11, 12</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">13, 14</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">17, 18</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type Material">
                    <title>Type Material.</title>
                    <p> Holotype: male, pinned with labels as follows: “USA: NM: Otero Co. White Sands Nat[ional] Mon[ument], interdune habitat, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">106°10.84'W, 32°46.64'N</named-content> 4,008', 17 May 2010 WsnmF, Eric H. Metzler, uv tr[a]p, Accss #: WHSA - 00131&quot; “HOLOTYPE USNM <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> Metzler &amp; Forbes” [red handwritten label] (USNM). Paratypes: 5 males and 7 females: USA: NM: Otero Co. White Sands Nat[ional] Mon[ument] (hereafter WSNM), interdune habitat, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">106°11.38'W, 32°46.69'N</named-content> 4,000', 15 July 2009 WSNM8, Eric H. Metzler, uv tr[a]p, Accss #: WHSA - 00131. USA: NM: Otero Co. WSNM, interdune habitat,<!--PageBreak--> <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">106°10.84'W, 32°46.64'N</named-content> 4,008’, 12 Sept. 2010 WSNMF, Eric H. Metzler, uv tr[a]p, Accss #: WHSA – 00131. WSNM, interdune habitat, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">106°11.38'W, 32°46.69'N</named-content> 4,000', 11 June 2010 WSNM8, Eric H. Metzler, uv tr[a]p, Accss #: WHSA - 00131. WSNM, interdune habitat, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">106°11.32'W, 32°45.72'N</named-content> 4,000', 22 July 2008 WSNM9, Eric H. Metzler, uv tr[a]p, Accss #: WHSA - 00131. WSNM, interdune habitat, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">106°11.32'W, 32°45.72'N</named-content> 4,000', 17 May 2010 WSNM9, Eric H. Metzler, uv tr[a]p, Accss #: WHSA - 00131. WSNM, interdune habitat, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">106°10.84'W, 32°46.64'N</named-content> 4,008', 14 Sept 2009 WsnmF, Eric H. Metzler, uv tr[a]p, Accss #: WHSA - 00131. WSNM, interdune habitat, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">106°10.82'W, 32°46.62'N</named-content> 4,008', 15 July 2009 WSNMD, Eric H. Metzler, uv tr[a]p, Accss #: WHSA - 00131. Paratypes are deposited with UNM, MSU and EHM.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> Gypsum sand is the substrate of the white dune field at White Sands National Monument. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arena</tp:taxon-name></italic> means sand in Latin. The Latin suffix -aria means connected with something. The specific epithet of this species, <italic>arenaria</italic>, a singular adjective, calls attention to the specialized sandy habitat where <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> was discovered.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2</xref>) is a gray moth with normal noctuid transverse markings and spots. The diagnostic features are 1) male with gray hindwings, 2) antemedial and subterminal areas of the forewing are pale tan (chamois colored), 3) smoothly rounded apex of the male valve without process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 11</xref>), and 4) blunt posteriorly directed processes on female 8<sup>th</sup> sternite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 13, 14</xref>). In White Sands National Monument <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> flies with and might be mistaken for a washed-out specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina inca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dyar, 1913 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3, 4</xref>).The male hind wing of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina inca</tp:taxon-name></italic> is white, the male hindwing of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> is gray. The clasper of the male genitalia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina inca</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>) is half the length of the valve and slender; the clasper of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> is shorter and heavier, more like that of A<italic>leptina clinopetes</italic> (Dyar, 1920) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 5, 6</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"> 9</xref>). The costal margin at the distal end of the valve of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina clinopetes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 9</xref>) has a finger-like process; the costal margin at the distal end of the valve of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> is without a process. The posteriorly directed processes of the female 8<sup>th</sup> sternite of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina inca</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 15</xref>) are thin, long, and pointed; the processes of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> are stout and short. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina clinopetes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the processes are stout and longer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>). In the key to species in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Todd et al. (1984)</xref>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> keys to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina inca</tp:taxon-name></italic> in couplet 1 because both species have the front (frons) produced into a shelf-like prominence. The differences noted above will separate <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina inca</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina clinopetes</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Adult male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Head - frons produced into a shelf, gray dorsad, pale tan (chamois colored) between the shelf and clypeus; vertex scales narrow strap-like, gray; labial palpus erect, scales spatulate, black laterally and dorsally, white ventrally, each segment pale tipped. Haustellum coiled between labial palpi. Antenna filiform, dorsally pale gray, closely scaled, ventrally naked, gray. Thorax - dorsum gray, mixture of pale and dark, scales spatulate; underside dirty white, scales erect long hair-like. Legs dark gray, closely scaled, sparse long hair-like whitish scales; tarsomeres dark gray and black, white tipped. Fore wing: Length 10 mm (no variation, n = 4). Gray with pale tan (chamois colored) in antemedial and subterminal areas. Basal line obscure, basal area pale gray; antemedial line double at costa, single at inner margin, antemedial area pale tan; postmedial line obscure, excurved beyond reniform, highlighted with dark dashes on veins, double at inner margin; subterminal line a white shade, postmedial area pale tan; terminal line black, subterminal area gray; orbicular spot a round black and white ring filled with gray; reniform spot a kidney shaped black and white ring filled with gray; costa at postmedial area pale gray; fringe gray with white bars; underside gray, darker along costal and terminal areas; fringe dark gray. Hind wing pale gray, darker in terminal areas, fringe pale gray; underside pale gray, costa darker, fringe pale gray. Abdomen - dorsum closely scaled, pale tan-gray; underside closely scaled, whitish. Genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 11</xref>) - tegumen expanded laterally, bilobed, uncus nearly straight, lightly setose, terminally produced to a small bulb, three stout dorsal setae; saccus short, narrowly V-shaped; juxta with long thin spine pointed anteriorly; valve strap-like, sacculus sclerotized, well developed, costa undul<!--PageBreak-->ating, sclerotized basal 2/3 length, cucullus membranous, corona not developed, clasper sinuous, 1/3 length of valve, stout at base, produced to a point. Aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 12</xref>) sinuous, sclerotized, apex with thin blunt point, vesica with two patches of thin setae.
                    </p>
                    <p>Adult female (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>): similar to male. Forewing length 10 mm, no variation, n = 7. Genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 13, 14</xref>): Papilla analis not sclerotized, setose; posterior apophysis extends anteriorly to mid-point of eighth segment; anterior apophysis short and stout; eighth segment anterior ventral margin with two posteriorly directed processes, broadly rounded, acute apices; ductus bursae sclerotized at extreme posterior end, else membranous, elongate directed to right; corpus bursae expanded to left, signa absent.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p> This new species is placed in the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Dyar (1902)</xref> based on appearance of the adult and the structure of the male and female genitalia.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution and biology">
                    <title>Distribution and biology.</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> occurs in White Sands National Monument, Otero County, New Mexico (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 17, 18</xref>). Adults were collected in black light traps placed within the white gypsum dunes, and interdunal areas. The immature stages and larval host plants are unknown.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>In 2006 the U.S. National Park Service invited Metzler to initiate a long-term study of the <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> at White Sands National Monument, Otero County, New Mexico. A primary purpose of the study was to compile an inventory of moths in habitats within and immediately adjacent to the white gypsum dunes in the Monument.
            </p>
            <p>White Sands National Monument preserves 285 km<sup>2</sup> (110 mi<sup>2</sup>), or about 40%, of the world’s largest snow-white gypsum dune field. The remainder of the 275 square miles dune field is under the jurisdiction of the U.S. Army in the White Sands Missile Range. The dune field is located in the northern Chihuahuan Desert in southern New Mexico’s Tularosa Basin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Schneider–Hector 1993</xref>). A complete description of the study site and some of its unique biological resources is in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Metzler et al<italic>.</italic> (2009)</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>There is a dearth of research on the invertebrate fauna in the gypsum dune field in the Tularosa Basin of New Mexico. Details of previous research pertinent to insects is in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Metzler et al. (2009)</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>In the period 9 February 2007 through 30 September 2010 Metzler and Forbes identified more than 430 species of <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> (unpublished data) from the Monument. Because of the unusual physical and biological qualities of the New Mexico white gypsum dunes, we were especially aware of the possibility of finding undescribed species of moths. This is the fifth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Metzler et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Metzler et al. 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Metzler et al. 2010b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Metzler and Forbes 2011</xref>) in a series of papers pertinent to a detailed study of the <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> at White Sands National Monument, and this is the third species of moth described as part of this study. The study of <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> at White Sands National Monument by Metzler and Forbes is projected to last approximately 10 years.
            </p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <caption><p><bold>Figures 1–6. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina</tp:taxon-name></italic> adults. 1</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> Metzler &amp; Forbes, male holotype <bold>2</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> Metzler &amp; Forbes, female paratype <bold>3</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina inca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dyar, male <bold>4</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina inca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dyar, female <bold>5</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina clinopetes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dyar, male <bold>6</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina clinopetes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dyar, female.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-149-125-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <caption><p><bold>Figures 7–12. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina</tp:taxon-name></italic> male genitalia. 7</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina inca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dyar, male genital details <bold>8</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina inca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dyar, male genital details of aedeagus <bold>9</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina clinopetes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dyar, male genital details <bold>10</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina clinopetes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dyar, male genital details of aedeagus <bold>11</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> Metzler &amp; Forbes, male genital details, paratype <bold>12</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> Metzler &amp; Forbes, male genital details of aedeagus. paratype.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-149-125-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <caption><p><bold>Figures 13–16. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina</tp:taxon-name></italic> female genitalia. 13</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> Metzler &amp; Forbes, female genital details. paratype <bold>14</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> Metzler &amp; Forbes, female genital details of two eighth sternite processes. paratype <bold>15</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina inca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dyar, female genital details <bold>16</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina clinopetes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dyar, female genital details.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-149-125-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <caption><p><bold>Figures 17–18. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina</tp:taxon-name></italic> <italic>arenaria</italic> habitat and distribution map. 17</bold> White dunes habitat of type locality of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>18</bold> Distribution map for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aleptina arenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-149-125-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>The Western National Parks Association, Tucson, Arizona contributed funding for travel for this study of <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> at White Sands National Monument. We are grateful for their financial support.
            </p>
            <p>Several persons, Hildy Reiser, Diane White, Cliff Spencer, and Kevin R. Schneider, from the U.S. National Park Service were instrumental in arranging and promoting this study of the moths at White Sands National Monument. We especially thank David Bustos from White Sands National Monument for his assistance and support of our research. The National Park Service renewed the study for 2007 through 2010. Representatives from research collections provided insect pins, alcohol, identification services, research consultation, and storage space for specimens collected. We thank the following persons for offering support from their respective institutions: David B. Richman (NMSU) Kelly B. Miller, Sandra L. Brantley, and David C. Lightfoot (UNM), Frederick W. Stehr, Anthony I. Cognato, and Gary L. Parsons (MSU), Charles V. Covell, Jr., University of Florida, Gainesville FL, J. Donald Lafontaine, Canadian National Collection, Ottawa ON, Larry Berger Ohio Department of Agriculture, and David G. Furth (USNM). Patricia A. Metzler faithfully assisted Metzler in many aspects of this study. We thank Sandra Brantley, Frederick W. Stehr, and two anonymous reviewers for reading the paper and offering valuable suggestions. Don Lafontaine assisted with dissections of male genitalia, and Jocelyn Gill assisted with layout of the color illustrations.<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Covell</surname><given-names>CV Jr</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<source> A Field Guide to Moths of Eastern North America. Virginia Museum of Natural History Special Publication Number 12.</source> <publisher-name>Martinsville</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Virginia</publisher-loc>, <lpage>496</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyar</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1902</year>)<source> Description of a new noctuid. The Canadian Entomologist 34: 105. </source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/Ent34105a-4" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.4039/Ent34105a-4</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyar</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1920</year>)<article-title> New Lepidoptera, chiefly from Mexico, with synonymic notes.</article-title> <source>Insecutor Inscitiae Menstruus </source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafontaine</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<source> The Moths of North America Including Greenland, Fascicle 27.1, Noctuoidea Noctuidae (part) Noctuinae (part - Agrotini).</source> <publisher-name>The Wedge Entomological Research Foundation, Washington</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>DC</publisher-loc>, <lpage>385</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzler</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bustos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> The Lepidoptera of White Sands National Monument, Otero County, New Mexico, USA 1.Two new species of Noctuidae (Lepidoptera, Noctuinae, Agrotini).</article-title> <source>ZooKeys </source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10:3897/zookeys.9.182." xlink:type="simple">doi: 10:3897/zookeys.9.182.</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzler</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bustos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010a</year>)<source> Moth Studies at White Sands National Monument. In: Greenwald David H (Ed) A Walk Through Time - The Tularosa Basin’s Past, 2009 Tularosa Basin Conference Proceedings. CD-ROM.
</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzler</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bustos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010b</year>)<article-title> First records, representing major range extensions, of three species of Lepidoptera (Erebidae, Noctuidae, and Lasiocampidae) from New Mexico.</article-title> <source>Southwestern Entomologist </source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>311</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3958/059.035.0309" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.3958/059.035.0309</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzler</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> The Lepidoptera of White Sands National Monument, Otero County, New Mexico, USA 2. Rediscovery and description of <italic>Sparkia immacula</italic> (Grote, 1883) (Noctuidae, Noctuinae, Hadenini).</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafontaine</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title> Contributions to the systematics of New World macro-moths III.</issue-title> <source>ZooKeys </source> <volume>149</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.149.1516" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.3897/zookeys.149.1516</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikkola</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafontaine</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> The Moths of North America including Greenland Fascicle 26.9 Noctuoidea Noctuidae (part) Xyleninae (part) Apameini (part – <italic>Apamea</italic> group of genera).</source> <publisher-name>The Wedge Entomological Research Foundation, Washington</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>DC</publisher-loc>, <lpage>192</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider–Hector</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<source> White Sands The History of a National Monument.</source> <publisher-name>The University of New Mexico Press. Albuquerque</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New Mexico</publisher-loc>, <lpage>270</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> A revision of the genus <italic>Aleptina</italic> (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae).</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington </source> <volume>86</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>951</fpage>-<lpage>960</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>