<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>ZooKeys</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.126.1229</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>New Palaearctic species of the tribe Thalassaphorurini Pomorski, 1998 (Collembola, Onychiuridae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Babenko</surname>
                        <given-names>Anatoly B.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:22C71A86-BDFB-4110-896F-BAEB6EA54D83</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Chimitova</surname>
                        <given-names>Ayuna B.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:06F46B7B-1F1B-4D78-A555-6E97C9AE375B</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Stebaeva</surname>
                        <given-names>Sophya K.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:8E9BCE43-7BBD-4068-9CB4-03BF4D6EB3AC</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Severtsov Institute of Ecology &amp; Evolution, Russian Academy of Sciences, Leninski pr. 33, Moscow 119071</aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Moscow State Pedagogical University, Kibalchich str. 6, korp. 5, Moscow 129164</aff>
                    <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Institute of Systematics &amp; Ecology of Animals, Siberian Branch of Russian Academy of Sciences, Frunze str. 11, Novosibirsk 630091</aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Anatoly B. Babenko (<email xlink:type="simple">lsdc@mail.ru</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: L. Deharveng</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
            	    <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>2</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>126</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>38</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>10</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>2</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Anatoly B. Babenko, Ayuna B. Chimitova, Sophya K. Stebaeva</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:A7EB628F-D17F-4FC6-9822-D6A0C7EBD48A</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The paper is devoted to a taxonomic revision of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006. Five new species of this genus, i.e. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus taimyrensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vegae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, as well as three new species of the related genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yoshii, 1995, i.e. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus unisetosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> are being described from various regions of Eurasia. The diagnoses of both genera are amended to include described species. Two genera, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski, 1996 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Weiner, 1996, are treated as junior synonyms of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura eisi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Rusek, 1976) is transferred to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Szeptycki, 1964) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus asiaticus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Babenko, 2007 to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. A review of morphological peculiarities of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is performed, comparisons with the other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> given, and a key to the known species provided.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>ά-taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>morphological review</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Sensillonychiurus</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Allonychiurus</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>northern Asia</kwd>
                <kwd>eastern Europe</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>This paper has been prompted through the discovery of a new species on the Barents coast of Kola Peninsula. This species from the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> is characterized by the combination of morphological features that fails to completely fit into any of the known genera of the tribe. Unfortunately, the tribe’s generic classification, as well as that of the whole subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurinae</tp:taxon-name>, is still far from perfect. Starting from the pioneering papers by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Bagnall (1948</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">1949</xref>) and until recently, about 15 genera have been proposed for various representatives of the tribe. Most of these genera are entirely valid, yet some are considered junior synonyms. For instance, at least four synonyms are known for the type genus of the tribe, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bagnall, 1949 alone (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Sun et al. 2010</xref>). At present, according to the database of Collembola of the World (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Bellinger et al. 1996–2011</xref>) the tribe includes nine widely accepted genera: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bagnall, 1949, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Uralaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> Martynova, 1978, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yoshii, 1995, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Weiner, 1996, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski, 1996, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski, 1998, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Detriturus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski, 1998, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006. In addition, there are several generic names that are only used occasionally. Thus, the provisional synonymy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Weiner, 1996 with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was recently rejected by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sun et al. (2011)</xref>.</p>
            <p>The only character uniting all of the members of the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> is the structure of the furcal remnant which forms a finely granulated area in mid-section of <italic>Abd</italic>.4 with 4 small setae arranged in two posterior rows. The second character shared, i.e. distinct antennal and tergal sensilla, is probably present in all genera, but not all species of the tribe. Taking this into account, evidently the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Uralaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> is to be excluded from the tribe in having nothing in common with the other <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, being characterized by a quite different structure of the furcal remnant with four posterior setae arranged in a line. Thus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Uralaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> is probably closer to <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurini</tp:taxon-name> than to <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Babenko 2009</xref>).</p>
            <p>According to R.J. Pomorski (personal communication), two of the remaining eight genera, i.e. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> are to be considered as synonyms. Nevertheless we do not follow here this suggestion as it was never officially published and a discussion on the status of these genera is beyond the scope of our paper. In his draft Synopsis on Palaearctic <tp:taxon-name>Onychiuridae</tp:taxon-name>, Pomorski also intended to synonymize the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (and also <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Most probably, this latter suggestion was dictated by its practical usefulness, as well as by the impossibility to unity the known species of all these “genera” into more or less natural groups, based only on our present knowledge. For instance, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Sun et al. (2009)</xref> only five of about two dozen known species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> completely correspond to the diagnoses as given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Yoshii (1995)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Weiner (1996)</xref>. Later the generic diagnosis was amended by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sun et al. (2011)</xref> to include some species showing a partly reduced tibiotarsal chaetotaxy and smooth sensillar clubs in <italic>AO</italic>. In this scope, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> only in having several rows of manubrial setae posterior to a furcal remnant, and more numerous labral setae.<!--PageBreak--> Two latter genera were separated by the position of <italic>MVO</italic> and a different number of distal setae on the tibiotarsi, namely seven setae in two so far known species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> whereas the type species of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has not eleven (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sun et al. 2011)</xref> but nine setae in distal whorl (personal communication of L. Deharveng). Such a generic classification of the complex partly simplified the situation, but did not completely solve the main problem existing in the group, i.e., the existence of many inadequately described species which can only provisionally be placed in this or that modern genus. Thus, six of 14 species treated as representatives of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the last paper of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sun et al. (2011)</xref> were marked by an asterisk indicating that “<italic>species assignment requires confirmation</italic>”. Furthermore, it is rather difficult to apply this division to some known species as well, since some are purely parthenogenetic or just lack modified setae in reproductive males, e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus asiaticus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Babenko, 2007, which is in other respects virtually identical to the members of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>/<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> complex. The degree of reduction of the tibiotarsal setae appears to be a rather variable character in some genera of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, still being unknown for many described forms. As a revision of all these related genera is beyond the scope of the present paper, we tentatively accept here a broadened conception of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see diagnosis in the end of the paper) and use the following generic classification of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> as consisting of seven genera: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic>d</italic>0 on head absent, <italic>PAO</italic> lobes compound, sternum of <italic>Abd</italic>.3 clearly subdivided, tibiotarsi with 11 setae in distal whorl), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Detriturus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic>d</italic>0 absent, <italic>PAO</italic> lobes compound, sternum of <italic>Abd</italic>.3 not subdivided, <italic>Abd</italic>.5–6 fused, tibiotarsi with 11 setae in distal whorl), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic>d</italic>0 absent, <italic>PAO</italic> lobes compound, sternum of <italic>Abd</italic>.3 not subdivided, <italic>Abd.</italic>5–6 clearly separated, tibiotarsi with 7 or 9 distal setae), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic>d</italic>0 present, <italic>PAO</italic> lobes simple), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic>d</italic>0 present, <italic>PAO</italic> lobes compound, <italic>Abd</italic>.6 with 1+1 prespinal microsetae, multiplication and unusual position of anterior <italic>pso</italic> on head and on abdominal tip, <italic>AS</italic> present or absent), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic>d</italic>0 present, <italic>PAO</italic> lobes compound, <italic>Abd</italic>.6 with 1+1 prespinal microsetae, low number of dorsal <italic>pso</italic> in usual position, <italic>AS</italic> absent) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic>d</italic>0 present, <italic>PAO</italic> lobes compound, <italic>Abd</italic>.6 with 2+2 prespinal setae, <italic>AS</italic> present). The latter genus includes two rather distinct species-groups, the <italic>flavescens</italic>-group and the <italic>volinensis</italic>-group, which clearly differ habitually, as well as in the number of labral setae and setal rows in the manubrial zone of <italic>Abd</italic>.4, but both latter characters may be size-dependent. At the same time, we are sure that this generic system requires additional attention, while the scopes of some genera might be cardinally changed in future.</p>
            <p>The new species mentioned in the beginning of Introduction appears to be especially similar to the known representatives of the small eastern Asiatic genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. A study of the available material from M. Potapov’s and authors’ collections reveals a whole number of closely related forms and shows that the original diagnosis of the genus must be somewhat amended. Thus, the present paper includes a brief review of the morphological peculiarities of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> as compared to the other genera of the tribe, a slightly changed diagnosis and a key to all of the known species of this genus, as well as descriptions of five new species. In addition, three further new species <!--PageBreak-->habitually similar but, according to the accepted system of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, assignable to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>,have also been described and used for comparative purposes. Types of all the new species are deposited in the collection of the Department of Zoology &amp; Ecology, Moscow State Pedagogical University (MSPU).</p>
            <p><bold>Abbreviations</bold></p>
            <p>A–E <bold>papilla,</bold> a, b, d, e <bold>guards</bold> – main labial papillae and associated guard setae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Fjellberg 1999</xref>)</p>
            <p>A, AB, AC and ABC – four types of labium in <tp:taxon-name>Onychiuridae</tp:taxon-name> in accordance with the presence of thickened and blunt-tipped setae on corresponding labial papillae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Fjellberg 1999</xref>)</p>
            <p>Abd<bold>.1–6</bold> – abdominal segments</p>
            <p>A-B<bold>,</bold> T-setae, setae M and Y – tibiotarsal setae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Deharveng 1983</xref>)</p>
            <p>Ant<bold>.1–4</bold> – antennal subsegments</p>
            <p>AO – antennal organ on Ant.3</p>
            <p>AS – anal spines on Abd.6</p>
            <p>bl. f. – basolateral field of labium (mentum)</p>
            <p>bm. f. – basomedial field of labium (submentum)</p>
            <p>d<bold>0</bold> – unpaired axial seta on area frontalis of the head</p>
            <p>a<bold>0</bold>, m<bold>0</bold> and p<bold>0</bold> – unpaired axial setae on terga</p>
            <p>Lg.<bold>1–3</bold> – legs</p>
            <p>ms – microsensillum</p>
            <p>MSPU – Moscow State Pedagogical University</p>
            <p>MVO – male ventral organ</p>
            <p>PAO – postantennal organ</p>
            <p>pso – pseudocellus</p>
            <p>psx – parapseudocellus</p>
            <p>px – proximal setae on labium</p>
            <p>Th<bold>.1–3</bold> – tergal segments</p>
            <p>Ti<bold>.1–3</bold> – tibiotarsi</p>
            <p>U<bold>3</bold> – inner edge of unguis on hind leg</p>
            <p>VT – ventral tube</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="A review of the main morphological characters of Sensillonychiurus Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006"><title>A review of the main morphological characters of Sensillonychiurus Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006</title>
            <p>The present review is based on the morphological peculiarities of five new species described in this paper, as well as on published data on all four so far known species of the genus. Three of them were described by the authors of the genus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Pomorski and Sveenkova 2006</xref>), the fourth one, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus eisi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Rusek, 1976), comb. n., has hitherto been treated as a species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Pomorski 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Arbea 2005</xref>). Nevertheless,<!--PageBreak--> there is good evidence of its similarity to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, for instance, in the absence of <italic>d</italic>0 on the head and in the presence of only three guard setae in <italic>AO</italic> (see figs 11A and 12D in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Rusek 1976</xref>).</p>
            <p><italic>Body shape and size.</italic> All of the so far known species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> are among the smallest <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurinae</tp:taxon-name>, with body size ranging between 0.4 and 0.7 mm. The body is slender and elongated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 8–9</xref>), with rather short antennae and clearly club-shaped <italic>Ant</italic>.4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>). Area antennalis is not distinctly demarcated.</p>
            <p><italic>Sensillar armature of the antennae</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Pomorski and Sveenkova (2006)</xref> considered the presence of only three guard setae in <italic>AO</italic> as the main diagnostic feature of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. These authors, based on an examination of all three species then known, found this character as being unique not only to <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, but to all other <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurinae</tp:taxon-name> as well. They wrote that it “<italic>may indicate that the new taxon is monophyletic</italic>”. However, our study reveals that not all of those species, albeit indeed strikingly similar, are characterized by such a deep reduction of the number of guard setae in <italic>AO</italic>. Thus, a far more usual number (4) of guard setae was found in the European <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., as well as in two eastern Asian species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., thus correlating with a full set (5) of papillae. Only one congener, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus geminus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006, has <italic>AO</italic> with five papillae but three guard setae. That is why not only the diagnosis of the genus has to be slightly amended, but its distinctions from the other genera of the tribe must be reconfirmed, although most of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> are characterized by a complete set (5) of guard setae in <italic>AO</italic>. Apart from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, species with less numerous (4) guard setae are known only among <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Discarding this character, the sensillar chaetotaxy of the antennae in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is not genus-specific, being more or less similar to that in the other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>: <italic>Ant</italic>.4 always bears two distinct thickened sensilla (a dorsal one subapically and an inner one in the mid-section of the segment), a small subapical organite (<italic>or</italic>) and a subbasal microsensillum (<italic>ms</italic>) which is clearly larger than that on <italic>Ant</italic>.3 (see, for instance, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">10</xref>). The latter character is also typical of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The position of <italic>ms</italic> on <italic>Ant</italic>.4 in relation to ordinary setae slightly varies between different species (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 11–14</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">15–17</xref>) and can be used in their identification. Sensorial elements in <italic>AO</italic> of different species of the genus are similar: clubs are smooth, more or less roundish, with or without clear ribs. A different type of sensorial clubs in <italic>AO</italic> (distinctly granulated, morula-like) is known among <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> only in some <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> and in the <italic>flavescens</italic>-group of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <p><italic>Structure of the PAO</italic>. All species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> show a relatively wide <italic>PAO</italic> consisting of few (6–8) vesicles with numerous secondary lobes. As a whole, it usually looks like a single mass with only traces of vesicle divisions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
            <p><italic>Labrum</italic>. All congeners are characterized by a constant number (7) of labral setae, four distal ones being longer and clearly thicker, and two or four prelabral setae. The variant with two prelabral setae seems to be more common (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), but this character is still unknown in <italic>Sensillonychiurus eisi</italic>, <italic>Sensillonychiurus virginis</italic> Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006 and <italic>Sensillonychiurus geminus</italic>. Such a slightly reduced number of labral setae is also typical of all <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> known for this character, as well as of the <italic>volinensis</italic>-group of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but not <!--PageBreak-->of the <italic>flavescens</italic>-group, at least some of which showing nine labral setae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Yoshii 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Sun et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">2011</xref>). This feature is completely unknown in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Detriturus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, whereas among <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> the existing information concerns only <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura calvoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Arbea, 2005, which has nine labral setae (a presumed basal set for <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurinae</tp:taxon-name>), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura sangelensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kaprus’ &amp; Stebaeva, 2006, with two prelabral and seven labral setae (our data).</p>
            <p><italic>Labium</italic>. The type of labium most frequently seen in the genus is <italic>AC</italic>, with the <italic>ABC</italic>-type is found only in two species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. The number of setae on the proximal, basal and laterobasal fields of the labium is more or less stable, although individual variations and some asymmetry are visible in some specimens. The number of distal guard setae of the labial palp corresponds to the most common (and also complete) set found in <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Fjellberg 1999</xref>): seven long guard setae (<italic>b</italic>3-4, <italic>d</italic>3-4, and <italic>e1</italic>-3) and four shorter (<italic>a</italic>1, <italic>b</italic>1-2 and <italic>d</italic>2) ones set on papillae. The only notable peculiarity of the labium in the study group is the unusual length of <italic>a</italic>1 seta which is clearly longer and thicker than <italic>b</italic>1-2 or <italic>d</italic>2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>). Unfortunately, the fine structure of the labium is known only for a few representatives of the tribe, this not allowing for serious comparisons to be made. We can only state that all three types of labium (<italic>А</italic>, <italic>АС</italic> and <italic>АВС</italic>) are known in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Sun et al. 2010</xref>), with <italic>АС</italic> being the most common. In the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, two types (<italic>AC</italic> and <italic>ABC</italic>) are found among species of the <italic>volinensis-</italic>group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Fjellberg 1999</xref>, our data), while only the <italic>AC</italic>-type is known in two species of the <italic>flavescens-</italic>group (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Sun et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">2011</xref>). The <italic>A</italic>-type is observed in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus epaphius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kaprus’ &amp; Tsalan, 2009 and, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Pomorski and Sveenkova (2006)</xref>, in the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Detriturus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The <italic>AB</italic>-type seems to be most characteristic of the genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Pomorski 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Arbea 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Kaprus’ and Stebaeva 2006</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Pomorski, pers. communication). The presence of a complete number of distal guard setae on the labial palp in such small-sized species as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is rather unexpected, as, for instance, all of the so far studied <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> and members of the <italic>volinensis</italic>-group of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, being usually larger, have only ten guards (<italic>e</italic>2 absent) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 41</xref>). The same is probably characteristic of the <italic>flavescens</italic>-group of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Sun et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">2011</xref>) although the authors believe that not <italic>e</italic>2 but one of the <italic>b</italic>–setae is absent. A relatively long <italic>a</italic>1–seta could be suggested as a possible apomorphy of the genus, but there is not enough information concerning the other groups of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> for such an assertion.</p>
            <p><italic>Dorsal and ventral pso</italic>. Contrary to the majority of <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurinae</tp:taxon-name>, the number of dorsal and ventral <italic>pso</italic> does not significantly vary within the genus, being almost always as following: 32/133/33343 (dorsal) and 1/000/0000 (ventral). There are only two exceptions: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus virginis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, with a lesser number of <italic>pso</italic> on thoracic terga(32/022/33343 as a whole), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus geminus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, with some <italic>pso</italic> on two abdominal sterna. The ventral pseudocellar formula of the latter species was given differently by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Pomorski and Sveenkova (2006)</xref> in the original description (1/000/0101) and in their comparative table of diagnostic characters (1/000/10010). The former version is probably the correct one. Apart from this, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurusmirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. often lacks the anteriormost <italic>pso</italic> of the postantennal group on a head. Such a dorsal formula (32/133/33343) is rather common in two other ge<!--PageBreak-->nera of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, namely, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, known also in some <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic>, as well as in different genera of <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Oligaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>. The absence of <italic>pso</italic> on abdominal sterna as the most usual character of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> can also be found among <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Detriturus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Parapseudocelli</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The complete absence of parapseudocelli (<italic>psx</italic>) on the subcoxae, femora and abdominal sterna is characteristic of most of the studied species of the genus, except for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vegae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. which sometimes possesses a pair of <italic>psx</italic> on <italic>Abd</italic>.4. Such a weak development of <italic>psx</italic> is rather frequent among <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, also known in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (in both <italic>flavescens</italic>- and <italic>volinensis</italic>-groups),and some <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Probably it at least partly correlates with the small size of specimens. Some intraspecific variations of <italic>psx</italic> numbers are likely (see, for instance, description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vegae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.n.) and need further attention.</p>
            <p><italic>Dorsal chaetotaxy.</italic> The chaetotaxy in the genus was originally described as follows: “<italic>Seta d0 on the head absent. Abdominal terga of IV, V and VI with 2, 1 and 1 medial setae, respectively</italic>”. It can be added that these unpaired setae (<italic>m</italic>0 and <italic>p</italic>0 on <italic>Abd</italic>.4, <italic>p</italic>0 on <italic>Abd</italic>.5 and <italic>a</italic>0 on <italic>Abd</italic>.6) are meso- or macrosetae probably belonging to the primary chaetotic set, but not microsetae which can appear during ontogeny. Terga of <italic>Th</italic>.2-3 in adults with 3+3, of <italic>Abd</italic>.1-4 with 2+2 and of <italic>Abd</italic>.5 with 1+1, axial microsetae, additionally each tergum with 2+2 mesosetae in the axial group set out of line with microsetae (see, for instance, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>). The same pattern is found in all studied species which appear to have an almost symmetrical (especially in the mid-section of terga) and virtually identical dorsal chaetotaxy. This pattern seems to be unique to <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>. Thus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> shares the absence <italic>d0</italic> with only two genera of the tribe, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Detriturus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Known representatives of both these genera show different distributions of unpaired setae on the abdominal tip (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Arbea and Jordana 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Palacios-Vargas and Diaz 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Pomorski 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Kaprus’ and Tsalan 2009</xref>), the most similar but yet not identical is that in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Detriturus jubilarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gisin 1957</xref>) (see fig. 97G in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Fjellberg 1998</xref>). In the group with <italic>d</italic>0 on the head, species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> with known chaetotic patterns possess a medial seta only on <italic>Abd</italic>.6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Palacios-Vargas and Deharveng 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Beruete et al. 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Pomorski 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Arbea 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Kaprus’ and Stebaeva 2006</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has quite a different chaetotaxy of <italic>Abd</italic>.6 with one or two medial setae and 2+2 prespinal microsetae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 40</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">49</xref>), unpaired setae on <italic>Abd</italic>.4 and 5 are microsetae if present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Lee 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Weiner 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Sun et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">2011</xref>). A similar pattern is typical of most <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <p><italic>Tergal and sternal sensilla.</italic> The lateral microsensillum in all studied species is always present on <italic>Th</italic>.2, but usually absent from <italic>Th</italic>.3, except for two species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus minusculus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus geminus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Several thickened macrosensilla in certain parts on terga and sterna are also very typical of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> and of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> as well. The most usual number of such sensilla in the studied species is as follows, 1/011/222111 from head to <italic>Abd.</italic>6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>), additionally two ventral sensilla are usually distinguishable on the anterolateral part of the head and one sensillum on each ventrolateral side of <italic>Abd</italic>.4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 33</xref>). Variations are not frequent and somewhat obscure; the only clear exception being the European <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. which shows more <!--PageBreak-->dorsal sensilla (2/022/222221 as a whole). The described variability of the character in various genera of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> permits to suggest that it can hardly be used in separating the genera. Moreover, the degree of sensillum differentiation varies widely both between and within species, being clearly age-dependent; sometimes the sensilla look like slightly thickened macrosetae distinguished only due to their positions. Some level of population variability of the character is not improbable either.</p>
            <p><italic>Ventral chaetotaxy.</italic> Most of the species of the genus lack setae on thoracic sterna. The only exception is <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., with 0-1-1 setae on each side of the <italic>linea ventralis</italic> on the thorax (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 33</xref>). Among <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, the complete absence of ventral setae on the thorax is only observed insome species of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Pomorski, pers. communication) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Pomorski 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Arbea 2005</xref>). All studied species also show no setae at the base of <italic>VT</italic> and a rather stable number of setae on its distal lobes (usually 6+6). These latter characters are not unusual in <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, known, e.g., in some <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tibiotarsal chaetotaxy</tp:taxon-name></italic> The pattern characteristic of all studied species of the genus can be described as follows: seven or nine setae in the distal whorl (all or two <italic>T</italic>-setae absent), 7-7-6 setae in <italic>B</italic>-whorl, <italic>Y</italic>-seta present, but <italic>M</italic>-seta absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 20</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">29–30</xref>). The same pattern with 9 distal setae was previously found in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus eisi</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Fjellberg (1991)</xref>. It is noteworthy that the latter character (absence of <italic>M</italic>-seta) only rarely occurs in Poduromorpha. Nevertheless, the same is probably characteristic of some <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Palacios-Vargas and Deharveng 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Arbea 2005</xref>) but the number of tibiotarsal setae in the latter genus is rather variable, with both distal and proximal whorls being partly reduced. For instance, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura sangelensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <italic>Ti</italic>.1-3 bare only 13-13-13 setae, respectively (seven in distal whorl, five <italic>B</italic>-setae and a slightly longer <italic>Y</italic>-seta set virtually in <italic>B</italic>-whorl, <italic>M</italic>-seta absent). Species of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> are known as having 7 or 9 distal setae and 8-8-7 setae in proximal whorls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Beruete et al. 1994</xref>), and so probably possess <italic>M</italic>-seta and lack one of the <italic>B</italic>-seta on <italic>Ti</italic>.3. All of the studied species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic>, as well as all <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the <italic>volinensis</italic>-group (also showing 7-9 distal setae on tibiotarsi), are characterized by a complete <italic>B</italic>-whorl on all legs (7-7-7) and the presence of both setae <italic>M</italic> and <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 47–48</xref>). The same pattern but with few additional proximal setae in <italic>C</italic>-whorls was known for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus antennalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sun, Chen &amp; Deharveng, 2011 from the <italic>flavescens</italic>-group but the data for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura megasomus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sun, Yan &amp; Chen, 2009 is different, with 11 distal setae, 8-7-7 setae in <italic>B</italic>-whorls, and 2-2-1 additional setae involved. All other genera of the tribe feature a complete set of distal setae; in addition, at least some of them, for instance <italic><tp:taxon-name>Detriturus jubilarius</tp:taxon-name></italic>, has <italic>M</italic>-seta (see fig. 389 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Pomorski 1998</xref>). These differences are evidently a good reason to complete the descriptions of tibiotarsal chaetotaxy in such oligochaetotic forms of <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurinae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p><italic>Subdivision of sterna.</italic> Among <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> there is a genus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, characterized by such a unique feature as a secondary division of <italic>Abd</italic>.3 sternum. Some traces of such division can also be seen in all well preserved specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>), as well as in some other small-sized species of various group of <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurinae</tp:taxon-name>. Nevertheless, the anterior subsegment in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is narrow and, contrary to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, lacks setae.<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <p><italic>Furcal remnant position.</italic> In complete agreement with the main diagnostic character of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, the furcal remnant in all studied <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is in the form of a finely granulated area in the mid-section of <italic>Abd</italic>.4, with four small setae arranged in two posterior rows. Individual variations in number and position of these setae are not frequent, but have been noted. The number of setal rows on manubrial area is also more or less stable: usually two rows (<italic>mm</italic> and <italic>mp</italic> according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Weiner (1996)</xref> with 4 setae in each can be distinguished (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 33</xref>) although some variations especially in their position are also seen. Additionally 1+1 setae (<italic>ma</italic>?) usually present at a level with finely granulated area. The most significant is the anterior position of the latter area at contact with the border between <italic>Abd</italic>.3-4 sterna (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">33</xref>). According to the available, mainly illustrative data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Fjellberg 1998</xref>, fig. 88A, Fig. 97F; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Kaprus' and Stebaeva 2006</xref>, Fig. 7; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Kaprus' and Tsalan 2009</xref>, Fig. 1.1), personal communication of R. Pomorski and our observations on the <italic>volinensis</italic>-group of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, all other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> are characterized by posterior position of furcal remnant in some distance from the border between <italic>Abd</italic>.3 and 4, and all of them (<italic>flavescens</italic>-group of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the only exception) possess only one row of manubrial setae behind dental setae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Weiner 1996</xref>). These two characters, i.e. position of furcal remnant and number of manubrial rows of setae, clearly correlate. Thus, all studied species of the <italic>volinensis</italic>-group of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> are characterized by the presence of the same number of 4+4 manubrial setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 43–44</xref>) as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> but due to posterior position of furcal remnant only one row of manubrial setae set posterior to dental setae. Species of the <italic>flavescens</italic>-group of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> appear to be also characterized by posterior position of finely granulated area (see fig. 14 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Sun et al. 2010</xref>), but possess more manubrial setae arranged in several rows; sometimes a few additional setae are present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Weiner 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sun et al. 2011</xref>). This difference was used as a main diagnostic feature in separation of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sun et al. (2011)</xref>. However, it can also be considered as a result of polychaetosis clearly seen on fig. 1B in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sun et al. (2011)</xref>. More investigation including a study of juveniles is probably needed to evaluate the significance of these differences.</p>
            <p><italic>Anal spines</italic>. A full spectrum from complete absence to strong spines set on low papillae is found among the studied species, but an intermediary situation is most frequent. The same is characteristic of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but not of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Detriturus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> (complete absence of spines), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic>AS</italic> absent as an exception) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (spines always present).</p>
            <p>Based on this review of the morphological features, the following can be concluded:</p>
            <p>Regardless of one’s opinion on the status of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, all studied species represent a rather homogeneous group of closely related forms, characterized by many common morphological features and seemingly congruent distributions mainly covering the northern parts of eastern Asia with insulated records from North America and Eastern Europe.</p>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> shares many characters with representatives of other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, but a combination of characters seems to be unique for the tribe. The only features, which set the genus apart from all other <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, <!--PageBreak-->appear to be not the number of guard setae in <italic>AO</italic> but dorsal chaetotaxy and anterior position of furcal remnant at a contact with border between <italic>Abd</italic>.3 and 4 although the data concerning other genera is still rather limited for a final decision.</p>
            <p>Briefly, the genus can be defined as <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> featuring compound vesicles in the <italic>PAO</italic>, a partial reduction of guard setae in the <italic>AO</italic> and on the tibiotarsi, the absence of <italic>d</italic>0 on the head, anterior position of furca remnant and a clearly demarcated dorsal border between <italic>Abd</italic>.5 and 6.</p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Sensillonychiurus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006</tp:taxon-authority>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type-species"><title>Type-species.</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus minusculus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006: 191, by original designation.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Small-sized <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> with low number of compound vesicles in PAO; labrum with 7 setae, labium of <italic>AC</italic> or <italic>ABC</italic>-type; <italic>AO</italic> with 4–5 papillae and 3–4 guard setae, smooth sensory clubs; distinct antennal, tergal and sternal sensilla, without <italic>d</italic>0 on head, <italic>Abd</italic>.4 with <italic>m</italic>0 and <italic>p</italic>0, <italic>Abd</italic>.5 with <italic>p</italic>0, <italic>Abd</italic>.6 dorsally with 1+1 prespinal microsetae and 1 medial macroseta; distal whorl of setae on <italic>Ti</italic>.1-3 with 7 or 9 setae, both <italic>M</italic> seta on all legs and <italic>B</italic>6 on <italic>Ti</italic>.3 absent; <italic>pso</italic> on <italic>Th</italic>.1 usually present, no tendency to dorsal <italic>pso</italic> multiplication, low number of sternal <italic>pso</italic>; <italic>psx</italic> usually absent; sternum of <italic>Abd</italic>.3 not clearly divided, furcal remnant situated at contact with border between <italic>Abd</italic>.3-4 sterna with two regular rows of manubrial setae set posteriorly to 4 dental setae; <italic>AS</italic> present or absent.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Description of species"><title>Description of species</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">mirus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E9A79C2A-7B38-405D-8C45-7B8E67C0C22C</object-id>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Sensillonychiurus_mirus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–7</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material"><title>Material.</title>
                    <p> Holotype ♀, Russia, NW of European part, Kola Peninsula, Dalnie Zelentsy [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">69°07'N, 36°03'E</named-content> ], coastal sandy steep with sparse vegetation (flotation), 19.vii.2009, leg. A. Babenko (MSPU).</p>
                    <p>Paratypes 5 ♀, same data as holotype (MSPU).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Colour white. Size 0.56–0.60 mm. Body slender and elongated. Antennae about as long as head, antennal area not clearly demarcated. <italic>Ant</italic>.4 with two distinct thickened sensilla, subapical organite and basal microsensillum present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.3 organ consisting of 5 papillae, 2 sensory rods, 2 smooth and usually slightly bilobed sensory clubs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>), 4 guard setae, and a lateral microsensillum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.1 and 2 with 7–8 and 12–13 setae, respectively. <italic>PAO</italic> with 7–8 composed vesicles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>).<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> Labrum with 7 setae and 4 prelabral ones. Apical part of labium with thick terminal setae on papillae <italic>A</italic>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic> (<italic>ABC</italic>-type), 11 guard setae, <italic>a</italic>1 clearly longer and thicker than other spiniformguard setae, i.e. <italic>b</italic>1-2 and <italic>d</italic>2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>), and 5 proximal setae. Basal fields of labium (mentum and submentum) with 4 and 5 setae, hypostomal complex reduced to one long seta and a minute projection. Maxillary palp simple, with 2 sublobal setae.</p>
                    <p>Pseudocellar formula (<italic>pso</italic>) as follows, dorsal: 2(3)2/133/33343 (rarely some <italic>pso</italic> duplicated), ventral: 1/000/0000, parapseudocelli (<italic>psx</italic>) invisible. Each upper subcoxa with one <italic>pso</italic>. Localization of <italic>pso</italic> as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>. Granulation fine and uniform, without areas of enlarged granules. Dorsal chaetotaxy almost symmetrical, setae smooth and clearly differentiated only on abdominal tip, in more anterior parts of body setae differing in shape but not in size: some of them straight, thick and blunt, others curved and pointed, sensilla distinct: 2/022/222221 (dorsal) and 2/000/00011 (ventral) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 5–6</xref>), occasionally some additional mesosetae can be thickened and look like other sensilla, thickened sensillum present on coxae <italic>Lg.</italic>3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 7</xref>). <italic>Th</italic>.1 with 6+6 setae as a rule. Lateral microsensilla present only on <italic>Th</italic>.2. Unpaired dorsal seta <italic>d</italic>0 on head absent, <italic>Abd</italic>.4 with <italic>m</italic>0 and <italic>p</italic>0, <italic>Abd</italic>.5 with <italic>p</italic>0, <italic>Abd</italic>.6 dorsally with one axial macroseta and 1+1 prespinal microsetae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>). Thoracic sterna without setae along <italic>linea ventralis</italic>, ventral chaetotaxy of abdomen as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>. <italic>Abd</italic>.3 sternum unclearly divided, anterior subsegment without setae. Furca reduced to a small area of fine granulation situated at contact with border between <italic>Abd</italic>.3-4 sterna, with 2+2 small posterior setae arranged in 2 rows, manubrial area with 4+4 setae set in two rows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>). Ventral tube with 6+6 distal setae, proximal ones at corpus base absent. Upper subcoxae usually with 3-3-4, tibiotarsi with 17-17-16, setae: distal whorl with 9 setae (7 <italic>A</italic> and two <italic>T</italic>-setae), row <italic>B</italic> with 7-7-6 setae, setae <italic>M</italic> absent but <italic>Y</italic> present. Unguis simple, with neither inner nor lateral tooth, unguiculus with an indistinct basal lamella, shorter than unguis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 7</xref>). Anal spine short but rather strong, set on unclear papillae.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 1–7.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>1</bold> <italic>Ant</italic>.3–4; <bold>2</bold> sensorial elements of <italic>Ant</italic>.3 organ <bold>3</bold> <italic>PAO</italic> and adjacent <italic>pso</italic> <bold>4</bold> labium <bold>5</bold> dorsal chaetotaxy and <italic>pso</italic> distribution <bold>6</bold> abdomen, lateral view <bold>7</bold> <italic>Lg</italic>.3. Scales: 5–6 – 0.1 mm, 1–4, 7 – 0.01 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-126-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Affinities"><title>Affinities.</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. clearly differs from the all previously described species of the genus first of all in having not three but four guard setae in <italic>AO</italic>. Nevertheless it is not a unique character for the group. The same structure of <italic>AO</italic> (5 papillae and 4 guards) as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is known in two other species of the genus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (see descriptions below). All these species which are characterized by only a weak reduction of <italic>AO</italic> with a highest possible number of papillae and 4 guard setae have many other characteristics in common (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.). Nonetheless, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. can easily be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the complete absence of setae on thoracic sterna, from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in the different type of labium (<italic>ABC</italic> in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. versus <italic>AC</italic> in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.), and in four prelabral setae (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. possesses only two prelabral setae which are more common in the genus).
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
            <label>Table 1.</label>
            <caption><p>Main diagnostic characters of the known species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic></p></caption>
            		
            <table>
            				
                <tbody>
            						
                    <tr>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal pso</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal sensilla</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AO papillae/guards</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Position of ms on Ant.4</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of prelabral setae</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of labium</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ms on Th.3</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of setae on Th.1</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral setae on thorax</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of distal tibiotarsal setae</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">pso/psx on Abd.4</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unguiculus / unguis ratio</th>
                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anal spines</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus eisi</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/133/33343</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/22211</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">low</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC </td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5+5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus minusculus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/133/33343</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/222111</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">low</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5+5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus virginis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/022/33343</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/222111</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">low</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5+5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus geminus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/133/33343</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/222111</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">low</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5+5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pso</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.n.</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(3)2/133/33343</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/022/222221</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">upper</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6+6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0.5</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus taimyrensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.n.</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/133/33343</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/221111</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">upper</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6+6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0.6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vegae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.n.</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/133/33343</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/221111</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">low</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6+6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–/psx</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0.6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.n.</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/133/33343</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/221111</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">upper</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6+6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0.6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.n.</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/133/33343</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/221111</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/4</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">upper</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6+6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0.7</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/133/33343</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/2222?11</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/3</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">low</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6+6</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                    </tr>
            				
                </tbody>
            		
            </table>
        </table-wrap></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> Initially, the name <italic>mirus</italic> (odd, strange, unusual in Latin) reflects both an isolated position of the new species within the genus and the gap between its type-locality and the distributions of the other known species of the genus which are pure Asiatic or American. The level of morphological uncommonness has lowered after the performed survey of all available material, but the geographical isolation still exists.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p> Known only from the type locality.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">taimyrensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:AC031C4C-13EA-45F9-9DD5-575BD8287653</object-id>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Sensillonychiurus_taimyrensis</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 8</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">10–14, 18, 21</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material"><title>Material.</title>
                    <p> Holotype ♀, Russia, Taimyr Peninsula, northern coast of Taimyr Lake, Postoyannaya River [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">74°38'N, 101°55'E</named-content> ], low river terrace, mosses, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dryas</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Astragalus</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp., 02.viii.1993, leg. A. Babenko (MSPU).</p>
                    <p>Paratypes 5 ♀ and 4 ♂, same data as holotype; 2 ♀ and 1 ♂, Taimyr Peninsula, northwestern coast of Lake Pyasino [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">70°04'N, 87°39'E</named-content> ], herbaceous meadow on south-facing slope, sand, 03.viii.2001; 16 ♀, 10 ♂ and 6 juv., Taimyr Peninsula, middle reaches of Pyasina River, Ust-Tareya [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">73°15'N, 90°35'E</named-content> ], herbaceous meadow on south-facing slope, 22.vii.2010, leg. A. Babenko (MSPU).</p>
                    <p>Other material. 1 ♀, Russia, Siberia, northwestern Buryatia, Ust’-Barguzin [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">53°25'N, 109°01'E</named-content> ], Lake Baikal shore, sandy beach (ca 5 m from water edge, flotation), 21.viii.2008, leg. M. Potapov; 1 ♀, Russia, Siberia, Buryatia, Vitim Plateau, vicinity of Eravna (Sosnovo-Ozerskoe) [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">52°27'N, 111°09'E</named-content> ], dry birch forest, 21.viii.2009, leg. A. Chimitova.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Colour white. Size 0.56–0.62 mm. Body slender and elongated. Antennae about as long as head, antennal area not clearly demarcated. <italic>Ant</italic>.4 with a subapical organite, two distinct thickened sensilla, and a subbasal microsensillum set well above proximal row of setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 10–14</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.3 organ consisting of 4 papillae, 2 sensory rods, 2 smooth sensory clubs, 3 guard setae, and a lateral microsensillum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.1 and 2 usually with 8 and 13 setae, respectively. <italic>PAO</italic> with 7(8) composed vesicles. Labrum with 7 setae and 2 prelabral ones (2/3-4). Apical part of labium of <italic>AC</italic>-type, with (5)6 proximal setae and usually with a complete set of guard setae (11), although asymmetrical absence of one of <italic>e</italic>-guard setae also visible, <italic>a</italic>1-guard long. Basal fields of labium (mentum and submentum) with 4 and 5 setae. Hypostomal complex with one long and one shorter projection. Maxillary palp simple, with 2 sublobal setae.</p>
                    <p>Pseudocellar formula (<italic>pso</italic>) as follows, dorsal: 32/133/33343, ventral: 1/000/0000, parapseudocelli (<italic>psx</italic>) invisible. Each upper subcoxa with one <italic>pso</italic>. Localization of <italic>pso</italic> as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>. Granulation rather fine and uniform, without areas of clearly enlarged granules. Dorsal chaetotaxy almost symmetrical, setae smooth and clearly differentiated, especially on last abdominal terga, in anterior parts of body meso and microsetae similar in size but differing in shape: mesosetae straight and blunt, microsetae curved and pointed, sensilla more or less distinct on terga and less evident on sterna: 1/011/221-2111 (dorsal) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>) and 2/000/0000-1 (ventral), sensillum on coxae of <italic>Lg.</italic>3 present but not distinct. <italic>Th</italic>.1 with 6+6 setae. Lateral microsensilla present only on <italic>Th</italic>.2. Unpaired dorsal seta <italic>d</italic>0 on head absent, <italic>Abd</italic>.4 with <italic>m</italic>0 and <italic>p</italic>0, <italic>Abd</italic>.5 with <italic>p</italic>0, <italic>Abd</italic>.6 with one axial macroseta (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 8</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">18</xref>). Axial microsetae <italic>p</italic>1 set anteriorly to mesosetae <italic>p</italic>2 on <italic>Abd</italic>.1-3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 21</xref>). Thoracic sterna without setae along <italic>linea ventralis</italic>. <italic>Abd</italic>.3 sternum unclearly divided, anterior subsegment without setae. Furca reduced to a small area of fine granulation situated at contact with border between <italic>Abd</italic>.3-4<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> sterna, with 2+2 small posterior setae arranged in two rows, manubrial area with 4+4 setae set in two rows. Ventral tube with 6+6 distal setae, proximal ones at corpus base absent. Upper subcoxae usually with 3-4-4, tibiotarsi with 15-15-14, setae: distal rows with 7 setae (all <italic>T</italic>-setae absent), row <italic>B</italic> with 7-7-6 setae, setae <italic>M</italic> absent but <italic>Y</italic> present. Unguis simple, with neither inner nor lateral tooth, unguiculus with an indistinct basal lamella, clearly shorter than unguis (about 0.6–0.65 <italic>U</italic>3).Anal spines short (0.7–0.75 <italic>U</italic>3) but rather thick (thickness/length 0.23–0.28), set on low papillae.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 8–9.</label>
                        <caption><p>Dorsal chaetotaxy and <italic>pso</italic> distribution, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus taimyrensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>8</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vegae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>9</bold> Scale: 0.01 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-126-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 10–23.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus taimyrensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>(10–14, 18, 21)</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vegae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>(15–17, 19–20, 22–23)</bold> <bold>10</bold> antenna <bold>11–17</bold> position of <italic>ms</italic> on <italic>Ant</italic>.4, different views <bold>18–19</bold> <italic>Abd</italic>.6 <bold>20</bold> tibiotarsus of <italic>Lg</italic>.3; <bold>21–22</bold> axial chaetotaxy of <italic>Abd</italic>.3 <bold>23</bold> ventral <italic>psx</italic> on posterolateral part of <italic>Abd</italic>.4 (specimen from Vitim Plateau). Scale: 0.01 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-126-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Affinities"><title>Affinities.</title>
                    <p> Apart from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus taimyrensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., only two known species of the genus, i.e. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus minusculus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vegae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., completely lack all <italic>T</italic>-setae on tibiotarsi (distal whorl with 7 setae). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus minusculus</tp:taxon-name></italic> clearly differs in having lateral <italic>ms</italic> on <italic>Th</italic>.3 and <italic>Abd</italic>.6 without <italic>AS</italic>. Two other species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vegae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus taimyrensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. are very similar, sharing many common characteristics (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Nonetheless <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus taimyrensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. can be easily distinguished due to stronger <italic>AS</italic> set on low papillae (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 18 and 19</xref>), more distal position of <italic>ms</italic> on <italic>Ant</italic>.4 (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 10–14</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">15–17</xref>) and clear differences in the mutual position of microsetae <italic>p</italic>1 and mesosetae <italic>p</italic>2 on <italic>Abd</italic>.3 (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 21 and 22</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> The new species was named after its <italic>terra typica</italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p> Despite a few records the new species is probably widespread in eastern Siberia being found in such remote regions as Taimyr’s tundras and mountainous Buryatia. Previously the species was erroneously listed for Taimyr as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Szeptycki, 1964) by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Babenko (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Babenko and Fjellberg (2006)</xref>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">vegae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0086C2ED-D20C-45F3-A220-4F4D9383558B</object-id>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Sensillonychiurus_vegae</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">15–17, 19–20, 22–23</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material"><title>Material.</title>
                    <p> Holotype ♂, Russia, eastern Siberia, Yakutia (Sakha Republic), mouth of Yana River, Shirokostan Peninsula, vicinity of Lake Ledyanoe [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">72°25'N, 141°00'E</named-content> ], <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dryas</tp:taxon-name></italic> association on steep slope, 04.viii.1994, leg. A. Babenko (MSPU).</p>
                    <p>Paratypes 6 ♀, 1 ♂, and 1 juv., Russia, eastern Siberia, Yakutia (Sakha Republic), left bank of Kolyma River [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">69°32'N, 160°44'E</named-content> ], grass (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Elymus sibiricus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) association on a polar fox hill, 19.viii.1994, leg. A. Babenko (MSPU).</p>
                    <p>Other material: 1♀ and 2♂, Russia, Siberia, northwestern Buryatia, Ust’-Barguzin [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">53°25'N, 109°01'E</named-content> ], shore of Lake Baikal, pine forest on sandy dunes (flotation), 21.viii 2008, leg. M. Potapov; 2♀, 6♂ and 6 juv., Russia, Siberia, Buryatia, Vitim Plateau, vicinity of Eravna (Sosnovo-Ozerskoe) [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">52°27'N, 111°09'E</named-content> ], pine forest with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhododendron dauricum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 08.ix.2008, leg. A. Chimitova; 2 ♂, same region, but birch forest, 25.viii.2009, leg. A. Chimitova (MSPU).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Colour white. Size 0.40–0.52 mm, holotype 0.47 mm long. Body slender and elongated. Antennae about as long as head, antennal area not clearly demarcated. Sensillar armature of <italic>Ant</italic>.4 as usual: two distinct thickened sensilla, a sub<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->apical organite and a basal microsensillum set almost in line with proximal row of setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 15–17</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.3 organ consisting of 4 papillae, 2 sensory rods, 2 smooth sensory clubs, 3 guard setae, and a lateral microsensillum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 15</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.1 and 2 usually with 8 and 13(14) setae, respectively. <italic>PAO</italic> with 6–7(8) composed vesicles. Labrum with 7 setae and 2 prelabral ones (2/3–4), four setae of apical row thicker. Apical part of labium with thick terminal setae on papillae <italic>A</italic> and <italic>C</italic> (<italic>AC</italic> – type), (5)6 proximal setae and a complete set (11) of guard setae: 7 long [<italic>b</italic>3-4, <italic>d</italic>3-4, <italic>e</italic>1-3] and 4 spiniform [<italic>a</italic>1, <italic>b</italic>1-2 and <italic>d</italic>2] ones set on papillae, <italic>a</italic>1 clearly longer than others. Basal fields (mentum and submentum) with 4 and 5 setae. Maxillary palp simple, with two sublobal setae.</p>
                    <p>Pseudocellar formula (<italic>pso</italic>) as follows, dorsal: 32/133/33343, ventral: 1/000/0000, <italic>Abd</italic>.4 sterna with or without 1+1 parapseudocelli laterally (see Variability). Each upper subcoxa with one <italic>pso</italic>. Granulation fine and uniform, slightly enlarged granules rarely present around medial <italic>pso</italic> on abdominal tip and on head. Dorsal chaetotaxy almost symmetrical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 9</xref>), setae smooth and clearly differentiated, especially on last abdominal terga, in anterior parts of body meso and microsetae only slightly differing in size but different in shape: mesosetae straight and blunt, microsetae curved and pointed. Tergal sensilla (1/011/221111 in number) distinct, sternal ones (2/000/0000-1) hardly distinguished, sensillum on coxae of <italic>Lg.</italic>3 evident. <italic>Th</italic>.1 usually with 6+6 setae. Lateral microsensilla present only on <italic>Th</italic>.2. Unpaired dorsal seta <italic>d</italic>0 on head absent, <italic>Abd</italic>.4 with <italic>m</italic>0 and <italic>p</italic>0, <italic>Abd</italic>.5 with <italic>p</italic>0, <italic>Abd</italic>.6 with one axial macroseta (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">18</xref>). Axial microsetae <italic>p</italic>1 lying almost in line with mesosetae <italic>p</italic>2 on <italic>Abd</italic>.3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 22</xref>) and sometimes also on <italic>Abd</italic>.2. Thoracic sterna without setae along <italic>linea ventralis</italic>. <italic>Abd</italic>.3 sternum unclearly divided, anterior subsegment narrow and without setae. Furca reduced to a small area of fine granulation situated at contact with border between <italic>Abd</italic>.3-4 sterna, with 2+2 small posterior setae arranged in two rows, manubrial area usually with 4+4 setae set in two rows. Ventral tube with 6+6 distal setae, proximal ones at corpus base absent. Upper subcoxae usually with 3-4-4, tibiotarsi with 15-15-14, setae: distal rows with 7 setae (all <italic>T</italic>-setae absent), row <italic>B</italic> with 7-7-6 setae, setae <italic>M</italic> absent but <italic>Y</italic> present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 20</xref>). Unguis simple, with neither inner nor lateral tooth, unguiculus with an indistinct basal lamella, about 0.6 times as long as inner edge of <italic>U</italic>3.Anal spine rather long (0.6–0.7 <italic>U</italic>3) but thin (thickness/length 0.13–0.23) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 19</xref>), set without papillae.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Variability"><title>Variability.</title>
                    <p>The types of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vegae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.n. completely lack <italic>psx</italic> as well as all so far studied species of the genus. Nonetheless, at least some of the specimens collected on Vitim Plateau possess 1+1 ventral parapseudocelli on <italic>Abd</italic>.4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 23</xref>) being otherwise identical to the types. This population may represent a separate species, but its reliable distinction is hardly possible. Anyway, more material from different points of the distributional range is needed to evaluate the constancy and significance of this character.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Affinities"><title>Affinities.</title>
                    <p> Virtually all of the main morphological characteristics of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vegae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (structure of <italic>AO</italic> and <italic>PAO</italic>, labrum and labium, dorsal and ventral chaetotaxy, number and distribution of <italic>pso</italic>, presence of <italic>ms</italic> only on <italic>Th</italic>.2, number of setae on subcoxae, tibiotarsi and <italic>VT</italic>) are identical to those of sympatric <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus taimyrensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Concerning the differences of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vegae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus taimyrensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. see description of the latter<!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> The new species was initially collected during the joint Swedish-Russian expedition arranged in 1994 in order to commemorate A.E. Nordenskiöld’s first trip on “Vega” board along the Northern Sea Route (1878–1879). That is why it is named after Nordenskiöld’s famous steamship “Vega”.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p> Known from several remote areas of eastern Siberia. Previously, it was erroneously listed for Yakutia as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Szeptycki, 1964) by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Babenko and Fjellberg (2006)</xref>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">amuricus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E99FF1BA-7739-4019-A89B-7F2E998A520F</object-id>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Sensillonychiurus_amuricus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 24–31</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material"><title>Material.</title>
                    <p> Holotype ♀, Russia, Asiatic part, Khabarovsk suburbs, right bank of Amur river [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">48°33'N, 135°01'E</named-content> ], upper part of sandy beach (flotation), 26 iv 2010, M. Potapov leg (MSPU).</p>
                    <p>Paratypes 3 ♀, 4 ♂ and 1 juv., same data as holotype (MSPU).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Colour white. Size of mature specimens 0.62–0.72 mm. Body slender and elongated. Antennae about as long as head, antennal area not clearly demarcated. <italic>Ant</italic>.4 with a subapical organite, two distinct thickened sensilla, and a subbasal microsensillum set well above proximal row of setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 25</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.3 organ consisting of 5 papillae, 2 sensory rods, 2 smooth sensory clubs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 26–27</xref>), 4 guard setae, and a lateral microsensillum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 25</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.1 and 2 usually with 8 and 13(14) setae, respectively. <italic>PAO</italic> with 6–7 composed vesicles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 28</xref>). Labrum with 7 setae and 2 prelabral ones (2/3–4). Apical part of labium with thick terminal setae on papillae <italic>A</italic> and <italic>C</italic> (<italic>AC</italic> – type), 7 long guard setae [<italic>b</italic>3-4, <italic>d</italic>3-4, <italic>e</italic>1-3] and 4 spiniform ones [<italic>a</italic>1, <italic>b</italic>1-2 and <italic>d</italic>2] set on low papillae, <italic>a</italic>1 clearly longer and thicker than <italic>b</italic>1. Proximal part of labium as usual, with 6 setae, basal fields (mentum and submentum) with 4 and 5 setae. Maxillary palp simple, with 2 sublobal setae.</p>
                    <p>Pseudocellar formula (<italic>pso</italic>) as follows, dorsal: 32/133/33343, ventral: 1/000/0000, parapseudocelli (<italic>psx</italic>) invisible. Each upper subcoxa with one <italic>pso</italic>. Localization of <italic>pso</italic> as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 24</xref>. Granulation rather fine and uniform, without areas of clearly enlarged granules. Dorsal chaetotaxy almost symmetrical, setae smooth and clearly differentiated, especially on last abdominal terga, differences between macro- and microsetae in anterior parts of body not so pronounced but visible: macrosetae more straight and blunt, microsetae curved and pointed. Dorsal sensilla distinct, flame-like, 1/011/221111 in number (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 24</xref>), ventral ones (2/000/0001) slightly thickened and sometimes hard to detect, sensillum on coxae of <italic>Lg.</italic>3 distinct. <italic>Th</italic>.1 with 6+6 setae. Lateral microsensilla present only on <italic>Th</italic>.2. Unpaired dorsal seta <italic>d</italic>0 on head absent, <italic>Abd</italic>.4 with <italic>m</italic>0 and <italic>p</italic>0, <italic>Abd</italic>.5 with <italic>p</italic>0, <italic>Abd</italic>.6 with one axial macroseta (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 24</xref>). Thoracic sterna without setae along <italic>linea ventralis</italic>. <italic>Abd</italic>.3 sternum unclearly divided, anterior subsegment without setae. Furca reduced to a small area of fine granulation situated at contact with border <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->between <italic>Abd</italic>.3-4 sterna, with 2+2 small posterior setae arranged in two rows, manubrial area with 4+4 setae set in two rows. Ventral tube with 6+6 distal setae, proximal ones at corpus base absent. Upper subcoxae usually with 3-4-4, tibiotarsi with 17-17-16, setae: distal rows with 9 setae (2 <italic>T</italic>-setae absent), row <italic>B</italic> with 7-7-6 setae, setae <italic>M</italic> absent but <italic>Y</italic> present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 29–30</xref>). Unguis simple, with neither inner nor lateral tooth, unguiculus with an indistinct basal lamella, shorter than unguis (ca 0.7 <italic>U</italic>3).Anal spines short (0.7–0.75 <italic>U</italic>3) and thin, set without papillae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 31</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 24–31.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>24</bold> dorsal chaetotaxy <bold>25</bold> <italic>Ant</italic>.3–4 <bold>26–27</bold> sensorial elements of <italic>Ant</italic>.3 organ, different view <bold>28</bold> <italic>PAO</italic> and adjacent <italic>pso</italic> <bold>29–30</bold> tibiotarsus of <italic>Lg</italic>.3, different views <bold>31</bold> <italic>Abd</italic>.6. Scales: 24 – 0.1 mm, 25–31 – 0.01 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-126-001-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Affinities"><title>Affinities.</title>
                    <p> The same structure of <italic>AO</italic> (five papillae and four guard setae) as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is only known in two species of the genus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. All these species which are characterized by only a weak reduction of <italic>AO</italic> with a full number of papillae and 4 guard setae also show the highest number of setae (9) in the distal tibiotarsal whorl. Both can easily be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in having a different type of the labium (<italic>ABC</italic> versus <italic>AC</italic> in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.) and four prelabral setae (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. possesses only two prelabral setae, which occurs more commonly in the genus). Apart from this, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is the largest congener.</p>
                    <p>Two other species of the genus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus virginis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus geminus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, are characterized by the most complete set of tibiotarsal setae (17-17-16) but against the background of a pronounced reduction of <italic>AO.</italic></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> The new species was named after its <italic>terra typica</italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p> Known only from the type locality.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">vitimicus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1EB550A9-8192-4BEF-8826-93D1ABB96418</object-id>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Sensillonychiurus_vitimicus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 32</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">36</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material"><title>Material.</title>
                    <p> Holotype ♂, Russia, Siberia, Buryatia, Vitim Plateau, vicinity of Telemba [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">52°44'N, 113°16'E</named-content> ], larch forest with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Betula fruticosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 23.viii.2009, leg. A. Chimitova (MSPU).</p>
                    <p>Paratypes 7 ♀ and 3 ♂, same data as holotype; 1♀ same region but… larch forest with rich herbaceous cover, 04.x.2009, leg. A. Chimitova (MSPU).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Colour white. Size 0.58–0.68 mm (females), 0.50–0.58 (males). Body slender and elongated. Antennae about as long as head, antennal area not clearly demarcated. <italic>Ant</italic>.4 with 2 distinct thickened sensilla, a subapical organite and a basal microsensillum present, the latter set well above proximal row of setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 34</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.3 organ consisting of 5 papillae, 2 sensory rods, 2 smooth sensory clubs, 4 guard setae, and a lateral microsensillum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 34</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.1 and 2 with 8 and (12)13 setae, respectively. <italic>PAO</italic> with 7–8 composed vesicles. Labrum with 7 setae and 4 prelabral ones. Labium of <italic>AC-</italic>type, but terminal setae on papillae <italic>C</italic> slightly thinner, guard setae as usual for genus: 7(6) long (<italic>b</italic>3-4, <italic>d</italic>3-4, <italic>e</italic>1-3) and 4 spiniform (<italic>a</italic>1, <italic>b</italic>1-2 and <italic>d</italic>2) ones, <italic>a</italic>1 clearly longer and thicker than others. Proximal part of labium with (5)6 setae, mentum and submentum with 4 and 5 setae, respectively. Maxillary palp simple, with 2 sublobal setae<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                    <p>Pseudocellar formula (<italic>pso</italic>) as follows, dorsal: 32/133/33343, ventral: 1/000/0000, parapseudocelli (<italic>psx</italic>) invisible. Each upper subcoxa with one <italic>pso</italic>. Localization of <italic>pso</italic> as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 32</xref>. Granulation fine and uniform, slightly enlarged granules often present around <italic>pso</italic> on last abdominal terga. Dorsal chaetotaxy almost symmetrical, setae smooth and clearly differentiated especially on abdominal tip, in more anterior parts of body macro and microsetae mainly differing in shape, sensilla distinct on terga and less evident on sterna: 1/022/221111 (dorsal) and 2/000/00011 (ventral) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 32–33</xref>), thickened sensillum present also on coxae of <italic>Lg.</italic>3. <italic>Th</italic>.1 with 6+6 setae. Lateral microsensilla present only on <italic>Th</italic>.2. Unpaired dorsal seta <italic>d</italic>0 on head absent, <italic>Abd</italic>.4 with <italic>m</italic>0 and <italic>p</italic>0, <italic>Abd</italic>.5 with <italic>p</italic>0, <italic>Abd</italic>.6 dorsally with one axial macroseta and 1+1 prespinal microsetae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 32</xref>). Thoracic sterna with 0-1-1 setae on each side of <italic>linea ventralis</italic>, ventral chaetotaxy of abdomen as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 33</xref>. <italic>Abd</italic>.3 sternum unclearly divided, anterior subsegment without setae. Furca reduced to a small area of fine granulation situated at contact with border between <italic>Abd</italic>.3-4, with 2+2 small posterior setae arranged in two rows, manubrial area with 4+4 setae set in two rows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 33</xref>). Ventral tube with 6+6(7) distal setae, proximal ones at corpus base absent. Upper subcoxae usually with 3-(3)4-4, tibiotarsi with 17-17-16 setae: distal rows with 9 setae (7 <italic>A</italic> and two <italic>T</italic>-setae), row <italic>B</italic> with 7-7-6 setae, setae <italic>M</italic> absent but <italic>Y</italic> present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 36</xref>). Unguis simple, with neither inner nor lateral tooth, unguiculus with indistinct basal lamella, clearly shorter than unguis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 36</xref>).Anal spine rather strong (about as long as 0.6–0.7 <italic>U</italic>3), set on unclear papillae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 35</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 32–33.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>32</bold> dorsal chaetotaxy <bold>33</bold> ventral chaetotaxy. Scale: 0.1 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-126-001-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 34–39.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>(34–36)</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>(37–39)</bold> <bold>34, 37</bold> <italic>Ant</italic>.3-4 <bold>35</bold> <italic>Abd</italic>.6 <bold>36, 39</bold> tibiotarsus of <italic>Lg</italic>. 3, different views <bold>38</bold> sensorial elements of <italic>Ant</italic>.3 organ. Scale: 0.01 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-126-001-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Affinities"><title>Affinities.</title>
                    <p> Due to the presence of four guard setae in <italic>AO</italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is the most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. All these three species have many other characteristics in common (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), but <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. can easily be distinguished by the presence of setae on thoracic sterna (a presumed apomorphic condition within <tp:taxon-name>Onychiuridae</tp:taxon-name> according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Fjellberg (1998)</xref>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> The new species was named after its <italic>terra typica</italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p> Known from several biotopes in vicinity of the type locality.</p>
                    <p>One more species of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was found on Kamchatka (vicinity of Petropavlovsk, sandy sea beach with weed debris, leg. L. Lobkova). It differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus virginis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in having setiform anal spines, from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus geminus</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the absence of lateral <italic>ms</italic> on <italic>Th</italic>.3. The lack of material (only a single female is available) did not allow us to describe it, but it is listed in the key and in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</p>
                    <sec sec-type="Key to the known species of Sensillonychiurus Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006"><title>Key to the known species of Sensillonychiurus Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006</title>
                        <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
																		<tr><td>1</td><td><italic>AS</italic> not differentiated</td><td>2</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>–</td><td><italic>AS</italic> present</td><td>4</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>2</td><td>Tibiotarsi with 7 distal setae</td><td><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus minusculus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>–</td><td>Tibiotarsi with 9 distal setae</td><td>3</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>3</td><td>Dorsal <italic>pso</italic> as 32/022/33343</td><td><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus virginis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>–</td><td>Dorsal <italic>pso</italic> as 32/133/33343</td><td><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus eisi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Rusek, 1976), comb. n.<!--PageBreak--></td></tr>
																		<tr><td>4</td><td>Tibiotarsi with 9 distal setae</td><td>5</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>–</td><td>Tibiotarsi with 7 distal setae</td><td>9</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>5</td><td>Both <italic>Th</italic>.2-3 with lateral <italic>ms</italic>, ventral <italic>pso</italic> on <italic>Abd</italic>.4 present [1/000/0101 as a whole]</td><td><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus geminus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski &amp; Sveenkova, 2006</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>–</td><td>Only <italic>Th</italic>.2 with lateral <italic>ms</italic>, <italic>Abd</italic>.4 without ventral <italic>pso</italic> [1/000/0000 as a whole]</td><td>6</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>6</td><td><italic>AO</italic> with 5 papillae and 4 guard setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">25</xref>)</td><td>7</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>–</td><td><italic>AO</italic> with 4 papillae and 3 guard setae (as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>)</td><td><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>7</td><td>Thorax with ventral setae</td><td><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vitimicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>–</td><td>Thorax without ventral setae</td><td>8</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>8</td><td>Labium of the <italic>ABC</italic> type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>), 4 prelabral setae present</td><td><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus mirus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>–</td><td>Labium of the <italic>AC</italic> type, only two prelabral setae present</td><td><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus amuricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>9</td><td><italic>AS</italic> strong, set on low papillae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 18</xref>), <italic>ms</italic> on <italic>Ant</italic>.4 clearly above proximal setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 10–14</xref>), microsetae <italic>p</italic>1 set anteriorly to mesosetae <italic>p</italic>2 on all terga from <italic>Abd</italic>.1 to <italic>Abd</italic>.3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 21</xref>)</td><td><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus taimyrensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td></tr>
																		<tr><td>–</td><td><italic>AS</italic> as thick short setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 19</xref>), <italic>ms</italic> on <italic>Ant</italic>.4 almost in line with proximal setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 15–17</xref>), microsetae <italic>p</italic>1 set in line with <italic>p</italic>2 on <italic>Abd</italic>.3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 22</xref>)</td><td><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sensillonychiurus vegae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td></tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
                    </sec>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature><label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Allonychiurus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Yosii, 1995</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Pseudonychiurus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Lin, 1980 (mistakenly created for the moulting specimen) (synonym)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Pomorski, 1996, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Weiner, 1996 (synonym)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type-species"><title>Type-species.</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus flavescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kinoshita, 1916: 458, by original designation.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Small- or medium-sized <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> with compound vesicles in PAO; labrum with 7 or 9 setae, labium of <italic>AC</italic> or <italic>ABC</italic>-type; <italic>AO</italic> with 4–5 papillae and 5 guard setae, smooth or granulated sensory clubs; antennal and tergal sensilla usually distinct, <italic>d</italic>0 on head present, <italic>Abd</italic>.4 and 5 usually with some axial microsetae, <italic>Abd</italic>.6 dorsally with 2+2 prespinal microsetae and 1–2 medial macrosetae; distal whorl on <italic>Ti</italic>.1-3 with 7, 9 or 11 setae, <italic>B-</italic>whorlusually complete on all tibiotarsi<italic>, M</italic> seta present; no tendency to dorsal <italic>pso</italic> multiplication, head and abdominal sterna with ventral <italic>pso</italic>, dorsal <italic>pso</italic> on <italic>Th</italic>.1 usually present; <italic>psx</italic> not numerous or absent; sternum of <italic>Abd</italic>.3 not subdivided, furcal remnant situated at some distance from border between <italic>Abd</italic>.3-4 sterna, with one or several rows of manubrial setae posterior to dental setae; <italic>MVO</italic> present or absent; <italic>AS</italic> present.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p> As it was already stressed in Introduction the genus is accepted here in a wider scope than it was proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sun et al. (2011)</xref> to include species described below. In this scope the genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pomorski, 1996 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic><!--PageBreak--> Weiner, 1996recognized as valid by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sun et al. (2011)</xref> are placed here in synonymy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. In our opinion, the generic value of main differentiated character of these genera, i.e. the number of setal rows on manubrial area, appears to be size and age dependent and needs further attention to be proved. The genus in the accepted scope is rather heterogeneous but completely analogous to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name></italic> which mainly differs in having simple vesicles in <italic>PAO</italic>. Here we only deal with the representatives of so called <italic>volinensis</italic>-group of the genus characterized by small size (less than 1.0 mm), smooth sensorial clubs and usually four papillae in <italic>AO</italic>. According to the generic classification proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sun et al. (2011)</xref>, the species described below should probably be assigned to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> since all of them are characterized by only one row of manubrial setae posterior to dental microsetae and by the position of <italic>MVO</italic> on <italic>Abd</italic>.4 sternum if present. In this case, the degrees of reduction of the tibiotarsal <!--PageBreak-->setae found in the new species completely fill up the gap between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (7–9 versus 9 setae, respectively) and make their distinction rather problematic, taking also into account that not all of these species possess a <italic>MVO</italic>. That is why we are inclined to leave a decision concerning the status of all these genera pending a complete revision of the complex.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">elikonius</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6843EC79-00D9-4039-96E1-D5088E2ACA99</object-id>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Allonychiurus_elikonius</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 37</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">44</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material"><title>Material.</title>
                    <p> Holotype ♀, Russia, Yakutia (Sakha Republic), Suntar-Khayata Mt Range, upper reaches of Kyubyume River [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">63°13'N, 139°32'E</named-content> ], 1,300 m alt., sandbank in Elikon River bed (flotation), 06.vii.2002, leg. O. Makarova (MSPU).</p>
                    <p>Paratypes: 22 females on slides and more than 300 specimens in alcohol, same data as holotype; 11 females, same region, 1,480 m alt., plant community with predominance of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dryas</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. on slope, 07.vii.2002; 7 females, same region, 1,430 m alt., herbaceous meadow on south-facing slope, 07.vii.2002; 14 females on slides and more than 800 specimens in alcohol, same region, greenhouse of “Vostochnaya” Meteorological Station, 1,287 m alt., 24.vii.2002, leg. O. Makarova (MSPU).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Colour white. Size 0.72–0.84 mm. Body slender and elongated. Antennae about as long as head, antennal area not clearly demarcated. <italic>Ant</italic>.4 rather long and narrow, with several curved and slightly thickened sensilla, 2 of which (dorso-subapical and inner-subbasal) straighter and especially distinct, a subapical organite small, usually spherical, a basal microsensillum present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 37</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.3 organ consisting of 4 (or rarely 4+5) low papillae, 2 sensory rods, 2 smooth sensory clubs with ribs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 38</xref>), 5 guard setae, and a lateral microsensillum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 37</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.1 and 2 as a rule with 9 and 12–13 setae. <italic>PAO</italic> with 10–12 composed vesicles set at some distance from each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 42</xref>). Labrum with 7 setae and 4 prelabral ones. Apical part of labium with thick terminal setae on papillae <italic>A</italic> and <italic>C</italic> (<italic>AC</italic>-type), 6 long (<italic>b</italic>3-4, <italic>d</italic>3-4, <italic>e</italic>1, 3; <italic>e</italic>2 absent) and 4 spiniform (<italic>a</italic>1, <italic>b</italic>1-2 and <italic>d</italic>2), guard setae, <italic>a</italic>1shorter than others (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 41</xref>). Proximal field of labium usually with 6 setae, basal fields (mentum and submentum) with 4 and 6 setae. Maxillary palp simple, with 2 sublobal setae.</p>
                    <p>Pseudocellar formula (<italic>pso</italic>) as follows, dorsal: 32/233/33343, ventral: 11/000/0112, additionally one parapseudocellus (<italic>psx</italic>) present on each side of <italic>VT</italic> anteriorly to basal setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 43</xref>). Each upper subcoxa with two <italic>pso</italic>. Localization of <italic>pso</italic> as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 40, 43</xref>. Granulation fine and uniform, without areas of enlarged granules. Dorsal chaetotaxy almost symmetrical, setae smooth and clearly differentiated, especially on abdominal tip, sensilla not always distinct, sometimes hard to detect, particularly so on sterna and medially on <italic>Abd</italic>.1-3: 2/011/222010 (dorsal) and 2/000/00010 (ventral) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 40</xref>), a thickened sensillum on coxae of <italic>Lg.</italic>3 present. <italic>Th</italic>.1 with 5-6(7) setae on each side. Terga of <italic>Th</italic>.2-3 and <italic>Abd</italic>.1-3 with 3+3, <italic>Abd</italic>.4 with 2+2 and <italic>Abd</italic>.5 with 1+1, axial<!--PageBreak--> microsetae. Lateral microsensilla present on both <italic>Th</italic>.2-3. Unpaired dorsal setae: <italic>d</italic>0 on head, microseta <italic>m</italic>0 on <italic>Abd</italic>.4, microseta <italic>a</italic>0 on <italic>Abd</italic>.5, and 2 macrosetae <italic>a</italic>0 and <italic>m</italic>0 on <italic>Abd</italic>.6, supplemented by 2+2 prespinal microsetae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 40</xref>).</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->Sterna of <italic>Th</italic>. 2-3 with 1+1 setae along <italic>linea ventralis</italic>, ventral chaetotaxy of abdomen as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 43</xref>. <italic>Abd</italic>.3 sternum unclearly divided, anterior subsegment without setae. Furca reduced to a small area of fine granulation situated at some distance from border between <italic>Abd</italic>.3-4, with 2+2 small posterior setae arranged in 2 rows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 44</xref>), manubrial area with 4+4 setae arrange in 2 rows but only one of them set posteriorly to small dental setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 43</xref>). Ventral tube with (5)6+6 distal setae and 2 proximal ones at corpus base. Upper subcoxae with (3)4-4-4, tibiotarsi with 18-18-18, setae: distal whorl with 9 setae (7 <italic>A</italic> and 2 <italic>T</italic>-setae), 7 setae in row <italic>B</italic> on each leg, setae <italic>M</italic> and <italic>Y</italic> present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 39</xref>). Unguis simple, with neither inner nor lateral tooth, unguiculus narrow with a long apical filament, latter usually reaching slightly beyond unguis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 39</xref>).Anal spine thick and slightly curved, set on unclear papillae.</p>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 40–44.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>40</bold> dorsal chaetotaxy <bold>41</bold> labium <bold>42</bold> <italic>PAO</italic> and adjacent <italic>pso</italic> <bold>43</bold> ventral chaetotaxy <bold>44</bold> furcal remnant. Scales: 40, 43 – 0.1 mm, 41-42, 44 – 0.01 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-126-001-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Affinities"><title>Affinities.</title>
                    <p> The main morphological features of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. are similar to those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura asiaticus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Babenko, 2007), comb. n. (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Thus, all four species are characterized by virtually identical dorsal chaetotaxy and similar numbers of <italic>pso</italic> on all terga, sterna and subcoxae. The presence of a complete set of <italic>B</italic>-setae and <italic>M</italic>-seta on all tibiotarsi is also shared by them. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. has a different type of the labium (<italic>AC</italic> in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. versus <italic>ABC</italic> in three other species) and differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the mutual position of antennal <italic>pso</italic> (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 40</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">45</xref>). There are also some variations of the number of distal setae on the tibiotarsi in these four species (7 setae in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura asiaticus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 9 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura asiaticus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the only species in the group showing five papillae in <italic>AO</italic> (found in <italic>elikonius</italic> only in exceptional cases), and only <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agraphorura subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is characterized by the presence of setae on all thoracic sterna (absent from <italic>Th</italic>.1 in all other species).</p>
                    <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Table 2.</label>
                        <caption><p>Main diagnostic characters of the known species of the <italic>volinensis</italic>-group of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic></p></caption>
            		
                        <table>
            				
                            <tbody>
            						
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal pso</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral pso</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pso on upper subcoxae</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AO papillae/ guards</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral setae on thorax</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal sensilla</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of  labium</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of prelabral setae</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of distal setae on tibiotarsi</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unguiculus / unguis ratio</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MVO position</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of setae on VT</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/233/33343</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/000/1112‡</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-2-2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0-1-1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/222121</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9-1.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abd.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/6/2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus foliatus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/233/33323†</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">01/000/0000 [?]</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-2-2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VT + genital plate</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?/6/?</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/233/33343</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/000/1112</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-2-2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-1-1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/011/111111</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">genital plate</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/6/2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus donjiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22/222/22222 [?]</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/200/0011 [?]</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-1-1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?/6/?</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus jindoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/233/33333</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/000/0102</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-1-1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?/6/?</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus asiaticus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/233/33343</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/000/0112</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-2-2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-1-1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/222221</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7-0.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">absent</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/6/2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/233/33343</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/000/0112</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-2-2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(5)/5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0-1-1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/011/222010</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9-1.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">males unknown</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/6/2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/233/33343</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/000/1112</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-2-2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-1-1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/222111</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abd.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/6/2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus unisetosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.n.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/233/33343</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/000/0111</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-2-2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0-1-1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/011/222121</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9-1.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abd.4 [?]</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/6/2</td>
                                </tr>
            				
                            </tbody>
            	
                        </table>
            	
                        <table-wrap-foot>
            			
                            <fn>
            					
                                <p>† According to the original description, the species is characterized by 33/233/33323 dorsal <italic>pso</italic> and complete absence of ventral <italic>pso</italic>; most lateral <italic>pso</italic> on posterior side of a head are considered here as being ventral.‡ Slightly different formula of ventral <italic>pso</italic>, i.e. 11/000/0112, is given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Fjellberg (1998)</xref></p>
            			
                            </fn>
            	
                        </table-wrap-foot>
                    </table-wrap>
                    <p>It is more difficult to distinguish <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. from three Korean and one Chinese species of the group, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thibaud &amp; Lee, 1994), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus donjiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Lee &amp; Kim, 1994), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus jindoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Lee &amp; Kim, 1994), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus foliatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Rusek, 1967), because their descriptions are incomplete and probably not fully correct in certain details. The most complete description is that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name></italic>. It is rather similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in having an almost identical chaetotaxy, the same number of dorsal <italic>pso</italic> and tibiotarsal setae (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). The only difference of the sternal <italic>pso</italic> formula is the presence of true pseudocellus on <italic>Abd</italic>.1 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name></italic> instead of an elongated parapseudocellus without clear cuticular ring in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. However, these organs are homologous and sometimes difficult to distinguish. The most characteristic feature of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the presence of <italic>MVO</italic> in mature males. Unfortunately, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in the region under study is only represented by parthenogenetic populations: among more than 100 specimens checked, all were females. Formally, these species differ in size (0.75–0.83 mm in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. versus 0.5–0.65 mm in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name></italic>), in the absence of ventral setae on <italic>Th</italic>.1 in <italic>elikonius</italic>, in the different number of setae on <italic>Ant</italic>.1 (9 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> versus 8 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name></italic>), by unguiculus length (equal to or slightly longer than unguis in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> versus 0.75 of <italic>U</italic>3 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name></italic>), and by the absence of <italic>a</italic>0 on <italic>Abd</italic>.5 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but all these characters are probably variable.<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p>Three remaining species of the <italic>volinensis</italic>-group were described as having a lesser number of dorsal and ventral <italic>pso</italic> (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Yet this probably needs verification. In any case, clear differences in the ecological preferences of compared species confirm the specificity of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. The monsoon subtropical climate of southern Korea (the habitats of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus donjiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus jindoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are sand beaches) and central China (vicinity of Shanghai, the only known locality of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus foliatus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) has nothing to do with the extremely continental conditions of mountainous Yakutia (about 160 km from Oymyakon, one of the coldest places on Earth), where <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. was found. Nevertheless, the probability that some of these nominate species can probe to be conspecific with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus elikonius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. cannot be completely ruled out until their adequate redescriptions.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> The new species was named after its type-locality, Elikon River.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p> Still known only from the region of the type-locality, where it inhabits a number of different communities up to 1,500 m alt.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2400049E-3FC5-4642-AD7D-05683CA7F275</object-id>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Allonychiurus_subvolinensis</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 45–49</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material"><title>Material.</title>
                    <p> Holotype ♂, Russia, Tuva Republic, northern macroslope of Eastern Tannu-Ola Mt Range, 5 km S of Lake Chagytai [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">51°00'N, 94°43'E</named-content> ], larch forest belt, 1,300 m alt., under larch (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Larix sibirica</tp:taxon-name></italic>), 16.vi.2003, leg. S.K. Stebaeva (MSPU).</p>
                    <p>Paratypes ♂, same region and locality, ca 1,400 m, 17.vi.2003; ♀, same region, meadow steppe, ca 1,200 m alt., under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dracocephalum ruyschiana</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 17.vi.2003; 6♀ and 3♂, Russia, Tuva Republic, southern macroslope of Eastern Tannu-Ola Mt Range, 20 km N of Khol’-Oozhu [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">50°44'N, 94°23'E</named-content> ], 1,600 m alt., meadow steppe, under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spiraea</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., 16.vii.1993; 7 specimens, Russia, Tuva Republic, foothills of southern macroslope of Eastern Tannu-Ola Mt Range, basin of Aryskannyg-Khem River, 15 km E of Khol’-Oozhu [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">50°41'N, 94°35'E</named-content> ], ca 1,100-1,250 m alt., dry steppe, under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nanophyton grubovii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 17.vii.1993; 12♀ and 10♂, Russia, Tuva Republic, Sangelen Plateau, 25–30 km NE of Erzin [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">50°15'N, 95°09'E</named-content> ], ca 1,000 m alt., upper terrace of Erzin River, steppe with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caragana spinosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 03viii.1995, all leg. S.K. Stebaeva (MSPU).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Colour white. Size 0.55–0.62 mm. Body slender and elongated, slightly wider in region of <italic>Abd</italic>.4. Antennae about as long as head, antennal area not clearly demarcated. <italic>Ant</italic>.4 rather short and wide, 2 usual sensilla not especially thickened but distinct, a subapical organite and a basal microsensillum present. <italic>Ant</italic>.3 organ consisting of 4 low papillae, 2 sensory rods, 2 smooth sensory clubs without clear ribs, 5 guard setae, and a lateral microsensillum. <italic>Ant</italic>.1 and 2 with 8 and (12)13 setae, respectively. <italic>PAO</italic> wide (length/width ratio ca 1.5), with about 7–10 composed vesicles set close together. Labrum as a rule with 7 setae and 4 prelabral ones, but holotype with an abnormal number of setae set asymmetrically. Apical part of labium with thick <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->terminal setae on papillae <italic>A</italic>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic> (<italic>ABC</italic> – type), seta <italic>A</italic> clearly thicker, 6 long (<italic>e</italic>2 absent) and four spiniform (<italic>a</italic>1, <italic>b</italic>1-2 and <italic>d</italic>2), guard setae, <italic>a</italic>1shorter than others. Proximal field of labium with 5 setae, basal fields (mentum and submentum) with 4 and 5 setae. Maxillary palp simple, with 2 sublobal setae.</p>
                    <p>Pseudocellar formula (<italic>pso</italic>) as follows, dorsal: 32/233/33343 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 45</xref>), ventral: 11/000/1112. Each upper subcoxa with two <italic>pso</italic>. Granulation fine and uniform, without areas of enlarged granules. Dorsal chaetotaxy more or less symmetrical, setae smooth and rather thick, clearly differentiated only on abdominal tip, sensilla: 1/011/222111 (dorsal) and 2/000/00010 (ventral), but distinguishable mainly because of their stable positions, only lateral ones on <italic>Th</italic>.2-<italic>Abd</italic>.1 and posterior one on <italic>Abd</italic>.5 always distinct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 45</xref>), as well as a sensillum on coxae of <italic>Lg.</italic>3. <italic>Th</italic>.1 with 5+5(6) setae. Terga of <italic>Th</italic>.2-<italic>Abd</italic>.1 with 3, <italic>Abd</italic>.2-3 with 3(4), <italic>Abd</italic>.4 with 2-3 and <italic>Abd</italic>. 5 with 1, pairs of axial microsetae, additionally each tergum with 1+1 posterior axial mesosetae set slightly out of line with microsetae. Some unpaired dorsal setae also present: <italic>d</italic>0 on head, microseta <italic>m</italic>0 on <italic>Abd</italic>.4, microseta <italic>a</italic>0 on <italic>Abd</italic>.5, and two macrosetae <italic>a</italic>0 and <italic>m</italic>0 on <italic>Abd</italic>.6, supplemented by 2+2 prespinal microsetae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 45, 49</xref>). Lateral microsensilla present on both <italic>Th</italic>.2-3.</p>
                    <p>Each sternum of <italic>Th</italic>. 1-3 with 1+1 setae along <italic>linea ventralis</italic>. Secondary division of <italic>Abd</italic>.3 sternum unclear because of bad preservation. Furca reduced to a small area of fine granulation situated at some distance from border between <italic>Abd</italic>.3-4 sterna with 2+2 small posterior setae arranged in 2 rows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 46</xref>), manubrial area with 4+4 setae arrange in 2 rows but only one of them set posteriorly to dental setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 46</xref>). Ventral tube usually with 1+1 frontal, 6+6(5–7) distal and 2 proximal setae at corpus base. Upper subcoxae usually with 4-4-4, tibiotarsi with 18-18-18. setae: distal row on each leg with 9 setae (7 <italic>A</italic> and 2 <italic>T</italic>-setae), 7 setae in row <italic>B</italic>, setae <italic>M</italic> and <italic>Y</italic> present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 47–48</xref>). Unguis simple, with neither inner nor lateral tooth, unguiculus narrow, almost as long as unguis (ca 0.9 <italic>U</italic>3).Anal spines thick and slightly curved, set without clear papillae. Reproductive males with <italic>MVO</italic> identical to that in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> with 4+4 modified club-like setae in mid-ventral section of <italic>Abd</italic>.4 behind furcal remnant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 46</xref>), in not reproductive males these setae spiniform.</p>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 45–49.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>45</bold> dorsal chaetotaxy <bold>46</bold> <italic>MVO</italic> on <italic>Abd</italic>.4 <bold>47–48</bold> tibiotarsus of <italic>Lg</italic>.3, different views <bold>49</bold> <italic>Abd</italic>.6, dorsal chaetotaxy. Scales: 45–46 – 0.1 mm, 47–49 – 0.01 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-126-001-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Affinities"><title>Affinities.</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is very similar to the European <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Szeptycki, 1964), comb. n. in many features. Both have a somewhat isolated position within the <italic>volinensis</italic>-group of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> due to the wide <italic>PAO</italic>, the presence of <italic>MVO</italic> on <italic>Abd</italic>.4 and the different positions of <italic>pso</italic> at the antennal base, with <italic>b</italic>-pseudocelli set closer to the mid-line than <italic>a</italic>-pseudocelli. They can easily be distinguished from each other due to the different number of tibiotarsal setae (9 setae in distal whorl in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. versus 7 setae in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and by the presence of ventral setae on all thoracic sterna in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> lacks setae on <italic>Th</italic>.1). The third very similar species of the same group, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus unisetosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., is described below. For differences with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. see the description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus unisetosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> The name reflects the general similarity to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p> The new species was previously listed for Tuva as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> s.str. by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Stebaeva (2003)</xref>. It appears to be rather common in the region in various plant communities, from mountain forests to arid steppes<!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">unisetosus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:613014D9-6782-4406-B0C6-CEC3DEEDB568</object-id>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Allonychiurus_unisetosus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 50–54</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material"><title>Material.</title>
                    <p> Holotype ♂, Russia, Tuva Republic, northern macroslope of Eastern Tannu-Ola Mt Range, vicinity Shuurmak [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">50°38'N, 95°18'E</named-content> ], spruce-larch (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Picea obovata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Larix sibirica</tp:taxon-name></italic>) forest, on larch stump under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cladonia chlorophaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 1,450 m alt., 12.viii.1997, leg. N.V. Sedel'nikova (MSPU).</p>
                    <p>Paratypes 8♀ and ♂, same sample as holotype; 1♀, same region, stony outcrops in mountain steppe, under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xanthoparmelia somloёnsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Parmelia saxatilis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 1,450 m alt., 12.viii.1997, leg. N.V. Sedel'nikova (MSPU).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Colour white. Size 0.55–0.65 mm. Body elongated, wider in region of <italic>Abd</italic>.4. Antennae about as long as head, antennal area not clearly demarcated. <italic>Ant</italic>.4 rather short and wide, 2 usual sensilla not especially thickened but distinct, a subapical organite and a basal microsensillum present. <italic>Ant</italic>.3 organ consisting of 4 low papillae, 2 sensory rods, 2 smooth sensory clubs without clear ribs, 5 guard setae, and a lateral microsensillum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 52</xref>). <italic>Ant</italic>.1 and 2 usually with 8 and 13 setae, respectively. <italic>PAO</italic> wide (length/width ratio ca 1.5), with (7)8–10 composed vesicles set close together. Labrum with 7 setae and 2 prelabral ones. Apical part of labium with thick terminal setae on papillae <italic>A</italic>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic> (<italic>ABC</italic> – type), seta <italic>A</italic> clearly thicker, 6 long (<italic>e</italic>2 absent) and four spiniform (<italic>a</italic>1, <italic>b</italic>1-2 and <italic>d</italic>2), guard setae, <italic>a</italic>1shorter than others. Proximal field of labium with 5 setae, basal fields (mentum and submentum) with 4 and 5 setae. Maxillary palp simple, with 2 sublobal setae.</p>
                    <p>Pseudocellar formula (<italic>pso</italic>) as follows, dorsal: 32/233/33343 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 50</xref>), ventral: 11/000/0111 (one specimen with 1+2 ventral <italic>pso</italic> on <italic>Abd</italic>.4 also visible), sternum of <italic>Abd</italic>.1 with 1+1 <italic>psx</italic> on each side of <italic>VT</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 53</xref>). Upper subcoxae with two <italic>pso</italic> and (2)3-(3)4-(3)4 setae, respectively. Generally granulation rather fine, but areas of clearly enlarged granules usually present around some <italic>pso</italic> and in mid and lateral parts of thorax. Dorsal chaetotaxy almost symmetrical, setae smooth and rather thick, clearly differentiated into macro and microsetae, sensilla poorly distinguishable, 1/011/222121 (dorsal) and 2/000/00010 (ventral), only lateral ones on <italic>Th</italic>.2-<italic>Abd</italic>.1 and posterior one on <italic>Abd</italic>.5 always distinct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 50, 54</xref>). Sensillum on coxae of <italic>Lg.</italic>3 present. <italic>Th</italic>.1 with (4)5+5 setae. Terga of <italic>Th</italic>.2-<italic>Abd</italic>.3 with 3, <italic>Abd</italic>.4 with 2 and <italic>Abd</italic>. 5 with 1, pairs of axial microsetae, additionally each tergum with 1+1 posterior axial mesosetae set slightly out of line with microsetae. Unpaired dorsal setae: <italic>d</italic>0 on head, microseta <italic>m</italic>0 on <italic>Abd</italic>.4, microseta <italic>a</italic>0 on <italic>Abd</italic>.5, and only one macrosetae (<italic>m</italic>0) on <italic>Abd</italic>.6, supplemented by 2+2 prespinal microsetae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 50, 54</xref>). Lateral microsensilla present on both <italic>Th</italic>.2-3.</p>
                    <p>Sterna of <italic>Th</italic>. 1-3 with 0-1-1 setae on each side of <italic>linea ventralis</italic>. Furca reduced to a small area of fine granulation situated at some distance from border between <italic>Abd</italic>.3-4 sterna with 2+2 small posterior setae arranged in 2 rows, manubrial area with 4+4 setae arrange in 2 rows but only one row set posteriorly to small dental setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 53</xref>). Ventral tube usually with 1+1 frontal, 6+6 distal and 2(3) proximal setae at corpus base. Tibiotarsi with 18-18-18 setae: distal row on each leg with 9 setae (7 <italic>A</italic> and 2 <italic>T</italic>-setae), <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->7 setae in row <italic>B</italic>, setae <italic>M</italic> and <italic>Y</italic> present. Unguis simple, without teeth, unguiculus narrow, gradually tapering, with fine filament reaching tip of unguis. Anal spines curved and rather thin, set without papillae. <italic>MVO</italic> in reproductive males probably identical to that in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> but in both available mature males only thickened setae present in mid-ventral section of <italic>Abd</italic>.4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 53</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 50–54.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus unisetosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>50</bold> dorsal chaetotaxy <bold>51</bold> position of anteromedial <italic>pso</italic> on head <bold>52</bold> <italic>AO</italic> <bold>53</bold> ventral chaetotaxy of abdomen <bold>54</bold> <italic>Abd</italic>.6, dorsal chaetotaxy. Scales: 50, 53 – 0.1 mm, 51–52, 54 – 0.01 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-126-001-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Affinities"><title>Affinities.</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus unisetosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. constitutes a rather homogeneous subgroup among the known species of the <italic>volinensis</italic>-group of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. All of them are characterized by identical position of antennal <italic>pso</italic> with <italic>b</italic>-pseudocellus set close to midline and out of antennal area (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 50–51</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">40</xref>). Such a position is unique for the group. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus unisetosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. shares equal number of tibiotarsal setae (9) with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus subvolinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and identical ventral chaetotaxy of thorax (0-1-1) with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus volinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>) but differs from both species in having only two prelabral setae, one ventral <italic>pso</italic> on <italic>Abd</italic>.4 as a rule, only one axial macroseta on dorsal side of <italic>Abd</italic>.6 (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 54</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">49</xref>), and clearly thinner <italic>AS</italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> The name reflects the presence of only one axial macroseta on <italic>Abd</italic>.6 in the new species separating it from similar congeners.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p> Known from several nearby localities of mountain Tuva, previously listed for the same region as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name></italic> s.str. sp. by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Stebaeva et al. (2001)</xref>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">asiaticus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Allonychiurus_asiaticus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Babenko, 2007)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status>comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                  	<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus asiaticus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Babenko 2007</xref> (synonym)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material"><title>Material.</title>
                    <p> 15 specimens, Russia, Siberia, Krasnoyarsk Territory, Achinsk Region, 7 km from Nazarovo [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">57°02'N, 90°39'E</named-content> ], ca 400 m alt., meadows of various types, 1987–88; 9 specimens, Russia, West Siberia, 25 km S of Novosibirsk, Academgorodok [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">54°49'N, 83°08'E</named-content> ], wet grass-herbaceous meadow, 02.X.1994, all leg. S. Stebaeva.</p>
                    <p>The above new material collected from an area lying far south (more than 1,000 km) of the terra typica of the species differs from the original description in having more clearly differentiated tergal sensilla, but otherwise being very similar. These specimens may even represent a separate species, but material from intermediate areas is needed to evaluate the significance of these differences.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We express our sincere thanks to M. Potapov, O. Makarova, I. Kaprus’ and Yu. Sveenkova for the loan of valuable material and for their friendly and fruitful comments. We are also much indebted to S. Golovatch for his kindly editing the English of an advanced draft, as well as to anonymous reviewers and Academic Editor, Louis Deharveng for critical remarks and constructive comments<!--PageBreak-->.</p>
            <p>The paper has been supported through grants of the Russian Foundation for Basic Research (projects 11-04-00941, 11-04-01725, 11-04-01655) and through several scientific programmes of the Russian Academy of Sciences.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Arbea</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> <italic>Agraphorura calvoi</italic> n.sp. from Venezuelan caves (Collembola: Onychiuridae).</article-title> <source>International Journal of Speleology </source> <volume>34</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Arbea</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Estudia ecologico de la collembofauna de los suelos del Macizo de Quinto Real (Pirineos Occidentales) y descripcion de dos especies nuevas: <italic>Anurida flagellata</italic> sp.n. y <italic>Onychiurus subedinensis</italic> sp.n. (Insecta, Collembola).</article-title> <source>Boletín de la Estación Central de Ecología </source> <volume>14</volume> (<issue>28</issue>): <fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Babenko</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> [Landscape chorology of Collembola on Taimyr Peninsula. II. Latitudinal differentiation of the fauna]</article-title>. <source>Zoologicheskii Zhurnal</source> <volume>82</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1051</fpage>–<lpage>1063</lpage> [in Russian, English translation: Entomological Review 83(9): 1194–1207]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Babenko</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Collembolan fauna of the Turukhansk Territory.</article-title> <source>Russian Entomological Journal </source> <volume>16</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>361</fpage>-<lpage>383</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Babenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Two new species of the genus <italic>Uralaphorura</italic> Martynova, 1978 (Collembola: Onychiuridae) from Siberia.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>2108</volume>: <fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Babenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fjellberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> Collembola Septentrionale.</source> <publisher-name>A Catalogue of Springtails of the Arctic Region. KMK Scientific Press Ltd.</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Moscow</publisher-loc>, <lpage>190</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagnall</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1948</year>)<article-title> Contribution towards a knowledge of the Onychiuridae (Collembola–Onychiuroidea). I-IV</article-title>. <source>Annals and Magazine of Natural History</source>, <volume>Ser. 11, 14</volume>: <fpage>631</fpage>–<lpage>642</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagnall</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1949</year>)<article-title> Contribution towards a knowledge of the Onychiuridae (Collembola–Onychiuroidea). V-X</article-title>. <source>Annals and Magazine of Natural History</source>, <volume>Ser. 12, 2</volume>: <fpage>498</fpage>–<lpage>511</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Bellinger PF, Christiansen KA, Janssens F (1996–2011) Checklist of the Collembola of the World. Available from: http://www.collembola.org [accessed 04.04.2011]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Beruete</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arbea</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Contribución al conocimiento de las especies de <italic>Onychiurus</italic> del grupo <italic>O. minutus</italic> (Collembola, Onychiuridae).</article-title> <source>Piblicaciones de Biologia de la Universidad de Naverra, Serie Zoológica </source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Deharveng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> Morphologie evolutive des Collemboles Neanurinae en particulier de la lignee Neanurienne.</article-title> <source>Travaux du Laboratoire d’Ecobiologie des Arthropodes Edaphiques, Toulouse </source> <volume>4</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fjellberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> Tibiotarsal chaetotaxy in Tullbergiinae (Collembola: Onychiuridae).</article-title> <source>Entomologica Scandinavica </source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>-<lpage>434</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fjellberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> The Collembola of Fennoscandia and Denmark. Part. I: Poduromorpha</article-title>. <source>Fauna Entomologica Scandinavica</source> <volume>35</volume>, <lpage>183</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fjellberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Labial palp in Collembola.</article-title> <source>Zoologischer Anzeiger </source> <volume>237</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>330</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gisin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1957</year>)<article-title> Redescription de quelques espèces de Collemboles.</article-title> <source>Acta Zoologica Cracoviensia </source> <volume>2</volume> (<issue>19</issue>): <fpage>453</fpage>-<lpage>468</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaprus’</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stebaeva</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> A new species of <italic>Agraphorura</italic> (Collembola: Onychiuridae) from Southern Siberia.</article-title> <source>Russian Entomological Journal </source> <volume>15</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>351</fpage>-<lpage>353</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaprus’</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsalan</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> New Collembola species from the floodplain forest of the Transcarpathian lowland (Ukraine).</article-title> <source>Vestnik Zoologii </source> <volume>43</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>178</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1916</year>)<article-title> Nipposan Tobimushi no Sanshinsu [On Japanese Collembola]</article-title>. <source>Zoological Magazine (Tokyo)</source> <volume>337</volume>: <fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>460</lpage>. [in Japan]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B-H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>)<article-title> Étude de la faune Coréenne des Collenbales. I. Liste des collemboles de Corée et description des trois espèces nouvelles.</article-title> <source>Revue d’Écologie et de Biologie du Sol </source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>435</fpage>-<lpage>449</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Systematic study on some interstitial Collembola (Insecta) from sand dunes of Korean western coast.</article-title> <source>Korean Journal of Systematic Zoology </source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>207</fpage>-<lpage>215</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S-X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> New subfamily of Onychiuridae.</article-title> <source>Acta Entomologica Sinica </source> <volume>23</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>188</fpage>-<lpage>189</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martynova</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>)<article-title> <italic>Uralaphorura</italic>, a new name for <italic>Uralia</italic> Martynova, 1976 (Collembola: Onychiuridae)</article-title>. <source>Entomologische Berichten</source> <volume>38</volume>: <lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Palacios-Vargas</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deharveng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<article-title> <italic>Onychiurus acuitlapanensis</italic> n.sp. (Collembola: Onychiuridae) cavernicola de Mexico.</article-title> <source>Nouvelle Revue d’Entomologie </source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Palacios-Vargas</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> Seven new species of Onychiuridae (Collembola) from the Neotropical region.</article-title> <source>Folia Entomológica Mexicana </source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pomorski</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> The first instar larvae of Onychiurinae – a systematic study (Collembola: Onychiuridae).</article-title> <source>Genus </source> <volume>7</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pomorski</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<source> Onychiurinae of Poland (Collembola: Onychiuridae).</source> <publisher-name>Genus (Supplement), Polish Taxonomical Society</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Wrocław</publisher-loc>, <lpage>201</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pomorski</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> <italic>Agraphorura spelaea</italic> n. sp. (Collembola: Onychiuridae) from North American caves.</article-title> <source>Journal of Cave and Karst Studies </source> <volume>66</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>76</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pomorski</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sveenkova</surname><given-names>YuB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> New genus with three new species of Thalassaphorurini (Collembola: Onychiuridae) from Russian Far East.</article-title> <source>Insect Systematics &amp; Evolution </source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>-<lpage>196</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/187631206788831092" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1163/187631206788831092</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rusek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> Beitrage zur Kenntnis der Collembola (Apterygota) Chinas.</article-title> <source>Acta Entomologica Bohemoslovaca </source> <volume>64</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>183</fpage>-<lpage>194</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rusek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>)<article-title> New Onychiuridae (Collembola) from Vancouver Island.</article-title> <source>Canadian Journal of Zoology </source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1139/z76-003" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1139/z76-003</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thibaud</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B-H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Three new species of interstitial Collembola (Insecta) from sand dunes of South Korea.</article-title> <source>Korean Journal of Systematic Zoology </source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stebaeva</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Collembola communities of the Ubsu-Nur Basin and adjacent mountains (Russia, Tuva).</article-title> <source>Pedobiologia </source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>-<lpage>356</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stebaeva</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sedel’nikova</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrievsky</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volonikhina</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Microarthropod communities under lichens in the Eastern Tannu-Ola Ridge (Tuva)</article-title>. <source>Zoologicheskii Zhurnal</source> <fpage>80</fpage>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>170</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>. [in Russian] <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1078/0031-4056-00198" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1078/0031-4056-00198</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J-X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> A new species of the genus <italic>Allonychiurus</italic> from China (Collembola: Onychiuridae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>2194</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J-X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deharveng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Six new species of <italic>Thalassaphorura</italic> (Collembola, Onychiuridae) from southern China, with a key to world species of the genus.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>2627</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J-X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deharveng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Redefinition of the genus <italic>Allonychiurus</italic> Yoshii, 1995 (Collembola, Onychiuridae) with description of a new species from China</article-title>. <source>ZooKeys</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.78.977" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.3897/zookeys.78.977</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Szeptycki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<article-title> Dwa nowe gatunki Collembola z wispy Wolin (północno-zachodnia Polska).</article-title> <source>Polskie Pismo Entomologiczne </source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>-<lpage>176</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Onychiurinae (Onychiuridae, Collembola) of North Korea: species of the <italic>Paronychiurus flavescens</italic> (Kinoshita, 1916) group.</article-title> <source>Acta Zoologica Cracoviensia </source> <volume>32</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Generic revision of Onychiuridae (Collembola: Onychiuridae) with cladistic analysis.</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société Entomologique de France (Nouvelle Série) </source> <volume>32</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>163</fpage>-<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshii</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> Identity of some Japanese Collembola. II. “<italic>Deuteraphorura</italic>” group of <italic>Onychiurus</italic>.</article-title> <source>Annales of Speleological Institute, Japan (Iwaizumi) </source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>