<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.81.940</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                The first Strigocis Dury (Coleoptera, Ciidae)  from the southern Neotropical region and  a provisional key to world species
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Lopes-Andrade</surname> 
                        <given-names>Cristiano</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"></xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:6A3F4101-8599-44D9-9210-BCD5DD8564E9</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>Departamento de Biologia Animal, Universidade Federal de Viçosa, 36570-000, Viçosa, Minas Gerais, Brazil</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Cristiano Lopes-Andrade (<email xlink:type="simple">ciidae@gmail.com</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Wolfgang Schawaller</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>18</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>81</issue>
            <fpage>27</fpage>
            <lpage>37</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>24</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>1</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Cristiano Lopes-Andrade</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:57DEF403-5471-478B-943A-F4231CE8C8FE</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lopes-Andrade, <bold>sp. n.</bold> is described based on specimens from a single locality (type locality: Viçosa, state of Minas Gerais, southeastern Brazil), being the southernmost record of a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dury species. Diagnostic to this new species are the dorsal vestiture consisting of stout yellowish bristles, pronotal punctures separated from each other by at least 0.75× puncture-width and sutural flange of elytra not diverging near apex. Males have both frontoclypeal ridge and anterior pronotal margin produced forward and emarginated at middle forming two small subtriangular plates, and a small abdominal sex patch. Among the New World <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, it most resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bilimeki</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Reitter), of which images of male terminalia, as far as ventral and dorsal SEM images of males are also provided. The morphological limits of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are briefly discussed and redefined, and a provisional key to the world species is provided.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Minute tree-fungus beetles</kwd>
                <kwd>Ciinae</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>southeastern Brazil</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dury (<tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Ciidae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Ciinae</tp:taxon-name>) comprises five described species (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Lawrence 1971</xref>): <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Mellié) from central and southern Europe, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bilimeki</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Reitter) from Mexico and probably occurring in southern Arizona, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opacicollis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dury <!--PageBreak-->and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opalescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Casey) from eastern North America and Mexico, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis tokunagai</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Nobuchi) from Hokkaido, Japan. Therefore, the known species occur in the Nearctic, northern Neotropical and Palearctic regions.</p>
            <p>In the latter decade, small series of a new <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> were collect at Viçosa, in the state of Minas Gerais, southeastern Brazil. In spite of the great collection effort in several states of Brazil, the species was not found in any other locality. Here, I describe it as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., compare to the other described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and provide a provisional key to the world species of the genus.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Measurements, final comparisons and description of general external morphology were made under a Zeiss Stemi 2000 stereomicroscope with a scale ocular. Digital photographs of the holotype were taken with a Canon S70 adapted to a Leica MZ16 stereomicroscope, and final images (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–3</xref>) were generated by combining 20 to 40 photographs in different focus using the image stacking freeware CombineZM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Hadley 2006</xref>). Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM) images of male paratypes of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and males of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bilimeki</tp:taxon-name></italic> were obtained using a LEO 1430VP. Specimens were analyzed under variable pressure (SEM-VP) using a backscattered electrons detector, without prior dehydration or gold covering. The holotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–3</xref>) was not dissected. Three male paratypes of the new species and five males <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bilimeki</tp:taxon-name></italic> were dissected for slide preparation and photographing of terminalia (one of each species shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">10</xref>, after dissection). Besides these, males of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opacicollis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opalescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> were also dissected for examining their terminalia. Permanent slide preparations were made using a water-soluble mounting media called “Downs’ gel” (polyvinyl lacto-phenol), prepared by mixing 56% saturated aqueous solution of polyvinil alcohol, 22% phenolic acid and 22% lactic acid. Detailed information on its preparation and use are provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Downs (1943)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Salmon (1947)</xref>. Examination and photography of slide preparations were made under a Zeiss Axioskop 40 compound microscope equipped with a Canon A640 digital camera.</p>
            <p>Terms for external morphology and male terminalia of ciids are explained and discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Lopes-Andrade and Lawrence (2005)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Lopes-Andrade (2008)</xref>. The new species described here was compared to named specimens of all the described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, except for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis tokunagai</tp:taxon-name></italic>. In the latter case, however, a drawing of an adult male was provided in the original description (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Nobuchi 1960</xref>).</p>
            <p>Ten males (including the holotype) and ten females were measured. Range, mean and standard deviation are given for measurements and ratios. Measurements of antennomeres were taken from the holotype. The following abbreviations are used for measurements and ratios: CL, length of the antennal club; EL, elytral length (median length from base of scutellum to elytral apex); EW, greatest elytral width; FL, length of the antennal funicle; GD, greatest depth of the body; PL, pronotal length along midline; PW, greatest pronotal width; TL, total length (EL+PL; head not included).<!--PageBreak--> The ratio GD/EW was taken as an indication of degree of convexity; TL/EW indicates degree of body elongation. The description is based on the holotype, which is a fully pigmented male. Differences among paratypes are given in the section on “Variation”, together with standard measurements and ratios of the type series.</p>
            <p>The following acronyms are used in this paper:</p>
            <p><bold>LAPC</bold>	Cristiano Lopes-Andrade Private Collection (Viçosa, MG, Brazil)</p>
            <p><bold>MZSP</bold>	Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de São Paulo (São Paulo, SP, Brazil)</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Strigocis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">vicosensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:34BA5411-44C2-4D28-B020-0C9F63DB1828</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Lopes-Andrade</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">7</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type-locality"><title>Type-locality.</title>
                    <p>Viçosa, in the state of Minas Gerais, southeastern Brazil (20°45'S, 42°53'W).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> The specific epithet is an adjective referring to the <italic>terra typica</italic> of the species.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> Dorsal vestiture consisting of stout yellowish bristles, pronotal punctures coarse and separated from each other by 0.75× to 1× puncture-width, and sutural flange of elytra not diverging near apex. Males have both frontoclypeal ridge and anterior pronotal margin produced forward and emarginated at middle forming two small subtriangular plates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">4, 5</xref>). Additionally, the abdominal sex patch of males is small, with around one-fifth the length of the first abdominal ventrite at the longitudinal midline.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Male holotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–3</xref>), measurements in mm: TL 1.70; PL 0.55; PW 0.68; EL 1.15; EW 0.73; GD 0.55. Ratios: PL/PW 0.81; EL/EW 1.59; EL/PL 2.09; GD/EW 0.76; TL/EW 2.34. Body elongate, moderately convex; dorsal and ventral surfaces mostly unicolored, almost black, with reddish brown appendages; dorsal vestiture consisting of stout suberect or decumbent yellowish bristles; ventral vestiture consisting of slender decumbent yellowish setae. Head barely seen from above; dorsal surface concave, glabrous; punctation sparse, consisting of course shallow punctures; frontoclypeal ridge slightly raised and produced, its anterior margin with an emargination at middle forming two short subtriangular plates with relatively rounded apices. Eyes coarsely facetted, each one bearing more than 60 ommattidia; greatest eye width 0.10 mm. Antenna (left antenna measured; FL 0.10 mm; CL 0.16 mm; CL/FL 1.63) with length of antennomeres (in mm) as follows: 0.06; 0.05; 0.04; 0.02; 0.01; 0.01; 0.01; 0.05; 0.05; 0.06; sensillifers of the antennal club whitish, conspicuous (seen in magnification of 50×). Pronotum densely punctate, the punctures being coarse and separated from each other by 0.75× to one puncture-width; in between punctures somewhat microreticulate; the stout bristles <!--PageBreak-->of the pronotal disc are decumbent, so attached to the surface that they resemble small scales and are more easily visible in lateral view; anterior portion produced forward and almost concealing the head when seen from above; anterior margin bearing an emargination at middle, forming two small subtriangular plates that are slightly larger than those of the head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">4–5</xref>); anterolateral angles (corners) produced forward and rounded; lateral margins slightly crenulate, almost straight, barely visible from above except for their posterior portions. Scutellum very small, so close to the elytra that makes it barely discernible; posterior margin broadly rounded, so that the entire structure resembles a half-circle; surface bearing small punctures very close to each other, giving a creasy appearance to its surface; basal width 0.07 mm. Hind wings fully developed (macropterous species). Elytra with lateral margins subparallel at basal half, then gradually converging to the apex; punctation single and confused, the punctures being coarser than those on pronotum and closer to each other; bristles similar to those on pronotum, but suberect and a little bit bigger; in between punctures smooth and shiny; sutural flange not diverging near apex (slightly divergent when examined in SEM; see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>, arrows). Ventral sclerites with most of their surfaces finely granulate. Hypomera unpunctate and bearing a few sparse slender setae. Prosternum biconcave and distinctly tumid at the longitudinal midline, carinate. Each protibial with its outer apical angle expanded forming a small acute tooth; apex bearing a row of spines closest to the inner apical angle. Metaventrite with a<!--PageBreak--> few very shallow and coarse punctures, barely discernible; discrimen with one-third the length of the ventrite at the longitudinal midline. Abdominal ventrites bearing several slender setae; first abdominal ventrite twice as long as the second, bearing a small oval margined sex patch, with near one-fifth the length of the ventrite at the longitudinal midline.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 1–3.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lopes-Andrade, sp. n., adult male holotype. <bold>1</bold> Dorsal view <bold>2</bold> Lateral view <bold>3</bold> Ventral view.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-081-027-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Male terminalia in paratypes (Fig. 7)."><title>Male terminalia in paratypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>).</title>
                    <p> Eighth sternite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>) with its posterior margin membranous (tending to collapse during slide preparation), sinuous; corners bearing long setae. Aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>) with near 0.3 mm of length; basal piece large, conspicuous, with two-fifths the length of tegmen; penis subcylindrical, membranous, 0.8× the length of tegmen; tegmen with its posterior portion bearing a narrow emargination at middle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>, small arrow) delimiting two lateral lobes, each lobe with a somewhat V-shaped concavity (dashed lines) ending in two sclerotized tips (large arrows).</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 4–7.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lopes-Andrade, sp. n., SEM-VP of adult male paratypes (4–6) and slide preparation of a male terminalia (7). <bold>4</bold> Slightly oblique dorsal view <bold>5</bold> Ventral view showing the sex patch at the first abdominal ventrite (arrow) <bold>6</bold> Dorsal view of the posterior portion of the elytra in an oblique position, showing the barely discernible diverging sutural flange (arrows) <bold>7</bold> Male terminalia showing the eighth sternite (pregenital sclerite) and dissected aedeagus with conspicuous subtriangular basal piece, subcylindrical membranous penis and tegmen. Note the emargination at the middle of the tegmen’s apex (small arrow), the two V-shaped concavities (dashed lines), and the two sclerotized tips of each lateral lobe (large arrows). Abbreviations: Eighth sternite (viii-st), basal piece (bp), tegmen (teg) and penis (pen).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-081-027-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 8–10.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bilimeki</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Reitter) from Cualac (Mexico, Guerrero), SEM-VP of adult males (8–9) and male terminalia (10). <bold>8</bold> Dorsal view <bold>9</bold> Ventral view showing the sex patch at the first abdominal ventrite (arrow) <bold>10</bold> Slide preparation of a male terminalia showing aedeagus and eighth sternite slightly squashed to emphasize their morphology. Note the membranous penis (dotted line) and the small basal piece (dashed line). Abbreviations: Eighth sternite (viii-st), basal piece (bp), tegmen (teg) and penis (pen).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-081-027-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Females"><title>Females.</title>
                    <p> Head with frontoclypeal ridge just slightly sinuous. Anterior margin of pronotum broadly rounded. Vertex of head with sparse suberect stout bristles. First abdominal ventrite devoid of sex patch.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Variation"><title>Variation.</title>
                    <p> Males, measurements in mm (n = 10, including the holotype): TL 1.33–1.75 (1.59 ± 0.14); PL 0.50–0.70 (0.60 ± 0.07); PW 0.55–0.75 (0.66 ± 0.06); EL 0.80–1.15 (0.98 ± 0.10); EW 0.63–0.78 (0.70 ± 0.05); GD 0.50–0.60 (0.54 ± 0.04). Ratios: PL/PW 0.81–1.00 (0.92 ± 0.06); EL/EW 1.27–1.59 (1.40 ± 0.09); EL/PL 1.43–2.09 (1.64 ± 0.21); GD/EW 0.73–0.83 (0.77 ± 0.03); TL/EW 2.12–2.34 (2.26 ± 0.08). A few males were almost devoid of secondary sexual characters on frontoclypeal<!--PageBreak--> ridge and anterior margin of pronotum. However, the small abdominal sex patch was observed in all available males.</p>
                    <p>Females, measurements in mm (n = 10): TL 1.30–1.65 (1.52 ± 0.13); PL 0.43–0.63 (0.54 ± 0.06); PW 0.53–0.70 (0.62 ± 0.06); EL 0.83–1.10 (0.99 ± 0.08); EW 0.60–0.75 (0.69 ± 0.06); GD 0.45–0.58 (0.54 ± 0.05). Ratios: PL/PW 0.75–0.96 (0.86 ± 0.06); EL/EW 1.38–1.54 (1.44 ± 0.06); EL/PL 1.60–2.18 (1.85 ± 0.17); GD/EW 0.75–0.81 (0.78 ± 0.02); TL/EW 2.14–2.30 (2.22 ± 0.05).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type series"><title>Type series.</title>
                    <p>Male holotype(MZSP) “BRASIL: MG Viçosa; Campus UFV 18.vi.2006 C.B. Oliveira leg. ex <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phellinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.” “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lopes-Andrade HOLOTYPUS” [printed on red paper]. Paratypes: one male (LAPC), same data as holotype; six females, three males (LAPC) “BRASIL: MG Viçosa; 2° Represa UFV; 20.ii.2006 leg. CB Oliveira”; one female (LAPC) “BRASIL: MG Viçosa 16.ii.2002 leg. C. Lopes-Andrade”; 13 females, five males (LAPC) “BRASIL: MG; Viçosa Campus UFV, 3° represa, próx. supermercado 18.vii.2007; colônia II leg C. B. Oliveira”. All paratypes distinguished labeled “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lopes-Andrade PARATYPUS” [printed on yellow paper].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Host fungus"><title>Host fungus.</title>
                    <p>Possibly a single species of an undetermined <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phellinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Quél. (<tp:taxon-name>Hymenochaetaceae</tp:taxon-name>). It’s important to emphasize that only adult ciids were found and they were not observed breeding in the collected basidiomes.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Natural history"><title>Natural history.</title>
                    <p> All the known specimens were collected in open areas of the Federal University of Viçosa’s campus. It was not found in either forested or urban areas of Viçosa, although ciids were continuously collected there from September 1998 until recently. Adults could not be maintained in laboratory for much longer, which suggests that it colonizes and consumes the basidiomes just after sporulation and before basidiomes’ decaying. Another possibility is that the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phellinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. is not a host for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., and adults were incidentally collected in the fungus. The latter explanation is supported by the fact that all the other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> species are known to feed on fungi in the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trametes</tp:taxon-name></italic> host-use group and were never found in association with fungi of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phellinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> host-use group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Orledge and Reynolds 2005</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xylographus gibbus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mellié were found in basidiomes possibly conspecific to the ones inhabited by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., in the same open areas. However, these two ciid species have not been collected together.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comparative notes"><title>Comparative notes.</title>
                    <p>Among the examined <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is the Mexican <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bilimeki</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The latter specieshas pronotal and elytral punctation comparatively denser, subtriangular plates of the frontoclypeal ridge in males usually with acute apices and anterior pronotal margin with a short and relatively narrow lamina bearing a small emargination at middle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 8</xref>). Additionally, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bilimeki</tp:taxon-name></italic> the male sex patch in the first abdominal ventrite is very large (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 9</xref>, arrow), its diameter being at least 0.55× the length of the sclerite at its longitudinal midline. Male terminalia of both species are similar in form, mainly in the subcylindrical membranous penis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">10</xref>) and the shape of the posterior portion of tegmen. However, the whole aedeagus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bilimeki</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>) has around 0.8× the length of the one of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., a proportionally smaller basal piece (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>, dashed lines) and is less sclerotized. Moreover, the posterior margin of the eighth sternite has a broad U-shape emargination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>) similar to that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opacicollis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opalescens</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    <!--PageBreak-->
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opalescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a vestiture of minute setae barely visible even in high magnifications (50×), sparse pronotal and elytral punctation, and broad lateral margins of pronotum forming a raised lip. The tegmen of its male terminalia is subquadrate, with a deep U-shaped emargination at middle delimiting two lateral lobes, each lobe bearing a small emargination at apex. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a small blackish species with shallow pronotal and elytral punctation, irregular elytral surface with in between punctures finely granulate, and dorsal vestiture of fine setae. Its tegmen is elongate, with a rounded posterior margin bearing a very narrow V-shape emargination at middle. It is similar to the examined named specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opacicollis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, in which the elytral margins are not so parallel and elytral punctation is coarser and denser. Additionally, the tegmen in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opacicollis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is quite different, with an almost straight posterior margin bearing a small U-shaped emargination at middle. I could not examine any named specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis tokunagai</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but data and drawing provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Nobuchi (1960)</xref> show that it is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in the vestiture of yellowish bristles, pronotal and elytral punctation. However, the abdominal sex patch of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis tokunagai</tp:taxon-name></italic> is described as being large.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Provisional key to the species of Strigocis Dury"><title>Provisional key to the species of Strigocis Dury</title>
            <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vestiture dense, especially on elytra, and consisting of short stout bristles</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1’</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vestiture of somewhat sparse fine setae, conspicuous or not</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(1)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotal punctation very dense, punctures separated by less than 0.75? puncture-width; in between punctures granulate, giving a dull appearance to the pronotal surface. Prosternum tumid but not carinate. Mexico and probably southern Arizona</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bilimeki</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Reitter)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2’</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotal punctures separated by a distance of at least 0.75?; in between punctures microreticulate. Prosternum carinate</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(2’)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male pronotum with apices of the subtriangular plates as separated as the ones of the frontoclypeal ridge. Male with small abdominal sex patch, with around 0.2? the length of the ventrite at the longitudinal midline. Known only from Vicosa (southeastern Brazil)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lopes-Andrade, sp. n.</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3’</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male pronotum with the apices of the subtriangular plates closer than those of the frontoclypeal ridge. Male with large abdominal sex patch. Japan: Hokkaido</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis tokunagai</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Nobuchi)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(1’)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body suboval. Lateral margins of pronotum relatively broad and with a raised lip. Elytral vestiture of barely visible (magnification of 50?) minute setae. Eastern North America</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opalescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Casey)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4’</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boby subparallel-sided. Lateral margins of pronotum narrow and devoid of raised lip. Elytral vestiture of small but distinct setae</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(4’)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral punctation coarse; punctures separated by a distance of one puncture-width or less. Eastern North America</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opacicollis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dury</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5’</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral punctation fine; punctures separated by a distance of 2? puncture-widths or more. Central and southern Europe</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Mellie)</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <!--PageBreak-->
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>The debate on the morphological limits, and consequently on the species that belong or not to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, is far from being concluded. In its original description, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Dury (1917)</xref> has not included any other species besides the type-species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opacicollis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bilimeki</tp:taxon-name></italic> were originally assigned to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Latreille, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis opalescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xestocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Casey, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis tokunagai</tp:taxon-name></italic> to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ropalodontus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mellié in their original descriptions. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Lawrence (1965)</xref> tentatively included <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis tokunagai</tp:taxon-name></italic> in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sulcacis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dury possibly due to their spinose protibial apex. Finally, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Lawrence (1971)</xref> transferred all the four species to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and provided a table of characters for distinguishing it from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sulcacis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However, some European taxonomists have considered <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> as belonging to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sulcacis</tp:taxon-name></italic> until recently (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Orledge and Booth 2006</xref> for a brief discussion). The greatest taxonomic problem of the genus, which possibly has led to such instability in literature, is the absence of exclusive characters for defining the taxon.</p>
            <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Lawrence (1971)</xref> proposed the spinose protibal apex and the diverging sutural flange of elytral apex as diagnostic to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. At that time, only species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Orthocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Casey were known to have the latter feature. Diagnostic to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Orthocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> were the rounded protibial apex, devoid of spines, and absence of secondary sexual modifications besides the male sex patch of several species. However, the diverging sutural flange of elytral apex was not observed in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., and it was already observed in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ennearthron pruinosulus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Perris), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wagaicis wagae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Wankowicz) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Odontocis denticollis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Nakane and Nobuchi (Lopes-Andrade pers. obs.). The spinose protibial apex is also not exclusive to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and it may vary among species in a single genus, like in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Several species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cis</tp:taxon-name></italic> have pronotal and frontoclypeal modifications and body form similar to those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, as well as spinose protibial apex in which the spines are concealed by long setae. These are the cases for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cis graecus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schilsky and species of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cis bilamellatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> group (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Lopes-Andrade et al. 2009</xref>), for instance. In the case of the abovementioned <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cis</tp:taxon-name></italic> species, they are distinguishable from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> by their dual elytral punctation.</p>
            <p>It is early to take the decision of synonymizing <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cis</tp:taxon-name></italic> before a careful taxonomic revision of both groups. Moreover, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is certainly not a clade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Buder et al. 2008</xref>) and remains as the most speciose and morphologically diversified genus of <tp:taxon-name>Ciidae</tp:taxon-name>, with around 375 described species. Although the matter on the limits of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> remains far from being satisfactorily resolved, I prefer to re-evaluate the diagnostic characters of the genus, as follows: (i) protibial apex bearing a row of spines, sometimes concealed by adjacent long setae; (ii) prosternum always biconcave, slightly tumid to carinate; (iii) elytra with both vestiture and punctation single; (iv) frontoclypeal ridge and anterior margin of pronotum in males usually emarginated at middle; (v) sutural flange of the elytral apex diverging near apex in most species (except in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis vicosensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.); (vi) ovipositor with gonostyli well-developed. The latter feature separates <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis</tp:taxon-name></italic> from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sulcacis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, in which the gonostyli, as far as the whole terminalia, are reduced (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Lawrence and Lopes-Andrade 2010</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>I’m grateful to John F. Lawrence for his comments and suggestions, to Caio Antunes de Carvalho for finding measurement errors in the final version of the manuscript and to Fernando Z. Vaz de Mello for the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Strigocis bilimeki</tp:taxon-name></italic> he collected in Mexico. Electron microscopy facilities were provided by “Núcleo de Microscopia e Microanálise” (NMM, UFV), with equipments financed by FINEP/FAPEMIG and CNPq. I made images of the holotype at “Laboratório de Orthopterologia” (DBG/UFV) during my post-doctoral research (CNPq post-doctoral fellowship nº 151800/2007-3, from November 2007 to October 2008). Images of male terminalia were made at “Laboratório de Acarologia” (DBA/UFV) by Vivian E. Sandoval Gómez. Financial supports were provided by FAPEMIG (Edital PPP 21/2008 2008, APQ-00049-09; Edital PPM 03/2010, PPM-00017-10), CNPq (PROTAX 52/2010 nº 562229/2010-8) and the Graduation Program in Entomology of the Federal University of Viçosa.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Buder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grossmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hundsdoerfer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klass</surname><given-names>K-D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> A contribution to the phylogeny of the Ciidae and its relationships with other cucujoid and tenebrionoid beetles (Coleoptera: Cucujiformia).</article-title> <source>Arthropod Systematics &amp; Phylogeny</source> <volume>66</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>-<lpage>190</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1943</year>)<article-title> Polyvinyl alcohol: a medium for mounting and clearing biological specimens. Science(N.S.</article-title> <source>)</source> <volume>97</volume> (<issue>2528</issue>):<fpage>539</fpage>-<lpage>540</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dury</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1917</year>)<article-title> Synopsis of the coleopterous family Cisidae (Cioidae) of America north of Mexico.</article-title> <source>Journal of the Cincinnati Society of Natural History</source> <volume>22</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> CombineZM public domain image processing software. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hadleyweb.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/CZM/combinezm.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://www.hadleyweb.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/CZM/combinezm.htm</ext-link></source>[accessed 10/March/2007]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>)<article-title> Comments on some recent changes in the classification of the Ciidae (Coloptera).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology</source> <volume>133</volume> (<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>273</fpage>-<lpage>293</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<article-title> Revision of the North American Ciidae (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology</source> <volume>142</volume>: <fpage>419</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopes-Andrade</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Ciidae Leach in Samouelle, 1819.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Leschen</surname><given-names>RAB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beutel</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Handbuch der Zoologie/Handbook of Zoology. Band/Volume IV Arthropoda: Insecta. Teilband/Part 38. Coleoptera, Beetles. Volume 2. Morphology and Systematics (Polyphaga partim).</source> <publisher-name>Walter de Gruyter</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>, <fpage>504</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopes-Andrade</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> An essay on the tribe Xylographellini (Coleoptera: Tenebrionoidea: Ciidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1832</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopes-Andrade</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> <italic>Phellinocis</italic>, a new genus of Neotropical Ciidae (Coleoptera: Tenebrionoidea).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1034</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopes-Andrade</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matushkina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klass</surname><given-names>K-D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> <italic>Cis pickeri</italic> sp. n. (Coleoptera: Ciidae) from Southern Africa.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2117</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nobuchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1960</year>)<article-title> Ciidae from Hokkaido (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Entomological Review of Japan</source> <volume>11</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Orledge</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> An annotated checklist of British and Irish Ciidae with revisionary notes.</article-title> <source>The Coleopterist</source> <volume>15</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Orledge</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Fungivore host-use groups from cluster analysis: patterns of utilisation of fungal fruiting bodies by ciid beetles.</article-title> <source>Ecological Entomology</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>620</fpage>-<lpage>641</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1947</year>)<article-title> New methods in microscopy for the study of small insects and arthropods.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the Royal Society of New Zealand</source> <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>250</fpage>-<lpage>253</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>