<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.135.1716</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>First report of <italic>Xiphinema brevicolle</italic> Lordello et Costa, 1961 (Nematoda, Longidoridae) in Japan
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Sakai</surname>
                        <given-names>Hiromichi</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Takeda</surname>
                        <given-names>Ai</given-names>
                    </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Mizukubo</surname>
                        <given-names>Takayuki</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>National Agriculture and Food Research Organization, Agricultural Research Center, Kannondai 3-1-1, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-8666, Japan
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Chiba Prefectural Agriculture and Forestry Research Center, 808 Daizenno, Midori-Ku, Chiba 266-0006 Japan
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Hiromichi Sakai (<email xlink:type="simple">sakaihm@affrc.go.jp</email>)
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Sergei Subbotin</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>7</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>135</issue>
            <fpage>21</fpage>
            <lpage>40</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>15</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>23</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Hiromichi Sakai, Ai Takeda, Takayuki Mizukubo</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Mixed populations of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group species were detected from a root zone soil sample of Japanese holly, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilex crenata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, during a survey for plant-parasitic nematodes of commercial ornamental plant nurseries in Chiba Prefecture, Japan. From the result of the morphological study, the species were identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. This is the first record of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Japan. Morphometrics of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> generally agree with those of the type specimens and the topotype specimens. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. morphometrically resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema paramonovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> except for tail length. The mitochondrial COI region, the nuclear 18S rDNA and the nuclear large subunit rDNA D2/D3 region of the species were sequenced and compared in the molecular study. For the COI region, PCR primers were newly designed to obtain longer sequences, ca. 900 bp, than previously used. Sequence identities of COI, 18S and D2/D3 regions between these two populations were 84.0-84.1%, 99.9% and 98.1-98.2%, respectively. Phylogenetic analyses of maximum likelihood trees were carried out to compare genetic relationships among the group and some suggestions were made on the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic>-subgroup.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>COI</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Ilex crenata</italic>
                </kwd>
                <kwd>Japanese holly</kwd>
                <kwd>rDNA</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Xiphinema americanum</italic>-group
                </kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Xiphinema brevicolle</italic>-subgroup
                </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>During a survey for plant-parasitic nematodes of commercial ornamental plant nurseries in Chiba Prefecture, Japan, we detected mixed populations of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group species from a root zone soil sample of Japanese holly, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilex crenata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thunb., <!--PageBreak-->one of the major garden tree species in Japan. This study was conducted using morphological characters of females and DNA sequences of the mitochondrial COI region and the nuclear ribosomal RNA (rDNA) regions to identify and characterize the species in the mixed populations.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
            <sec sec-type="Collection of the nematode specimens"><title>Collection of the nematode specimens</title>
                <p>The soil sample containing the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. (No. 001-001) was taken from the root zone of Japanese holly growing in a commercial plant nursery at Sosa City, Chiba, Japan. Nematodes were extracted with Cobb’s wet-sieving technique. Material collected on a 75 µm mesh sieve was placed on a Baermann funnel and nematodes were collected after one day at room temperature.
                </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Morphological observation"><title>Morphological observation</title>
                <p>Females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. were removed from the nematode suspension using a dissecting microscope and nematode pick. Female nematodes were transferred to a small amount of water then killed by either heating at 60°C for 2 min or by adding hot FP4:1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Netscher and Seinhorst 1969</xref>). Killed nematodes were fixed with FG4:1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">De Grisse 1969</xref>). The specimens were fixed for more than one week, processed into glycerin by the ethanol/glycerin method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Seinhorst 1959</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">De Grisse 1969</xref>), and mounted in dehydrated glycerin supported with both minute glass beads and paraffin on glass slides. Morphological observations were made using a DIC microscope (BX51, Olympus Co., Japan). A digital camera, Olympus DP20 or DP21 was used for measuring and taking photo images. The body length and position of vulva were measured with a digital curvimeter (CV-9 Jr., Koizumi Sokki Mfg. Co. Ltd., Japan) on nematode line drawings prepared using a drawing tube. Illustrations of nematodes were sketched directly on highly transparent tracing film (No. 200Z-A4 (S): Tochiman Technical Paper Co. Ltd., Japan) by tracing DP21 digital camera images on a panel-protected LC-display. Sketched images were converted to digital images using the software Adobe Illustrator CS4 (Adobe Systems Inc., USA) and a pen tablet (Intuos4: Wacom Co., Ltd., Japan).
                </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Molecular study"><title>Molecular study</title>
                <p>DNA extractions from single female specimens were carried out according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Sakai (2010)</xref>, which yielded 200 μL lysate for each specimen. Before DNA extraction, the specimens were tagged, killed by gentle heat, prepared as temporary water mounts,<!--PageBreak--> digital images of mounts were photographed, and then images were measured for body and odontostyle length, respectively.
                </p>
                <p>DNA fragments of the mitochondrial COI region were amplified by PCR using the set of primers, CO1-F1 and CO1-R1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), which were originally designed from sequence comparison of the COI region between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">He et al. 2005a</xref>: GenBank accession AY382608; NCBI Reference Sequence NC_005928) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caenorhabditis elegans</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Howe and Denver 2008</xref>: GenBank accession EU407804). CO1-R1 is virtually identical to COIR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">He et al. 2005a</xref>), with the latter having only a difference in degeneracy. The PCR reaction mixture consisted of 0.2 mM dNTPs, 0.3 μM of each primer, 0.5 U PrimeSTAR HS DNA Polymerase with PrimeSTAR Buffer (5 mM Mg<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup> plus) (Takara Bio Inc., Japan), and 10 μL of DNA lysate as PCR template, in a total volume of 20 μL. The reaction conditions were as follows: a single step of pre-denaturation at 94°C for 2 min, followed by 35 cycles of denaturation at 94°C for 30 s, annealing at 40°C for 15 s, 0.5°C/s ramp up to extension temperature, and extension at 72°C for 1 min.
                </p>
                <p>DNA fragments of the nuclear 18S rDNA region were amplified using the set of primers, 18S 39 and 18S 1573R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Mullin et al. 2005</xref>). The PCR reaction mixture consisted of 0.2 mM dNTPs, 0.2 μM of each primer, 0.5 U TaKaRa Ex Taq Hot Start Version with Ex Taq Buffer (Mg<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup> plus) (Takara Bio), and 2 μL of DNA lysate as PCR template, in a total volume of 20 μL. The reaction conditions were as follows: a single step of pre-denaturation at 94°C for 2 min, followed by 35 cycles of denaturation at 94°C for 30s, annealing at 55°C for 30s, and extension at 72°C for 1 min.
                </p>
                <p>DNA fragments of the nuclear large subunit rDNA D2/D3 region were amplified using the set of primers, D2Ab (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">De Ley et al. 1999</xref>) and D3B (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Thomas et al. 1997</xref>). The PCR reaction conditions were the same as those for 18S rDNA.
                </p>
                <p>These PCR products were purified with QIAquick PCR Purification Kit (Qiagen K.K., Japan), subjected to cycle sequencing with BigDye Terminator v3.1 Cycle Sequencing Kit (Life Technologies Japan), purified with either DyeEx 2.0 Spin Kit (Qiagen) or Agencourt CleanSEQ (Beckman Coulter Inc., USA), and sequenced on the ABI PRISM 3100 Genetic Analyzer (Life Technologies Japan Ltd., Japan). Primers 18S 599R, 18S 550, 18S 977R, 18S 965 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Mullin et al. 2005</xref>), and D3B (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Thomas et al. 1997</xref>) were also used as inner primers for sequencing as well as those designed by us (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The DNA sequences were aligned by MUSCLE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Edgar 2004</xref>) and arranged using BioEdit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Hall 1999</xref>). Multiple alignments were manually refined where necessary.
                </p>
                <p>Phylogenetic analyses including substitution model selections were performed using MEGA5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Tamura et al. 2011</xref>) to compare the obtained sequences with homologous sequences of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group in GenBank searched via BLAST. A maximum likelihood (ML) tree was constructed using 1,578 sites for multiply aligned sequences of the 18S rDNA region, where the model K2 + G, the heuristic search with the Close-Neighbor-Interchange (CNI) method, bootstrapping with 500 replications, gaps treatment using all sites, and the neighbor-joining (NJ) tree as the initial tree were employed. A ML tree was constructed using 676 sites for multiply aligned sequences of the D2/D3 region with gaps and an ambiguous site deleted, where the model K2 + <!--PageBreak-->G, the CNI method, bootstrapping with 500 replications, and a maximum parsimony (MP) tree as the initial tree were employed. A ML tree was constructed using 342 sites for multiply aligned sequences of the COI region, where the model T92 + G + I, the CNI method, bootstrapping with 500 replications, and a MP tree as the initial tree were employed. Among COI homologous sequences of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group in the database, those including alignment gaps were excluded from the analysis because they possibly represent pseudogenes. Sequences of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Longidorus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species available in GenBank were used to root those trees.
                </p>
                <table-wrap position="float" orientation="portrait" id="T1">
                    <label>Table 1.</label>
                    <caption><p>Primers designed and employed originally in this study for PCR amplification and sequencing of mitochondrial COI region and rDNA D2/D3 region.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">primer name</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Note</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CO1-F1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5’-ATAATTTTTTTTATGGTAATACC-3’</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR, sequencing</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CO1-R1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5’-ACTACATAATAAGTATCATG-3’</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR, sequencing</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CO1-F2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5’-TATATTTTAATTTTACCTGG-3’</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">sequencing</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CO1-R2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5’-CCAGGTAAAATTAAAATATA-3’</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">sequencing</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D3A-R</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5’-AGACTCCTTGGTCCGTGTTTC-3’</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">sequencing</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results"><title>Results</title>
            <p>The DNA sequence analysis of the mitochondrial COI region for 9 specimens suggested two different <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group species were present. Morphometric data were used to identify them as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lordello et Costa, 1961, and an undescribed <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group species.
            </p>
            <sec sec-type="Morphological observations"><title>Morphological observations</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">brevicolle</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Xiphinema_brevicolle</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Lordello &amp; Costa, 1961</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, 1C, 1E, 1G</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Measurements"><title>Measurements.</title>
                        <p>See <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Tables 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>Morphometrics of the specimens obtained here generally agree with  those of the type specimens and topotype specimens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Lamberti et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Luc et al. 1998</xref>) of the species (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). No male was detected.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Nomenclatorial note"><title>Nomenclatorial note.</title>
                        <p>The emended name of this species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicollum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, was proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Luc et al. (1998)</xref> and used in many works to date. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Monteiro (2010)</xref> claimed that the correct species name is <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lordello et Costa, 1961, and should have been preserved unaltered. We support the claim by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Monteiro (2010)</xref> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> is used here.<!--PageBreak-->
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1B, 1D, 1F, 1H</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Measurements"><title>Measurements.</title>
                        <p>See <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Tables 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>These specimens morphometrically resemble <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema paramonovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Romanenko, 1981, except for the clearly different tail length (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). The morphometrics of the specimens partly overlap those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic>. General morphology and DNA information addressed below suggest that these specimens belong to some species related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic>, though a specific species accommodating them was not found. We finally regarded these specimens as an unidentified <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group species. Further information is required to identify the specimens as a new species or determine if they represent intra-specific variation of species previously described. No male was detected.
                        </p>
                        <table-wrap position="float" orientation="portrait" id="T2">
                            <label>Table 2.</label>
                            <caption><p>Morphometrics of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema paramonovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema diffusum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (female). Mean ± standard deviation (range) in μm, except for L in mm, and ratios.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="3" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                        <td rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.(this study)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema paramonovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Paratypes(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Romanenko 1981</xref>)
                                        </td>
                                        <td rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema diffusum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Paratypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Lamberti and Bleve-Zacheo 1979</xref>)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Populationin this study</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="2">Topotypes</td>
                                        <td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Lordello and Costa 1961</xref>)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Luc et al. 1998</xref>)
                                        </td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Lamberti et al. 1992</xref>)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93 ± 0.11(1.71-2.10)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92 ± 0.122(1.7-2.16)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 ± 0.1(1.8-2.2)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.82-2.20)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30 ± 0.12(2.08-2.47)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1(2.0-2.3)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7(1.6-1.8)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.1 ± 2.6(40.5-50.5)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.1 ± 1.72(44-51)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5 ± 2.3(40.7-50.1)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(36.0-42.2)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.8 ± 2.4(45.0-52.3)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.6(44-54.2)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47(46-51)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6 ± 0.6(5.5-8.2)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.92 ± 0.37(5.1-6.7)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4 ± 0.6(5.6-7.7)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.0-10.5)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 ± 0.4(6.5-8.1)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1(4.8-7.1)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9(5.3-8.9)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">c</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.8 ± 4.4(60.5-79.1)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.9 ± 5.64(67.6-89.9)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.8 ± 0.6(60.3-94.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(62.5-93.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.6 ± 8.5(67.5-94.5)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.5(49.1-68.5)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72(63-84)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">c’</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 ± 0.1(0.9-1.2)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 ± 0.06(0.89-1.10)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 ± 0.06(0.9-1.1)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 ± 0.1(0.8-1.2)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1(0.9-1.2)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9(0.8-1.1</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.5 ± 1.2(48.1-53.6)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 ± 1.9(50-55)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 ± 0.9(51.0-54.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(50.0-54.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.4 ± 1.1(50.9-54.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.1(50.8-55.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50(47-52)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total stylet</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149.0 ± 4.4(144-161)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">159 ± 8.05(144-173)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(156.0-168.3)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">166.5 ± 2.6(161-171)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odontostyle</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.1 ± 3.3(88-102)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 ± 6.14(89-110)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.9 ± 7.2(84.7-108.2)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.3 ± 2.7(103-111)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.5(88.5-120.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87(84-89)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Odontophore</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.9 ± 2.1(51-59)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 ± 3.43(50-64)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.0 ± 2.9(48.8-60.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(61.2-62.7)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.2 ± 1.6(57-62)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.7(53.1-60.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50(48-51)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oral apertureto guide ring</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.5 ± 3.8(67-83)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.0 ± 4.23(77-92)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.3 ± 5.6(72.3-92.3)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.5 ± 5.0(78-93)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.6(66.0-103.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62(60-64)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pharyngeal bulblength</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.3 ± 4.0(73-86; n = 10)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(61-79)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.9 ± 2.7(82-90; n = 7)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.2(65.0-117)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pharyngeal bulbwidth</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2 ± 1.2(18-23; n = 21)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(12-19)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.9 ± 1.7(20-26)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1(18.0-24.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tail</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.8 ± 2.0(25-32)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.0 ± 1.71(23-28)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8 ± 2.0(24.1-31.2)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(24.5-29.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.2 ± 2.8(24-34)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.1(33.0-47.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24(21-28)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyaline portionof tail (J)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4 ± 1.5(8-13)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 ±0.9(5.9-9.4)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 ± 1.5(9-14)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(7-11)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12(10-14)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body diam.at lip region</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 ± 0.4(12-13)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5(11-13)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5 ± 0.5(10.6-12.3)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4 ± 0.4(11-13)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6(13.5-15.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11(10-12)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body diam.at guide ring</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.4 ± 0.8(29-32)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8 ± 1.5(27.1-31.8)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6 ± 0.8(31-34)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.7(30.0-36.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26(26-27)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body diam.at base of pharynx</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.9 ± 1.2(35-40)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4 ± 2.9(35.3-45.3)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3 ± 2.2(38-45)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.1(36.0-42.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33(31-35)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body diam.at vulva</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.0 ± 2.0(38-46)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.6 ± 3.4(39.4-50.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(49.0-59.7)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.2 ± 2.5(44-52)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4(39.0-47.2)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36(33-38)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body diam.at anus</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.0 ± 1.6(24-30)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26(22-29)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6 ± 1.7(21.8-29.4)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(30.6-36.7)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.7 ± 1.1(28-32)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.4(27.0-41.0)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25(23-28)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body diam.at beginning of J</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2 ± 2.2(12-20)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7 ± 1.1(11.2-14.7)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.4 ± 2.2(15-22)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7(6-8)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17(15-20)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
                        <table-wrap position="float" orientation="portrait" id="T3">
                            <label>Table 3.</label>
                            <caption><p>Uterine and vaginal region lengths of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. measured in this study (female). Mean ± standard deviation (range; number of specimens) in μm, except where indicated.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic></th>
                                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</th>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior uterus length</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.3 ± 4.8(34-54; n = 14)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.1 ± 2.9(32-40; n = 9)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior uterus length</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.1 ± 2.9(37-46; n = 9)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7 ± 2.7(29-37; n = 9)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pars proximalis vaginae</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9 ± 0.7(5-7; n = 22)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 ± 1.5(5-10; n = 13)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pars distalis vaginae</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5 ± 0.7(9-12; n = 22)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3 ± 1.0(9-13; n = 13)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vagina length</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4 ± 1.0(14-18; n = 22)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9 ± 1.5(17-22; n = 13)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vagina length /body diam. at vulva (%)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.2 ± 3.2(31.3-44.6; n = 22)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.1 ± 2.9(34.8-44.2; n = 13)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Molecular study"><title>Molecular study.</title>
                        <p>DNA sequences of 886 bp except for primer regions were obtained for the mitochondrial COI region. The five <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens observed had identical sequences, whereas a single nucleotide in the sequence differed among the four specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. though this variation resulted in no difference between the translated amino acid sequences within the specimens. Sequence identity between these two species was 84.0-84.1%, whereas the sequences of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. were 80.7 and 80.4-80.5% identical to that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">He et al. 2005a</xref>) respectively, with no gap found among them (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). Putative amino acid sequences were available without any stop codon when translations were made from the second base of the obtained sequences. DNA sequences of 1,566 bp except for primer regions were obtained for the 18S rDNA region from one specimen for each species. The difference between sequences of the two species studied here was only a single nucleotide, resulting in 99.9% identity without any gap. DNA sequences of 788-791 bp except primer regions were obtained for the D2/D3 region from four specimens for each species. A single nucleotide variation of sequence among four specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> was observed, whereas no variation of sequence was observed among four specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. Sequence identity between these two species was 98.1-98.2%, with gaps found.
                        </p>
                        <p>ML trees inferred for the 18S rDNA and D2/D3 regions placed our specimens in similar clades, which include <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> and its junior synonyms by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Luc et al. (1998)</xref> such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema diffusum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lamberti et Bleve-Zacheo, 1979, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema incognitum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lamberti and Bleve-Zacheo, 1979, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema taylori</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lamberti et al., 1992, as well as other different species like <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema inaequale</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Khan et Ahmad, 1975) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema lamberti</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bajaj et Jairajpuri, 1977 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 8</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>). On the other hand, the ML tree inferred for the COI region didn’t show strong support for such a clade because of a low bootstrap value though several subclades were strongly supported by high bootstrap values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>This study reports the occurrence of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Japan for the first time. The only member species of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group recorded to date in Japan was <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema incognitum</tp:taxon-name></italic> <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->Lamberti &amp; Bleve-Zacheo, 1979, described as a new species for nematode specimens detected from soil of bonsai trees exported from Japan to England (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Lamberti and Bleve-Zacheo 1979</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>The specimens of this study were obtained from mixed populations of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group. Information on juveniles was not included because the coexistence of the two closely related nematodes requires special care to separate juvenile specimens of the different species. Situations like this will make matters worse if one is to identify the species, since it is difficult enough to identify even a single population of the group in many cases. Detection of mixed populations of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cobb, 1913 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema rivesi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dalmasso, 1969 were reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Vrain et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Vrain 1993</xref>), and such coexistence of multiple populations and/or species of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group may be common. Therefore, it is strongly recommended to check the genetic uniformity of a given population to be identified. The mitochondrial COI region has been recently used to examine variations in populations of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> species including members of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Lazarova et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Kumari et al. 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">2010b</xref>), where ca 400 bp sequences were examined. This genetic region has much more information to differentiate between populations than 18S rDNA and D2/D3 regions. As shown above, we developed new primers and examined longer sequences of the COI region than previously used. Examination of longer sequences provides not only more reliable comparative results but also another option to develop a more specific primer to the species to be tested since high variability of this region may contribute to some unfitness of reported primers. Among options available at present, sequences of the COI region can be efficiently used to examine the diversity of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens.
            </p>
            <p>ML phylogenetic analyses of 18S rDNA and D2/D3 regions moderately supported the clade including <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema diffusum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema phinema  inaequale</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema incognitum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema lamberti</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema taylori</tp:taxon-name></italic> with our materials (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 8</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>), whereas such a clade was not so highly supported in the ML tree of COI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref>). Member species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group harbor endosymbionts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Vandekerckhove et al. 2000</xref>). T<!--PageBreak-->he difference in phylogenetic inference between nuclear and mitochondrial genetic regions may result from the symbionts’ effect on mitochondrial DNA since unreliable results of phylogenetic inference based on mitochondrial DNA due to the presence of a symbiont are known (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hurst and Jiggins 2005</xref>). Furthermore, the ML tree of COI brought another problem to us. It showed closer relationship of our <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> population to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema diffusum</tp:taxon-name></italic> than to other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> populations. Our specimens identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> were reasonably larger than type specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema diffusum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>), and our identification was made considering more overlapping morphometrics of type specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic>. If COI sequences can differentiate species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group, our specimens may be identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema diffusum</tp:taxon-name></italic> rather than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic>. In such a situation, morphological features used to identify species should be reconsidered since a single species like <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema diffusum</tp:taxon-name></italic> can have a wide range of morphometrics which may result in more difficult diagnoses without reducing the number of species by synonymizing them intensively. In any case, it should be desirable to collect much more COI sequences of other species and populations, such as the sequence data of topotype specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema diffusum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, which is unavailable at present. Our results of phylogenetic analyses, however, may be helpful to refine the concept of a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic>-subgroup, which was previously discussed in some works (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Romanenko and Stegaresku 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Lamberti and Ciancio 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">He et al. 2005b</xref>). Taking our results of phylogenetic analyses into consideration, we suggest that the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic>-subgroup includes at least the five species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema diffusum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema inaequale</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema incognitum</tp:taxon-name></italic>,and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema taylori</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and our specimens also belong to the subgroup, though the validity of respective species is a different matter. Appropriate establishment of subgroups within the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group will contribute to a more feasible identification process of the member species and requires further research.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title>
            <p>In this study, specimens from mixed populations of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic>-group, present in the root zone of Japanese holly in Japan, were identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. This record of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the first for Japan. PCR primers to amplify longer sequences of the mitochondrial COI regions were originally designed and used to efficiently differentiate the specimens. Phylogenetic analyses using 18S rDNA, D2/D3, and COI regions supported a close relationship among our specimens and species related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> or the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic>-subgroup.
            </p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>The first author thanks Tom Prior for useful suggestions and information and Dr. Nobuhiro Minaka for helpful comments on phylogenetic analyses. The authors thank Dr. Jerome <!--PageBreak-->T. Gaspard for improving the manuscript. This study was supported by Research and development projects for application in promoting new policy of Agriculture Forestry and Fisheries (21043) from the Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries of Japan.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>De Grisse</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>)<article-title> Redescription ou modifications de quelques techniques utilisées dans l’étude des nématodes phytoparasitaires.</article-title> <source>Mededelingen van de Rijksfaculteit Landbowwetenschappen Gent </source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>351</fpage>-<lpage>369</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>De Ley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Félix</surname><given-names>M-A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frisse</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadler</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Molecular and morphological characterisation of two reproductively isolated species with mirror-image anatomy (Nematoda: Cephalobidae).</article-title> <source>Nematology </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>591</fpage>-<lpage>612</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput.</article-title> <source>Nucleic Acids Research </source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1792</fpage>-<lpage>1797</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkh340" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1093/nar/gkh340</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT.</article-title> <source>Nucleic Acids Symposium Series </source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamberti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005a</year>)<article-title> The mitochondrial genome of <italic>Xiphinema americanum sensu stricto</italic> (Nematoda: Enoplea): considerable economization in the length and structural features of encoded genes.</article-title> <source>Journal of Molecular Evolution </source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>819</fpage>-<lpage>833</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00239-005-0102-7" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1007/s00239-005-0102-7</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subbotin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubtsova</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamberti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DJF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005b</year>)<article-title> A molecular phylogenetic approach to Longidoridae (Nematoda: Dorylaimida).</article-title> <source>Nematology </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>124</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/1568541054192108" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1163/1568541054192108</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denver</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<source> Muller’s Ratchet and compensatory mutation in <italic>Caenorhabditis briggsae</italic> mitochondrial genome evolution. BMC Evolutionary Biology 8: 62. </source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-8-62" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1186/1471-2148-8-62</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>GDD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiggins</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Problems with mitochondrial DNA as a marker in population, phylogeographic and phylogenetic studies: the effects of inherited symbionts.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B </source> <volume>272</volume>: <fpage>1525</fpage>-<lpage>1534</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2005.3056" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1098/rspb.2005.3056</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Decraemer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Luca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010a</year>)<article-title> Molecular characterization of <italic>Xiphinema brevicollum</italic> (Nematoda: Longidoridae) from the Czech Republic.</article-title> <source>European Journal of Plant Pathology </source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>-<lpage>250</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10658-010-9651-8" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1007/s10658-010-9651-8</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Decraemer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Luca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiefenbrunner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010b</year>)<article-title> Cytochrome c oxidase subunit 1 analysis of <italic>Xiphinema diversicaudatum</italic>, <italic>X. pachtaicum</italic>, <italic>X. simile</italic> and <italic>X. vuittenezi</italic> (Nematoda, Dorylaimida).</article-title> <source>European Journal of Plant Pathology </source> <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>493</fpage>-<lpage>499</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10658-010-9614-0" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1007/s10658-010-9614-0</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamberti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bleve-Zacheo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> Studies on <italic>Xiphinema americanum sensu lato</italic> with descriptions of fifteen new species (Nematoda, Longidoridae).</article-title> <source>Nematologia Mediterannea </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamberti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciancio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Diversity of <italic>Xiphinema americanum</italic>-group species and hierarchical cluster analysis of morphometrics.</article-title> <source>Journal of Nematology </source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>332</fpage>-<lpage>343</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamberti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciancio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agostinelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coiro</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Relationship between <italic>Xiphinema brevicolle</italic> and <italic>X. diffusum</italic> with a redescripiton of <italic>X. brevicolle</italic> and descriptions of three new species of <italic>Xiphinema</italic> (Nematoda: Dorylaimida).</article-title> <source>Nematologia Mediterranea </source> <volume>19</volume> (<issue>1991</issue>): <fpage>311</fpage>-<lpage>326</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazarova</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malloch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>CMG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hübschen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neilson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Ribosomal and mitochondrial DNA analyses of <italic>Xiphinema americanum</italic>-group populations.</article-title> <source>Journal of Nematology </source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>404</fpage>-<lpage>410</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lordello</surname><given-names>LGE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>)<article-title> A new nematode parasite of coffee roots in Brazil.</article-title> <source>Revista Brasileira de Biologia, </source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>-<lpage>366</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Luc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coomans</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loof</surname><given-names>PAA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baujard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> The <italic>Xiphinema americanum</italic>-group (Nematoda: Longidoridae). 2. Observations on <italic>Xiphinema brevicollum</italic> Lordello &amp; da Costa, 1961 and comments on the group.</article-title> <source>Fundamental and Applied Nematology </source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>-<lpage>490</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Nomenclatorial note on <italic>Xiphinema brevicolle</italic> Lordello &amp; Costa, 1961 (Nematoda: Longidoridae).</article-title> <source>Nematologia Brasileira </source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>2</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullin</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Phylogenetic relationships of Nygolaimina and Dorylaimina (Nematoda: Dorylaimida) inferred from small subunit ribosomal DNA sequences.</article-title> <source>Nematology </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>79</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/1568541054192199" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1163/1568541054192199</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Netscher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seinhorst</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>)<source> Propionic acid better than acetic acid for killing nematodes. Nematologica 15: 286.
</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Romanenko</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<source> [Discovery of a new species of nematode <italic>Xiphinema paramonovi</italic> n. sp. (Nematoda: Longidoridae) in the territory of the soviet Union]. Tezisy Dokladov, Pervaya Konferentsiya po Nematodam Rastenii, Nasekomykh, Pochvy i Vod, 68–69.
</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Romanenko</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stegaresku</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> [Taxonomic problem in nematodes of the <italic>Xiphinema americanum</italic> group (Nematoda, Dorylaimoidea)].</article-title> <source>Parazitologiya </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>434</fpage>-<lpage>442</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> A DNA extraction method with SDS from single nematodes for direct application to PCR amplification.</article-title> <source>Nematological Research </source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3725/jjn.40.13" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.3725/jjn.40.13</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Seinhorst</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>)<article-title> A rapid method for the transfer of nematodes from fixative to anhydrous glycerin.</article-title> <source>Nematologica </source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>69</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/187529259X00381" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1163/187529259X00381</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> MEGA5: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods. Molecular Biology and Evolution. </source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msr121" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1093/molbev/msr121</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vida</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frisse</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mundo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> DNA Sequences from formalin-fixed nematodes: integrating molecular and morphological approaches to taxonomy.</article-title> <source>Journal of Nematology </source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>250</fpage>-<lpage>254</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandekerckhove</surname><given-names>TTM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coomans</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Occurrence of novel verrucomicrobial species, endosymbiotic and associated with parthenogenesis in <italic>Xiphinema americanum</italic>-group species (Nematoda, Longidoridae).</article-title> <source>International Journal of Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology </source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>2197</fpage>-<lpage>2205</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1099/00207713-50-6-2197" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1099/00207713-50-6-2197</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrain</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Restriction fragment length polymorphism separates species of the <italic>Xiphinema americanum</italic> group.</article-title> <source>Journal of Nematology </source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>-<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrain</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakarchuk</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lévesque,</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Intraspecific rDNA restriction fragment length polymorphism in the <italic>Xiphinema americanum</italic> group.</article-title> <source>Fundamental and Applied Nematology </source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>563</fpage>-<lpage>573</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
        <sec sec-type="Figures."><title>Figures.</title>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Female morphology of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>(A, C, E, G)</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. <bold>(B, D, F, H) A–B</bold> Anterior region <bold>C–D</bold> Tail <bold>E–F</bold> Reproductive system <bold>G–H</bold> Entire body.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-135-021-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 2.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> (female) <bold>A–C</bold> Anterior region <bold>D–G</bold> Tail <bold>H–K</bold> Vulval region <bold>L–P</bold> Entire body.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-135-021-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 3.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.(female) <bold>A–C</bold> Anterior region <bold>D–F</bold> Tail <bold>G–I</bold> Vulval region <bold>J–M</bold> Entire body.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-135-021-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 4.</label>
                <caption><p>Intra-population variation of lip region in females <bold>A</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>B</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-135-021-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 5.</label>
                <caption><p>Intra-population variation of tail in females <bold>A</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>B</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-135-021-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 6.</label>
                <caption><p>Intra-population variation of vagina in females <bold>A</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>B</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-135-021-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 7.</label>
                <caption><p>Sequence comparison of mitochondrial COI region. Xbre: <italic><tp:taxon-name>X. brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> (this study: GenBank accession AB604337); Xsp1, Xsp2: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. (this study: AB604338 and AB604339 respectively); Xame: <italic><tp:taxon-name>X. americanum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (He et al. 2005: usAY382608).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-135-021-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 8.</label>
                <caption><p>Maximum likelihood tree for 18S rDNA region. Bootstrap values higher than 50 are shown. Arrows indicate specimens examined in this study: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> GenBank accession AB604340; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. AB604341. The tree is drawn to scale, with branch lengths measured in the number of substitutions per site.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-135-021-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 9.</label>
                <caption><p>Maximum likelihood tree for D2/D3 region. Bootstrap values higher than 50 are shown. Arrows indicate specimens examined in this study: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema brevicolle</tp:taxon-name></italic> GenBank accession AB635401 and AB635402; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xiphinema</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. AB635403. The tree is drawn to scale, with branch lengths measured in the number of substitutions per site.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-135-021-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 10.</label>
                <caption><p>Maximum likelihood tree for COI region. Bootstrap values higher than 50 are shown. Arrows indicate specimens examined in this study. The tree is drawn to scale, with branch lengths measured in the number of substitutions per site.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-135-021-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
        </sec>
    </back>
</article>		