<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.243.3408</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new genus and new species of Agathotanaidae (Crustacea, Tanaidacea) from West Australia</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Jóźwiak</surname>
                        <given-names>Piotr</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:259B1C01-6C78-4ACC-9449-67EDF76030B7</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Jakiel</surname>
                        <given-names>Aleksandra</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:68831008-1426-4C32-96BA-D8D193613CC3</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Laboratory of Polar Biology and Oceanobiology, University of Łódź, Banacha 12/16, Łódź, Poland
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Piotr Jóźwiak (<email xlink:type="simple">pjozwiak@biol.uni.lodz.pl</email>)
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: M. Blazewicz-Paszkowycz</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>16</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>243</issue>
            <fpage>15</fpage>
            <lpage>26</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>21</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>20</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Piotr Jóźwiak, Aleksandra Jakiel</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:0E70926F-ABE7-42B0-87B8-15CA1A15D0A5</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new genus of <tp:taxon-name>Tanaidacea</tp:taxon-name> – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia</tp:taxon-name></italic>,collected from the region of Ningaloo in the vicinity of Bunbury (Western Australia), is erected to accommodate the new species – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia prima</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> This genus is classified in the family <tp:taxon-name>Agathotanaidae</tp:taxon-name> and it can be distinguished from the other members of the family by having a combination of antennulae covered with minute setae, reduced uropods and unusual setation of the propodus of pereopods 4 to 6. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia prima</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the second species of <tp:taxon-name>Agathotanaidae</tp:taxon-name> known so far from Australia.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><italic>Bunburia</italic>
                </kwd>
                <kwd>NW Australia</kwd>
                <kwd>Tanaidacea</kwd>
                <kwd>Agathotanaidae</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The family <tp:taxon-name>Agathotanaidae</tp:taxon-name> erected by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Lang (1971a)</xref> is represented by 41 species in four genera, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hansen, 1913, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metagathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bird and Holdich, 1988, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lang, 1971 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranarthrura</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hansen, 1913 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Anderson 2012</xref>). The fifth genus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranarthrurella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lang, 1971, which had been previously considered as a member of this family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Larsen and Wilson 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Larsen 2005</xref>) was recently removed from <tp:taxon-name>Agathotanaidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Jóźwiak et al. 2009</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>The diagnosis of <tp:taxon-name>Agathotanaidae</tp:taxon-name>, modified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Larsen (2005)</xref>, includes mandibles having a pointed or reduced molar, the absence of pleopods in the females and the uropod endopod that consists of one or two articles. The uropod exopods of <tp:taxon-name>Agathotanaidae</tp:taxon-name> is reduced to a blunt spur and only the presence of distal and middle setae suggests it is a fused exopod rather than a basis process. Another character that Larsen (op. cit.) has pinpointed as diagnostic for <tp:taxon-name>Agathotanaidae</tp:taxon-name> is cheliped attached directly to the cephalothorax or via pseudocoxa, however it was later questioned by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Larsen (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bird (2010)</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic> is distinguishable from the other agathotanaid genera by its finely setulose body, 3-articled antennulae, reduced antennae, cheliped attached directly to the cephalothorax and uropodal endopod fused to the basis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hansen 1913</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Larsen 1999</xref>, 2005). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metagathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the genus with strongly-reduced uropods (endopod fused with basis), but in contrast to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic> it has fully-developed antennae that consist of six articles and 4-articled antennulae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Guerrero-Kommritz 2003</xref>). An unique feature of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metagathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the fusion of the pleonites with the pleotelson in females, although the males retain complete pleonite segmentation. Members of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic> have both antennulae and antennae well-developed and the pleon with five distinct pleonites, while the uropods endopod is separated from the basis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Lang 1971b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bird and Holdich 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Larsen 2005</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranarthrura</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the only genus of the family with uropod supported by a visible projection. The number of articles in the uropodal endopod of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranarthrura</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be either one or two.
            </p>
            <p>The collection of <tp:taxon-name>Tanaidacea</tp:taxon-name> from the shelf and continental margin of Western  Australia (WA), taken from on board the FRV <italic>Southern Surveyor</italic> in 2005 and 2007 has represented close to three hundred species new for science (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Poore et al. in press</xref>). About 60% of the taxa are represented by single or few specimens only, while 82% of the taxa occurred just twice in the series of over two hundred samples. This scarcity of the material, together with the minute size of the specimens, which are often no longer than 1 mm, impede the formal taxonomical descriptions of the species.
            </p>
            <p>One of the few species represented by more than one specimen was found to be a representative of a new genus of the family <tp:taxon-name>Agathotanaidae</tp:taxon-name>. The present paper presents the formal description of this species and the definition of the new genus that has been erected to accommodate it.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The material was collected in 2005 during the voyage of the FRV <italic>Southern Surveyor</italic> organized under the aegis of CSIRO (<italic>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organization)</italic>. The 14 specimens studied by us were recorded at ten of two hundred grab samples taken along the west coast of Australia from Dampier in the north to Albany in the south (from <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">21.0084°S, 114.381°E</named-content> to <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">35.384°S, 118.316°E</named-content>).
            </p>
            <p>Appendages were dissected using chemically-sharpened tungsten-wire needles, stained with chlorazol black and mounted in glycerine. Drawings were prepared u<!--PageBreak-->sing a microscope combined with a <italic>camera lucida</italic> and redrawn on a digital tablet as proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Coleman (2003)</xref>. The morphological terminology follows that proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Błażewicz-Paszkowycz and Bamber (2007)</xref>. The body-length to width ratio was calculated using measurements from tip of the rostrum to end of pleotelson and of the widest part of cephalothorax. The ratio of particular articles was measured along their central axis. Abbreviations used in the morphological description: A1 – antennule, A2 – antenna, Mxp – maxilliped, P1-P6 – pereopods from first to sixth pair respectively.
            </p>
            <p>The type material is deposited at Museum Victoria, Melbourne.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics">
            <title>Systematics</title>
            <sec sec-type="Order Tanaidacea Dana, 1849">
                <title>Order <tp:taxon-name>Tanaidacea</tp:taxon-name> Dana, 1849
                </title>
                <p>Suborder <tp:taxon-name>Tanaidomorpha</tp:taxon-name> Sieg, 1980
                </p>
                <p>Family <tp:taxon-name>Agathotanaidae</tp:taxon-name> Lang, 1971
                </p>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bunburia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:70EF00B3-B23A-4C38-B552-1E4FBDBE6192</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bunburia</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Pleon with five free pleonites; antennulae 4-articled, with first article covered by numerous minute setae; antenna 6-articled, article 3 with dense setation; mandibles molar reduced; labium without outer or medial, setose process; maxillipedal bases unfused distally, endites unfused; epignath elongated and naked; cheliped sclerites unfused ventromedially, carpus stout (1.4 times as long as wide), chela with keel; pereopods with coxa; P1 propodus with elongate ventral seta, P1-P3 merus with long serrated seta, P4-P6 propodus with two long, serrated setae ventrodistally and three short setae dorsodistally, P5 and P6 with propodus shorter than carpus, dactylus/unguis of these pereopods setulated ventrally; ischium of all pereopods with only one seta; pleopods absent in female and well developed in male; uropod short, not projecting beyond pleotelson, with basis terminated with small projection, endopod short, one-articled.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                        <title>Type species.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia prima</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.  <italic>–</italic> by monotypy.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The name refers to Bunbury, a port city near the type locality of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia prima</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>At first glance <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n., with its short uropods that not protrude the pleotelson, resembles the members of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The new genus can be distinguish however from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic> by presence of dense setationon the proximal article of the antennulae and the fourth article of the antennae and by unusual chetotaxy of propodus of last three pereopods, which consists of three short setae dorsodistally and two long setae ventrodistally. The setation of propodus P4-P6 is variable in members of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic>. For example <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais abyssorum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Larsen, 2007, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais insolitus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Guerrero-Kommritz, 2003 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais ipy</tp:taxon-name></italic> Jóźwiak i Błażewicz-Paszkowycz, 2011 have three long, distal setae, while five other species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bird and Holdich, 1988, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais nanus</tp:taxon-name></italic><!--PageBreak--> Bird and Holdich, 1988, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais robustus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bird and Holdich, 1988, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais typicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lang, 1971 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais vikingus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bird, 2010 have three long setae in propodus of pereopods 4 and 5, but four setae in pereopod 6. Another species – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais macrocephalus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kudinova-Pasternak, 1986 lack of setae on propodus of pereopod 4, but it has three setae in pereopod 6. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais medius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Larsen, 2002 there are four long, distal setae at propodus of P4-P6. Beside the pereopods setation <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be separated from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic> by lack of medial process on the labium and bases of maxilliped unfused distally.
                        </p>
                        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Larsen (2007)</xref> has pointed out that size of uropods and theirs position on the pleotelson distinguish <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic> from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranarthrura</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n., with uropods similar to those observed in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paragathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic>, can be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paranarthrura</tp:taxon-name></italic> by short uropods, that are not reaching over pleotelson and are inserted more ventrally. The 4-articled antennula and the 6-articled antenna distinguish <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia</tp:taxon-name></italic> from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic>, that has 3-articled antennula and antenna reduced to one short article (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Larsen 1999</xref>, 2005). An evident is also the difference between females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metagathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic>, which have all pleonites fused with pleotelson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bird and Holdich 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Guerrero-Kommritz 2003</xref>). Males of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metagathotanais</tp:taxon-name></italic> have pleotelson with five distinct pleonites, but they differs from males of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia</tp:taxon-name></italic> in propodus P4-P6 chetotaxy. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metagathotanais insulcatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bird and Holdich, 1988 propodus of these pereopods bears one short and three long setae distally and in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metagathotanais loerzae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Guerrero-Kommritz, 2003 there are only three long setae.
                        </p>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia</tp:taxon-name></italic> represented by only one species is the second taxon of <tp:taxon-name>Agathotanaidae</tp:taxon-name> known so far from Australia, after <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agathotanais spinipoda</tp:taxon-name></italic> Larsen, 1999.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bunburia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">prima</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:ECDC9C27-D624-479B-9276-6E13A322B702</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bunburia_prima</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The Latin ordinal number ‘<italic>prima</italic>’ denotes the fact that the species described herein is the first member of genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, non-ovigerous female, J62967, 2.5 mm long, St. SS07/2005, 153,Bunbury, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">33.0003°S, 114.579°E</named-content>, depth 399 m, 07 August 2005.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes">
                        <title>Paratypes.</title>
                        <p>1 female dissected on slides, J62968, St. SS07/2005, 152, Bunbury, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">32.9987°S, 114.576°E</named-content>, depth 417 m, 2005.
                        </p>
                        <p>1 male partially dissected, J62969, St. SS07/2005, 85, Zyutdorp, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">27.1676°S, 112.778°E</named-content>, depth 375 m, 29 July 2005.
                        </p>
                        <p>1 specimen, J62974, St. SS07/2005, 8, Ningaloo, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">22.0796°S, 113.797°E</named-content>, depth 205 m, 2005; 1 specimen, J62973, St. SS07/2005, 23, Ningaloo, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">22.0629°S, 113.723°E</named-content>, depth 715 m, 2005; 2 specimens, J62971, St. SS07/2005, 24, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">22.0631°S, 113.724°E</named-content>, depth 713 m, 2005; 1 specimen, J62972, St. SS07/2005, 68, Point Cloates, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">22.859°S, 113.328°E</named-content>, depth 448 m, 2005; 1 specimen, J62970, St. SS07/2005, 75, Carnarvon, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">24.5875°S, 112.253°E</named-content>, depth 405 m, 2005; 2 specimens, J63690, St. SS07/2005,<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> 76, Carnarvon, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">24.5863°S, 112.254°E</named-content>, depth 405 m, 2005; 3 specimens, J62975, St. SS07/2005, 126, Jurian Bay, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">29.8604°S, 114.372°E</named-content>, depth 499 m, 2005.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality">
                        <title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p>near Bunbury, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">33.0003°S, 114.579°E</named-content>, depth 399 m.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>as for thegenus.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description of female.</title>
                        <p>Habitus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, F</xref>): body 2.5 mm long, 6.2 times as long as wide. Carapace 23% of total body length, 1.5 times as long as wide. Length/width ratios of pereonites 1 to 6: 0.7, 0.8, 0.9, 1.0, 1.1 and 0.7 respectively. Pleon about 18% of total body length; pleonites equal in length; fifth pleonite with lateral simple seta. Pleotelson (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref>) with a pair of bipinnate setae and two pairs of simple setae distally.
                        </p>
                        <p>Antennule (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>) 4-articled; article 1 longest, with three bipinnate setae and one simple seta on outer margin, inner margin covered with numerous minute setae; article 2 about 0.4 times as long as article 1, with one bipinnate and two simple setae distally; article 3 trapezoidal, wider than long, with two distal setae; article 4 twice as long as article 3, distally with one bipinnate, one short simple, five long simple setae and one aesthetasc.
                        </p>
                        <p>Antenna (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>) 6-articled; article 1 broken; article 2 with one simple seta distally; article 3 square, with one simple, distal seta; article 4 longest, four times as long as article 3, with one simple and one bipinnate setae distally and row of small spines laterally; article 5 half as long as article 4, with minute lateral setation and one long seta distally; last article very short, distally with six long setae.
                        </p>
                        <p>Mouthparts: labrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>) covered with dense setation; mandibles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2B, C</xref>) molar bent downward and tapering distally; right mandible incisor with four denticulations, left mandible with four denticulations on incisor and small lacinia mobilis with dorsal tooth. Maxillule (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2D, D’</xref>) ventrally with combs of short, simple setae, distally with six spines, two simple setae and minute setation, palp lost during dissection; maxilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2E</xref>) ovate. Labium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2F</xref>) bilobed, with minute setation distally. Maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2G</xref>) bases unfused distally, endites with pair of distal, simple setae and one tubercle; palp article 1 naked; article 2 with three inner setae; article 3 with three setae on inner margin, outer margin setulated; last article with five long spiniform setae and minute setation. Epignath (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2H</xref>) elongated, strap-like and naked.
                        </p>
                        <p>Cheliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1D–E’</xref>) pseudocoxa massive, about as long as wide, naked, incompletely fused on midline of cephalothorax ventrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>); basis trapezoidal and naked; merus triangular, with one seta ventrally; carpus 1.4 times as long as wide, with pair of setae on both dorsal and ventral margins; chela larger than carpus, propodus with one seta on ventral margin, inner comb of three serrated setae and row of minute spines; fixed finger with three setae on inner margin, and well calcified, inner teeth, ventrally with keel; dactylus with one small spiniform seta on inner margin and one seta dorsally.
                        </p>
                        <p>Pereopod 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A, A’</xref>) coxa with seta; basis four times as long as wide, naked; ischium with simple seta; merus with one serrated seta; carpus as long as merus, with two serrated setae and one spiniform seta distally; propodus elongate, 1.5 times as long as merus, with three spiniform setae distally; dactylus 0.6 times as long as unguis, both together longer than carpus.
                        </p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->Pereopod 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>) coxa with simple seta; basis five times as long as wide, with one bipinnate seta; ischium with single seta; merus with one serrated seta; carpus as long as merus, with two serrated setae and one spiniform seta distally; propodus elongate, 1.2 times as long as merus, with two spiniform setae distally, combs of small spines present; dactylus little shorter than unguis, with proximal seta.
                        </p>
                        <p>Pereopod 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>) coxa with simple seta; basis four times as long as wide; ischium with one seta; merus with serrated seta ventrodistally; carpus longer than merus, with one spiniform and two serrated setae distally; propodus elongate, almost twice as long as merus, with one spiniform seta ventrally, combs of minute spines present; dactylus 0.6 times as long as unguis.
                        </p>
                        <p>Pereopod 4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>) coxa with one seta; basis 4.6 times as long as wide, with one bipinnate seta ventrally; ischium with single seta; merus with two serrated setae distally and row of minute setation; carpus longer than merus, with three serrated, strong setae ventrally, minute setation present on ventral margin; propodus little longer than carpus, with two serrated and three spiniform setae distally, ventral margin with rows of minute setation; dactylus twice as long as unguis, with numerous minute spines ventrally.
                        </p>
                        <p>Pereopod 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref>) basis with one bipinnate seta; ischium with single seta; merus with two serrated setae ventrally; carpus longer than merus, with one simple and three serrated setae distally, minute setation on ventral margin; propodus clearly shorter than carpus, with two serrated long setae and three short spiniform setae, ventrally with rows of minute setation; dactylus almost twice as long as unguis, dorsal margin with minute setation.
                        </p>
                        <p>Pereopod 6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3F, F’</xref>) similar to pereopod 5, but dactylus/unguis slightly shorter.
                        </p>
                        <p>Pleopods absent.</p>
                        <p>Uropod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G</xref>) basis with small projection bearing one long and one short, simple distal setae; endopod one-articled, as long as basal article, with four long, simple setae distally and two bipinnate setae at midlength of article.
                        </p>
                        <p>Male. Habitus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>): body 2.7 mm long, 6.7 times as long as wide. Carapace 20% of total body length, about 1.5 times as long as wide. Lateral margins of pereonites covered by small papillae; length/width ratios of pereonites 1 to 6: 0.7, 0.8, 0.8, 1.0, 1.0 and 0.8 respectively. Pleon about 18% of total body length; pleonites equal in length.
                        </p>
                        <p>Antennule (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>) stouter than that of female; 4-articled; article 1 longest and naked, 1.8 times as long as wide; article 2 0.4 times as long as first article, with four bipinnate setae distally; third article trapezoidal, about half as long as second article, with one outer and one inner simple setae; last article elongated, about half as long as first article; terminally with two bipinnate and five long, simple setae.
                        </p>
                        <p>Cheliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>) similar to that of female; merus with single seta; carpus stout – 1.3 times as long as wide, with single outer seta and pair of ventral setae (in figure only one). Propodus about as long as wide, with three setae near dactylus insertion, fixed finger with one ventral seta and three setae on inner (cutting) margin, ventral margin with keel. Dactylus as long as propodus, with single outer seta<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->.
                        </p>
                        <p>Pleopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>) basis 0.8 times as long as each ramus, naked. Rami subequal, exopod terminating in eight strong, simple setae, endopod with one seta subdistally and six setae distally.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>The species is known from Western Australia and was recorded between Ningaloo and Bunbury City in a depth range from 205 to 715 m.</p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 1.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia prima</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype female. <bold>A</bold> body, dorsal view; paratype female <bold>B</bold> antennule <bold>C</bold> antenna (proximal article not shown) <bold>D</bold> cephalothorax, ventral view <bold>E</bold> cheliped <bold>E’</bold> details of fixed finger and dactylus <bold>F</bold> pleotelson, ventral view. Scale lines = 1 mm for <bold>A</bold> and 0.1 mm for <bold>B–E</bold>.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-243-015-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 2.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia prima</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., paratype female. <bold>A</bold> labrum <bold>B</bold> mandible molar <bold>B’</bold> incisor of right mandible <bold>C</bold> left mandible <bold>D</bold> maxillule endite <bold>D</bold> details of distal part of maxillule <bold>E</bold> maxilla <bold>F</bold> labium <bold>G</bold> maxilliped <bold>H</bold> epignath. Scale line = 0.1 mm.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-243-015-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 3.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia prima</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., paratype female. <bold>A</bold> pereopod 1 <bold>A’</bold> detailes of P1 propodus <bold>B</bold> pereopod 2 <bold>C</bold> pereopod 3 <bold>D</bold> pereopod 4 <bold>E</bold> pereopod 5 <bold>F</bold> pereopod 6 <bold>F’</bold> details of P6 propodus <bold>G</bold> uropod. Scale line = 0.1 mm.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-243-015-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 4.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bunburia prima</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., allotype male. <bold>A</bold> body, dorsal view <bold>B</bold> antennule <bold>C</bold> cheliped <bold>D</bold> pleopod. Scale line = 0.1 mm.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-243-015-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We would like to thank Dr. Gary Poore (Museum Victoria) for making the material available for the study, Dr. Roger Bamber for improving the English throughout the manuscript and to two anonymous referees for their comments on manuscript. Financial support was provided by the Ministry of Science and Higher Education: grant N N303 798440.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> Tanaidacea – Taxa and Literature. Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://peracarida.usm.edu" xlink:type="simple">http://peracarida.usm.edu</ext-link></source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bird</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Tanaidacea (Crustacea, Peracarida) of the North-east Atlantic: the Agathotanaidae of the AFEN, BIOFAR and BIOICE projects, with a description of a new species of <italic>Paragathotanais</italic> Lang.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>2730</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bird</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holdich</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> Deep-sea Tanaidacea (Crustacea) of the North-east Atlantic: the tribe Agathotanaini.</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History </source> <volume>22</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1591</fpage>-<lpage>1621</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222938800771001" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/00222938800771001</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Błażewicz-Paszkowycz</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bamber</surname> <given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> New apseudomorph tanaidaceans (Crustacea: Peracarida: Tanaidacea) from Eastern Australia: Apseudidae, Whiteleggiidae, Metapseudidae and Pagurapseudidae.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of Museum Victoria </source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>148</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname> <given-names>CO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> “Digital inking”: How to make perfect line drawings on computers.</article-title> <source>Organism, Diversity and Evolution (Electronic Supplement) </source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dana</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1849</year>)<article-title> III. Zoology. 1. Conspectus Crustaceorum. Conspectus of the Crustacea of the Exploring Expedition.</article-title> <source>The American Journal of Science and Arts (Series 2)</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>424</fpage>–<lpage>428</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerrero-Kommritz</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Agathotanaididae (Crustacea: Tanaidacea) from the Angola Basin.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>330</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname> <given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1913</year>)<article-title> Crustacea, Malacostraca. II. IV. The Order Tanaidacea.</article-title> <source>The Danish Ingolf Expedition </source> <volume>3</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>145</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jóźwiak</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stępień</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Błażewicz-Paszkowcz</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> A revision of the genus <italic>Paranarthrurella</italic> Lang, 1971a (Crustacea: Tanaidacea).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>2238</volume>: <fpage>56</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jóźwiak</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Błażewicz-Paszkowycz</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> New records of the family Agathotanaidae (Crustacea: Tanaidacea) in the Antarctic, with remarks on <italic>Arthrura monacantha</italic> (Vanhöffen, 1914).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>2785</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kudinova-Pasternak</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> Abyssal Tanaidacea (Crustacea, Malacostraca) from the south-western part of the Indian Ocean. The suborder Tanaidomorpha.</article-title> <source>Zoologicheskii Zhurnal </source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>66</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971a</year>)<article-title> Taxonomische und phylogenetische Untersuchungen über die Tanaidaceen. 6. Revision der Gattung <italic>Paranarthrura</italic> Hansen, 1913, und Aufstellung von zwei neuen Familien, vier neuen Gattungen und zwei neuen Arten.</article-title> <source>Arkiv för Zoologi (Series 2)</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971b</year>)<article-title> Die Gattungen <italic>Agathotanais</italic> Hansen und <italic>Paragathotanais</italic> gen. n. (Tanaidacea).</article-title> <source>Crustaceana </source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/156854071X00229" xlink:type="simple">10.1163/156854071X00229</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Pacific Tanaidacea (Crustacea): Revision of the genus <italic>Agathotanais</italic>, with description of three new species.</article-title> <source>Records of the Australian Museum </source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>112</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3853/j.0067-1975.51.1999.1299" xlink:type="simple">10.3853/j.0067-1975.51.1999.1299</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Tanaidacea (Crustacea: Peracarida) of the Gulf of Mexico. X. The question of being male.</article-title> <source>Gulf and Caribbean Research </source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Deep-Sea Tanaidacea (Peracarida) from the Gulf of Mexico.</source> <publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Leiden</publisher-loc>, <lpage>381</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Family Agathotanaidae Lang, 1971a.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimomura</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds.</role>). <issue-title> Tanaidacea (Crustacea: Peracarida) From Japan III. The Deep Trenches: The Kurile-Kamchatka Trench and Japan Trench.</issue-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1599</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>GDF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Tanaidacean phylogeny, the first step: the superfamily Paratanaidoidea.</article-title> <source>Journal of Zoological Systematics and Evolutionary Research </source> <volume>40</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>205</fpage>-<lpage>222</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1439-0469.2002.00193.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1046/j.1439-0469.2002.00193.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poore</surname> <given-names>GCB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Błażewicz-Paszkowycz</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Browne</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruce</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerken</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Staples</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Syme</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker-Smith</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mark Warne</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>A</surname> <given-names>Williams</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>in press</year>)<source> Measuring biodiversity on the continental slope: issues and a case study.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sieg</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Sind die Dikonophora eine polyphyletische Gruppe?</article-title> <source>Zoologischer Anzieger</source> <volume>205</volume>(<issue>5/6</issue>): <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>416</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>