<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
	
    <front>

        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>

        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.56.523</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    Taxonomic notes on the afrotropical genera Hapalogenius Hagedorn, Hylesinopsis Eggers, and Rhopalopselion Hagedorn (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Scolytinae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
	
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Beaver</surname>
                        <given-names>Roger A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <aff>
                        161/2 Mu 5, Soi Wat Pranon, T. Donkaew, A. Maerim, Chiangmai 50180, Thailand
                    </aff>
			           				         	             	
                </contrib>             
            </contrib-group>

            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Roger A. Beaver (<email xlink:type="simple">rogerbeaver6@gmail.com</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: B. H. Jordal</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>

            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>17</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>56</issue>
            <fpage>157</fpage>
            <lpage>170</lpage>

            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>15</day>
                    <month>7</month>
                    <year>2009</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>20</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2009</year>
                </date>
            </history>

            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Roger A. Beaver</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Taxonomic confusion among the afrotropical scolytine genera <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> Hagedorn, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> Eggers and <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name> Hagedorn, and their synonyms is discussed with especial reference to the catalogues of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal (2009)</xref>. A key is given to separate the three genera recognised, and the species considered to be included in each genus are listed. <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> is resurrected from synonymy with <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name>, and shown not to be closely related to it. <tp:taxon-name>Chilodendron</tp:taxon-name> Schedl is considered to be a synonym of <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> and not of <tp:taxon-name>Xylechinus</tp:taxon-name> Chapuis. The following new synonymy is proposed at specific level: <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius africanus</tp:taxon-name> (Eggers) (= <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius lesnei</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, = <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus brincki</tp:taxon-name> Schedl); <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius fuscipennis</tp:taxon-name> (Chapuis) (= <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius bimaculatus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers); <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius oblongus</tp:taxon-name> (Eggers) (= <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus striatus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl); <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis fasciata</tp:taxon-name> (Hagedorn) (= <tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus punctatus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers); <tp:taxon-name>Phrixosoma niger</tp:taxon-name> Eggers (= <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius niger</tp:taxon-name> Schedl). The following species are returned to <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> from <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> to which they were transferred by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal (2009)</xref>: <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis alluaudi</tp:taxon-name> (Lepesme), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis angolensis</tp:taxon-name> (Schedl), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis arabiae</tp:taxon-name> (Schedl), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis atra</tp:taxon-name> (Nunberg), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis confusa</tp:taxon-name> (Eggers), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis decellei</tp:taxon-name> (Nunberg), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis dubia</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis emarginata</tp:taxon-name> (Nunberg), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis fasciata</tp:taxon-name> (Hagedorn), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis ficus</tp:taxon-name> (Schedl), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis granulata</tp:taxon-name> (Lepesme), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis hirsuta</tp:taxon-name> (Schedl), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis joveri</tp:taxon-name> (Schedl), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis pauliani</tp:taxon-name> (Lepesme), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis punctata (</tp:taxon-name>Eggers), <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis saudiarabiae</tp:taxon-name> (Schedl). The following new combination is given: <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis leprosula</tp:taxon-name> (Browne) from <tp:taxon-name>Cryphalus</tp:taxon-name> Erichson. New distributional records are given for some species.</p>
            </abstract>
	
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Afrotropical region</kwd>
                <kwd>Curculionidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Hapalogenius</kwd>
                <kwd>Hylesinopsis</kwd>
                <kwd>Rhopalopselion</kwd>
                <kwd>Scolytinae</kwd>
                <kwd>new synonymy</kwd>
                <kwd>new combination</kwd>            	           	
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>

    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>There has been considerable confusion in the literature about the relationships and limits of the scolytine genera <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> Hagedorn, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name> Hagedorn, and some other scolytine nominal genera from the Afrotropical region. In this paper, I attempt to resolve some of this confusion, and give some resultant taxonomic changes. The conclusions are based on the study of type material and other specimens from the following institutions: Deutsches Entomologisches Institut, Müncheberg (DEI), Hungarian Natural History Museum, Budapest (NHMB), Musée Royale de l’Afrique Centrale, Tervuren (MRAC), Museum and Institute of Zoology, Polish Academy of Sciences, Warsaw (MIZW), Museum fur Naturkünde der Humboldt Universität, Berlin (MNB), National Collection of Insects, Pretoria (NCIP), Natural History Museum, London (NHML), Naturhistorisches Museum, Wien (NMW), Transvaal Museum, Pretoria (TMP), Zoological Museum of Lund University (ZMLU), supplemented by specimens sent for identification by B. Jordal (University of Bergen, Norway), and in my own collection (RAB).</p>
            <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name> was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Hagedorn (1909)</xref> with <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion bituberculatum</tp:taxon-name> Hagedorn the only included species. The genus <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Hagedorn (1912)</xref> with <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius globosus</tp:taxon-name> the only included species. The genus <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Eggers (1920b)</xref> with <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis dubius</tp:taxon-name> the only included species. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Schedl (1951)</xref> considered that <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> (together with a third genus, <tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers) were synonymous, an opinion that he later retracted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Schedl 1963a</xref>). In fact, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Schedl (1963a)</xref> placed <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> in three different tribes, <tp:taxon-name>Strombophorini</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hypoborini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Phloeosini</tp:taxon-name> [sic] respectively, within his subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinae</tp:taxon-name> [sic]. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Wood (1978</xref>, 1986) continued to consider <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> as a synonym of <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name>, and included it and <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> in the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinini</tp:taxon-name>. Between 1983 and 1988, Wood synonymised with <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> the following genera: <tp:taxon-name>Trypographus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Chilodendron</tp:taxon-name> Schedl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Wood 1983</xref>); <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers (a replacement name for <tp:taxon-name>Pseudohylesinus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers nec Swaine), <tp:taxon-name>Hapalophloeus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Hemihylesinus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Wood 1984</xref>); <tp:taxon-name>Glochicopterus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, a genus synonymised with <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Wood (1983)</xref>; and <tp:taxon-name>Aridiamerus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Wood 1988a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">b</xref>). In addition, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Schedl (1957a)</xref> had already synonymised <tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers with <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus</tp:taxon-name>, a synonymy accepted by Wood (1986). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref> in their catalogue of <tp:taxon-name>Scolytidae</tp:taxon-name> maintain this position, and give further references to the genera and species mentioned.</p>
            <p>Recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal (2009)</xref> recognised that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref> had placed the type species of <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> in synonymy with <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis fuscipennis</tp:taxon-name> (Chapuis), and consequently reinstated <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> as the valid name for the genus <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name>. This resulted in a large number (38) of recombinations of species transferred from <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> to <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal (2009)</xref> retain <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name> as a valid genus, with the same twenty-four species included by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref>.</p><!--PageBreak-->
            <p>Wood (1986) has suggested that <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> sensuWoodand <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name> sensuWood are rapidly evolving genera, and that they could either be amalgamated into a single, large genus, or split up into a number of small genera. I believe that the most satisfactory solution at present is to distinguish three genera, based on morphological and biological criteria: <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name>. The first two of these genera are closely related, the third, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name>, is quite distinct from them. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> illustrate a representative species of each genus. The three genera may be distinguished using the following key, which also serves to diagnose the genera:</p>
        
            <table-wrap content-type="key" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
												                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennal funicle 7-segmented, club rounded to ovate with several annuli of closely-placed hairs. Pronotum almost quadrate, without a subapical constriction, the anterior angles prominently spinulose with strong asperities. Scutellum rather large, quadrate. Fifth abdominal ventrite with a median, approximately triangular process. Protibia with closely placed socketed teeth, and a well-developed tarsal groove on the anterior side. Large or moderately sized, stoutly-built, black species, 2.5 mm or more long. Xylophagous</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name> Hagedorn</td>
                        </tr>
												                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennal funicle 6- or 7-segmented, club sometimes more elongate, with or without more rows of setae than segments. Pronotum trapezoidal, narrowed anteriorly, usually with a subapical constriction, the anterior angles less prominently or not spinulose, the asperities often weakly developed. Scutellum small or not visible. Fifth abdominal ventrite without a median process. Protibia with or without socketed teeth; tarsal groove strongly or weakly developed. Smaller, less robust, usually brown or ferruginous species, usually less than 2.5 mm long. Phloeophagous, except <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius horridus</tp:taxon-name> (Eggers), which is reportedly xylophagous</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        </tr>
												                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennal club oblong-oval or egg-shaped, apex rounded, sometimes septate, usually with 4–7 annuli of closely placed hairs not corresponding to the sutures. Funicle 6- or 7-segmented, at least the last 1–2 segments much more strongly transverse than the more basal segments, symmetrically inserted into club. Eye usually shallowly emarginate. Costate ridge extends from procoxa to anteroventral margin of pronotum. Apical half of protibia widened, with convex outer margin rounded to apex and bearing 5–9 small, closely placed socketed teeth. Anterior face of protibia with well-developed, glabrous tarsal groove, anterior tarsi retractile into groove</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> Hagedorn</td>
                        </tr>
												                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennal club elongate, apex somewhat pointed, basal suture usually partly or completely septate, with no more than 3 rows of setae on outer face. Funicle always 6-segmented, the apical segments not strongly transverse, usually only slightly wider than more basal segments, more or less asymmetrically inserted <!--PageBreak-->into club. Eye entire. Costate ridge between procoxa and anteroventral margin of pronotum absent. Outer margin of protibia not convexly rounded in apical half, without a series of small socketed teeth, extended apically into a backwardly-pointing spine, at most 3 smaller spines basal to it on the outer margin, apical margin truncate, with 1–3 similar spines. Anterior face of protibia with a very short tarsal groove, tarsi not retractile</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> Eggers</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
        </sec>

        <sec sec-type="Systematics"><title>Systematics</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hagedorn</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Hagedorn 1912: 352.</xref> (Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius globosus</tp:taxon-name> Hagedorn, monobasic).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Pseudohylesinus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Eggers 1920a: 234.</xref> (Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Pseudohylesinus togonus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, monobasic, preoccupied by Swaine 1917: 11).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Eggers 1922: 165. (Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Pseudohylesinus togonus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, automatic, replacement name for <tp:taxon-name>Pseudohylesinus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers nec Swaine).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Eggers 1933: 18.</xref> (Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus africanus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, original designation). (The subsequent designation by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Schedl 1960: 75</xref> was unnecessary).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Glochicopterus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Schedl 1954: 75. (Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Glochicopterus baphiae</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, monobasic).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hapalophloeus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Schedl 1966: 363.</xref> (Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus brincki</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, original designation).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hemihylesinus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Schedl 1967: 224. (Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Hemihylesinus endroedyi</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, monobasic).<tp:taxon-name>Aridiamerus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl 1982: 284. (Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Aridiamerus angolensis</tp:taxon-name> Schedl , monobasic). (<tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis angolana</tp:taxon-name> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Wood 1988a: 32</xref> is an unnecessary replacement name.)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec>
                	<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Eggers (1927)</xref>, having compared the types of <tp:taxon-name>Phloeotribus fuscipennis</tp:taxon-name> (Chapuis, 1869) and <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius globosus</tp:taxon-name>, concluded that the species were identical. Chapuis’ name had priority, but the species did not belong in <tp:taxon-name>Phloeotribus</tp:taxon-name> and was transferred to <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name>. This conclusion was accepted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Schedl (1963a)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992: 94)</xref> placed <tp:taxon-name>Phloeotribus fuscipennis</tp:taxon-name> and its synonym <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius globosus</tp:taxon-name> in <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name>, overlooking the fact that <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> has priority, but they also (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright 1992: 96</xref>) cited <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name>, with its type species, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius globosus</tp:taxon-name>, as a synonym of <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name>. As noted above, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal (2009)</xref> reinstated <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> as the correct name for the species treated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref> under <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name>. I consider that <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> is a valid genus, but that it is distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> by the characters given in the key above, and with the synonymy given. I have examined the type species of all the genera involved. In addition to the type species listed above, the following 30 nominal<!--PageBreak--> species can be assigned to the genus: <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius acaciae</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius congonus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius immaturus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius lesnei</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius lonchocarpae</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius maculatus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius occidentalis</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius primus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius rufus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius senegambiensis</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius subseriatus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius suturalis</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis kenyae</tp:taxon-name> Wood, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis kenyae ugandae</tp:taxon-name> Wood*, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinus horridus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinus pusillus</tp:taxon-name> Gerstaecker, <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus brincki</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus dimorphus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus hispidus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus orientalis</tp:taxon-name> Eggers*, <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus quadrituberculatus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus striatus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus sulcatus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers*, <tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus africanus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers*, <tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus oblongus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers*, <tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus rhodesianus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers*, <tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus seriatus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, <tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus squamosus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers*, <tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus variegatus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers*, <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion atakorae</tp:taxon-name> Schedl* (* - type(s) examined). The genus clearly belongs in the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinini</tp:taxon-name> sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Wood (1986a)</xref>, but this tribe seems likely to be paraphyletic (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Farrell et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Jordal et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">McKenna et al. 2009</xref>), and may need to be redefined.</p>

                	<fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                	    <label>Figure 1.</label>
                	    <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius oblongus</tp:taxon-name> (Eggers), dorsal, A and lateral, B.</p></caption>
                	    <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/523/supp/ZooKeys-056-157-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                	</fig>
               </tp:treatment-sec>
						</tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>    
        
				<sec sec-type="New synonymy in Hapalogenius"><title>New synonymy in <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name></title>
            
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">africanus</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Eggers)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus africanus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Eggers 1933: 19</xref>.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion africanus</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Eggers): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Schedl 1951: 1104.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus africanus</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Eggers): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Schedl 1960: 76.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis africanus</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Eggers): Wood 1986: 39.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius africanus</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Eggers): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal 2009: 69.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius lesnei</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Eggers 1943: 73</xref>, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion lesnei</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Eggers): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright 1992: 97.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus brincki</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Schedl 1957b: 323</xref>, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Glochicopterus brincki</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Schedl): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Schedl 1963b: 262.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hapalophloeus brincki</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Schedl): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Schedl 1966: 363.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis brincki</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Schedl): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Wood 1984: 225</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright 1992: 93.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec>
                	<p>I have examined the female holotype of <tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus africanus</tp:taxon-name> (NHML) from Zambia, and other specimens from Zimbabwe (NHML), and compared them with syntypes of <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius lesnei</tp:taxon-name> (NMW), and with specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus brincki</tp:taxon-name> from Namibia which had earlier been compared with syntypes of this species in ZMLU. I have also examined specimens from Angola, Botswana, Namibia, and South Africa (NICP, TMP, RAB). Only a single species is represented, which varies in length from 1.5–2.2 mm, and in size-related characters, such as the number of teeth (6 or 8) on the anterior margin of the pronotum, and the detailed arrangement of the setae on the elytra.</p>
                	<p>It may be noted that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Eggers (1933)</xref> described the genus <tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus</tp:taxon-name> as having seven funicular segments. The genus <tp:taxon-name>Hapalophloeus</tp:taxon-name> was separated from <tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus</tp:taxon-name> because its type species (<tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus brincki</tp:taxon-name>) had only six funicular segments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Schedl 1966</xref>). I can confirm that the latter figure is correct. A seventh segment appears to have become fused to the base of the antennal club. The number of funicular segments is normally constant within a species in the <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinini</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                	<p><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius africanus</tp:taxon-name> is quite widely distributed in southern Africa. In addition to the distribution given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref>, it is known from Angola, Botswana and Mozambique. However, no host plants have been recorded. Specimen labels indicate that the species has been collected mostly at light.</p>
            		</tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">fuscipennis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Chapuis)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Phloeotribus fuscipennis</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Chapuis 1869: 44.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius fuscipennis</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Chapuis): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Eggers 1927: 196.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis fuscipennis</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Chapuis): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright 1992: 94.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius globosus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Hagedorn 1912: 352</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Eggers 1927: 196</xref> (Synonymy).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius bimaculatus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Eggers 1933: 22</xref>, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec>
                	<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Eggers (1933)</xref> distinguished his new species <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius bimaculatus</tp:taxon-name> from <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius fuscipennis</tp:taxon-name> by the presence of two flecks of dark setae on the posterior third of the elytra among the pale setae of the remainder of the elytra. I have compared the holotype of <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius bimaculatus</tp:taxon-name> (NHML) with a series of specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius fuscipennis</tp:taxon-name> from South Africa (NCIP, TMP). The series includes specimens in which the elytral setae are wholly pale, intermediates<!--PageBreak--> resembling <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius bimaculatus</tp:taxon-name>, and specimens in which the setae are almost entirely dark. In the absence of any other distinguishing characters, I conclude that <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius bimaculatus</tp:taxon-name> is a synonym of <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius fuscipennis</tp:taxon-name>. The shape of the median row of setae on the elytral interstriae varies from almost circular to somewhat elongate and truncate in different individuals. The species is known only from South Africa and Mozambique. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref> give Zimbabwe, but this appears to be in error for Mozambique. The only hosts recorded are <tp:taxon-name>Millettia grandis</tp:taxon-name> (‘Umzimbiti’ of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Hagedorn 1912</xref>) (Leguminosae), and an unidentified tree ‘sandalo’. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Hagedorn (1912)</xref> briefly described and illustrated the gallery system under bark.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">oblongus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Eggers)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Pseudophloeotribus oblongus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Eggers 1935: 299.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus oblongus</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Eggers): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Schedl 1960: 80.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis oblongus</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Eggers): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright 1992: 95.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius oblongus</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Eggers): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal 2009: 69.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
											  <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus striatus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Schedl 1957: 865, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec>
                	<p>The holotypes of both oblongus and striatus are in NHML. They have been directly compared, and I consider that they represent a single species, with minor variation in the density of the vestiture. I have also examined a series collected by Dr. B. Valentine in Kenya, and compared them with the holotype of <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius oblongus</tp:taxon-name>. The species is recorded from Kenya, Uganda and Tanzania, and from the host tree genera: <tp:taxon-name>Acacia</tp:taxon-name> (Leguminosae), <tp:taxon-name>Croton</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Euphorbiaceae</tp:taxon-name>) and <tp:taxon-name>Eucalyptus</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Myrtaceae</tp:taxon-name>). This suggests that it is a polyphagous species.</p>
								</tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Phrixosoma</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">nigra</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Eggers)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Bothryperus niger</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Eggers 1933: 21</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Phrixosoma nigra</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Eggers): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright 1992: 190</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius niger</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Schedl 1952: 7</xref>, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation> 
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Metahylesinus niger</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Schedl): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Schedl 1960: 79</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec>
                	<p>I have examined the holotype of <tp:taxon-name>Phrixosoma nigra</tp:taxon-name> (NHML), and the two syntypes of <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius niger</tp:taxon-name> and a further specimen standing under this name in the Schedl collection (NMW). Both species were described from Uganda, from the same host species (<tp:taxon-name>Harungana madagascariensis</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Clusiaceae</tp:taxon-name>)), and are clearly synonymous. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Schedl (1952)</xref> appears not to have noticed that the eyes of his species are bipartite, and that the antennal club is asymmetrical with a partly septate first segment – characteristics of <tp:taxon-name>Phrixosoma</tp:taxon-name> and not of <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Schedl (1963a)</xref> briefly describes the biology of the species, and illustrates the gallery system (as <tp:taxon-name>Bothryperus niger</tp:taxon-name>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Eggers</tp:taxon-authority> 
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">stat. res.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Eggers 1920b: 40.</xref> (Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis dubia</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, monobasic).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Trypographus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Schedl 1950: 213. (Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Trypographus joveri</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, monobasic).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Chilodendron</tp:taxon-name><comment> Schedl 1953: 74. (Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Chilodendron planicolle</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, monobasic).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec>
                		<p>These genera share the type of eye, antenna and protibia given in the key above. <tp:taxon-name>Trypographus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Chilodendron</tp:taxon-name> were synonymised with <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Wood (1983)</xref>. Wood and Bright (1992: 92) give <tp:taxon-name>Chilodendron</tp:taxon-name> as a synonym of <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name>, but its type species, <tp:taxon-name>Chilodendron planicolle</tp:taxon-name>, is also listed on page 118 under the genus <tp:taxon-name>Xylechinus</tp:taxon-name> Chapuis, with a note that the transfer of the species was to be published by Wood in a paper in press in 1992. However, this paper was apparently never published. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal (2009)</xref>, apparently basing their decision on the notes in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref>, synonymise <tp:taxon-name>Chilodendron</tp:taxon-name> with <tp:taxon-name>Xylechinus</tp:taxon-name>. I have examined a syntype of <tp:taxon-name>Chilodendron planicolle</tp:taxon-name> (NMW), and find that the synonymy given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal (2009)</xref> appears to be excluded by the 6-segmented funicle (always 5-segmented in <tp:taxon-name>Xylechinus</tp:taxon-name>), entire eye (always emarginate in <tp:taxon-name>Xylechinus</tp:taxon-name>),<!--PageBreak--> fore tibia without socketed teeth, and plumose metepisternal setae (scalelike in <tp:taxon-name>Xylechinus</tp:taxon-name>), even though the pronotum lacks asperities (as in some <tp:taxon-name>Xylechinus</tp:taxon-name>) (Wood 1982, 1986). Until further detailed studies are made of the species here included in <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name>, I prefer to leave <tp:taxon-name>Chilodendron</tp:taxon-name>, and its single included species, as a synonym of that genus.</p>
                  	
                		<fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                		    <label>Figure 2.</label>
                		    <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis dubius</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, dorsal, A and lateral, B.</p></caption>
                		    <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/523/supp/ZooKeys-056-157-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                		</fig>
                		
                		<p>The lack of close relationship of this genus to <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name>, based on morphology, seems to be corroborated by some analyses based on molecular data. In the phylogenetic tree of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Farrell et al. (2001: Fig. 6)</xref>, the single species of <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> studied (<tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis dubia</tp:taxon-name>) is widely separated from the two species of <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> included (<tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis oblonga</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis seriata</tp:taxon-name>) (both labelled as <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> sp. in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Farrell et al. 2001</xref>). In the phylogenetic tree of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">McKenna et al. (2009: Fig. 2)</xref>, the same species of <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis dubia</tp:taxon-name>) (McKenna, pers. comm. 2009) is widely separated from the two genera (<tp:taxon-name>Alniphagus</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinus</tp:taxon-name>) currently included in the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinini</tp:taxon-name>. In both cases, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> seems to be more closely related to genera included in the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Scolytinae</tp:taxon-name> sensu Wood by Wood (1986) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref>. One phylogenetic tree (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Jordal et al. 2008</xref>, Fig. 4) suggests a closer relationship between <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis dubia</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius seriata</tp:taxon-name>, and <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinus varius</tp:taxon-name> (F.), but in other analyses the relationship between these species is unresolved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Jordal et al. 2008</xref>). The tribal classification of the <tp:taxon-name>Scolytinae</tp:taxon-name> sensu Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal needs revision (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Jordal et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal 2009</xref>), and no attempt to place <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> in an existing tribe is made here.</p>
                		<p>In addition to the type species, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis dubia</tp:taxon-name>, and the type species of <tp:taxon-name>Trypographus</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Trypographus joveri</tp:taxon-name>),the following nominal species must be removed from <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> to which they were transferred by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal (2009)</xref> and returned to <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name> in which they are listed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref>: <tp:taxon-name>Chilodendron saudiarabiae</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis angolensis</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis arabiae</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus alluaudi</tp:taxon-name> Lepesme, <tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus confusus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers*, <tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus fasciatus</tp:taxon-name> Hagedorn*, <tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus ficus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus granulatus</tp:taxon-name> Lepesme, <tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus pauliani</tp:taxon-name> Lepesme, <tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus punctatus</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, <tp:taxon-name>Trypographus ater</tp:taxon-name> Nunberg, <tp:taxon-name>Trypographus decellei</tp:taxon-name> Nunberg, <tp:taxon-name>Trypographus emarginatus</tp:taxon-name> Nunberg, <tp:taxon-name>Trypographus hirsutus</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*. (* - type(s) examined). In addition, the following species belongs to the genus: <tp:taxon-name>Cryphalus leprosulus</tp:taxon-name> Browne* (see below). References to all these species can be found in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref>.</p>
                		<p>The species are normally associated with trees of the family <tp:taxon-name>Moraceae</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Ficus</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Morus</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Bosqueia</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Treculia</tp:taxon-name>). There are only three records from other families, one each from <tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Meliaceae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Rosaceae</tp:taxon-name>. This narrow host range contrasts with the wide host range of <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                		<p>On the basis of the limited distributional data available, nearly 50% (8 ex 17) of the species appear to be confined to montane habitats above 1500m. This includes the following species: <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis alluaudi</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis confusa</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis emarginata</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis fasciata</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis granulata</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis pauliani</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis punctata</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis saudiarabiae</tp:taxon-name>. Eight species appear to be more lowland species: <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis angolensis</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis arabiae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis atra</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis decellei</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis dubia</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis ficus</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis joveri</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis leprosula</tp:taxon-name>. <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis planicolle</tp:taxon-name> was described from Mt. d’Ambre in Madagascar, but no altitude is given.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
       </sec>
                
       <sec sec-type="Taxonomic changes in Hylesinopsis"><title>Taxonomic changes in <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name></title>
            
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">fasciata</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Hagedorn)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus fasciatus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Hagedorn, 1909: 737.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis fasciatus</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Hagedorn): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright 1992: 94.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Chilodendron fasciatus</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Hagedorn): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Schedl 1963b: 261.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus punctatus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Eggers 1932: 28</xref>, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec>
                	<p>I have compared two specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus punctatus</tp:taxon-name> (NMW), which had been compared with the damaged holotype by Eggers and Schedl respectively, with a series of specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis fasciata</tp:taxon-name> in my own collection from Tanzania and Nigeria. The latter had earlier been compared to a syntype of that species, and other specimens from East Africa in NHML. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Eggers (1932)</xref> distinguished the two species by the more elongate shape, stronger shine, more distinct puncturation, and the presence of granules on the basal part of the elytra. Comparisons suggest that <tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus punctatus</tp:taxon-name> lies at one end of the range of variation found in <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis fasciata</tp:taxon-name>. The small differences noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Eggers (1932)</xref> are insufficient to separate <tp:taxon-name>Kissophagus punctatus</tp:taxon-name> as a separate species, and the latter is, therefore, placed in synonymy. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref> cite a holotype for <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis fasciata</tp:taxon-name>. However, Hagedorn described the species from “compluria specimina”, indicating that he had a series of syntypes before him.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                      <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">leprosula</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Browne)</tp:taxon-authority> 
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cryphalus leprosulus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Browne 1980: 774.</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec>
                	<p>I have examined the holotype (MRAC), and twenty-one paratypes (MRAC, NHML). It is not clear why <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Browne (1980)</xref> assigned this species to the genus <tp:taxon-name>Cryphalus</tp:taxon-name> Erichson. Such an assignment within the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Cryphalini</tp:taxon-name> is ruled out by the six–segmented funicle, the elongate eyes, the lack of a visible scutellum, the raised and crenulate basal margin of the elytra, and other characters. The species is here removed from <tp:taxon-name>Cryphalus</tp:taxon-name> and transferred to <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hagedorn</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec>
                		<p>When the species described in <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> are omitted, the remaining eleven species included in <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion</tp:taxon-name> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref> form a cluster of closely related species distinguished by the quadrate pronotum with strong asperities at the antero-lateral corners, and the large quadrate scutellum. The apical visible sternite<!--PageBreak--> has a triangular, median projection. The beetles are strongly built, black in colour, and 2.5–4.5 mm long. All those with known habits are xylophagous (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Schedl 1960</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Browne 1963</xref>). Like <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name>, the genus belongs in the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinini</tp:taxon-name> sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Wood (1986a)</xref></p>
                  	
                		<fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                		    <label>Figure 3.</label>
                		    <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion thompsoni</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, dorsal, A and lateral, B.</p></caption>
                		    <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/523/supp/ZooKeys-056-157-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                		</fig>
                		
                		<p>In addition to the type species, <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion bituberculatum</tp:taxon-name> Hagedorn*, I consider the following species to belong in the genus: <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion atrum</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion confusum</tp:taxon-name> Eggers, <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion conjungens</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion dentatum</tp:taxon-name> Nunberg*, <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion grande</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion immune</tp:taxon-name> Eggers*, <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion intermedium</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion nitidum</tp:taxon-name> Schedl, <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion orientale</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*, <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion thompsoni</tp:taxon-name> Schedl*. (* - type(s) examined). The remaining species listed under the genus by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref> belong in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> (see above) in which almost all were originally described. It may be noted here that the holotype of <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalopselion bituberculatum</tp:taxon-name> is in DEI and not MNB as stated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Wood and Bright (1992)</xref>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
				</sec>
				
        <sec sec-type="New records of Hapalogenius and Hylesinopsis"><title>New records of <tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis</tp:taxon-name></title>
            <p>The following new records extend the known geographical distribution of the species.</p>
    				<p><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius atakorae</tp:taxon-name> (Schedl). GHANA: Northern Reg., Nakpanduri escarp., 10°38'N; 0°12'W, 19.vi.1971, under tree bark (Endrödy-Younga) (37exx.) (TMP, RAB).</p>
    				<p><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius pusillus</tp:taxon-name> (Gerstaecker). SOUTH AFRICA, West Cape, Knysna, Gouna, 6.xi.2006, ex <tp:taxon-name>Virgilia oroboides</tp:taxon-name> (B. Jordal) (4exx.) (RAB) (Further specimens in B.Jordal’s collection).</p>
    				<p><tp:taxon-name>Hapalogenius sulcatus</tp:taxon-name> (Eggers). NAMIBIA: East Caprivi, Katima, Mulilo, 17°29'S; 24°17'E, 3–8.iii.1992 (M. Uhlig) (1 ex.); Kavango, Kaudom Camp, 18°21'S; 20°43'E, 22–25.ii.1992, lux (M. Uhlig) (1 ex.); Kavango, Mahango Game Res., 20.i.1993 (F. Koch) (ZMB); SOUTH AFRICA: E.Transvaal, Berlin, 300m below, 25°33'S; 30°43'E, 4.ii.1987, UV light (E-Y:2416) (1 ex.); N.Transvaal, Entabeni – L.Trich.,c. 23°05'S; 30°12'E, airplankton (E-Y:1138) (1 ex.); Tvl., Nelshoogte, gallery for. below St., 25°51'S; 30°53'E, 4.xii.1987, UV light (E-Y:2354) (1ex.); Tvl., Nelspruit Nat.Res., dry valley, 25°29'S; 30°55'E, 8.ii.1987, UV light, top valley (E-Y:2432) (4 exx.) (all coll. Endrödy-Younga) (TMP, RAB); ZIMBABWE: Chipinga, 1.ii.1990 (C. R. Owen) (1 ex.) (TMP); Kyle Recr. Park at Lake Mutirikwi, 20°13'S; 31°00'E, 1–5.xii.1993, lux (M. Uhlig) (1 ex.) (ZMB).</p>
    				<p><tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis dubia</tp:taxon-name> Eggers. GUINEA: Seredou, 4.iv.1975, lux (Zott) (1 ex.) (ZMB).</p>
    				<p><tp:taxon-name>Hylesinopsis fasciata</tp:taxon-name> (Hagedorn). SOUTH AFRICA : S.Natal, Weza, Bangeni Forest, 30°38'S; 29°39'E, 21.xi.1989, beating in forest (Endrödy &amp; Klimaszew) (E-Y:2708) (1 ex.); as previous except: 30°32'S; 29°41'E, 23.xi.1989 (E-Y: 2716) (1 ex.) (TMP).</p>
        </sec>
    
    </body><!--PageBreak-->
    
    <back>
        <ack>
            <label>Acknowledgements</label>
            <p>I am most grateful to the following curators for their willingness to loan type and other specimens for this study (and in many cases for their friendly access to the collections in their charge): L. Zerche (DEI), D.Mierzwa (MIZW), J.Frisch (MNB), E.de Coninck (MRAC), R.Stals (NCIP), O.Merkl (NHMB), M.W.V.Barclay (NHML), H.Schönherr (NMW), C.Bellamy (TMP), R.Danielsson (ZMLU), and to B.Jordal both for material from his private collection, and comments on the paper. I am indebted to C.Lyal (NHML) for making available a copy of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal (2009)</xref> prior to publication. I thank A. Cognato and S. Smith for assistance with the photographs.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Zarazaga</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyal</surname> <given-names>CHC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> A catalogue of family and genus group names in Scolytinae and Platypodinae with nomenclatural remarks (Coleoptera: Curculionidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2258</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>134</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaver</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>New synonymy, new combinations and taxonomic notes on Scolytidae and Platypodidae (Insecta: Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Annalen des Naturhistorisches Museum, Wien 100B</source>: <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Browne</surname> <given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<article-title> Notes on the habits and distribution of some Ghanaian bark beetles and ambrosia beetles (Coleoptera: Scolytidae and Platypodidae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of Entomological Research</source> <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>266</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Browne</surname> <given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Some new species of Scolytidae and Platypodidae from Africa and the Seychelles Islands.</article-title> <source>Revue de Zoologie Africaine</source> <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>773</fpage>-<lpage>779</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapuis</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1869</year>) <source>Synopsis des Scolytides.</source> <publisher-name>J.Desoer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Liège</publisher-loc>, <lpage>56</lpage>pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eggers</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1920a</year>) <article-title>60 neue Borkenkäfer (Ipidae) aus Afrika, nebst zehn neuen Gattungen, zwei Abarten.</article-title> <source>Entomologische Blätter</source> <volume>15</volume> (<issue>1919</issue>): <fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>243</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eggers</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1920b</year>)<article-title> 60 neue Borkenkäfer (Ipidae) aus Afrika, nebst zehn neue Gattungen, zwei Abarten. (Fortsetzung).</article-title> <source>Entomologische Blätter</source> <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eggers</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1927</year>)<article-title> Neue Borkenkäfer (Ipidae, Col.) aus Africa (Nachtrag III).</article-title> <source>Revue de Zoologie et de Botanique Africaines</source> <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>172</fpage>-<lpage>199</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eggers</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1932</year>)<article-title> Neue Borkenkäfer (Ipidae, Col.) aus Africa (Nachtrag IV).</article-title> <source>Revue de Zoologie et de Botanique Africaines</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eggers</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1933</year>)<article-title> Neue Borkenkäfer (Col., Scolytidae) aus Africa (Nachtrag V).</article-title> <source>Stylops</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eggers</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1943</year>)<article-title> Neue Borkenkäfer (Ipidae) aus Afrika. Nachtrag VIII.</article-title> <source>Entomologische Blätter</source> <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrell</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sequeira</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Meara</surname> <given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Normark</surname> <given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordal</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> The evolution of agriculture in beetles (Curculionidae: Scolytinae and Platypodinae).</article-title> <source>Evolution</source> <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>2011</fpage>-<lpage>2027</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagedorn</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1909</year>)<article-title> Diagnosen bisher unbeschreibener Borkenkäfer. II Serie.</article-title> <source>Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift</source> <volume>1909</volume>:<fpage>733</fpage>-<lpage>746</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagedorn</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>)<article-title> Neue Borkenkäfergattungen und Arten aus Afrika (Col.).</article-title> <source>Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift</source> <volume>1912</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>-<lpage>356</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordal</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillespie</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cognato</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Secondary structure alignment and direct optimization of 28S rDNA sequences provides limited phylogenetic resolution in bark and ambrosia beetles (Curculionidae: Scolytinae).</article-title> <source>Zoologica Scripta</source> <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenna</surname> <given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sequeira</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marvaldi</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrell</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Temporal lags and overlap in the diversification of weevils and flowering plants.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source> <volume>106</volume>:<fpage>7083</fpage>-<lpage>7088</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1951</year>)<article-title> Fauna aethiopica VII. Bark and ambrosia beetles from Dahomey and Togo collected by Mr.A.Villiers.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de l’Institut Française de l’Afrique Noire</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1103</fpage>-<lpage>1106</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1952</year>)<article-title> Scolytoidea Congolais IV.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de l’Institut royale des Sciences naturelles de Belgique</source> <volume>28</volume> (<issue>32</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1957a</year>)<article-title> Scolytoidea nouveaux du Congo Belge II.</article-title> <source>Annales du Musée royale du Congo Belge, Tervuren, Série in 8vo, Sciences Zoologiques</source> <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>162</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1957b</year>) <article-title>Coleoptera: Scolytidae and Platypodidae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanström</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brinck</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudebeck</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>), <source>South African Animal Life. Results of the Lund University expedition in 1950–1951, vol.IV</source>, <fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1960</year>)<article-title> Scolytidae und Platypodidae Afrikas. Band I. (Fortsetzung).</article-title> <source>Revista de Entomologia Moçambique</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963a</year>)<article-title> Scolytidae und Platypodidae Afrikas. Band I. (Fortsetzung).</article-title> <source>Revista de Entomologia Moçambique</source> <volume>4</volume> (<issue>1961</issue>):<fpage>335</fpage>-<lpage>742</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963b</year>)<article-title> Zur Synonymie der Borkenkäfer, IX.</article-title> <source>Entomologische Abhandlungen und Berichten aus dem Staatliches Museum für Tierkunde, Dresden</source> <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>257</fpage>-<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>)<article-title> New bark and timber beetles forwarded by the Commonwealth Institute of Entomology.</article-title> <source>Novos Taxos Entomologia</source> <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1966</year>)<article-title> Interessante und neue Scolytoidea aus Afrika.</article-title> <source>Revista de Entomologia Moçambique</source> <volume>8</volume> (<issue>1965</issue>):<fpage>349</fpage>-<lpage>379</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>)<article-title> A reclassification of the subfamilies and tribes of Scolytidae (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société entomologique de France (N.S.)</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>122</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> New synonymy and new species of American bark beetles (Coleoptera: Scolytidae), Part IX.</article-title> <source>Great Basin Naturalist</source> <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>647</fpage>-<lpage>659</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> New generic synonymy and new genera of Scolytidae (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Great Basin Naturalist</source> <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>223</fpage>-<lpage>230</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986a</year>)<article-title> A reclassification of the genera of Scolytidae (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Great Basin Naturalist Memoirs</source> <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>126</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986b</year>)<article-title> New synonymy and new species of American bark beetles (Coleoptera: Scolytidae), Part XI.</article-title> <source>Great Basin Naturalist</source> <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>265</fpage>-<lpage>273</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988a</year>)<article-title> Nomenclatural changes and new species of Scolytidae (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Great Basin Naturalist</source> <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988b</year>)<article-title> Nomenclatural changes and new species of Scolytidae (Coleoptera), Part II.</article-title> <source>Great Basin Naturalist</source> <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>-<lpage>195</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bright</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> A catalog of Scolytidae and Platypodidae (Coleoptera), Part 2: Taxonomic index, Volume A.</article-title> <source>Great Basin Naturalist Memoirs</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>833</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>