<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.87.1295</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new species of the rare chrysidid subfamily Loboscelidiinae from China: the third species of <italic>Rhadinoscelidia</italic> Kimsey, 1988 (Hymenoptera, Chrysididae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Liu</surname> 
                        <given-names>Jing-xian</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"></xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7EACA0FA-87AA-42E6-8C86-645FA893F53C</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Yao</surname> 
                        <given-names>Jie-min</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"></xref>
										<uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:0851B937-80C7-45E9-9B7F-201681396E24</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Xu</surname> 
                        <given-names>Zai-fu</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"></xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:2C2DE0CA-C34F-4440-8A9C-84F9B5969815</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label></label>College of Nature Resources and Environment, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510640, the People’s Republic of China</aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Zai-fu Xu (<email xlink:type="simple">xuzaifu@scau.edu.cn</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Michael Sharkey</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
            	    <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>87</issue>
            <fpage>11</fpage>
            <lpage>17</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>16</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Jing-xian Liu, Jie-min Yao, Zai-fu Xu</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:F0B31053-855D-4585-AA27-3549C0A01498</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia delta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Liu, Yao &amp; Xu, <bold>sp. n.</bold> (<tp:taxon-name>Chrysididae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Loboscelidiinae</tp:taxon-name>) is described and illustrated based on two female specimens from Hainan province. It represents the first record of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kimsey, 1988 for China. A key to the world species of this genus is given. All specimens are preserved in the Hymenopteran Collection, South China Agricultural University (SCAU).</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Aculeata</kwd>
                <kwd>Chrysidoidea</kwd>
                <kwd>Oriental Region</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Loboscelidiinae</tp:taxon-name> is a small subfamily of <tp:taxon-name>Chrysididae</tp:taxon-name> distributed in the Oriental and Australian regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Cameron 1910</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Kieffer 1916</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Fouts 1925</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Maa and Yoshimoto 1961</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Lin 1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Day 1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Terayama et al. 1998</xref>), which includes two genera: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Loboscelidia</tp:taxon-name></italic> <!--PageBreak-->Westood, 1874 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kimsey, 1988. Thirty-five species in total are recognized in <tp:taxon-name>Loboscelidiinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Kimsey and Bohart 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kojima and Ubaidillah 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Xu et al. 2006</xref>), of which thirty-three species belong to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Loboscelidia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and two species belong to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia</tp:taxon-name></italic>: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia malaysiae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kimsey, 1988 from Malaysia and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia halimunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ubaidillah, 2003 from Indonesia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Kimsey 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kojima and Ubaidillah 2003</xref>).</p>
            <p>Hosts of most species of this subfamily are unknown, but a few species are suggested to be parasitoids of <tp:taxon-name>Formicidae</tp:taxon-name> or <tp:taxon-name>Phasmatidae</tp:taxon-name>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Fouts (1922)</xref> suggested that <tp:taxon-name>Loboscelidiinae</tp:taxon-name> were probably myrmecophilous because they have the habitus of ants and the woolly appearance of the neck which is the characteristic of many myrmecophiles. Some species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Loboscelidia</tp:taxon-name></italic> were inferred to be egg parasitoids of <tp:taxon-name>Phasmatidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Hadlington and Hoschke 1959</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Heather 1965</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Riek 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Krombein 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Kimsey and Bohart 1990</xref>). However, there are no any host records of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Most chrysidids are diurnal, but species of <tp:taxon-name>Loboscelidiinae</tp:taxon-name> are probably active during dusk or nocturnally based on their dark brown body and large ocelli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Kimsey and Bohart 1990</xref>).</p>
            <p>Males of <tp:taxon-name>Loboscelidiinae</tp:taxon-name> are much more commonly collected than females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Kimsey and Bohart 1990</xref>). Recently, two specimens of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia</tp:taxon-name></italic> were discovered in Hainan, China, representing a new species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia delta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Liu, Yao &amp; Xu, sp. n. It represents the first record of this genus for China.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods"><title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>Two specimens of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia</tp:taxon-name></italic> were collected in 2007 from Hainan. Type specimens are deposited in the Hymenopteran Collection of South China Agricultural University (SCAU).</p>
            <p>The antenna, wings and legs on one side of the type specimen were cut off and mounted on a slide using Canada balsam. Specimens were examined and described using stereomicroscopes Leica MZ12.5 and Olympus SZ61. All pictures were made by Zeiss Imager A1 attached to a digital camera, CoolSNAP, and software Image-Pro Plus.</p>
            <p>Abbreviations used in the descriptions as follows: POL= posterior ocellar line, the shortest distance between the posterior ocelli; MOD= mid ocellar diameter; OL= distance between middle and posterior ocelli; OOL=oculo-ocellar line, the shortest distance between the posterior ocellus and compound eye.</p>
            <p>Morphological terminology and wing vein nomenclature are mostly based on that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Kimsey and Bohart (1990)</xref>. However, <italic>mesoscutum</italic> and <italic>metasoma</italic> are used, respectively, for ‘scutum’ and ‘abdomen’.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Rhadinoscelidia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Kimsey, 1988</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Kimsey 1988</xref>: 77. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia malaysiae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Kimsey 1988</xref>, original designation.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> Antenna with scape distinctly longer than head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 4</xref>); vertex sharply declivitous behind ocelli (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3, 5</xref>); cervical projection of head with posterior shield-like expansion clearly separate from rest of head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>); fore wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>) venation highly reduced, restricted to basal sixth or less; all tibiae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–9</xref>) without longitudinal semitransparent flanges.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Host"><title>Host.</title>
                    <p> Unknown.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p> China (Hainan), Malaysia, Indonesia.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Rhadinoscelidia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">delta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7A454BDD-8BDA-4E64-9992-E8FBD5CDFDBC</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Liu, Yao &amp; Xu</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">12</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis (Female)"><title>Diagnosis (Female).</title>
                        <p> This new species can be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia halimunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ubaidillah, 2003 by having the scape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 4, 6</xref>) without transparent flange (the latter species with transparent flange), and frons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>) with median carina not forked at upper end (the latter with median carina of frons forked at upper end); it is also easily separated from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia malaysiae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by fore wing venation restricted to basal 1/7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>) (the latter species with fore wing venation restricted to basal 1/13) and first anal vein distinct (the latter with first anal vein indistinct).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p> Holotype Female. Body length 2.3 mm; fore wing length 2.5 mm. Body shiny, with sparse setae.</p>
                        <p><italic>Head</italic>. Head in anterior view triangular, as wide as width of mesosoma at tegulae and 1.5 times the interocular distance; head in lateral view oblong (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>). Eyes situated on dorsal upper half of head (Fig.3). Clypeus with short and erect setae. Frontal projection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2–3</xref>) in frontal view bilobate and trapezoid, in lateral view weakly up curved and obliquely truncate, lower lateral corner with transverse carinae extending to two sides of clypeus, upper lateral corner with carinae extending backward along middle of inner margin of eye then to posterior ocelli. Frons sparsely and finely punctuate, with a reverse triangular depression area. Gena polished. Ocelli oval, with some micropunctures and short wrinkles around, MOD=2, POL=3, OL=1, OOL=8. Vertex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3, 5</xref>) abruptly sloping and angulate posteriad lateral ocelli. Cervical projection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>) strongly constricted behind ocelli and eyes, and posteriorly expanded and shield-like dorsally, centrally with a shallow longitudinal furrow. Vertex, gena and anterior lateral sides of cervical projection with ribbon-like setae. Antenna stout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4, 6</xref>), covered with long and dense setae, about equals to the length of body. Scape 5.0 times <!--PageBreak-->as long as wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>), curved, without transparent flange. Pedicel similar to flagellar segments, 1.8 times as long as wide. Relative proportion of length to width of flagellomeres as follows: 40 : 32; 36 : 32; 36 : 32; 36 : 32; 36 : 32; 36 : 32; 36 : 34; 32 : 37; 31 : 39; 33 : 41; 67 : 40.</p>
                        <p><italic>Mesosoma</italic>. Pronotum polished, with maximum width 1.4 times as long as maximum length, proximal basal width 0.8 times as long as ultimate apical width. Lateral margin of<!--PageBreak--> pronotum rounded (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>), not sharp; anterior lateral sides of pronotum with short, narrow row of ribbon-like setae. Mesoscutum smooth, posterolateral projections lamellate, sparsely setose. Notauli complete, mesoscutum between notauli weakly concave. Parapsides indistinct. Tegula as long as pronotum, sparsely setose, and extending to posterior margin of scutellum. Scutellum smooth. Propodeal projection obtuse, inconspicuous.</p>
                        <p><italic>Legs</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–9</xref>). Slender, with sparse bristles; all femora with small apical transparent flanges 1/8 times as long as femur; all tibiae without transparent flanges.</p>
                        <p><italic>Wings</italic>. Fore wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>) infuscate, with hyaline streaks, covered with dense pubescence; venation highly reduced, restricted to basal 1/7; first anal vein distinct, paral<!--PageBreak-->lel to and as long as M+Cu vein, cu-a vein indistinct, short. R1 vein 0.9 times, Rs vein 2.8 times and cu-a vein 0.3 times as long as length of stigmal vein. Hind wing veinless.</p>
                        <p><italic>Metasoma</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). First tergite subtriangular, maximum length 0.5 times the maximum width; second tergite weakly trapezoid, with maximum length 0.75 times maximum width; third tergite narrow, 0.5 times as long as wide; fourth tergite weakly exposed; all tergites smooth, scattered with sparse setae. Segments and ovipositor that retracted within metasoma as illustrated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 11, 12</xref>).</p>
                        <p><italic>Colour</italic>. Body dark red. Antennae and legs reddish brown.</p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 1–6.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia delta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Liu, Yao &amp; Xu, sp. n. holotype. <bold>1</bold> lateral habitus <bold>2</bold> head in frontal view <bold>3</bold> head and pronotum in lateral view <bold>4–5</bold> dorsal view of head and pronotum <bold>6</bold> antenna.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-087-011-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 7–12.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia delta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Liu, Yao &amp; Xu, sp. n. holotype. <bold>7</bold> fore leg <bold>8</bold> mid leg <bold>9</bold> hind leg <bold>10</bold> fore wing and hind wing <bold>11</bold> seventh tergite, seventh sternite and ovipositor (indicated by T7, S7 and ovip) <bold>12</bold> sixth tergite.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-087-011-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Male"><title>Male.</title>
                        <p> Unknown.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                        <p> Holotype, female, China: Hainan, Mt. Wuzhishan (18.85°N, 109.66°E), May 16–20, 2007, Li-qiong Weng, No. 200800122. Paratype: 1 female, same data as type, No. 200800160.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The specific name derives from Greek ‘delta’, meaning triangular, referring to the triangular depression on frons.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p> The terminal segments and ovipositor structure of these females from China are similar to those of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Loboscelidia</tp:taxon-name></italic> as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Day (1979)</xref>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
						<sec sec-type="Key to species of Rhadinoscelidia of the World"><title>Key to species of <tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia</tp:taxon-name> of the World</title>
		            <p>Males are not known for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia delta</tp:taxon-name></italic> and females are not known for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia halimunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia malaysiae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, so the following key has limited utility.</p>
		            <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
		                <table>
		                    <tbody>
		                        <tr>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male. Metasoma with five visible segments</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
		                        </tr>
		                        <tr>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female. Metasoma with four visible segments. Fore wing venation restricted to basal 1/7; first anal vein distinct; frons with a reversed triangular depression near antennal sockets. China (Hainan)</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia delta</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
		                        </tr>
		                        <tr>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape with transparent flange on basal 1/4; frons with median carina forked at upper end near anterior margin of anterior ocellus. Indonesia</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia halimunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ubaidillah</td>
		                        </tr>
		                        <tr>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape without transparent flange on basal 1/4; frons with median carina not forked at upper end near anterior margin of anterior ocellus. Malaysia</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhadinoscelidia malaysiae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kimsey</td>
		                        </tr>
		                    </tbody>
		                </table>
		            </table-wrap>
		        </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We are very grateful to Mr. Xin-dao Qin, Zhong-run Zhang, for their kind help during field work in Hainan Province; to Prof Roger A. Beaver and Keith Wilson for their kind help to improve the manuscript English. We thank two anonymous reviewers for their useful comments to improve the manuscript. The project was jointly supported by National Nature Science Foundation of China (No.30770265) and the Ministry of Science and Technology of P. R. China (MOST grant N. 2006FY110500).<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1910</year>)<article-title> Description of a new genus and species of <italic>Oxyura</italic> (Hymenoptera) from Kuching.</article-title> <source>Borneo Entomologist</source> <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> The affinities of <italic>Loboscelidia</italic> Westwood.</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fouts</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1922</year>)<article-title> New parasitic Hymenoptera from the oriental islands.</article-title> <source>The Philippine Journal of Science</source> <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>619</fpage>-<lpage>637</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fouts</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1925</year>)<article-title>. Descriptions of three new Hymenoptera from the Philippine Islands.</article-title> <source>The Philippine Journal of Science</source> <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>515</fpage>-<lpage>519</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadlington</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoschke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>)<article-title> Observations on the Ecology of the Phasmatid <italic>Ctenomorphodes tessulatus</italic> (Gray).</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Linnaean Society of New South Wales</source> <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>146</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heather</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>)<article-title> Occurrence of Cleptidae (Hymenoptera) parasites in eggs of <italic>Ctenomorphodes tessulatus</italic> (Gray) (Phasmida: Phasmidae) in Queensland.</article-title> <source>Journal of the Entomological Society of Queensland</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>-<lpage>87</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kieffer</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1916</year>)<article-title> Diapriidae.</article-title> <source>Das Tierreich</source>, <volume>44</volume>: <lpage>627</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimsey</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> Loboscelidiinae, new species and a new genus from Malaysia (Hymenoptera: Chrysidae).</article-title> <source>Psyche</source> <volume>95</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimsey</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohart</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>The Chrysidid Wasps of the World.</source> <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>. <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ubaidillah</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Two new species of the cryptic chrysidid parasitoid subfamily Loboscelidiinae: the second species in <italic>Rhadinoscelidia</italic> and the first <italic>Loboscelidia</italic> for the Indonesian fauna.</article-title> <source>Entomological Science</source> <volume>6</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Krombein</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> Biosystematic studies of Ceylonese wasps, XI: a monograph of the Amiseginae and Loboscelidiinae (Hymenoptera: Chrysididae).</article-title> <source>Smithsonian Contribution to Zoology</source> <volume>376</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<article-title> The Taiwanese Loboscelidiidae (Hymenoptera: Bethyloidea).</article-title> <source>Quarterly Journal of the Taiwan Museum</source> <volume>17</volume> (<issue>3–4</issue>):<fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>245</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maa</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshimoto</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>)<article-title> Loboscelidiidae, a new family of Hymenoptera.</article-title> <source>Pacific Insects</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>523</fpage>-<lpage>548</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Riek</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>) <source>The Insects of Australia. Hymenoptera.</source> <publisher-loc>Melbourne</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Melbourne University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>867</fpage>–<lpage>959</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Terayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muroi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamagishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> A new record of the subfamily Lobosceliidinae (Hymenoptera, Chrysididae) from Japan.</article-title> <source>The Japanese Journal of Systematic Entomology</source> <volume>4</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Westwood</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1874</year>) <source>Thesaurus Entomologicus Oxoniensis.</source> <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name>, xxi+<lpage>205</lpage>pp+40pls.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He J</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> A new species of the genus <italic>Loboscelidia</italic> (Insecta, Hymenoptera) from China.</article-title> <source>Acta Zootaxonomia Sinica</source> <volume>31</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>208</fpage>-<lpage>210</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>