<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.78.977</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    Redefinition of the genus Allonychiurus Yoshii, 1995 (Collembola, Onychiuridae) with description of a new species from China
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Xin</surname>
                        <given-names>Sun</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:2E68A57F-2AE1-45F3-98B2-EEF252590DC3</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Jian-Xiu</surname>
                        <given-names>Chen</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:80E5F786-E8DA-44BA-AABF-91A196480B5F</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Louis</surname>
                        <given-names>Deharveng</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:E777E18C-47CB-4967-9634-6F93FD9741A7</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>Department of Biological Science and Technology, Nanjing University, Nanjing 210093, P.R. China</label></aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle, UMR7205 du CNRS, CP50, 45, rue Buffon, 75005 Paris, France</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Louis Deharveng (<email xlink:type="simple">deharven@mnhn.fr</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Wanda Maria Weiner</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>28</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>78</issue>
            <fpage>27</fpage>
            <lpage>41</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>5</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>17</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Xin Sun, Jian-Xiu Chen, Louis Deharveng</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:D489679D-D571-447A-AE12-A5DA158F9E7E</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>In this paper, we describe a new species of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> Yoshii, 1995, characterized by the presence of an apical swelling on the fourth antennal segment as well as a combination of chaetotaxic and pseudocellar characters. The genus <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> is redefined. Four of its species are considered as <italic>incertae sedis</italic>: <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus michelbacheri</tp:taxon-name> (Bagnall, 1948), <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus spinosus</tp:taxon-name> (Bagnall, 1949), <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus caprariae</tp:taxon-name> (Dallai, 1969) and <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus sensitivus</tp:taxon-name> (Handschin, 1928). The three species <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus borensis</tp:taxon-name> (Beruete, Arbea &amp; Jordana, 1994), <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus sensilatus</tp:taxon-name> (Thibaud &amp; Massoud, 1979) and <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus vandeli</tp:taxon-name> (Cassagnau, 1960) are removed from <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> and placed in <tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name> Bagnall, 1949, <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name> Bagnall, 1949 and <tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> Weiner, 1996 respectively. The synonymy of <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name> Weiner, 1996 with <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> is rejected and <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus foliatus</tp:taxon-name> (Rusek, 1967) and <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name> (Thibaud &amp; Lee, 1994) are re-allocated to <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name>. List and identification key to the world species of the genus are given.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Collembola</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Allonychiurus</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Micronychiurus</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Spinonychiurus</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Thalassaphorura</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Thibaudichiurus</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>chaetotaxy</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>China</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> Yoshii, 1995 includes 23 species according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>. They are distributed in Asia, Europe and America. However, as stressed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Sun et al. (2009)</xref>, generic assignment of most of these species is disputable. To improve this confusing situation, we re-examined all available taxonomic descriptions and type specimens of several species. We redefined the genus accordingly. As a result, five species are translocated to other genera and four are considered as <italic>incertae sedis</italic>. A new species discovered in China, <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus antennalis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., is described.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Redefinition of Allonychiurus Yoshii, 1995"><title>Redefinition of Allonychiurus Yoshii, 1995</title>
            <p><bold>Type-species: </bold>Onychiurus flavescens<bold> Kinoshita, 1916: p. 458</bold></p>
            <sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis</title>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Onychiurinae</tp:taxon-name> <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>. Postantennal organ oval, with numerous compound vesicles perpendicular to the long axis; antennal basis rather well delimited. Clubs of antenna III organ smooth or granulated. No invaginated apical bulb on Ant. IV. Labral chaetae formula 4/3,4,2; labium of AC type (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Fjellberg 1999</xref>); chaeta d0 present on head. No multiplication of dorsal pseudocelli; 3 (rarely 2) anterior pseudocelli on head, located inside the area antennalis; Th. I tergite usually with 1 or 2 pseudocelli per half-tergite (rarely absent). Abd. III sternite not subdivided into two subsegments; 4 (rarely 2, 3 or 5) pseudocelli per half-tergite on Abd. IV; 3 (rarely 2 or 4) pseudocelli per half-tergite on Abd. V (2–3 postero-internal and 0–1 postero-lateral). Abd. VI with 1 or 2 uneven axial chaetae (a0 or p0, or both); anal spines present. Tibiotarsus with 9 or 11 chaetae in the distal whorl, clavate tenent hairs absent. Furcal rudiment as finely granulated area with 4 posterior minute dental chaetae regularly arranged in 2 rows. Two or three rows of manubrial chaetae posteriorly to the 4 dental chaetae.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> is very similar to <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> Gervais, 1841 differing from it by a furcal area with 4 small posterior chaetae arranged in two rows versus arranged in one row. It is also the only difference between <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurini</tp:taxon-name>. The attempt to restrict the genus <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> to species with 11 distal chaetae on tibiotarsus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Sun et al. 2009</xref>) versus 9 in <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> cannot be retained on current available evidence, as discussed below.<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <sec sec-type="The problem of species assigned to Allonychiurus"><title>The problem of species assigned to Allonychiurus</title>
                <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Yoshii (1995)</xref> as a subgenus of <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> Gervais, 1841, to include species of the <italic>flavescens</italic>-group of <tp:taxon-name>Paronychiurus</tp:taxon-name> previously recognized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Weiner (1989)</xref>. This last author upgraded it to genus level in 1996, characterizing it mostly on the basis of its furcal area similar to that of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name> Bagnall, 1949, and its post-antennal organ with several compound vesicles. Recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Sun et al. (2009)</xref> restricted the definition of <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> to species with 11 chaetae in the distal whorl of tibiotarsus (a character erroneously stated as being drawn from the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Weiner 1996</xref> diagnosis); according to this conception, only four species (out of the 24 species listed at this time on the Janssens and Christiansen website at http://www.collembola.org) could be confirmed as <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> (<italic>flavescens</italic>, <italic>jongaksanensis</italic>, <italic>shanghaiensis</italic> and <italic>shinbugensis</italic>), in addition to <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus megasomus</tp:taxon-name> that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Sun et al. (2009)</xref> described in their paper. The authors also reallocated tentatively two species, <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus edinensis</tp:taxon-name> (Bagnall, 1935) and <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus subedinensis</tp:taxon-name> (Arbea &amp; Jordana, 1985) to the genus <tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> Weiner, 1996, a move formally confirmed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Kaprus’ and Tsalan (2009)</xref>; they stressed that 12 species did not match the genus as they defined it, nine because they had fewer than 11 chaetae in the distal whorl of tibiotarsus, two because they had smooth clubs in antenna III organ, and one because it had simple PAO vesicles. The remaining 6 species were not documented for distal tibiotarsal chaetae, and their status was considered as doubtful. In short, 80% of species assigned to <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> did not match the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Sun et al. (2009)</xref> definition of the genus before our study.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Thalassaphorurini versus Onychiurini"><title><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> versus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurini</tp:taxon-name></title>
                <p>A further concern is that furcal area chaetotaxy, i.e. the diagnostic character that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Pomorski (1998)</xref> proposed to distinguish the tribes <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, where <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> is placed, and <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurini</tp:taxon-name>, is not documented in most of the 23 species assigned to <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by Bellinger et al. in 2010. These species could belong as well to a genus of <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurini</tp:taxon-name>, like <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name>. In this respect, a few <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> species described in the recent paper of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Pomorski, Furgoł and Christiansen (2009)</xref> have a furcal area similar to that of <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name>, but the authors do not formally discuss the important taxonomic implications of this finding. They nevertheless recognize that «Many of the features he (Pomorski) used to redefine the genus (<tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name>) are not given in many descriptions». A large number of species assigned to <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref> need therefore to be re-examined in detail, as it is not known if they match the modern diagnoses of these genera. In parallel, differences between both genera as well as between <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> have to be re-assessed.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="The chaetotaxy of tibiotarsus"><title>The chaetotaxy of tibiotarsus</title>
                <p>The use of the number of chaetae in the distal whorl of tibiotarsus as a diagnostic character to define <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> deserves further comments. This character is not mentioned in the published descriptions of <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Yoshii (1995)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Weiner (1996)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref> key out the genus as having “more than 7” chaetae in this whorl. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Sun et al. (2009)</xref> characterize <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> as having 11 chaetae in the distal whorl of tibiotarsus. Actually, only six species have these 11 chaetae including the type species of the genus, <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus flavescens</tp:taxon-name> (though it needs to be confirmed on type locality specimens) and the new species <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus antennalis</tp:taxon-name> described here. Among the species listed as <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> in the web site of Janssens and Christiansen at this time, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Sun et al. (2009)</xref> recognized 9 species with less than 11 distal tibiotarsal chaetae (easily seen on original drawings of <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mediasetus</tp:taxon-name> (Lee, 1974), and <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus pseudocellitriadis</tp:taxon-name> (Lee, 1974), less obvious for other species). Other morphological characters are very similar between 9- and 11-chaetae species. In order to avoid the splitting of <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> in weakly defined entities, and given our poor knowledge of other diagnostic characters (furcal area and antenna III organ) in several species, we define <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> as having 9 or 11 chaetae in the distal whorl of tibiotarsus. This is in line with the other large genus of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name>, i.e. <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name>, where distal tibiotarsal chaetae are 7 or 9 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Sun et al. 2010</xref>), suggesting that this character may have lower taxonomical value in some genera than recently thought.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Taxonomical approach"><title>Taxonomical approach</title>
                <p>In this contribution and as a first step, we address the taxonomic problems raised above in three ways. First, in order to accommodate several species that would otherwise necessitate the creation of new poorly defined genera, we extended the diagnosis of <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Sun et al. (2009)</xref> to include species with sensory clubs of antenna III organ smooth or granulated (<italic>versus</italic> only granulated), and species with 9 or 11 distal chaetae on tibiotarsus (<italic>versus</italic> only 11). This new definition is compatible with the characters of <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> extracted from the key of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>. Second, we remove from the <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> list of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref> nine species that do not match diagnostic characters of <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name>: four are considered <italic>incertae sedis</italic>, and five are reallocated to other genera. Third, we provisionally keep in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> several insufficiently described species listed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref> that do not conflict with the definition of the genus, but could belong as well to other genera like <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> or <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name> Weiner, 1996; their generic assignment will have to be checked from fresh material.<!--PageBreak--></p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Critical checklist of the world species of Allonychiurus Yoshii, 1995"><title>Critical checklist of the world species of Allonychiurus Yoshii, 1995</title>
            <p>In the checklist given below, an asterisk (*) indicates that species assignment requires confirmation.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus flavescens</tp:taxon-name> (Kinoshita, 1916) (type species of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by original designation). Originally described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from Japan, later found in Korean caves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Yosii and Lee 1963</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Yosii 1966</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Weiner 1989</xref>) and largely distributed across USA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Muzzio 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Christiansen and Bellinger 1998</xref>). The different populations of Eastern Asia might however represent closely related geographic species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Weiner 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Yoshii 1995</xref>). Those of USA exhibit geographical variability according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Christiansen and Bellinger (1998)</xref>, at a level unusual in other <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> species, and would deserve closer examination.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus donjiensis</tp:taxon-name> (Lee &amp; Kim, 1994)*. Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from South Korea, later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Babenko (2007</xref>, following the tentative key of <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurinae</tp:taxon-name> on <italic>www.collembola.org</italic>). Morphological similarity with <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name> (Thibaud &amp; Lee, 1994) was stressed in the original description. Smooth sensory clubs of third antennal segment and four protecting papillae in the sense organ of third antennal segment are shared by the two species. Ecology (coastal habitats) and distribution are also similar. A redescription of the species would probably result in its reallocation to <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus hangchowensis</tp:taxon-name> (Stach, 1964). Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from China (Zhejiang: Hangzhou), later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus indicus</tp:taxon-name> (Choudhuri &amp; Roy, 1965)*. Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from India (West Bengale), later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus jindoensis</tp:taxon-name> (Lee &amp; Kim, 1994)*. Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from South Korea, later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Babenko (2007</xref>, following the tentative key of <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurinae</tp:taxon-name> on <italic>www.collembola.org</italic>). Remarks regarding the species affinities of <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus donjiensis</tp:taxon-name> with <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name> apply here.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus jongaksanensis</tp:taxon-name> (Weiner, 1989). Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Paronychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from North Korea, later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Weiner (1996)</xref>.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus kimi</tp:taxon-name> (Lee, 1973). Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from South Korea, reported from North Korea by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Weiner (1989)</xref>, later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Yoshii (1995)</xref>.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mediasetus</tp:taxon-name> (Lee, 1974). Described as <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus mediaseta</tp:taxon-name> from South Korea, reported from North Korea by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Weiner (1989)</xref>, later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> as <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mediaseta</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Weiner (1996)</xref>.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus megasomus</tp:taxon-name> Sun, Yan &amp; Chen, 2009. Described from China (Nanjing).</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus pamirensis</tp:taxon-name> (Martynova, 1975)*. Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from Tajikistan at high altitude (East Pamir), later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>.</p>
            <p><!--PageBreak--><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus pseudocellitriadis</tp:taxon-name> (Lee, 1974). Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from South Korea, later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Weiner (1996)</xref>.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus shanghaiensis</tp:taxon-name> (Rusek, 1971)*. Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from China (Shanghai), later placed in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Sun et al. (2009)</xref>.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus shinbugensis</tp:taxon-name> (Lee, 1974). Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from South Korea, reported from North Korea by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Weiner (1989)</xref>, later placed in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Weiner (1996)</xref>.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus tianshanicus</tp:taxon-name> (Martynova, 1971)*. Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from Kyrgyzstan at high altitude, later placed in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>.</p>
            <sec sec-type="Incertae sedis"><title>Incertae sedis</title>
                <p>Four of the species currently placed in the genus<italic> Allonychiurus</italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>are very insufficiently described or exhibit characters that are not those of the genus. They are considered here as <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> <italic>incertae sedis</italic>.</p>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus caprariae</tp:taxon-name> (Dallai, 1969). Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> , later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>. Only known from the type locality (Capraia Island in Italy). For its antennal basis not differentiated and the presence of 4+4 anterior pseudocelli on head, this species departs from <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus michelbacheri</tp:taxon-name> (Bagnall, 1948). Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiuroides</tp:taxon-name> Bagnall, 1948from the USA, later placed in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>. In the original description, considered to be closely related to <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus edinensis</tp:taxon-name> Bagnall, 1935 (type of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> Weiner, 1996).</p>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus sensitivus</tp:taxon-name> (Handschin, 1928). Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from Bulgaria<italic></italic> , later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>.</p>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus spinosus</tp:taxon-name> (Bagnall, 1949). Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiuroides</tp:taxon-name> from Ireland<italic></italic> , later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>. The ‘dorsal spines’ of the abdomen mentioned in the original description are likely to be thickened S-chaetae. The “exceptionally long” lateral chaetae on head and body remind a first instar chaetotaxy.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Species removed from Allonychiurus"><title>Species removed from Allonychiurus</title>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura sensilata</tp:taxon-name> (Thibaud &amp; Massoud, 1979), comb. n.</p>
                <p>This species was originally described from Lesser Antilles (Central America) in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Protaphorura</tp:taxon-name> and later transferred to <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>. PAO with simple vesicles undoubtedly places this species in <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name> Bagnall, 1949 according to original description, to observation of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Sun et al. (2009)</xref> and to re-examination of type specimens.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus borensis</tp:taxon-name> (Beruete, Arbea &amp; Jordana, 1994), comb. n.</p>
                <p>Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from Spanish Pyrenees, later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>. It rather belongs to <tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name> Bagnall, 1949 <italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Weiner (1996)</xref>, as indicated by the number of pso on Abd. IV and V (5–7 and 5–6 respectively in <tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name> versus a lower number in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name>). It was correctly placed in the “<tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name>” <italic>minutus</italic> species-group (equivalent to <tp:taxon-name>Micronychiurus</tp:taxon-name>) in the original description.</p>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus vandeli</tp:taxon-name> (Cassagnau, 1960), comb. n.</p>
                <p>Described in the genus<italic> Onychiurus</italic> from the French Pyrenees at high altitude, later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>. We have checked Cassagnau’s type specimens in the Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle of Paris. Because of the absence of d0 on head and the subdivision of Abd. III sternite into two subsegments, the species should be assigned to <tp:taxon-name>Spinonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> as redefined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Kaprus’ and Tsalan (2009)</xref>.</p>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus foliatus</tp:taxon-name> (Rusek, 1967). Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from China (Shanghai), reallocated to <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Weiner (1996)</xref>, later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bellinger et al. (2010)</xref>. See discussion about the validity of <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name> at <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus mariangeae</tp:taxon-name> (Thibaud &amp; Lee, 1994). Described in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> from South Korea, given as type species of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name> Weiner, 1996, later placed in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Babenko (2007</xref>, following the tentative key of <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurinae</tp:taxon-name> on <italic>www.collembola.org</italic>), cited again as <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name> from Santo island (Vanuatu) by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Thibaud (2009)</xref>. The proposed synonymy of <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> has never been documented in the literature, and is not accepted here, after re-examination of the type specimens from the Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle of Paris. The key difference between <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Weiner (1996)</xref> is the presence of 2+2 <italic>versus</italic> l+1 pseudocelli on first thoracic tergite. The same character is supposed to separate two other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorurini</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Jailolaphorura</tp:taxon-name> Yosii &amp; Suhardjono, 1992 and <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name> Bagnall, 1949), but was not considered of generic value by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Sun Xin et al. (2010)</xref>, as typical and closely related species of <tp:taxon-name>Thalassaphorura</tp:taxon-name> may have either 1+1 or 2+2 on this tergite. In the same way, we did not retained this character as discriminant for <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name> . However, <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name> is maintained here on the basis of its single row of manubrial chaetae posterior to dental chaetae (several in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Weiner 1996</xref> and comm. pers.), and the presence of characteristic, thickened chaetae on the male genital plate that are not recorded in <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> species. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Pomorski (1998)</xref> <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name> is also closely related to <tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> Pomorski, 1996 from which is differs by modified chaetae of male restricted to the genital plate and position of dorso-median pseudoscelli on abdomen IV and V tergites; we confirm also the difference suspected by Pomorski in number of distal chaetae of tibiotarsi (11 in <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name>, 7 in <tp:taxon-name>Tantulonychiurus</tp:taxon-name>). Arrangement of chaetae on and around furcal area (but not their morphology) is identical between the two genera.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Note on species ecology and distribution"><title>Note on species ecology and distribution</title>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> occurs in a wide range of habitats. Most described species live in soil and litter of lowland areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Weiner 1989</xref>). The type species of the genus (<tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus flavescens</tp:taxon-name>) has been found in caves in Korea, but is described from soil in Japan. The identity of the Korean specimens and the original specimens from Japan may be questioned given the diversity of the genus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Yoshii 1995</xref>). No other location in cave habitats is mentioned in the literature for <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name>, in contrast to <tp:taxon-name>Onychiurus</tp:taxon-name> which is highly diversified in caves. Two species (<tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus pamirensis</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus tianshanicus</tp:taxon-name>) live at high altitude in central Asia. Two others (<tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus donjiensis</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus jindoensis</tp:taxon-name> from Korea) are coastal halophilous species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Lee and Kim 1994</xref>); their generic assignation needs however confirmation, as this ecology and several morphological characters rather points to <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name> from the same habitat and same region.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Abbreviations and vocabulary used"><title>Abbreviations and vocabulary used</title>
            <sec sec-type="Material"><title>Material.</title>
                <p> The codes between brackets are field codes of the samples which contained the specimens, for instance (C9581).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Material deposit"><title>Material deposit.</title>
                <p> Nanjing University (China)—NJU, Museum national d’Histoire naturelle de Paris (France)—MNHN.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Morphology"><title>Morphology.</title>
                <p> Labial papillae types are named after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Fjellberg (1999)</xref>. Labium areas and chaetal nomenclature follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Massoud (1967)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">D’Haese (2003)</xref>. Chaetae on anal valves are named after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Yoshii (1996)</xref>.</p>
                <p><bold>Ant</bold> antennal segments, <bold>AIIIO</bold> Sensory organ of third antennal segment, <bold>PAO</bold> postantennal organ, <bold>Th</bold> thoracic segments, <bold>Abd</bold> abdominal segments, <bold>p-chaeta</bold> chaeta of row p on head, <bold>Sp</bold> posterior S-chaeta (on Abd. V or on head), <bold>ms</bold> S-microchaeta (microsensillum auct.), <bold>pso</bold> pseudocelli, <bold>a-pso</bold> postero-internal pso on head, <bold>psp</bold> pseudopore, <bold>AS</bold> anal spines, <bold>x</bold> axial psp of Abd. IV.</p>
                <p>The uneven axial chaeta m0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Sun et al. 2010</xref>) of Abd. VI tergite is named here p0 in agreement with the literature.</p>
                <p>Labral chaetae formula is the number of chaetae from prelabrals to distal row of labrum; for instance: 4/342.</p>
                <p>Pseudocellar and pseudopore formulae are the number of pseudocelli and pseudopores by half-tergite (dorsally) or half-sternite (ventrally) as follows: head anterior, head posterior/Th. I, Th. II, Th. III/Abd. I, Abd. II, Abd. III, Abd. IV, Abd. V (for instance: 32/022/33343).</p>
                <p>S-chaetae formula is the number of S-chaetae by half-tergite from head to Abd. VI (for instance: 11/012/222120).</p>
                <p>Formula of tibiotarsal chaetotaxy: total number of chaetae (number of chaetae in the distal whorl (A+T), number of chaetae in the proximal whorl B, number of basal chaetae); for instance: 21 (11, 8, 2).<!--PageBreak--></p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics"><title>Systematics</title>
            <p><bold><tp:taxon-name>Onychiuridae</tp:taxon-name> Börner, 1913</bold></p>
            <p><bold><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> Yoshii, 1995</bold></p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">antennalis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3F37A29C-FD87-45DD-94AC-C73FCFCF6A7C</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1.</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material:</title>
                    <p>Holotype female, 3 female paratypes. China: Jiangsu Province: Nanjing: Zijinshan: 10.iv.2009, litter, Berlese extraction, Zhang Feng et al. leg. (C9581). –ibid: Nanjing: Baima Park: 14 paratypes (2 males, 3 females and 9 juveniles) on slides, 13.v. 2007, litter, Berlese extraction, Chen Jian-xiu et al. leg. (C9544).</p>
                    <p>Holotype and 13 paratypes on slides are deposited in the Department of Biological Science and Technology of NJU, 4 paratypes on slides in MNHN.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis:</title>
                    <p> pso formula as 32/133/33343 dorsally, 11/000/01000 ventrally; subcoxa 1 of legs I, II and III with 1, 1 and 1 pso respectively; parapseudocelli (psx) absent; presence of small, finely granulated, apical swelling at the apex of Ant. IV; Th. II and III each with 3 dorsal chaetae on both side of axial line; tibiotarsus with 11 chaetae in the distal whorl, no clavate tenent hair; ventral tube with 6+6 distal chaetae, without anterior or basal chaetae.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description:</title>
                    <p>Body length: 1.3–1.7 mm (females), 1.0 mm (males). Body shape cylindrical, Abd. III–IV more or less broadened. Body colour white in alcohol.</p>
                    <p>Pseudocellar formulae as 32/133/33343 dorsally, 11/000/01000 ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, B</xref>), subcoxa 1 of legs I, II and III with 1, 1 and 1 pso respectively. Parapseudocelli absent. Pseudopore formulae as 00/011/11110 dorsally, 00/111/000x0 ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, B</xref>).</p>
                    <p>S-chaetae formula as 11/012/222120 dorsally. Sp present on head. S-microchaetae tiny and blunt, present on Th. II and III dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Head. Antennae short and distinctly segmented, as long as head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Length ratio of antennal segments I: II: III: IV = 1: 1.8–2: 1.8–2: 3.8–4.0. Ant. I with 9–10 chaetae. Ant. II with 14–15 chaetae. Ant. III sensory organ composed of 5 papillae, 5 guard chaetae, 2 small rods and 2 weakly granulated sensory clubs, both morel-like; lateral ms just posterior to sensory organ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Ant. IV subapical organite rod-like; basolateral ms at about 2/5 length from base; presence of a small, finely granulated (probably only primary granulation), flat apical swelling at the apex of antenna (possibly remnant of apical bulb fused to the apex) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>); invaginated apical bulb absent. Antennal base with distinct granulation. PAO composed of 18–22 compound vesicles arranged in 2 rows along axis of organ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Dorsal cephalic chaeta d0 present. 4+4 p-chaetae between posterior a-pso on head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Mandible with strong molar plate and 4 apical teeth. Maxilla bearing 3 teeth and 6 lamellae. Maxillary palp simple with 1 basal chaeta and 2 sublobal hairs. Labral chaetae formula 4/342. Labium with 6 proximal, 4 basomedian (E, F, G, and f) and 6 basolateral (a, b, c, d, e, e’) chaetae; <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->labial papillae of AC type, papillae A–E respectively with 1, 3, 0, 3 and 3 guard chaetae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>). Postlabial chaetae 4+4 along ventral groove (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Body chaetotaxy. Ordinary chaetae differentiated in meso- and macro-chaetae, ratio Sp: m1: p1 on Abd. V = 1: 0.6: 1.1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Th. I with 7+7 chaetae dorsally. Three chaetae on both side of axial line and no uneven axial chaetae from Th. II to Abd. III tergites. Abd. IV tergite with two uneven axial chaetae (m0 and p0 ), Abd. V tergite with one uneven axial chaeta (m0), Abd. VI with two uneven axial chaetae (a0 and p0) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Th. I, II and III sternites with 0+0, 1+1 and 1+1 chaetae respectively.</p>
                    <p>Appendages. Subcoxa 1 of legs I, II and III with 4, 4 and 4 chaetae, subcoxa 2 with 1, 4 and 4 chaetae, respectively. Tibiotarsi of legs I, II and III with 22 (11, 8, 3), 21 (11, 8, 2) and 21 (11, 8, 2) chaetae. Unguis without tooth. Unguiculus slender and pointed, 0.6 times as long as inner edge of unguis, with narrow inner basal lamella (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1G</xref>). Ventral tube with 6+6 distal chaetae, anterior and basal chaetae absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Furca reduced to a finely granulated area, with 4 short chaetae in two rows posterior to furcal rudiment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1H</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Male genital plate with 30 circumgenital and 8 genital chaetae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>); female genital plate with 16–18 anterior and 2 genital chaetae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>). No modified chaetae ventrally in males. Anal valves with numerous acuminate chaetae; each lateral valve with chaetae a0 and 2 a1; upper (posterior) valve with chaetae a0, 2 b1, 2 b2, c0, 2 c1, 2 c2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>). Anal spines set on distinct papillae, 0.6 times as long as inner edge of leg III unguis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2E</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus antennalis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <bold>A</bold> dorsal side of body with chaetotaxy, S-chaetae, pso and psp <bold>B</bold> ventral side of Abd. II–VI <bold>C</bold> organ of Ant. III <bold>D</bold> dorsal side of left Ant. IV <bold>E</bold> labium (p, proximal group of chaetae of labial palp) <bold>F</bold> ventral side of head <bold>G</bold> distal part of leg III <bold>H</bold> furcal area. Scales: 0.1 mm (A, B &amp; F), 0.01 mm (C–E &amp; G–H).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-078-000-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus antennalis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <bold>A</bold> ventral tube, lateral side <bold>B</bold> male genital plate <bold>C</bold> female genital plate <bold>D</bold> anal valves <bold>E</bold> anal spine. Scales: 0.1 mm (D), 0.01 mm (A–C &amp; E).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-078-000-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Derivatio nominis"><title>Derivatio nominis.</title>
                    <p>Named for its peculiar antennal morphology.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Ecology"><title>Ecology.</title>
                    <p>In broadleaved litter, in a recreational park in town, and at the forested foot of a hill close to the town, altitude 10 to 50 m a.s.l.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p> Bisexual species. <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus antennalis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. can be easily recognized by the presence of its apical swelling on Ant. IV, not reported in other species of the genus. It has the same dorsal pseudocellar formula (32/133/33343) as <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus shinbugensis</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus megasomus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mediasetus</tp:taxon-name>. Diagnostic characters are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Table 1.</label>
                        <caption><p>Comparison of the four species of <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus</tp:taxon-name> with a dorsal pseudocellar formula of 32/133/33343.</p></caption>
                        <table>
            		
                            <tbody>
										
                                <tr>
											
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
											
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus antennalis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</th>
											
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mediasetus</tp:taxon-name> (Lee, 1974)</th>
											
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus megasomu</tp:taxon-name>s Sun et al., 2009</th>
											
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus shinbugensis</tp:taxon-name> (Lee, 1974)</th>
										
                                </tr>
										
                                <tr>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ant. IV apical swelling</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">present</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">not mentioned</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">absent</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">not mentioned</td>
										
                                </tr>
										
                                <tr>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral pso formula</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/000/01000</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/000/01110</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/000/01110</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/000/01010</td>
										
                                </tr>
										
                                <tr>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inner basal lamella of unguiculus</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">present</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">present</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">absent</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">present</td>
										
                                </tr>
										
                                <tr>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of chaetae on ventral tube</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6+6</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8+8</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8+8</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8+8</td>
										
                                </tr>
										
                                <tr>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of chaetae on Th. I tergite</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7+7</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9+9</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-8+7-8</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7+7</td>
										
                                </tr>
										
                                <tr>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of p-chaetae between posterior a-pso on head </td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4+4</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4+4</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4+4</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+3</td>
										
                                </tr>
										
                                <tr>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of axial chaetae on Th. II and III tergites</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+3</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4+4</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4+4</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4+4</td>
										
                                </tr>
										
                                <tr>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uneven axial chaetae on Abd. IV</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">m0 and p0</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p0</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">m0 and p0</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">m0 and p0</td>
										
                                </tr>
										
                                <tr>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum length (mm)</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
											
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
										
                                </tr>
            		
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Key to world species of Allonychiurus Yoshii, 1995"><title>Key to world species of Allonychiurus Yoshii, 1995</title>
            <p>Note. Some forms of <tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus flavescens</tp:taxon-name> from USA may lack pso on Th. I or are polymorphic (Christiansen and Bellinger, 1998). In the absence of more detailed information regarding other characters, they are not included in this key.</p>
            <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIIIO with 4 papillae, 2+2 or 3+3 pso on Abd IV</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIIIO with 5 papillae, more than 3+3 pso on Abd IV</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(1)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal pso formula 22/222/22222 after original description</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus donjiensis</tp:taxon-name>(Lee &amp; Kim)(South Korea)</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal pso formula 32/233/33333</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus jindoensis</tp:taxon-name> (Lee &amp; Kim) (South Korea)</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(1)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th. I tergite with 2+2 pso</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th. I tergite with 1+1 pso or without pso</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(3)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th. I tergite with 12+12 chaetae, Abd. I tergite with 4+4 pso, dorsal pso formula 33/233/4444-54</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus pamirensis</tp:taxon-name>(Martynova) (Russia)</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th. I tergite with 8+8 chaetae, Abd. I tergite with 3+3 pso, dorsal pso formula 32/233/34454 after original figure (given as 32/233/34445 in original description), ventral pso formula 1/000/00010, ventral tube with 8+8 distal chaetae</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus tianshanicus</tp:taxon-name> (Martynova) (Russia)</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(3)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th. I tergite without pso, dorsal pso formula 32/022/33343, ventral pso formula 11/000/00000, 4+4 p-chaetae between posterior a-pso on head, Th. I tergite with 8+8 chaetae, subcoxa 1 of legs I, II and III with 2, 2 and 2 pso respectively, ventral tube with 8+8 distal chaetae</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus pseudocellitriadis</tp:taxon-name> (Lee) (South Korea)</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th. I tergite with 1+1 pso</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6(5)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th. II and III each with 3+3 pso dorsally; dorsal pso formula 32/133/33343</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of pso on Th. II and III not as above</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7(6)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral pso formula 11/000/01110, 4+4 p-chaetae between posterior a-pso on head</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral pso formula not as above</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8(7)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal whorl of tibiotarsi with 9 chaetae (interpretation of original drawing), Th. I tergite with 9+9 chaetae, unguiculus with basal lamella, Abd. IV tergite with one uneven axial chaeta (p0) dorsally</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus mediasetus</tp:taxon-name> (Lee) (South and North Korea)</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal whorl of tibiotarsi with 11 chaetae, Th. I tergite with 7-8+7-8 chaetae, unguiculus without basal lamella, Abd. IV tergite with two uneven axial chaetae (m0 and p0) dorsally</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus megasomus</tp:taxon-name> Sun, Yan &amp; Chen (China)</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(7)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral pso formula 10/000/01010, Ant. IV without apical swelling, 3+3 p-chaetae between posterior a-pso on head, 4+4 axial chaetae on Th. II and Th. III tergites, ventral tube with 8+8 distal chaetae</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus shinbugensis</tp:taxon-name> (Lee) (South and North Korea)<!--PageBreak--></td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral pso formula 11/000/01000, Ant. IV with a flat apical swelling, 4+4 p-chaetae between posterior a-pso on head, 3+3 axial chaetae on Th. II and Th. III tergites, ventral tube with 6+6 distal chaetae</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus antennalis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (China)</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(6)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th. II and III with 2+2 and 2+2 pso dorsally; dorsal pso formula 32/122/33343</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of pso on Th. II and III not as above</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11(10)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unguiculus with basal lamella, Th. I tergite with 9+9 chaetae, Abd. V tergite without uneven axial chaeta dorsally after original drawing</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus shanghaiensis</tp:taxon-name> (Rusek) (China)</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unguiculus without basal lamella, Th. I tergite with 8+8 chaetae, Abd. V tergite with one uneven axial chaeta (m0) dorsally</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12(11)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral pso formula 10/000/01000, Abd. IV tergite with two axial chaetae (m0 and p0) dorsally</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus kimi</tp:taxon-name> (Lee) (South and North Korea)</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral pso formula 10/000/01110, Abd. IV tergite with one axial chaeta (p0) dorsally</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A. flavescens (Kinoshita) (Japan, South Korea, USA)</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13(10)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal pso formula 32/123/33343, distal whorl of tibiotarsi with less than 11 chaetae (interpretation of original figure)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus hangchowensis</tp:taxon-name> (Stach) (China)</td>
                        </tr>
												
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal pso formula 32/132/33343, distal whorl of tibiotarsi with 11 chaetae, 4+4 p-chaetae between posterior a-pso on head, 3+3 axial chaetae on Th. II and Th. III tergites</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Allonychiurus jongaksanensis</tp:taxon-name> (Weiner) (North Korea)</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>To the China Scholarship Council (CSC) who gave the grant to the first author, to the Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle of Paris who supported the laboratory work, to the Ministry of Science and Technology of the People’s Republic of China (2006FY120100) who supported the study, to Wanda M. Weiner for invaluable help about the status of <tp:taxon-name>Thibaudichiurus</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Babenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Collembolan fauna of the Turukhansk Territory.</article-title> <source>Russian Entomological Journal</source> <volume>16</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>361</fpage>-<lpage>383</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellinger</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source> Checklist of the Collembola of the World</source>. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.collembola.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.collembola.org</ext-link> [accessed on August, 2010]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellinger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<source> The Collembola of North America North of the Rio Grande. 2nd ed. Part 2</source>, <publisher-name>Grinnell College</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>D’Haese</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Homology and morphology in Poduromorpha (Hexapoda, Collembola).</article-title> <source>European Journal of Entomology</source> <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>-<lpage>407</lpage>.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fjellberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> The Labial Palp in Collembola.</article-title> <source>Zoologischer Anzeiger</source> <volume>237</volume>:<fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>330</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaprus’</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsalan</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> New collembola species from the floodplain forests of the transcarpathian lowland (Ukraine).</article-title> <source>Vestnik zoologii</source> <volume>43</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>178</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Systematic study on some interstitial Collembola (Insecta) from sand dunes of Korean western coast.</article-title> <source>The Korean Journal of Systematic Zoology</source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>207</fpage>-<lpage>215</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Massoud</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> Monographie des Neanuridae, Collemboles Poduromorphes à pièces buccales modifiées</article-title>. <source>Biologie de l’Amérique Australe</source>, <publisher-name>CNRS</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <fpage>7</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Muzzio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> A preliminary annotated list of the Collembola of Santa Cruz County, California.</article-title> <source>The Canadian Entomologist</source> <volume>116</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pomorski</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<source> Onychiurinae of Poland (Collembola: Onychiuridae)</source>. Genus (Supplement): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>201</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pomorski</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furgoł</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Review of North American species of the genus Onychiurus (Collembola: Onychiuridae), with a description of four new species from caves.</article-title> <source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</source> <volume>102</volume> (<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1037</fpage>-<lpage>1049</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> A new species of the genus <italic>Allonychiurus</italic> from China (Collembola: Onychiuridae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2194</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deharveng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Six new species of <italic>Thalassaphorura</italic> (Collembola, Onychiuridae) from southern China, with a key to world species of the genus.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2627</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thibaud</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Les Collemboles (Collembola) Interstitiels des Sables Littoraux de l'île d'Espiritu Santo (Vanuatu).</article-title> <source>Zoosystema</source> <volume>31</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>499</fpage>-<lpage>505</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Onychiurinae (Onychiuridae, Collembola) of North Korea: species of the <italic>Paronychiurus flavescens</italic> (Kinoshita, 1916) group.</article-title> <source>Acta Zoologica Cracoviensia</source> <volume>32</volume> (<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Generic revision of Onychiurinae (Collembola: Onychiuridae) with a cladistic analysis.Annales de la Société Entomologique de France (N.S.</article-title> <source>)</source> <volume>32</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>163</fpage>-<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshii</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> Identity of some Japanese Collembola II. “<italic>Deuteraphorura</italic>” group of <italic>Onychiurus</italic>.</article-title> <source>Annals of the Speleological Research Institute of Japan (Iwaizumi)</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshii</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Identity of some Japanese Collembola IV. “<italic>Deuteraphorura</italic>” group of <italic>Onychiurus -</italic> continued.</article-title> <source>Annals of the Speleological Research Institute of Japan (Iwaizumi)</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yosii</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1966</year>)<article-title> Results of the speleological survey in South Korea 1966 IV. Cave Collembola of South Korea.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the National Science Museum</source> <volume>9</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>541</fpage>-<lpage>561</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yosii</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<article-title> On some Collembola of Korea, with notes on the genus <italic>Ptenothrix</italic>.</article-title> <source>Contribution from the Biological Laboratory Kyoto University</source> <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>