<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.124.1561</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Tungurahualini, a new tribe of Neotropical leafhoppers, with notes on the subfamily Mileewinae (Hemiptera, Cicadellidae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Dietrich</surname>
                        <given-names>C. H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:82FCB86C-54B4-456A-AE5E-D7847D271CB9</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label/>Illinois Natural History Survey, University of Illinois, 1816 S. Oak St., Champaign, IL 61820, USA
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: C. H. Dietrich (<email xlink:type="simple">dietrich@inhs.uiuc.edu</email>).
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Mick Webb</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>18</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>124</issue>
            <fpage>19</fpage>
            <lpage>39</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>17</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>7</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>C. H. Dietrich</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:80965FF6-6BF3-4C64-958B-DE17FDE89604</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new cicadellid tribe, <tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name>, is recognized to include <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kramer, and a related new genus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>gen. n.</bold>, based on six new species. The tribe is included in subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name>, the concept of which is further expanded to include tribes <tp:taxon-name>Makilingiini</tp:taxon-name> Baker, and <tp:taxon-name>Tinteromini</tp:taxon-name> Godoy and Webb, taxa previously treated as separate subfamilies. Keys to tribes of <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name> (sensu lato) and genera of <tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name> are provided. A new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala acuminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, is also described and keys to species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name></italic> are provided. The new tribe is presently recorded only from cloud forests in the northern Andes Mountains of South America.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Homoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Auchenorrhyncha</kwd>
                <kwd>morphology</kwd>
                <kwd>identification</kwd>
                <kwd>distribution</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The leafhopper subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name> comprises small to medium-sized, slender, usually darkly pigmented species that inhabit wet tropical forests worldwide. Most species appear to inhabit montane cloud forests where they occur on herbaceous vegetation in the understory. The group was established by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Evans (1947)</xref> as a tribe of <tp:taxon-name>Cicadellinae</tp:taxon-name> (as “<tp:taxon-name>Tettigellinae</tp:taxon-name>") based <!--PageBreak-->on the dorsal ocelli, narrow gena, and strongly convex frontoclypeus. Evans distinguished the tribe from other <tp:taxon-name>Cicadellinae</tp:taxon-name> based on the forewing “with a reduced clavus, a wide appendix and lacking vein M1+2 [= r-m1]." <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Young (1965)</xref> transferred the tribe from <tp:taxon-name>Cicadellinae</tp:taxon-name> to <tp:taxon-name>Typhlocybinae</tp:taxon-name> because he considered <tp:taxon-name>Mileewini</tp:taxon-name> to have “much more in common" with the latter subfamily, but did not mention particular characters that supported this new placement. In his subsequent comprehensive revision of world <tp:taxon-name>Cicadellinae</tp:taxon-name>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Young (1968)</xref> initially continued to treat <tp:taxon-name>Mileewini</tp:taxon-name> as a tribe of <tp:taxon-name>Typhlocybinae</tp:taxon-name> but later (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Young 1986</xref>) followed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Linnavuori and DeLong (1977)</xref> who elevated <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name> to status as a separate subfamily. This latter status was adopted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Dietrich (2005)</xref> in a key to cicadellid family-group taxa. Two other taxa most recently treated as separate subfamilies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Young 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Dietrich 2005</xref>), <tp:taxon-name>Makilingiinae</tp:taxon-name> Baker and <tp:taxon-name>Tinterominae</tp:taxon-name> Godoy &amp; Webb, inhabit similar wet tropical montane forest habitats and resemble <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name> in having dorsal ocelli, reduced forewing venation, and also the hind wing submarginal vein very close to the wing margin distally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Dietrich 2005</xref>). Both are currently known only based on their type genera: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Makilingia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Baker, previously known only from the Philippines but recently recorded from Thailand (Dietrich, unpublished); and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tinteromus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Godoy &amp; Webb, previously known only from Costa Rica, but recently recorded from Colombia and Peru (D. M. Takiya, unpublished).
            </p>
            <p>Phylogenetic analyses of both morphological and molecular data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Dietrich 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Dietrich et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2010</xref>) have consistently placed <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Makilingiinae</tp:taxon-name>, and <tp:taxon-name>Tinterominae</tp:taxon-name> in a well-supported clade also comprising subfamilies <tp:taxon-name>Evacanthinae</tp:taxon-name> (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Dietrich 2004</xref>), <tp:taxon-name>Cicadellinae</tp:taxon-name> (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Young 1968</xref>), <tp:taxon-name>Signoretiinae</tp:taxon-name> (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Dietrich 2005</xref>), and <tp:taxon-name>Typhlocybinae</tp:taxon-name> but have not adequately resolved the relationships among major lineages within this clade. However, because the first three mentioned taxa share a unique combination of morphological traits (see below), they may represent a monophyletic group. Thus, they are here treated as tribes of a single subfamily, <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name> (sensu lato).
            </p>
            <p>In a recent taxonomic review and morphology-based phylogenetic analysis of <tp:taxon-name>Evacanthinae</tp:taxon-name> sensu lato (including tribes <tp:taxon-name>Balbillini</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Evacanthini</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Nirvanini</tp:taxon-name>, and <tp:taxon-name>Pagaroniini</tp:taxon-name>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Dietrich (2004)</xref> excluded the enigmatic Andean genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kramer from that subfamily, placing it in <tp:taxon-name>Cicadellinae</tp:taxon-name> based on the structure of the ovipositor. Further morphological study of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic> and several South American species representing a new genus (described below), suggests that these two genera are most closely related to <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name>. The unique features uniting these two genera and their lack of apparent close relationship to other known leafhoppers support their placement in a new tribe, described below.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
            <title>Methods</title>
            <p>Morphological terminology follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Oman (1949)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Kramer (1950)</xref> except that groups of macrosetae on the legs are named using the system of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Rakitov (1998)</xref> and terminology for nymphs follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Dmitriev (2002)</xref>. Setal rows on the femur and tibia are referred to according to their position, assuming that the leg is fully extended perpendi<!--PageBreak-->cular to the sagittal plane of the body, as follows: AD=anterodorsal; AM=anteromedial; AV=anteroventral, PD=posterodorsal; and PV=posteroventral. Individual setae are numbered sequentially, beginning with the most distal. Numerical formulae are used to indicate the numbers of setae on the pro- and mesothoracic tibiae and the metathoracic femur. For tibiae the formula given is AD+PD; for the femur, the formula follows standard practice in which, for example, 2+2+1 means that a distal pair, a penultimate pair, and a single antepenultimate seta are present. Measurements are given in millimeters for males and females, respectively; body length is measured from the apex of the head to the apex of the forewing in repose. Digital photographs were taken using a Q-Imaging Micropublisher digital camera mounted on a stereo or compound microscope.
            </p>
            <p>Specimens examined are deposited in the following institutions: Humboldt Institute, Villa Leyva, Colombia (HIC); Illinois Natural History Survey (INHS); North <tp:taxon-name>Carolina</tp:taxon-name> State University, Raleigh (NCSU); and Universidad de San Marcos, Lima, Peru (USML).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Subfamily</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subfamily">Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">htp://species-id.net/wiki/Mileewinae</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name><comment> Evans, 1947</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Makilingiinae</tp:taxon-name><comment> Evans, 1947, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Tinterominae</tp:taxon-name><comment> Godoy &amp; Webb, 1994, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Redescription">
                    <title>Redescription.</title>
                    <p>Head with lorum extended little or no farther dorsad than clypeal suture; gena partially or entirely concealing triangular proepisternum; anteclypeus strongly convex, tapered distally; frontoclypeus without median longitudinal carina; ocelli on crown anteromesad of eyes, well separated from anterior margin; crown glabrous or punctate, without oblique lateral submarginal carinae; antennal base near anterodorsal corner of eye. Forewing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 19, 21, 23, 25, 27, 29</xref>) with crossvein s (= “r" of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Evans 1947</xref>) absent (outer anteapical cell absent); inner apical cell elongate, more or less parallel-sided, extended to apical margin. Hind wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 20, 22, 24, 26, 28, 30</xref>) with submarginal vein very close to or coincident with edge of wing along apical and costal margins; R2+3 complete. Front femur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 33, 34</xref>) row AV without enlarged basal setae; hind femoral setal formula 2+1+1; hind tarsomere I pecten with 4 or fewer setae, including 0–2 platellae. Male subgenital plates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 37–45</xref>) usually elongate, depressed basally, expanded medially or distally in lateral view (triangular in <tp:taxon-name>Makilingiini</tp:taxon-name>), macrosetae when present well separated from lateral margin and scattered or uniseriate; style apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 47</xref>) usually cheliform, apophysis usually with preapical tooth; connective Y- or T-shaped, usually with median anterior lobe. Female second valvulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 71, 75</xref>) with distal paired blades comprising 50% or more of entire length of ovipositor.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name>, as here redefined, are most readily distinguished from other <tp:taxon-name>Cicadellidae</tp:taxon-name> by the following combination of features: head with ocelli on crown distant from eyes and margin, frontoclypeus without median longitudinal carina; forewing with only two anteapical cells; hind wing submarginal vein very close to margin at wing apex; female second valvulae with paired distal blades occupying 50% or more of their length. They key to couplet 46 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Dietrich's (2005)</xref> key to tribes of <tp:taxon-name>Cicadellidae</tp:taxon-name>, which comprises the three previously recognized taxa included here as tribes. Comparative study of morphological characters indicates that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic>, previously placed in <tp:taxon-name>Nirvaninae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Kramer 1965</xref>), and a related new genus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, are not closely related to other nirvanines and are more closely allied to <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Dietrich 2004</xref>). <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name> previously included only the nominotypical tribe but is here redefined to include tribes <tp:taxon-name>Tinteromini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Makilingiini</tp:taxon-name> (both previously treated as separate subfamilies), as well as a new tribe, <tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name>, described below.
                    </p>
                    <p>The hind wing venation is very similar among the tribes here included in <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name>, although the extant Old World genera currently included in <tp:taxon-name>Mileewini</tp:taxon-name> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Mileewa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Distant, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ujna</tp:taxon-name></italic> Distant, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Processina</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yang, Deitz &amp; Li ) share a unique pattern in which vein R2+3 is complete but does not extend to the wing apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 22</xref>); thus in these three genera there appear to be only three closed apical cells reaching the wing apex instead of the usual four (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 26</xref>). Interestingly, this pattern does not occur in the New World mileewine genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Amahuaka</tp:taxon-name></italic> Melichar, or in the two genera of <tp:taxon-name>Mileewini</tp:taxon-name> described from Eocene Baltic amber (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Gebicki and Szwedo 2001</xref>), all of which have vein R2+3 extended to the wing apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 26</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Gebicki and Szwedo (2001)</xref> suggested that, based on the wing venation, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Orsalebra robusta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Young belongs in <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name>; however, species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Orsalebra</tp:taxon-name></italic> have the ocelli on the anterior margin of the crown and are similar to <tp:taxon-name>Alebrini</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Typhlocybinae</tp:taxon-name>) in other respects, so Young's (1952) original placement in <tp:taxon-name>Alebrini</tp:taxon-name> appears to be correct. As noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Takiya (2007)</xref>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vidanoana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Young, a genus endemic to Chile and currently placed in <tp:taxon-name>Cicadellini</tp:taxon-name> has hind wing venation similar to that of <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Young 1977</xref>). The placement of this genus needs to be re-evaluated through further comparative study beyond the scope of the present paper.
                    </p>
                    <p><bold>Key to tribes of <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name></bold>
                    </p>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head with margin of crown sharply carinate and encroaching onto eye laterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 13, 16</xref>); pronotum distinctly punctate; front femur with setae AM1 and AV1 small or absent (Phillippines, Thailand)
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Makilingiini</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head with margin of crown at most weakly carinate, not encroaching onto eye laterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 12, 17, 18</xref>); pronotum without distinct punctations or, if punctures present, then pronotum also strongly rugose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–3</xref>); front femur with one or more enlarged ventral setae at or near apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 33–34</xref>)
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body strongly depressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 11–12</xref>), rostrum not exceeding front trochanters, frontoclypeus with distinct transverse ridge visible as shelf in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 11–12</xref>); forewing crossvein r-m1 present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 27, 29</xref>); hind tarsus much<!--PageBreak--> less than half length of tibia, tarsomere I without platellae (pale, baloonlike setae), apical pecten bearing spiniform macrosetae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 35–36</xref>); female second valvulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 71, 75</xref>) with dorsal margin bearing numerous large teeth with smaller serrations between teeth (Neotropical region)
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body not depressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 16–18</xref>), rostrum extended well beyond front trochanters; frontoclypeus evenly convex or flat in profile without transverse ridge; forewing with or without crossvein r-m1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 21, 23</xref>); hind tarsus approximately half length of tibia or longer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 18</xref>), tarsomere I with apical pecten bearing one or more platellae; second valvulae with dorsal margin smooth or minutely serrate, without large teeth
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennae longer than body; forewing crossvein r-m1 present, appendix absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 23</xref>)
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Tinteromini</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennae shorter than body; forewing crossvein r-m1 absent, appendix well developed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 21, 25</xref>)
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Mileewini</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–18.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name>, scale bars = 1 mm <bold>1–10</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name>, dorsal habitus <bold>1</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala basilisca</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male from Colombia <bold>2</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala acuminata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male <bold>3</bold> same, female <bold>4</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa bifida</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male <bold>5</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa loca</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male <bold>6</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa longispina</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male <bold>7</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa ochrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male <bold>8</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa recurvata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male <bold>9</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male <bold>10</bold> same, 5th instar nymph <bold>11–12</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name>, lateral habitus <bold>11</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala acuminata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male <bold>12</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male <bold>13–18</bold> Other <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name> <bold>13</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Makilingia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., male from Thailand, dorsal habitus <bold>14</bold> same, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mileewa margheritae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male <bold>15</bold> same, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tinteromus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., male from Colombia (full length of antenna not shown) <bold>16</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Makilingia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., lateral habitus <bold>17</bold> same, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mileewa margheritae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>18</bold> same, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tinteromus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-124-019-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="tribe">Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E466750A-38A1-4798-A4E4-4E169D37F6E8</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">htp://species-id.net/wiki/Tungurahualini</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">trib. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type genus">
                    <title>Type genus.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kramer
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Medium-sized leafhoppers (~6–8 mm), body depressed, head produced, face horizontal in profile, antenna shorter than width of head, frontoclypeus with transverse carina forming distinct shelf in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 11–12</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">31–32</xref>); anteclypeus extended to or slightly beyond lower margin of gena; lorum with lateral margin not extended to lateral margin of gena; rostrum short, not surpassing front trochanters. Front femur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 33–34</xref>) with AM1 and AV1 enlarged, row AV with 0–1 preapical setae; intercalary row with 12 or more slender setae; hind tarsomere I without platellae, pecten with four tapered macrosetae. Forewing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 27, 29</xref>) vein R with three branches; two r-m crossveins present; appendix absent or very narrow; hind wing vein R2+3 complete, extended to wing apex. Male pygofer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 37</xref>) with well developed ventral appendage, dorsal appendage absent, several macrosetae present distally; anal tube usually with paired ventrolateral processes; valve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 38</xref>) short, transverse, broadly fused to pygofer; subgenital plate broadest near base in ventral view, expanded medially in lateral view, with numerous scattered stout submarginal setae; connective stem as long as or longer than arms; style (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 47–51</xref>) cheliform with preapical lobe greatly enlarged and preapical tooth distinct. Female first valvulae with dorsal sculpturing strigate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 70</xref>) or concatenate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 73</xref>); second valvulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 71, 74</xref>) with small serrations between larger teeth.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name> resemble other <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name> in having the ocelli on the crown distant from the margin, the frontoclypeus and clypellus strongly convex, the forewing with the inner apical cell elongate and parallel-sided, the hind femur with macrosetal formula 2+1+1, and the second valvulae with the toothed distal blades longer than the <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->basal fused section. They differ from other <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name> in having the head depressed with the face horizontal, the frontoclypeus with a transverse carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 31–32</xref>) forming a distinct shelf in profile, the first hind tarsomere pecten with spiniform setae (platellae absent), and the subgenital plate with numerous scattered macrosetae (see also Key).
                    </p>
                    <p>A previous cladistic analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Dietrich 2004</xref>) consistently grouped the two genera included in <tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name> together in a clade also comprising the single included rep<!--PageBreak-->resentative of <tp:taxon-name>Makilingiini</tp:taxon-name>. A more recent morphology-based analysis of the entire family <tp:taxon-name>Cicadellidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Dietrich et al. 2010</xref>) placed <tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name> within a paraphyletic assemblage, comprising the other tribes here included in <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name>, that gave rise to <tp:taxon-name>Cicadellinae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Typhlocybinae</tp:taxon-name>. More detailed analysis of this entire lineage will be needed to further elucidate the phylogenetic status of <tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name> and its included tribes.
                    </p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak--><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name> resemble <tp:taxon-name>Nirvanini</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Evacanthinae</tp:taxon-name>, sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Dietrich 2004</xref>) in having the body depressed with the head strongly produced and the face horizontal. The male genitalia also resemble those of <tp:taxon-name>Nirvanini</tp:taxon-name>, particularly the structure of the style (apex foot-shaped) and aedeagus (base with paired dorsal processes). However, unlike <tp:taxon-name>Nirvanini</tp:taxon-name> (and other <tp:taxon-name>Evacanthinae</tp:taxon-name>), the crown of the new tribe lacks a distinct marginal carina, the ocelli are distant from the margin, the face lacks a median longitudinal carina, crossvein r-m1 is present in the forewing, and the front femur lacks enlarged basal setae in row AV. The presence of spiniform setae rather than platellae at the apex of the first hind tarsomere is an unusual trait shared with some Oriental <tp:taxon-name>Evacanthini</tp:taxon-name>, but evacanthines differ in having the crown distinctly elevated mesad of the eyes, with marginal and submarginal carinae, and ocelli near the crown margin.
                    </p>
                    <p>Species of <tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name> are presently known only from cloud forests in the northern and central Andean regions of the New World tropics.</p>
                    <p><bold>Key to genera of <tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name></bold>
                    </p>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head and pronotum uniformly black dorsally; crown margin pentagonal in dorsal view</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kramer</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head and pronotum pale orange, white or green with distinct reddish orange markings; crown margin parabolic in dorsal view</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">htp://species-id.net/wiki/Tungurahuala</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Kramer</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name>
                        <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Kramer 1965</xref>: 68. Type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala basiliscus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kramer by original designation. New placement.</comment>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Redescription">
                    <title>Redescription.</title>
                    <p>Elongate, strongly depressed, leafhoppers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–3, 11</xref>). Coloration dark brown to black; face with dull yellow band extended from lora across base of clypellus and apex of clypeus. Crown unevenly convex, coarsely granulose and densely clothed with minute setae, pentagonal in dorsal view; marginal carina present apically, becoming obsolete posterolaterally; median longitudinal carina weakly delimited; ocelli on crown anterad of eyes, slightly closer to lateral margin than to midline; antennal ledge broad, depressed, coincident with lateral margin of crown; flagellum slightly shorter than crown width; mesal margin of eye entire; lateral frontal suture absent dorsad of antennal ledge; frontoclypeus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 31</xref>) rugulose medially with well developed muscle scars laterally, oblique anteroventral section separated from nearly horizontal posteroventral section by transverse ridge; transclypeal suture indistinct; anteclypeus tapered, weakly convex, apex wider than lorum; lorum well separated from ventral genal margin; gena angulately produced, largely concealing proepisternum. Pronotum depressed, rugulose and minutely setose, narrower than head, lateral margins strongly<!--PageBreak--> carinate, carina even with eye, margins subparallel in dorsal view; exposed part of mesonotum and scutellum together wider than long. Forewing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 27</xref>) opaque basally, gradually becoming translucent distally; veins raised and well delimited, with marginal setae; costal flange well developed basally; R three-branched (rarely with 1–2 supranumerary branches), branches not reflexed; crossvein s absent (outer anteapical cell open distally); two r-m and three m-cu crossveins present; inner apical cell narrow; appendix absent. Hind wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 28</xref>) with cell distad of r-m crossvein broadened distally. Prothoracic femur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 33</xref>) stout, AM1 and AV1 well developed, intercalary row with ~13 close-set preapical setae; tibia short, weakly expanded distally, dorsal rows with few indistinct, widely spaced setae, AV well developed, PV with few scattered setae. Mesothoracic femur longer and wider than prothoracic femur, compressed, AV and PV each with several irregular setae, tibial rows with numerous poorly differentiated setae. Metathoracic tibia row AV with setae evenly spaced from base to apex; tarsomere I with several scattered plantar setae. Male sternum III apodemes well developed; pygo<!--PageBreak-->fer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 37</xref>) short with scattered macrosetae dorsolaterally, with long, slender process densely clothed with minute spicules arising from ventrolateral margin and extending mesad into genital capsule, then dorsad; anal tube well sclerotized, broader than long in dorsal view, venter flat; valve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 38</xref>) short, straplike, narrowly fused to pygofer; plates triangular, depressed, extended well beyond posterior margin of pygofer, with lateral band and irregular submedial row of macrosetae, dorsolateral margin weakly sinuate in lateral view, base weakly constricted in ventral view; aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 46–52</xref>) in lateral view with shaft split into dorsal gonopore-bearing section and tapered ventral process; connective (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 47–51</xref>) trilobed basally; style with large preapical lobe and attenuated, hooked apex. Female sternite VII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 65</xref>) subtruncate, concealing base of ovipositor; first valvulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 69</xref>) slender, with dorsal and ventral preapical sculpturing irregularly strigate; second valvulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 71</xref>) with basal fused area short, distal blades large, dorsal margin ascending in straight line, then gradually descending toward apex, declivous portion with ~7 widely spaced conical teeth and intervening serrations, apical fourth serrate, without teeth; third valvulae without macrosetae. Nymph unknown.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Kramer (1965)</xref> described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic> based on a single male specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala basiliscus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kramer from Baños, Tungurahua, Ecuador, placing it in <tp:taxon-name>Nirvaninae</tp:taxon-name> but noting that it is “vastly different from any previously described" genus. Recent Malaise trap sampling in Colombia has yielded additional specimens of the type species and a new, closely related species, including the first known female specimen of the genus. The genus may be distinguished from its only known relative, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name></italic>,by the characters noted in the key.
                    </p>
                    <p><bold>Key to species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic> (males)</bold>
                    </p>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anal tube without distinct apical ventrolateral spines; aedeagal shaft (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 46, 48</xref>) broad in lateral view, ventral process with dorsolateral lobes
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala basilisca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kramer</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anal tube with pair of distinct apical ventrolateral spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 37</xref>); aedeagal shaft (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 50</xref>) narrow in lateral view, ventral process without dorsolateral lobes
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala acuminata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">basilisca</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">htp://species-id.net/wiki/Tungurahuala_basilisca</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Kramer</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">46–49</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala basiliscus</tp:taxon-name>
                        <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Kramer 1965</xref>: 68 [incorrect original spelling]</comment>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Redescription">
                    <title>Redescription.</title>
                    <p>Length male 7.6–7.9. Head (male) approximately ¼ length of forewing. Forewing dark brown to black. Male anal tube with apical ventrolateral spines very weakly developed or absent. Aedeagus with gonopore-bearing shaft in lateral view broad, apex obliquely truncate, posteroapical margin concave; ventral process with pair of micr<!--PageBreak-->otrichiate dorsolateral lobes, in ventral view abruptly expanded preapically, apex broadly bilobed, in lateral view with apex convergent toward shaft and with dorsal margin entire.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male: ECUADOR: Mt. Tungurahua, Baños, 2500m, August 20, 1937 (W. Clarke-Macintyre) [USNM]. Other material: 1 male, COLOMBIA, Cundinamarca, PNN Chingaza Charrascales, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">4°31'N, 73°45'W</named-content>, 2990m, Malaise, 4–18 October 2001 (L. Cifuentes), M.2551 [HIC]; 1 male, Cundinamarca, PNN Chingaza Alto de la Bandera, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">4°31'N, 73°45'W</named-content>, 3660m, Malaise, 30 March -12 April 2001 (L. Cifuentes), M.1585 [HIC]; 1 male, same data except 27 December 2001–11 January 2002 (E. Raigoso), M.3023 [INHS].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p>The specimens examined from Colombia are here considered conspecific with the holotype from Ecuador, although there is slight variation among specimens in size, coloration, and the shape of the aedeagus. Given the small number of specimens available, it seems prudent to consider these minor variations to be intra-specific, despite the considerable geographic disjunction among the known populations.</p>
                    <p>Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Kramer (1965)</xref> did not explicitly indicate the gender of the name <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic>, it is here interpreted as feminine due to its ending (ICZN Art. 30.2.4). Thus, Kramer's original spelling of the species name, which has a masculine ending, is incorrect and the spelling here emended to agree in gender with the genus name.
                    </p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 19–30.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Mileewinae</tp:taxon-name>, wings <bold>19–20</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Makilingia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. (Thailand), fore- and hind wing <bold>21–22</bold> same, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mileewa margheritae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>23–24</bold> same, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tinteromus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. (Colombia) <bold>25–26</bold> same, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Amahuaka</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. (Mexico) <bold>27–28</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala acuminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>29–30</bold> same, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-124-019-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 31–45.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name> <bold>31–32</bold> head, anteroventral view <bold>31</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala acuminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>32</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>33–34</bold> prothoracic femur, anterior view <bold>33</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala acuminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>34</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>35–36</bold> hind tarsomere I, ventral view <bold>35</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala acuminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>36</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>37</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala acuminata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, genital capsule, lateral view <bold>38</bold> same, valve and subgenital plates, ventral view <bold>39</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa bifida</tp:taxon-name></italic>, genital capsule, lateral view <bold>40</bold> same, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa loca</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>41</bold> same, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa longispina</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>42</bold> same, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa ochrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>43</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa ochrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic>, left subgenital plate, ventral view <bold>44</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa recurvata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, genital capsule, lateral view <bold>45</bold> same, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-124-019-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">acuminata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FD180D56-E0FC-4CCC-9C28-4F4C8FB090FE</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">htp://species-id.net/wiki/Tungurahuala_acuminata</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2, 3, 11</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">27, 28</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">31, 33, 35, 37, 38</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">50–52</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">65, 69–71</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Length male 7.5–7.6 mm, female 7.6 mm. Head (male) approximately 1/3 as long as forewing (female with head proportionately longer compared to forewing). Forewing dark brown with tan pigment along costal area, mostly tan in female. Male anal tube with apical ventrolateral spine well developed. Aedeagus with gonopore-bearing shaft slender, apex rounded; ventral process acuminate, without dorsolateral lobes, apex in ventral view narrower than shaft.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male: COLOMBIA, Boyacá, SFF Iguaque Lagunillas, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">5°25'N, 73°27'W</named-content>, 3380m, Malaise 2–18 May 2001 (P. Reina), M.1756. Paratypes: 1 male, same data except 28 June–19 July 2001, M.1966 [HIC]; 1 male, Boyacá, SFF Iguaque Qda. Carrizal, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">5°25'N, 73°27'W</named-content>, 3350m, Malaise 13 – 30 July 2000 (P. Reina), M.379; 1 male, same data except 21 January–9 February 2001; 1 male and 1 female, Boyacá, SFF Iguaque Cabaña Mamarramos, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">5°25'N, 73°27'W</named-content>, 2855m, Malaise 7–21 January 2001 (P. Reina), M.1252; 1 male, same data except 21 December 2000–7 January 2001, M.1072 [HIC, INHS].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The name refers to the acuminate ventral process of the aedeagus.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p>This species resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala basilisca</tp:taxon-name></italic> in overall structure, but the head is proportionately longer and the coloration of the forewing is lighter overall, although variable among specimens examined.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7A6B2217-9F1E-4D41-B680-BFD78F3FE553</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">htp://species-id.net/wiki/Ilyapa</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                    <title>Type species.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa longispina</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Medium sized, depressed leafhoppers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 4–10, 12</xref>). Coloration pale orange or green with red/orange markings dorsally; crown with pair of oblique red maculae mesad of ocelli, pronotum with semicircular orange macula anteriorly, face and thoracic sternites black, legs dark basally and pale distally, abdomen heavily marked with dark brown dorsally and with varying amounts of dark brown pigmentation ventrally. Crown depressed, finely granulose, without setae, weakly pentagonal in dorsal view, marginal and medial carinae absent; ocelli on crown anterad of eyes slightly closer to lateral margin than to midline; antennal ledge broadly depressed, coincident with crown margin; flagellum slightly shorter than crown width; mesal margin of eye emarginate; frontoclypeus granulose with oblique anterodorsal section separated from nearly horizontal posteroventral section by distinct transverse ridge; muscle scars distinct laterally; clypeal suture obsolete medially; anteclypeus convex, tapered, apex narrower than lorum; lorum well separated from ventral genal margin; gena weakly produced laterally, partially concealing proepisternum. Pronotum weakly convex with irregular transverse striations, lateral margins divergent posterad, slightly wider than head, strongly carinate, carina even with eye. Exposed part of mesonotum and scutellum wider than long. Forewing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 29</xref>) opaquely sclerotized except apical cells, veins distinct but without marginal setae; R three branched, crossvein s absent; two r-m and 3–4 m-cu crossveins present; apical cells 2 and 3 very short; inner apical cell relatively broad; appendix very narrow. Hind wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 30</xref>) with cell distad of r-m crossvein parallel-sided or narrowed distally. Prothoracic femur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 34</xref>) slender, AM1 large, located on ventral margin, AV1 well developed, row AV without preapical setae; intercalary row with ~17 slender, close-set setae; tibia 1+1, PV absent. Mesothoracic femur equal in length but wider than prothoracic femur; AV and PV with few widely separated setae, tibial row PD with apical seta, other rows with few irregularly spaced setae. Metathoracic femur macrosetal formula 2+1+1, rarely 2+1+1+1, tibia and tarsus as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Male with apodemes of sternite III well developed; pygofer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 39–45</xref>) short with scattered macrosetae dorsolaterally, with ventral process glabrous, slender, arising posteroventrally and curved posterodorsad; anal tube in dorsal view as long as broad, flat ventrally, with or without pair of ventrolateral processes distally; valve short, rectangular, narrowly fused to pygofer; plates depressed basally, expanded and slightly compressed distally with band of macrosetae extended from lateral margin of base posteriorly across middle of apex; aedeagal shaft (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 53–62</xref>) arcuate posteriorly, often asymmetrical, gonopore apical; connective trilobed anteriorly, stem broad and depressed; style sinuate with large, sparsely setose preapical lobe, apophysis acuminate with ventral preapical tooth. Female seventh sternite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 65–68</xref>) longer than sixth and concealing basal half of ovipositor in repose, posterior margin produced; first valvulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 72–73</xref>) slender, dorsal sculpturing concatenate, second valvulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 74</xref>) similar to those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic> but with dorsal teeth more numerous, prominent and closely spaced, and dorsum at base of blade evenly rounded rather than angulate.<!--PageBreak--> Fifth instar nymph (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 10</xref>) with overall form and chaetotaxy similar to that of adult except coloration pale greenish yellow with median dorsal longitudinal white stripe; crown with acrometope well delimited, longer than wide; metope well delimited; ocellar precursors well delimited and positioned as in adult on coryphe anteromesad of eyes, well separated from margin; face with distinct transverse shelf corresponding to epistomal suture (as in adult), cibarial muscle scars distinct; dorsum glabrous with scattered sparse, minute setae; enlarged setae absent; hind tarsomere I with three apical platellae.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The name <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name></italic> is based on that of the Inca god of thunder, lightning, and rain, but the gender is here considered feminine due to its ending.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p>This genus is closely related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic>, as indicated by the similarities in cephalic structure (ocelli distant from margin, frontoclypeus with transverse carina), forewing venation (crossvein s lacking), leg chaetotaxy (hind tarsomere I pecten with tapered macrosetae), and male genitalia (pygofer with recurved posteroventral process, style with strong preapical lobe). It differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the characters noted in the key.
                    </p>
                    <p>The genus is described based on six species from the Andean region of South America. The species inhabit cloud forests and have been collected by sweeping grasses and other herbaceous vegetation in the understory. They are readily distinguished by differences in coloration, head proportions, and the structure of the male genitalia.</p>
                    <p><bold>Key to species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (males)</bold>
                    </p>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aedeagal shaft (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 59–60</xref>) bilaterally symmetrical, compressed and broad in lateral view
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa ochrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aedeagal shaft strongly asymmetrical, elongate, slender and tubular</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 55–56</xref>) with depressed, apically truncate ventral process arising near base; gonopore-bearing shaft elongate, spinelike, evenly tapered distally, without process
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa loca</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aedeagus without basal process, shaft with one or more distal processes</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 58, 64</xref>) with distal process extended laterad at approximately right angle in ventral view
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aedeagus with distal process not extended laterad at right angle, either strongly recurved ventrad or more or less continuing in line with shaft</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal process of aedeagus bifid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 64</xref>)
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distal process of aedeagus unbranched (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 58</xref>)
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa longispina</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 61</xref>) with single distal process strongly recurved ventrad, apex branched; anal tube with several small, irregular ventrolateral teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 44</xref>)
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa recurvata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 53–54</xref>) with two distal processes more or less aligned with shaft, asymmetrically curved, one process with angulate projection near base; anal tube with pair of short triangular projections near base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 39</xref>)
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa bifida</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n.<!--PageBreak--></td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">bifida</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:26BD4DCA-8225-43E5-AD09-1D484CC59C40</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">htp://species-id.net/wiki/Ilyapa_bifida</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 4, 12</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">39</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">53, 54</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Length male 6.6–6.9 mm, female 7.0 mm. Crown pale orange-yellow, orange-red maculae broad, overlapping ocelli, anterior margin forming acute angle; pronotum and opaque areas of forewing bright green (mottled with yellow in specimens removed from ethanol), pronotum with semicircular macula distinct. Male pygofer processes extended mesad and curved dorsad but not or only slightly crossing midline; anal tube process short, triangular. Aedeagus asymmetrical, shaft tubular, in lateral view V-shaped basally, arched and sinuate distally, terminating in two slender, bladelike processes continuing in line with shaft but asymmetrically curved, one process with angulate projection near base. Female seventh sternite with posterior margin slightly produced, rounded medially. Fifth instar nymph pale olive green dorsally with broad white median longitidinal stripe extended entire length of body; venter white.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male: PERU, Pasco, Yanachaga-Chemillén N.P., Refugio El Cedro, 2420 m, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">10°33'07"S, 75°21'27"W</named-content>, 10 October 2002 (D. M. Takiya) PE07 [USML]. Paratypes: 1 male, same data except 12 October 2002 (R. Rakitov) [INHS].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The species name refers to the bifid apex of the aedeagus.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p>This species may be distinguished by its relatively long crown and the bifid apex of the aedeagus.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">loca</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8E950B3B-7F16-47E6-96F5-C5729EA156C0</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">htp://species-id.net/wiki/Ilyapa_loca</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 5</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">40</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">55–56</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Length male 6.1 mm. Coloration as described for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa bifida</tp:taxon-name></italic> except crown margin white, orange-red maculae broader, and pronotum almost entirely orange; apical margin of crown forming obtuse angle. Male pygofer processes short, broad, and digitiform; anal tube without processes. Aedeagus highly asymmetrical; gonopore-bearing shaft acuminate, extended to left posterodorsad and gradually curved mesad, apex without process; ventral process depressed, apex expanded, truncate, and even with style apices. Female unknown.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male, PERU, Chanchamayo, 25 July 1960 (Young and Ramirez) [NCSU].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The species name means “crazy" and refers to the bizarre, asymmetrical aedeagus.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p>This species may be distinguished by its relatively short crown and by the presence of a long, unpaired ventral process arising from the base of the aedeagal shaft.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">longispina</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:00015CA5-8E24-4357-A657-7B8D3B5F6638</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">htp://species-id.net/wiki/Ilyapa_longispina</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 6</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">41</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">57–58</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">67, 72–74</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Length male 5.9–6.2 mm; female 7.1–7.5 mm. Coloration as described for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa bifida</tp:taxon-name></italic> except crown margin mostly white; apical margin of crown forming approximately right angle. Male pygofer processes slender, crossing posteromedially; anal tube with pair of retrorse posterolateral spines; plate apex angulate mesally. Anal tube processes long with apices curved ventrad; pygofer processes shorter, not meeting medially; apical process of aedeagus more elongate, with minute preapical spine posteriorly. Female seventh sternite with posterior margin trilobed with median lobe acute and larger than lateral lobes.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male: PERU, Chanchamayo, 25 July 1960 (Salazar and Ramirez) [NCSU]. Paratypes: 1 male, same locality, 22 July 1960 (C. Ramirez) [INHS]; 3 females, same locality except 21 and 25 July 1960 [NCSU, INHS]. Other material: 3 males, PERU, Ucayali, 8 km E Abra La Divisoria, 1250 m, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">9°9'57"S, 75°48'11"W</named-content>, 25 October 2002 (R. A. Rakitov) sweeping, 02-39-2; 1 male, 1 female, PERU, Pasco, Yanachaga-Chemillén N.P., Puesto de Control Huampal, 1050 m, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">10°1'09"S, 75°34'27"W</named-content>, 8 October 2002 (R. A. Rakitov) on grass; 1 male, same data except Refugio El Cedro, 2420 m, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">10°33'07"S, 75°21'27"W</named-content>, 10 October 2002, D.M. Takiya, PE07; 1 female PERU, Junin, 1 km S Minapichita, 2100 m <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">11°6'1"S, 75°25'30"W</named-content>, 19 October 2002 (C. H. Dietrich) sweeping, 02-20-1 [INHS].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The species name refers to the long distal spine of the aedeagus.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p>This species may be distinguished by its moderately long crown and by the elongate, laterally directed distal spine of the aedeagus.</p>
                    <p>One specimen from Yanachaga-Chemillén National Park, Peru, has the distal spine of the aedeagus extended to the right, mirroring the condition found in other examined specimens of this species. Specimens examined from Yanachaga-Chemillén National Park have the anal tube processes considerably shorter than those in the type series from Chanchamayo, but such variation is here considered to be intraspecific. Based on the material available for study, this is the most widespread and common species of the genus.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">ochrescens</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1D932E94-61AA-400E-B8D3-40F45CEF0D3D</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">htp://species-id.net/wiki/Ilyapa_ochrescens</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 7</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">42</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">59–60</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Length male 6.5–6.8 mm. Nearly uniform pale orange dorsally, orange-red maculae slender; apical margin of crown forming acute angle, pronotal macula indistinct. Male pygofer processes robust, not crossing posteromedially; anal tube <!--PageBreak-->without ventrolateral processes; aedeagal shaft symmetrical, pillarlike, compressed, in lateral view extended dorsad and bent posterad at right angle, with pair of acute anterodorsal processes extended anterad, posterodorsal extension with ventral margin irregular, apex expanded with ventral spine. Female unknown.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male: COLOMBIA, Cundinamarca, PNN Chingaza Valle Del Fraylejon, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">4°31'N, 73°45'W</named-content>, 3170m, Malaise 31 August–13 September 2000 (A. Pérez), M.732. Paratypes: 1 male, same coordinates, Chingaza Bosque Palacio, 2930m, Malaise 8–22 December 2000 (A. Cifuentes), M.1027; 1 male, same data except 3–16 March 2001(C. Vinchira and A. Cifuentes), M.1492 [HIC].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The species name refers to the mostly orange coloration of the dorsum.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p>This species may be distinguished by its relatively long crown, predominantly orange coloration, and broad, strongly compressed aedeagal shaft.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">recurvata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:987F8A00-CC54-494D-AE56-7FDAD4F92AF3</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">htp://species-id.net/wiki/Ilyapa_recurvata</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 8</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">44</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">61–62</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Length male 5.9 mm. External morphology and male terminalia similar to those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa longispina</tp:taxon-name></italic>, except as follows: anal tube without pair of ventrolateral processes but with several irregular teeth; aedeagus with distal process strongly recurved ventrad and anterad, branched near midlength with one branch about half length of other. Female unknown.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male: PERU, Huánuco, Carpish Pass, 2600 m, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">9°43'3"S, 76°5'38"W</named-content>, 27 October 2002 (C. H. Dietrich) sweeping, 02-45-1 [USML].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The species name refers to the strongly recurved apex of the aedeagus.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p>This species may be distinguished by its relatively short crown and strongly recurved aedeagal apex.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">viridis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D530E660-0B0C-4159-9EDF-4FD394B048C4</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">htp://species-id.net/wiki/Ilyapa_viridis</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 9</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">29–30</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">32, 34, 45</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">63–64</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">68</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Length male 5.8–6.0, female 7.0 mm. Crown pale yellow medially, white laterally, orange/red maculae broad, overlapping ocelli; anterior margin forming approximately right angle; pronotum and opaque areas of forewing dark green (mottled with yellow in specimens removed from ethanol), pronotum with semicircular macula distinct. Male pygofer processes slender, crossing posteromedially; anal tube with pair of retrorse posterolateral spines. Aedeagus asymmetrical, shaft narrow, tubular and gradually tapered distally, in lateral view narrowly U-shaped with distal part<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> attenuated and arcuate; apex with slender bifurcate process extended to left at right angle to shaft. Female seventh sternite posterior margin with small acute median tooth.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male: PERU, Pasco, Yanachaga-Chemillén N.P., <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">10°32'39.7"S, 75°22'00.1"W</named-content>, 2300m, 10–13 October 2002 (D. Takiya, C. Peña, R. Rakitov) Malaise trap across Rio San Alberto [USML]. Paratypes: 1 male and 1 female, <!--PageBreak-->same data; 2 males, Yanachaga-Chemillén N.P., <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">10°32'S, 75°21'W</named-content>, S. Alberto Valley ca. Refugio El Cedro, 2270–2420m, 12 October 2002 (R. Rakitov); 2 males, 1 female, same data except 10 October 2002 (D. M. Takiya); 8 females, same data except 12 October 2002 (D. M. Takiya) [INHS].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The species name refers to the mostly pale green coloration of the dorsum.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p>This species closely resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa longispina</tp:taxon-name></italic> in external morphology and in the male genitalia, but may be distinguished by the shorter, distinctly branched distal aedeagal process and by the distinctly smaller median lobe of female abdominal sternite VII.
                    </p>
                    <p>In one examined male specimen, the configuration of the aedeagus is the mirror image of that of the other specimens.</p>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 46–52.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male genitalia <bold>46</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala basilisca</tp:taxon-name></italic> (specimen from PNN Chingaza Alto de la Bandera, Cundinamarca, Colombia), genitalia, lateral view <bold>47</bold> same, ventral view (only right style shown) <bold>48</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala basilisca</tp:taxon-name></italic> (specimen from PNN Chingaza Churrascales, Cundinamarca, Colombia), genitalia, lateral view <bold>49</bold> same, ventral view <bold>50</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala acuminata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, genitalia, lateral view <bold>51</bold> same, ventral view <bold>52</bold> same, aedeagus, posteroventral view.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-124-019-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 53–64.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male genitalia, lateral and ventral views <bold>53–54</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa bifida</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>55–56</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa loca</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>57–58</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa longispina</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>59–60</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa ochrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>61–62</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa recurvata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>63–64</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-124-019-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 65–74.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahualini</tp:taxon-name>, female terminalia <bold>65–68</bold> sternite VII <bold>65</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala acuminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>66</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa bifida</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>67</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa longispina</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>68</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>69–71</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tungurahuala acuminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>69</bold> first valvula <bold>70</bold> same, detail of dorsal sculptured area <bold>71</bold> second valvulae <bold>72–74</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ilyapa longispina</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>72</bold> first valvula <bold>73</bold> same, detail of dorsal sculptured area <bold>74</bold> second valvulae</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-124-019-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>I am indebted to Paul Freytag and Michael Sharkey (University of Kentucky) for access to their Malaise trap samples from Colombia, to Robert Blinn (NCSU) for the loan of additional specimens, to Carlos Peña and Pedro Lozada for help with field work in Peru, to Daniela Takiya and Dmitry Dmitriev for helpful discussions, and to Mick Webb and Chandra Viraktamath for constructive criticism of the manuscript. This work was supported in part by grants from the U.S. National Science Foundation.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> The role of grasslands in the diversification of leafhoppers (Homoptera: Cicadellidae): a phylogenetic perspective.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Warwick</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>Proceedings of the Fifteenth North American Prairie Conference.</issue-title> <source>Natural Areas Association, Bend, Oregon</source>: <fpage>44</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of the leafhopper subfamily Evacanthinae with a review of Neotropical species and notes on related groups (Hemiptera: Membracoidea: Cicadellidae).</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology </source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>455</fpage>-<lpage>487</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.0307-6970.2004.00250.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.0307-6970.2004.00250.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Keys to families of Cicadomorpha and subfamilies and tribes of Cicadellidae (Hemiptera: Auchenorrhyncha).</article-title> <source>Florida Entomologist </source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>502</fpage>-<lpage>517</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1653/0015-4040(2005)88[502:KTTFOC]2.0.CO;2" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1653/0015-4040(2005)88[502:KTTFOC]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakitov</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Black IV</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of the major lineages of Membracoidea (Insecta: Hemiptera: Cicadomorpha) based on 28S rDNA sequences.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>-<lpage>305</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/mpev.2000.0873" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1006/mpev.2000.0873</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dmitriev</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakitov</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takiya</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahniser</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of Cicadellidae (Cicadomorpha: Membracoidea) based on combined morphological and 28S rDNA sequence data.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Abstracts of Talks and Posters: 12th International Auchenorrhyncha Congress, Berkeley, CA, 7–12 August, 2005</source>, <fpage>S13</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dmitriev</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakitov</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takiya</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahniser</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of Cicadellidae (Hemiptera: Cicadomorpha: Membracoidea) based on morphological characters.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Soulier-Perkins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouvrard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourgoin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>13th International Auchenorrhyncha Congress Abstracts</source>, <publisher-name>Museum National d'Histoire Naturelle</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dmitriev</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> General morphology of leafhopper nymphs of the subfamily Deltocephalinae (Hemiptera: Cicadellidae).</article-title> <source>Acta Entomologica Slovenica </source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1947</year>)<article-title> A natural classification of leaf-hoppers (Jassoidea, Homoptera) Part 3. Jassidae.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the Royal Entomological Society of London </source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>-<lpage>271</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2311.1947.tb01054.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.1365-2311.1947.tb01054.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebicki</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szwedo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> The first record of fossil Mileewinae from Eocene Baltic amber (Hemiptera: Membracoidea: Cicadellidae).</article-title> <source>Annales Zoologici </source> <volume>511</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>-<lpage>422</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Godoy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Recognition of a new subfamily of Cicadellidae from Costa Rica based on a phenetic analysis with similar taxa (Hemiptera Homoptera Auchenorrhyncha).</article-title> <source>Tropical Zoology </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>)<article-title> Studies of Neotropical leafhoppers. I. (Homoptera: Cicadellidae).</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington </source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1950</year>)<article-title> The morphology and phylogeny of Auchenorrhynchous Homoptera (Insecta).</article-title> <source>Illinois Biological Monographs </source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Linnavuori</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeLong</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>)<article-title> Studies of the Neotropical Mileewaninae (Homoptera: Cicadellidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society </source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>410</fpage>-<lpage>421</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oman</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1949</year>)<article-title> The Nearctic leafhoppers–a generic classification and check list.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the Entomological Society of Washington </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>253</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oman</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielson</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<source> Leafhoppers (Cicadellidae): a Bibliography, Generic Check-list, and Index to the World Literature 1956–1985.</source> <publisher-name>CAB International Institute of Entomology</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Wallingford</publisher-loc>, <lpage>368</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakitov</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> On differentiation of cicadellid leg chaetotaxy (Homoptera: Auchenorrhyncha: Membracoidea).</article-title> <source>Russian Entomological Journal </source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Takiya</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> Systematic studies on the leafhopper subfamily Cicadellinae (Hemiptera: Cicadellidae).</source> PhD thesis, <publisher-name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Urbana, Illinois</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>)<article-title> Western Hemisphere Mileewanini (Homoptera, Cicadellidae).</article-title> <source>Zoologische Beiträge </source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>-<lpage>380</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> Taxonomic study of the Cicadellinae (Homoptera: Cicadellidae). Part 1. Proconiini.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the United States National Museum </source> <volume>261</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>287</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>)<article-title> Taxonomic study of the Cicadellinae (Homoptera: Cicadellidae). Part 2. New World Cicadellini and the genus <italic>Cicadella</italic>.</article-title> <source>North Carolina Agricultural Experiment Station Technical Bulletin </source> <volume>239</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>1135</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> Taxonomic study of the Cicadellinae (Homoptera: Cicadellidae), Part 3. Old World Cicadellini.</article-title> <source>North Carolina Agricultural Research Service Technical Bulletin </source> <volume>281</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>639</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>