<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.159.2476</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Review of 
                    <italic>Anhoplocampa</italic> Wei (Hymenoptera, Tenthredinidae), with description of a new species and a new combination
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Wei</surname>
                        <given-names>Meicai</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:18D7AFE0-6CA9-403C-B03B-697D68EED8B7</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Niu</surname>
                        <given-names>Gengyun</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:AD829700-118D-4B33-BF08-1B44022CED07</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>College of Life Science and Technology, Central South University of Forestry and Technology, 498 South Shaoshan Road, Changsha 410004, P. R. China
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Meicai Wei (<email xlink:type="simple">weimc@126.com</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: S. Blank</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>23</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>159</issue>
            <fpage>81</fpage>
            <lpage>90</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>6</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Meicai Wei, Gengyun Niu</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:F7DA805F-BB46-4FA5-94A2-FEB367215FD2</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> is redescribed based on new material. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa bicoloricornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> from China is described. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa yunanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Haris &amp; Roller, 1999), <bold>comb. n.</bold> is transferred from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichiocampus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. A key to species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> is provided. The differences between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichiocampus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hartig, 1837, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Priophorus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dahlbom, 1835, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hartig, 1837 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Renonerva</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wei &amp; Nie, 1998 are briefly discussed.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Hymenoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Tenthredinidae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Anhoplocampa</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>new combination</kwd>
                <kwd>China</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Wei (1998)</xref> described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and its type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa fumosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> from China based on a single female. The genus is quite peculiar from other taxa of <tp:taxon-name>Nematinae</tp:taxon-name> by with the presence of a distinct smoky band below pterostigma in the forewing; mesepisternum<!--PageBreak--> with a deep, broad and strongly curved furrow along the anterior and dorsal margins of the mesepisternum, and the epicnemium long, narrow, and strongly elevated.</p>
            <p>Specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> are rarely collected in the field. Except for the holotype of the type species, which was collected from Sichuan Province in 1983, one specimen was collected in Henan Province in 2001 and one in Yunnan Province in 2004. The two specimens represent two additional species of the genus.</p>
            <p>In 1999, Haris and Roller described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichiocampus yunanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Yunnan, China based on a female specimen. Examination of the holotype shows that it is a species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and identical to the specimen collected from Yunnan in 2004.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> is redescribed based on new material. A new species is described and a new combination is proposed below.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="material|methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Terminology of sawfly genitalia follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Ross (1945)</xref>. Wing venation is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref> with names of cells on the right side and names of veins on the left side.</p>
            <p>The images were obtained using a Nikon D2x digital camera and Motic BA400 microscope and further processed with Helicon Focus 5.1(©HeliconSoft) and Adobe Photoshop CS2 software.</p>
            <p>Abbreviations used are: OOL = distance between the eye and outer edge of lateral ocellus; POL = distance between the mesal edges of the lateral ocelli; OCL = distance between a lateral ocellus and the occipital carina or hind margin of the head.</p>
            <p>Rules for spelling Chinese personal and place names follow GB/T 16159-1996 and ISO 7098: 1991: “Chinese people’s names are to be written separately with the surname first, followed by the personal name written as one word, with the initial letters of both capitalized.”. “Chinese place names should be alphabetized according to the “Spelling Rules for Chinese Geographical Place Names,” document no. 17 (1984) of the State Committee on Chinese Geographical Place Names.”</p>
            <p>Specimens examined are deposited in the Insect Collection of the Central South University of Forestry and Technology, Changsha, P. R. China (CSCS) and the Hungarian Natural History Museum, Budapest, Hungary (HNHM).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Anhoplocampa</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Wei, 1998</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name><comment> Wei, 1998: 14. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa fumosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wei, 1998, by original designation.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body length 7–11 mm. Clypeus flat, anterior margin emarginated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>); malar space about as long as diameter of lateral ocellus; eyes small, distance between eyes at level of antennal sockets (toruli) 1.2–1.8 × greatest diameter of eye; supraantennal area distinctly protruding between antennal sockets; frontal area surrounded by strong carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">16</xref>), upper margin of lateral fovea carinate; occipital carina absent; left mandible in lateral view with swollen base, narrowing to thin blade-like apex (similar to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Benson 1958</xref>, fig. 380). Head weakly dilated behind eyes in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">16</xref>). Antenna long and slender, basal two antennomeres short, much broader than long, third antennomere clearly shorter than fourth antennomere, other flagellomeres subequal in length. Prepectus lanceolate, distinct, about 3 × longer than wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>); epicnemium narrow, strongly elevated, furrow between epicnemium and mesepisternum deep and broad in entire length, strongly curved in upper part across upper 0.10 of mesepisternum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">9</xref>). Inner tibial spur of front leg bifid apically, much longer than outer spur. Hind tibia with longitudinal furrow on outer side, tibial spurs short, 1.1–1.3 × apical breadth of tibia; hind tarsus about 0.8 × length of hind tibia; metabasitarsus about 1.1 × length of following 3 tarsomeres together; claw without basal lobe, inner tooth large, slightly shorter than or about as long as outer tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">15</xref>). Forewing with a distinct dark band below pterostigma, vein R+M longer than cu-a, Sc slightly basad apex of vein 1M; vein 2r1 absent; vein 1M strongly convergent toward pterostigma with 1m-cu; cell 2Rs subequal to 1Rs in length and about 2 × as long as broad; 2m-cu joining cell 2Rs at basal 0.20–0.25; cell 1R1 about as long as broad, cell 2M longer than broad; vein 2A+3A meeting 1A at basal 0.3, basal anal cell closed; cu-a meeting cell 1M at about middle to basal 0.4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">14</xref>). Hind wing with cells Rs and M closed, anal cell closed, petiole of anal cell as long as width of anal cell and subequal to vein cu-a (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">7</xref>). Cerci usually slender (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">17</xref>). Ovipositor sheath not longer than middle tibia, apical section of sheath with 3 processes in dorsal view, scopae distinct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">17</xref>). Lancet with or without ctenidia, without stout annular setae, serrulae without denticles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">18</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Yunnan, Sichuan, Henan).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wei, 1998 is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichiocampus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hartig, 1837 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Priophorus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dahlbom, 1835 but differs from those two genera by the very narrow and strongly elevated epicnemium; presence of a broad, deep furrow between the epicnemium and mesepisternum, strongly curved in the upper part of the mesepisternum; prepectus distinct; front wall and upper margin of the lateral fovea strongly carinate; left mandible in lateral view with a swollen base and a thin blade-like apex; vein R+M in forewing longer than cu-a; apical sheath with large scopae; cerci long and slender; forewing with a dark band below pterostigma; petiole of hind anal cell as long as width of anal cell; as well, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichiocampus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and other <tp:taxon-name>Cladiini</tp:taxon-name> the vein 1M meets vein R close to the point where Rs+M meets R+M; vein 1M is far removed from that point in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    <!--PageBreak-->
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hartig, 1837 by the much larger body; antenna longer than the abdomen with the scape and pedicel much broader than long; forewing with a dark band below pterostigma and vein 2r absent; petiole of anal cell of hind wing not longer than cu-a; left mandible in lateral view with a swollen base and a thin blade-like apex; epicnemium very narrow and strongly elevated, with a broad and deep furrow between the epicnemium and mesepisternum, strongly curved in the upper part of the mesepisternum; supraclypeal area strongly protruding between antennal sockets and distance between antennal sockets distinctly narrower than the inner orbit at the same level; frontal walls strongly carinate; and ovipositor sheath shorter than middle tibia and with distinct scopae.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> is also somewhat similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Renonerva</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wei &amp; Nie (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Wei and Nie 1998</xref>) sharing the narrow and strongly elevated epicnemium with a deep and broad furrow between epicnemium and mesepisternum, but <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from the latter by the robust body and stout antenna; the distinctly emarginated clypeus; malar space about as long as diameter of middle ocellus; prepectus distinct; cerci not linear; forewing with a dark band below pterostigma, vein 2r1 absent, 2A+3A on forewing straight and the basal anal cell open; the hind basitarsus longer than the following three tarsomeres together; ovipositor sheath with distinct scopae; lancet not strongly reduced and lamnium not shorter than radix.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hemichroa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Stephens, 1835 in the very narrow and strongly elevated epicnemium; presence of a broad, deep furrow between the epicnemium and mesepisternum, strongly curved in the upper part of the mesepisternum; front wall and upper margin of the lateral fovea strongly carinate; left mandible in lateral view with a swollen base and a thin blade-like apex; apical sheath with large scopae; forewing with a dark band below pterostigma, vein 2r1 absent and the middle petiole of anal cell on forewing shorter than vein R+M.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> also shares some characters with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pristiphora</tp:taxon-name></italic> Latreille, 1810, for example the bladelike mandibles and the apical sheath with distinct scopae. But <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pristiphora</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the very narrow and strongly elevated epicnemium; presence of a broad, deep furrow between the epicnemium and mesepisternum; front wall and upper margin of the lateral fovea strongly carinate; the forewing with a dark band below pterostigma, the vein 2A+3A curved up and meeting 1A and therefore the basal anal cell closed.</p>
                    <p>Three species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> are now known. They can be identified with the following key.</p>
                    <sec sec-type="Key to species of Anhoplocampa Wei"><title>Key to species of <tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name> Wei</title>
                        <table-wrap content-type="key" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clypeus deeply incised to about 0.5 × length of clypeus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>); postocellar area and temple flat (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>); cerci not extending to end of sheath in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 12</xref>); forewing with a not strongly defined cross band posterior of pterostigma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>); head, antenna, mesothorax dorsally, abdomen<!--PageBreak--> entirely, and all tibiae and tarsi reddish brown; cu-a of fore wing meeting cell 1M at about middle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>); upper half of mesepisternum distinctly microsculptured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 9</xref>); lateral furrows of postocellar area deep and broad (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>); lancet slender, with 16 serrulae and 14 annuli, annuli without ctenidia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 13</xref>). Yunnan</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa yunanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clypeus shallowly incised to about 0.25 × length of clypeus; postocellar area declined posteriorly, temple distinctly convex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">16</xref>); apex of cercus extending clearly beyond apex of sheath in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">17</xref>); cross band posterior of pterostigma dark, sharply defined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">14</xref>); at least apical half of antenna, most of mesothorax dorsally, abdomen except 2<sup>nd</sup> tergite, hind tibia and tarsus entirely black; cu-a of fore wing meeting cell 1M at about basal 0.4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">14</xref>); mesepisternum strongly shiny, without microsculpture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>); lateral furrows of postocellar area very fine or narrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">16</xref>); lancet short, with 9 serrulae and 8 annuli, annuli with ctenidia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">18</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antenna entirely black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 14</xref>); labrum, supraclypeal area and frons black; prescutum entirely black; middle tibia and middle tarsus pale brown; posterior half of postocellar area strongly declined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>); frontal basin longer than broad, deep, 0.5 × as deep as width of basin; distance between eyes at level of antennal sockets 1.5 × wider than greater diameter of eye; anterior part of the deep brown band on forewing almost as broad as length of pterostigma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 14</xref>); lancet with teeth of 1<sup>st</sup> ctenidium obtuse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 18</xref>). Sichuan</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa fumosa</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antenna with basal half reddish brown, apical half black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>); head orange except for obscure dark band across postocellar area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>); anterior 0.6 of prescutum reddish brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>); middle tibia and tarsus black brown; posterior half of postocellar area weakly declined; frontal basin broader than long, very shallow, 0.13 × as deep as width of basin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>); distance between eyes at level of antennal sockets 1.2 × wider than greater diameter of eye; anterior part of the deep brown band on forewing about as broad as 0.5 × length of pterostigma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>); lancet with teeth of 1<sup>st</sup> ctenidium acute (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>). Henan</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa bicoloricornis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
                    </sec>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">bicoloricornis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:792A18AE-754C-4F1C-9685-BB411A50FA24</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Anhoplocampa_bicoloricornis</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–6</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Female</bold> (holotype, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Body length 9 mm (excluding antenna, cerci and sheath). Head orange, extreme narrow margin of antennal socket and a transverse band over ocelli black, apical half of antenna black; thorax and abdomen black, pronotum except lower corners, anterior 0.6 of prescutum and anterior corner of lateral lobe of scutum orange; 2<sup>nd</sup> abdominal tergite entirely and a spot near spiracle of 3<sup>rd</sup> tergite pale brown; <!--PageBreak-->legs black, tibia and tarsus of fore leg yellow brown. Wings hyaline, vein C except for both ends pale brown, other veins and pterostigma black brown, anterior breadth of sharply defined smoky macula on forewing about half length of pterostigma. Body hairs brown.</p>
                    <p>Body shiny, without distinct punctures and microsculptures. Clypeus shallowly and roundly emarginated to about 0.25 length of clypeus; malar space slightly longer than diameter of lateral ocellus; postocellar area 2 × as broad as long, with a shallow and broad middle furrow, posterior half of postocellar area weakly declined; postocellar furrow distinct; lateral furrows very shallow, weakly curved; temple weakly bulged; frontal basin shallow, 1.3 × broader than long, with depth about 0.13 × breadth of basin; frontal walls broad, strongly elevated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>); distance between eyes at level of antennal sockets 1.2 × wider than greater diameter of eye. Antenna slender, as long as body, slightly tapering towards apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Prepectus, epicnemium and dorsal part of mesepisternum as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>. Claw with inner tooth hardly shorter and distinctly broader than outer tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>). Forewing: cell 2Rs slightly longer than 1Rs, vein cu-a joining cell 1M at basal 0.43. Cerci and apical sheath in dorsal view as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>, cerci about 5.5 × as long as broad. Lancet with 8 annuli and 9 serrulae, 1<sup>st</sup> annulus with distinct annular teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
                    <p><bold>Male.</bold> Unknown.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–6.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa bicoloricornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype <bold>1</bold> Adult female, dorsal view (scale bar = 1mm) <bold>2</bold> Head, dorsal view <bold>3</bold> Prepectus, epicnemium and dorsal part of mesepisternum <bold>4</bold> Claw <bold>5</bold> Cerci and apical sheath, dorsal view <bold>6</bold> Lancet</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-081-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Henan Province).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The new species is named after the color of the antenna.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype"><title>Holotype.</title>
                    <p>♀, China: Henan Province, Songxian, Baiyunshan, 1800 m, 2001.VI.2, Zhong Yihai leg. (CSCS).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>See above key for differences between the three species of the genus.</p>
                    <!--PageBreak-->
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">yunanensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Anhoplocampa_yunanensis</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Haris &amp; Roller, 1999)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–13</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Trichiocampus yunanensis</tp:taxon-name><comment> Haris &amp; Roller, 1999: 231–232.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Female</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>). Body length 7 mm (excluding antenna, cerci and sheath). Body orange, extreme narrow margin of antennal socket, propleuron, parapsis of mesothorax largely, narrow posterior margin of mesoscutellum, parapsis of metanotum, posterior of metascutellum, ventral half of mesopleuron, ventral margin of metapleuron, black; legs black, apical 1/3 of fore femur, all tibiae and tarsi yellow brown. Wings hyaline, apical third weakly infuscate, vein C pale brown, other veins and pterostigma black brown, anterior breadth of a feebly defined smoky macula about half length of pterostigma. Body hairs silver brown.</p>
                    <p>Body shiny, dorsal side of pronotum distinctly punctured, dorsal half of mesopleuron distinctly microsculptured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 9</xref>). Clypeus distinctly and roundly emarginated to about half length of clypeus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>); malar space about 1.15 × diameter of lateral ocellus; postocellar area flat, 2.2 × as broad as long, with a deep middle fovea and a shallow middle furrow, posterior of postocellar area not declined; postocellar furrow broad and shallow; lateral furrows deep and very broad, weakly divergent backwards; temple flat; frontal basin shallow, 1.1 × as broad as long, with depth about 0.13 × breadth of basin; frontal walls distinctly elevated, not very sharp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>); distance between eyes at level of antennal sockets 1.8 × wider than greater diameter of eye. Antenna stout, 1.2 × length of abdomen, much shorter than thorax and abdomen together, tapering towards apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>). Prepectus, epicnemium and dorsal part of mesepisternum as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 9</xref>. Claw with inner tooth clearly shorter and slightly broader than outer tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 11</xref>). Forewing: cell 2Rs slightly shorter than 1Rs, vein cu-a joining cell 1M at middle. Cerci and apical sheath in dorsal view as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 12</xref>, cerci about 3.5 × as long as broad, not beyond apex of sheath. Lancet slender, with 14 annuli and 16 serrulae, annuli simple, without annular teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 13</xref>).</p>
                    <p><bold>Male.</bold> Unknown.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 7–13.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa yunanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Haris &amp; Roller, 1999) comb. n., specimen from Xiaozhongdian, Yunnan <bold>7</bold> Adult female, dorsal view (scale bar = 1mm) <bold>8</bold> Head, dorsal view <bold>9</bold> Prepectus, epicnemium and dorsal part of mesepisternum <bold>10</bold> Clypeus <bold>11</bold> Claw <bold>12</bold> Cerci and apical sheath, dorsal view <bold>13</bold> Lancet</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-081-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Yunnan).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Specimens examined"><title>Specimens examined.</title>
                    <p>1♀, holotype: “China, Yunan [Yunnan], 24-29. VI. 93, 50 km N. of Lijieng [Lijiang], Yulongshan, Nat. Res., E. Jednek, O. Sausa leg.” (HNHM); 1 female, “Xiaozhongdian, Shangri-La, Yunnan, China, alt. 3000m, 19 July 2004, Xiao Wei coll.” (CSCS).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>This species is easily separated from the other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> species by the orange body; antenna stout and much shorter than body; forewing with a weak cross band below pterostigma; postocellar area not declined and with deep and broad lateral furrows; the upper half of mesopleuron distinctly microsculptured; cerci shorter; clypeus deeply incised; claw with inner tooth clearly shorter than outer tooth; cu-a of fore wing meeting cell 1M at about middle; and female lancet slender with 14 simple annuli.</p>
                    <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Haris and Roller (1999)</xref> placed this species in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichiocampus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However, left mandible in lateral view bearing a strongly swollen base and narrowing to a thin blade-like apex<!--PageBreak-->, the long vein R+M, the narrow and strongly elevated epicnemium with a deep and strongly curved furrow, and the distinctly carinate frontal walls show that it is member of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and does not belong to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichiocampus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    <p>The weak cross-band of the forewing, the comparatively short antenna, the short cerci, the slender lancet with simple annuli, the flat temple and postocellar area of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa yunanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> show that it is morphologically remote from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa bicoloricornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa fumosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Anhoplocampa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">fumosa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Anhoplocampa_fumosa</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Wei, 1998</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 14–18</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa fumosa</tp:taxon-name><comment> Wei, 1998: 15.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Female</bold> (holotype, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 14</xref>). Body length 11 mm (excluding antenna, cerci and sheath). Head dark orange, narrow margin of antennal socket, frons and ocellar<!--PageBreak--> area, a broad transverse band along posterior margin of head black; antenna entirely black; thorax and abdomen black, middle half of pronotum orange; 2<sup>nd</sup> abdominal tergite largely pale brown; legs black, fore tibia and tarsus yellow brown, middle tibia and tarsus pale brown. Wings hyaline, apical third of forewing weakly infuscate, veins and pterostigma black brown, anterior breadth of a sharply defined smoky band below pterostigma about as long as pterostigma. Body hairs brown.</p>
                    <p>Body shiny, without distinct punctures and microsculptures. Clypeus shallowly and roundly emarginated to about 0.25 × length of clypeus; malar space slightly longer than diameter of lateral ocellus; postocellar area 2 × as broad as long, with a shallow middle fovea, posterior half of postocellar area strongly declined; postocellar furrow distinct; lateral furrows shallow but distinct, weakly curved; temple distinctly bulged; frontal basin long and deep, 1.2 × longer than broad, with depth about 0.5 × breadth of basin; frontal walls broad, strongly elevated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>); distance between eyes at level of antennal sockets 1.5 × wider than greater diameter of eye. Antenna slender, 1.3 × length of abdomen, not tapering towards apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 14</xref>). Prepectus, epicnemium and dorsal part of mesepisternum similar to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>. Claw with inner tooth hardly shorter and distinctly broader than outer tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 15</xref>). Forewing: cell 2Rs slightly longer than 1Rs, vein cu-a joining cell 1M at basal 0.4. Cerci and apical sheath in dorsal view <!--PageBreak-->as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 17</xref>, cerci about 5.5 × as long as broad, middle tooth of sheath acute and much longer than roundish lateral teeth. Lancet with 8 annuli and 9 serrulae, 1<sup>st</sup> annulus with obscure annular teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 18</xref>).</p>
                    <p><bold>Male.</bold> Unknown.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 14–18.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anhoplocampa fumosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wei, 1998, holotype <bold>14</bold> Adult female, dorsal view (scale bar = 1mm) <bold>15</bold> Claw <bold>16</bold> Head, dorsal view <bold>17</bold> Cerci and apical sheath, dorsal view <bold>18</bold> Lancet</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-081-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Sichuan Province).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Specimens examined"><title>Specimens examined.</title>
                    <p>1♀, holotype: “China, Sichuan, Baoxing, 2200 m, 27 June, 1983, Xiong Jiang leg.” (CSCS).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>Our thanks are due to Dr. Sándor Csõsz, the curator of Hungarian Natural History Museum, for allowing study of Haris’ type. This work is supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (no.31172142 and 30771741) and the Graduate’s Scientific Research Foundation of Central South University of Forestry and Technology (2009bx02).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>)<source> Hymenoptera Symphyta, Tenthredinidae. Handbooks for the Identification of British Insects 6(2c): 139–258.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Haris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Four new sawfly species from Yunan (Hymenoptera: Tenthredinidae).</article-title> <source>Folia Entomologica Hungarica </source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>237</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1945</year>)<article-title> Sawfly genitalia: terminology and study techniques.</article-title> <source>Entomological News </source> <volume>61</volume> (<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>261</fpage>-<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> Three new genera of Hoplocampinae (Hymenoptera: Nematidae) from China with a key to known genera of the subfamily in the world.</article-title> <source>Journal of Central South University</source> <volume>18</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>12</fpage>-<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> New genera and species of Nematidae of West China (Hymenoptera: Tenthredinidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of Central South University </source> <volume>18</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>14</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>