<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.190.3011</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Phylogenetic reconsideration of 
                    <italic>Myrmekiaphila</italic> systematics with a description of the new trapdoor spider species 
                    <italic>Myrmekiaphila tigris</italic> (Araneae, Mygalomorphae, Cyrtaucheniidae, Euctenizinae) from Auburn, Alabama
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Bond</surname>
                        <given-names>Jason E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:F5B56990-8D68-4D59-A5C3-07E11FD31661</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Hamilton</surname>
                        <given-names>Chris A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:A11AB4EE-74C3-455C-8819-213462B86F2A</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Garrison</surname>
                        <given-names>Nicole L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:1B165257-BF5C-4FEC-8157-0470DFBF6D2F</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Ray</surname>
                        <given-names>Charles H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7EBE305E-0B5B-4CE2-8784-A4F30C9D1F5A</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Auburn University Museum of Natural History, Auburn University, Auburn, AL, 36849, USA
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Jason E. Bond (<email xlink:type="simple">jbond@auburn.edu</email>)
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: M. Kuntner</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>4</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>190</issue>
            <fpage>95</fpage>
            <lpage>109</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Jason E. Bond, Chris A. Hamilton, Nicole L. Garrison, Charles H. Ray</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:F6500AE5-B3F1-4DF3-9A11-B9B74D386B06</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The trapdoor spider genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila</tp:taxon-name></italic> currently comprises 11 nominal species. A recent molecular phylogenetic evaluation of the group identified a number of problems with respect to how species and species groups were delineated by Bond and Platnick in their 2007 taxonomic revision of the genus. We report herein the discovery of a new species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> The phylogenetic position of the species is evaluated using a molecular phylogenetic approach based on a set of mtDNA markers. Our preferred phylogenetic hypothesis supports the recognition of a new species and further highlights the need to more carefully investigate species boundaries within the genus. These results further indicate that palpal bulb morphology is rapidly evolving and has likely been a contributing factor in rendering a number of species paraphyletic with respect to the molecular data.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>New species</kwd>
                <kwd>Integrative taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>Molecular taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>Southeastern United States</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Myrmekiaphila</italic>
                </kwd>
                <kwd>Cyrtaucheniidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Euctenizinae
<!--PageBreak--></kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila</tp:taxon-name></italic> Atkinson, 1886 is a moderately diverse assemblage of trapdoor spiders distributed predominantly throughout the southeastern United States. Revised recently by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick (2007)</xref>, it presently comprises 11 nominal species that range from Virginia southward to the Gulf Coast and extending as far west as central Texas. All known <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila</tp:taxon-name></italic> species construct a silk-lined burrow, covered by a silken-soil trapdoor, from which they forage as sit and wait predators; many burrows are uniquely modified to include a side chamber that can be closed from the main chamber by a second trapdoor. As discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick (2007)</xref> the familial placement of the genus has been somewhat problematic, however, molecular studies of mygalomorph phylogeny (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bond and Hedin 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Hedin and Bond 2006</xref>, and Bond et al. in review) place the genus in what is now recognized as the North American cyrtaucheniid subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Euctenizinae</tp:taxon-name>, to be elevated to family rank (Bond et al. in review).
            </p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila</tp:taxon-name></italic> species delimitation and diagnosis relies heavily on modifications of the male first walking leg – often termed the mating clasper – and the morphology of the palpal bulb. Mating clasper morphology is typically discriminated on the basis of unique spination patterns whereas palpal bulb modifications are often quite dramatic comprising relatively pronounced branched and serrated structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Such major differences in palpal bulb morphology stand in relatively stark contrast to the paucity of differentiation observed for palpal bulb structure in other related mygalomorph taxa (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bond 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Stockman and Bond 2008</xref>). Despite the disparities in male morphology, female specimens are relatively homogenous with only subtle differences in spermathecae morphology rendering them nearly impossible to identify without the aid of molecular markers. Consequently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick (2007)</xref> provided a morphological key only for male specimens.
            </p>
            <p>On the basis of palpal differences, presence or absence of a second prong and serration patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> but also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bailey et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick (2007)</xref> divided the genus into three species groups; they acknowledged at the time that these groupings were without phylogenetic support. A subsequent molecular based study of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila</tp:taxon-name></italic> species relationships by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bailey et al. (2010)</xref> indeed demonstrated these species groups were not monophyletic. Most notably the results of their analysis indicated that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic> Gertsch &amp; Wallace, 1936, a species with a dual pronged bulb, is paraphyletic with respect to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila coreyi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bond &amp; Platnick, 2007, a species with a single prong and diminutive serration. Consequently, the species “tree” (i.e., prior hypothesis of species boundaries) was in conflict with the gene tree. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bailey et al. (2010)</xref> hypothesized that palpal bulb evolution appeared to be quickly outpacing the evolutionary patterns conveyed by the mitochondrial and nuclear markers (incomplete lineage sorting) used to infer phylogeny and that it was unlikely that the putative <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic> lineages harbored cryptic diversity because of a general lack of geographical concordance among its lineages. This paper documents the discovery of a new <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila</tp:taxon-name></italic> species that brings into question the hypothesis that incomplete lineage is the cause of the observed gene-tree species-tree incongruence. Rather, the study system may suffer from<!--PageBreak--> “bad taxonomy” (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Funk and Omland 2003</xref>). That is, that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick (2007)</xref> may have overlooked some of the morphological diversity contained within the group.
            </p>
            <p>The focus of this paper is the description of a new species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bond &amp; Ray. This species was brought to the attention of the first author by C. Ray who collected numerous specimens during the winter months (Dec-Jan) of 2011/2012 from sidewalks and swimming pools located in the town of Auburn, Alabama in a moderately populated housing subdivision. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick (2007)</xref> had examined specimens from the vicinity of the type locality reported herein, but seemingly misidentified them as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila foliata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Atkinson, 1886. Examination of the newly acquired specimens and reexamination of the earlier collected material found these specimens to bear some likeness to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila foliata</tp:taxon-name></italic> but upon close inspection, notable differences in the palpal structure (discussed in the diagnosis of the species below) came to light. That said, given the putative widespread distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila foliata</tp:taxon-name></italic> it would not be unreasonable to infer that the variation noted in these specimens simply represents a geographic variant of the species and thus recognition of new species is not necessarily warranted (i.e., if we ignore the fact that mygalomorph taxa are prone to species crypsis; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Bond and Stockman 2008</xref>). As such, it seemed prudent to consider an independent assessment of the hypothesized new taxon using molecular data before proposing a new name. The study reported here provides molecular evidence that warrants recognition of a new species, further documents the somewhat complicated relationships of species contained within the genus, and formally describes this newly recognized lineage as a nominal species.
            </p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Line drawing of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> male pedipalp; distal aspect of palpal bulb shown for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila foliata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic> for comparative purposes.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-190-095-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
            <title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>Unique voucher numbers were assigned to all specimens (AUMS) and corresponding labels added to each vial. Collecting locality latitude/longitude data was georeferenced as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick (2007)</xref>; georeferenced specimens from older museum labels given in brackets [ ] in the material examined section of the species description. All measurements were taken with a Leica MZ16.5 stereomicroscope equipped with a 10X ocular and ocular micrometer scale. Measurements were taken from the left appendage, usually in retrolateral view, using the highest magnification possible. Leg article measurements were taken as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick (2007)</xref>. Illustrations were prepared using a Visionary Digital Imaging System (Ashland, VA). Photographs were recorded in multiple focal planes and assembled using the Zerene Stacker software package (Zerene Systems LLC, Richland, WA). Carapace and leg coloration are described using Munsell Soil Color Charts (Windsor, NY) and are given using the color name and hue value/chroma notation.
            </p>
            <p>Species descriptions are formatted similarly to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bond (2004)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick (2007)</xref> for consistency and comparative purposes. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Institutional abbreviations</tp:taxon-name></italic>: AMNH – American Museum of Natural History; CAU and AUMNH – Auburn University Museum of Natural History; CDF – personal collection of D. Folkerts, deposited in AUMNH; FMNH – Field Museum of Natural History. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Morphological abbreviations</tp:taxon-name></italic>: Cl/w (carapace length/width), STRl/w (sternum length/width), LBl/w (labium length/width), A/PER (anterior/posterior eye row), A/PME (anterior/posterior median eye), TSp/r and TSrd (male tibia I spines prolateral/retrolateral and retrolateral distal), PTw/l (male palpal tibia width/length), Bl (palpal bulb length), PT/TB3s (female patella/tibia III spines). Leg I article measurements are in the following order: femur, tibia, metatarsus, and tarsus; leg IV measurements are femur and tarsus only.
            </p>
            <p>Protocols for sample, tissue, DNA extraction, polymerase chain reaction (PCR), and sequencing follow those outlined in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Hendrixson and Bond (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bailey et al. (2010)</xref>. Using those procedures we amplified for five exemplar specimens the 12S/16S mitochondrial DNA region using the PCR primers LR-J-12887 and SR-N-14612 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Simon et al. 1994</xref>). This mtDNA region was used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bailey et al. (2010)</xref> in combination with a nuclear coding protein gene that showed a largely congruent phylogenetic pattern. Paratype specimens AUMS077, 089, 119 comprised a male and two female specimens collected from the type locality; AUMS095 is from a locality in the region, Tuskegee State Park. Specimen AUMS078 is a putative <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic> Gertsch &amp; Wallace, 1936 juvenile specimen from the proximity of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> type locality (outskirts of Auburn, AL, Lee County). The resulting fragment was sequenced using the PCR amplification primers plus an additional internal primer, SR-N-13xxxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Bond and Stockman 2008</xref>). The fragments were assembled and edited using the computer program Geneious Pro v5.5.4 (Auckland, New Zealand). The final edited sequences (Genbank accession numbers JQ708211- JQ708215) were added to the existing <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila</tp:taxon-name></italic> 12S/16S data matrix (Treebase accession S10740) and aligned to the existing alignment using the pairwise alignment tool in Mesquite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Maddison and Maddison 2009</xref>). Data partitions and model choice for Bayesian phylogenetic inference is outlined in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bailey et al. (2010)</xref>.<!--PageBreak-->
            </p>
            <p>Tree searches on the partitioned data set using Maximum Likelihood and Bayesian inference were conducted using RAxML ver. 7.2.8 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Stamatakis 2006</xref>) and MrBayes ver 3.1.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Huelsenbeck and Ronquist 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Ronquist and Huelsenbeck 2003</xref>), respectively. RAxML analyses comprised 1,000 random sequence addition replicates (RAS) using the commands “-# 1000” and “–m GTRGAMMA”. Bootstrap support values were calculated using the same search parameters with 1,000 replicates. Results from the bootstrap analysis were then applied to the best tree recovered from the RAS search. The MrBayes tree search comprised two independent runs of four simultaneous Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) chains. The Bayesian analyses were run for 20,000,000 generations with trees sampled every 1,000 generations; the first 25% were discarded as <italic>burn-in</italic>. Likelihood values for all post-analysis trees and parameters were evaluated for convergence and <italic>burn-in</italic> using the “sump” command in MrBayes and the computer program Tracer ver. 1.5 (Rambaut and Drummond; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://evolve.zoo.ox.ac.uk/software.html?id=tracer" xlink:type="simple">http://evolve.zoo.ox.ac.uk/software.html?id=tracer</ext-link>). Trees remaining after <italic>burn-in</italic> were used to calculate posterior probabilities using the “sumt” command.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Data resources">
            <title>Data resources</title>
            <p>Phylogenetic data sets (NEXUS and PHYLIP format) for all specimens evaluated in this study; locality data for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
            </p>
            <p>The data underpinning the analysis reported in this paper were deposited on 25 April 2012 in the Dryad Data Repository at doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.pk24v" xlink:type="simple">10.5061/dryad.pk24v</ext-link>  (Bond et al. 2012) and at GBIF, the Global Biodiversity Information Facility, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ipt.pensoft.net/ipt/resource.do?r=myr_dataset" xlink:type="simple">http://ipt.pensoft.net/ipt/resource.do?r=myr_dataset</ext-link>.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results and discussion">
            <title>Results and discussion</title>
            <p>The –ln likelihood value for the best scoring tree recovered from the RAxML analysis was -11,248.44. The harmonic and arithmetic means of the log likelihood values for all post <italic>burn-in</italic> topologies following MrBayes analyses were -11,307.70 and -11,364.56, respectively. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> summarizes the results of the phylogenetic analysis. The trees inferred from the both the Bayesian and likelihood analyses were largely congruent with respect to tree topology; bootstrap support values were less than posterior probabilities at some nodes.
            </p>
            <p>The inferred phylogeny clearly indicates the hypothesized new species is not closely related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila foliata</tp:taxon-name></italic> and is placed within the somewhat enigmatic <italic>torreya</italic> species group (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bailey et al. 2010</xref>). Although its exact placement within the group as sister to a clade that includes both taxa with unbranched (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila coreyi</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and branched (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sensu lato) emboli lacks strong nodal support, its placement among taxa with divergent morphologies is strongly supported and unequivocal with respect to these data. Given the distinctiveness of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> palpal bulb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), it would be impossible to confuse the new species with other members of the <italic>torreya</italic> clade. And, these specimens clearly do not share common ancestry with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila foliata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, thus do not represent a distinct <!--PageBreak-->geographic variant of that species. Based on these molecular data coupled with the distinctive, easily diagnosable morphology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), the recognition of a new species is clearly warranted. As discussed in the Taxonomy section below, specimens incorrectly identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila foliata</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick (2007)</xref> are in need of reexamination.
            </p>
            <p>The discovery of a second species with an unbranched embolus phylogenetically “embedded” within the <italic>torreya</italic> species group further complicates the systematics of the genus and generates more questions regarding species delimitation and the nature of the<!--PageBreak--> evolution of these somewhat enigmatic palpal bulb modifications. As discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bailey et al. (2010)</xref>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic> remains a paraphyletic species with respect to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila coreyi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and now <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Solutions to resolving the conflict between the gene tree and the taxonomy of this species group include recognizing all “basal” lineages as species (speciation by remote control sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Templeton 1998</xref>) or collapsing the entire clade into a single species. Given the degree of morphological divergence contained within the lineage (sensu lato), considering the entire clade as one species is not sufficient and would overlook significant diversity. Alternatively, recognizing all of the lineages within the <italic>torreya</italic> group as species seems premature. First, as hypothesized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bailey et al. (2010)</xref> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic> paraphyly may simply reflect the rate at which genitalic change has occurred within the group as a consequence of sexual selection by female choice or sexual conflict thereby resulting in incomplete lineage sorting in the mtDNA data. The phylogeographic pattern reported here also fits with the hypothesis discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bailey et al. (2010)</xref> that branched and unbranched palpal bulb conditions always occur where congeners are sympatric. Indeed, the phylogenetic position of specimen AUMS0078 (Auburn, AL, putative <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen) seems to suggest that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> may be sympatric. However, the full extent and potential overlap of both species has not yet been thoroughly investigated. Nevertheless it does seem plausible that genitalic evolution by selection and/or as a consequence of classical character displacement could be outpacing the rate of molecular divergence. However, that hypothesis may continue to breakdown as specimens are more closely examined in light of the molecular data. The discovery of a new species coupled with the phylogenetic hypothesis further magnifies the complexities contained with the genus and may indicate that the lineages contained within the torreya clade be considered as five species. As such it seems clear that considerable work remains in terms of sampling more extensively (i.e. geographical, morphological, and molecular data); we simply lack sufficient data to properly delineate all of the species at this time. Consequently, considerable work remains if we are to gain an understanding of species boundaries and genitalic evolution within this interesting group of trapdoor spiders.
            </p>
            <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 2.</label>
                <caption><p>Preferred tree topology based on Bayesian analysis of the 12S/16S mitochondrial DNA data set. Color key and three-letter identifiers (inset) refer to species defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick 2007</xref> along with the new species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic>, described in this study and palpal bulb condition (one-pronged vs. two-pronged). Thickened black branches indicated posterior probabilities &gt; 0.95; gray branches denote values of 0.90–0.95. Numbers at nodes are bootstrap percentages from the maximum likelihood analysis conducted in RAxML.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-190-095-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Myrmekiaphila</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">tigris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1879EB33-3133-4A1A-96E5-5C2176A1AFB7</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Myrmekiaphila_tigris</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Bond &amp; Ray</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Map 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 3</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">11</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila foliata</tp:taxon-name><comment> Atkinson, 1886 (misidentification): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick 2007</xref>: 9–10.</comment>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Common name: The Auburn Tiger Trapdoor Spider">
                    <title>Common name: The Auburn Tiger Trapdoor Spider</title>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                    <title>Type material.</title>
                    <p>Male holotype (AUMS090), female paratype (AUMS089, from Alabama, Lee County, Auburn, along Grove Hill Road, forested area across from intersec<!--PageBreak-->tion with High Point Drive, 32.5786, -85.4543, 180m, coll. J. Bond 25.i.2012; additional male paratypes (AUMS077, 081–084) from same vicinity, coll. C. Ray i.2012. Male holotype and female paratype deposited in AUMNH; additional male paratypes deposited in AUMNH, AMNH and FMNH.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Additional material examined">
                    <title>Additional material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>ALABAMA: Choctaw Co.:</bold> Silas [31.7654,  -88.3290, MYR013], 19.ii.1912 (H. Smith, CUC), 1♂. <bold>Lee Co.:</bold> Opelika [32.6454.  -85.3783, MYR133], 1.i.1985 (D. Folkerts, CDF), 1♂; 3.2km S Auburn along Wire Road [32.5776, -85.5246, MYR135], 24.ii.1974 (R. Skinner, CAU), 1♂; Auburn [32.6099, -85.4808, MYR124], (AMNH), 2♀, 1 juv., [MYR127], (N. Banks, C. Baker, MCZ), 1♀, [MYR132], 10.iv.1941 (AMNH), 3♀, [MYR137], 3.iii.1968 (W. Ivey, CAU), 1♂, [MYR139], 10.v.1975 (B. Muse, CAU), 1♀, [MYR288], 1.vi.1986 (G. Mullen, CAU), 1♀; Auburn, Grove Hill subdivision, 32.5786, -85.4543 (AUMS086–088, 091, 096–115, 117–119, 121, 123–127, 130–138), 180m, xii.2011-i.2012 (C. Ray, D. Held, J. Bond, N. Garrison, AUMNH), 41♂ 2♀, 5 juv. <bold>Macon Co.:</bold> Tuskegee National Forest, Wire Road, S Interstate 85 [32.4577,  –85.6576, MYR138], 12.xii.1975 (Weatherby, Brooks, CAU), 1♀; Tuskegee National Forest, 32.4522, -85.6378 [AUMS094–095], 30.i.2012 (C. Hamilton, AUMNH),<!--PageBreak--> 2 juv. <bold>Montgomery Co.:</bold> McGus Station [MYR140], 24.x.1915 (H. Smith, CUC), 1♂. <bold>GEORGIA: Putnam Co.:</bold> no specific locality [33.3335, -83.3499, MYR040], 23.iv.1974 (W. Merrill, FSCA) 1♂; Eatonton [33.3268, -83.3885, MYR131], 18.iv.1974 (W. Merrill, FSCA), 1♂.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific epithet, the Latin name for tiger, is a noun taken in apposition and refers to the mascot of Auburn University.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Male palpal bulb morphology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 7, 8</xref>) is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila foliata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, inset) but <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens have a longer sinuous embolus with an elongate sub distal tooth. Potentially sympatric <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic> males have two-pronged bulb whereas  <!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> males have only a single prong. Males also appear to have a more robust palpal tibia with a larger retro-distal lateral ledge than in other species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 7</xref>). Females are much more difficult to definitively recognize from other species on the basis of morphological differences, however, the spermathecal base is considerably less wide than noted for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bond and Platnick 2007</xref>) and central bulb has a more elongate stalk (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 9</xref>). Also, male and female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens tend to be larger in size than recorded for closely related <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila coreyi</tp:taxon-name></italic>: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cl male&gt; 6.50, female 7.36; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila coreyi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cl male &lt; 4.50, female &lt; 6.00. Specimens are phylogenetically distinct as a monophy<!--PageBreak-->letic lineage exclusive of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila coreyi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila foliata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Known only from central Alabama and Georgia.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description of male holotype.</title>
                    <p><italic>Specimen preparation and condition</italic>. Specimen collected live from burrow, preserved in 80%. Pedipalp, leg I left side removed, stored in vial with specimen. <italic>General coloration</italic>. Carapace dark red 2.5YR 3/6; legs, chelicerae <!--PageBreak-->darker in color, dusky red 10R 3/4. Abdomen dark brown 7.5YR 3/2 with broad faint dusky stripes posteriorly dorsal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 3, 4</xref>), ventrum spinnerets pale yellow. <italic>Cephalothorax</italic>. Carapace 6.56 long, 5.63 wide, hirsute with thin black short setae, stout black bristles along fringe; surface smooth, pars cephalica elevated. Fringe, posterior margin with black bristles. Foveal groove deep, straight. Eyes only slight elevated. AER slightly procurved, PER slightly recurved. PME slightly larger in diameter than AME. Sternum moderately setose, STRl 3.72, STRw 3.35. Posterior sternal sigilla large, irregularly shaped, nearly contiguous, anterior sigilla pairs small, oval, marginal. Chelicerae with distinct anterior tooth row comprising 11 teeth, posterior margin with single row small denticles. Palpal endites with patch of small cuspules on proximal, inner margin, labium lacks cuspules, LBw 1.19, LBl 0.70. Rastellum consists of 4 stout spines on distinct mound. <italic>Abdomen</italic>. Setose, heavy black setae intermingled with fine black setae. <italic>Legs</italic>. Leg I: 5.85, 2.88, 4.25, 3.41, 2.84; leg IV: 6.00, 3.25. Light scopulae on tarsi, metatarsi legs I, II. Tarsus I with single, slightly staggered row of 9 trichobothria. Leg I spination pattern illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4, 5</xref>; TSp 12, TSr 10, TSrd 2. <italic>Pedipalp</italic>. Articles stout, lacking distinct spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">figs 6, 7</xref>). PTw 1.50, PTl 3.00, Bl 1.24. Distinct, elongate ledge on distal-retrolateral aspect tibia. Embolus stout, tapering sharply towards tip, with serrations, elongate distal tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 8</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p><bold>Variation (8).</bold> Cl 6.81–10.30, 7.56±0.41; Cw 5.40–8.08, 6.08±0.30; STRl 3.80–5.25, 4.14±0.17; STRw 3.38–4.85, 3.71±0.17; LBw 1.02–1.57, 1.21±0.07; LBl 0.56–0.70, 0.64±0.02; leg I: 5.35–8.32, 6.29±0.31; 4.60–5.75, 4.73±0.16; 3.25–4.85, 3.75±0.18; 2.88–4.20, 3.14±0.16; leg IV: 5.75–8.88, 6.52±0.35; 3.09–4.45, 3.48±0.16; PTl 3.00–4.32, 3.27±0.15; PTw 1.56–2.13, 1.68±0.07; Bl 1.20–1.60, 1.30±0.04; TSp 12–21, 15.25±1.01; TSr 10–14, 11.75±0.41; TSrd 1–2, 1.88±0.13.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description of female paratype.</title>
                    <p><italic>Specimen preparation and condition</italic>. Female collected live from burrow, preserved in same manner as male holotype. Genital plate removed, cleared in trypsin, stored in microvial with specimen. <italic>Color</italic>. Carapace dark reddish gray 2.5YR 3/1; legs, chelicerae, dark reddish brown 2.5YR 3/4. Abdomen reddish black dorsally 2.5YR 2.5/1 faint dusky bands dorsally; ventrum, spinnerets pale yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">figs 10, 11</xref>). <italic>Cephalothorax</italic>. Carapace 7.36 long, 6.38 wide, generally glabrous, few thin setae, pars cephalica elevated. Fringe lacks setae. Foveal groove deep, slightly procurved. Eye group slightly elevated on very low mound. AER slightly procurved, PER slightly recurved. PME-AME subequal in diameter. Sternum widest at coxae II/III, moderately setose, STRl 4.60, STRw 4.08. Three pairs of sternal sigilla anterior pairs moderate size, oval, positioned marginally, posterior pair larger, irregularly shaped, nearly contiguous. Chelicerae anterior tooth row armed with 10 teeth with single posterior margin denticle row. Palpal endites with 47 cuspules concentrated at the inner promargin posterior heel; labium with 5 cuspules, LBw 1.46, LBl 0.97. Rastellum consist of 10 very stout spines positioned on distinct mound. <italic>Abdomen</italic>. Moderately setose, posterior median spinnerets reduced in size. <italic>Walking legs</italic>. Anterior two pairs noticeably more slender than posterior pairs. Leg I 16.39 long. Tarsus I with single staggered row of 10 trichobothria. Legs I, II with moderately heavy scopulae on tarsi, metatarsi. PT3s 14, TB3s 9. Rudimentary preening comb on retrolateral distal<!--PageBreak--> surface, tarsus - metatarsus joint metatarsus III, IV. <italic>Spermathecae</italic>. Two simple spermathecal bulbs, moderately elongate neck, arranged on low subtriangular base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">fig. 9</xref>).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Variation">
                    <title>Variation.</title>
                    <p>Females known only from three specimens.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution and natural history.</title>
                    <p>Known from central Alabama, counties of Choctaw, Lee, Macon, and Montgomery, and the piedmont region of Georgia, Putnam County (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Map 1</xref>). The type locality comprises primarily young second growth mixed deciduous forest located at the transition from the Piedmont to Coastal Plan physiographic region. The population known from the additional material in western Alabama is located in Coastal Plain Province. Specimens were found to be presumably syntopic with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclocosmia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Antrodiaetus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ummidia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and possibly <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila torreya</tp:taxon-name></italic> (collected from the region). Male specimens were collected from swimming pools and wandering on warm, damp mornings during the months of December and January. Females were collected from 6–8 cm deep burrow, some with below-ground side chambers with a trapdoor.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Genbank accession numbers">
                    <title>Genbank accession numbers.</title>
                    <p>JQ708212–JQ708215</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Map 1.</label>
                        <caption><p>Geographic distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic>. County outlines for Alabama and Georgia are shown. Lower color inset, dotted line, shows extent of distribution map.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-190-095-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 3, 4.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. male holotype specimen in life. <bold>3</bold> oblique view <bold>4</bold> dorsal view. Scale bar = 5mm.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-190-095-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 5–9.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. male holotype and female paratype. <bold>5, 6</bold> 1<sup>st</sup> walking leg of male, left side retrolateral and prolateral view <bold>7</bold> pedipalp, retrolateral view <bold>8</bold> palpal bulb <bold>9</bold> cleared spermathecae. Scale bars = 1mm.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-190-095-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 10, 11.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. female paratype specimen in life. <bold>10</bold> oblique view <bold>11</bold> dorsal view. Scale bar = 5mm.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-190-095-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>This project was supported by NSF grant DEB 0315160 and Auburn University. We are grateful to Dr. David Held for access to his property and specimens from his swimming pool. Rebecca Godwin assisted in taking measurements. Les Goertzen suggested the specific epithet tigris.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname> <given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1886</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of some new trap-door spiders; their nests and food habits.</article-title> <source>Entomologica Americana </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>-<lpage>137</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0012744" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0012744</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brewer</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendrixson</surname> <given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny and classification of the trapdoor spider genus Myrmekiaphila: an integrative approach to evaluating taxonomic hypotheses.</article-title> <source>PLoS ONE </source> <volume>5</volume> (<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Systematics of the Californian euctenizine spider genus Apomastus (Araneae: Mygalomorphae: Cyrtaucheniidae): the relationship between molecular and morphological taxonomy.</article-title> <source>Invertebrate Systematics </source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>-<lpage>376</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/IS04008" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/IS04008</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname> <given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> A taxonomic review of the trapdoor spider genus <italic>Myrmekiaphila</italic> (Araneae, Mygalomorphae, Cyrtaucheniidae).</article-title> <source>American Museum Novitates </source> <volume>3596</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1206/0003-0082(2007)3596[1:ATROTT]2.0.CO;2" xlink:type="simple">10.1206/0003-0082(2007)3596[1:ATROTT]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedin</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> A total evidence assessment of the phylogeny of the diverse North American trapdoor spider subfamily Euctenizinae (Araneae, Mygalomorphae, Cyrtaucheniidae).</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution </source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>-<lpage>85</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2006.04.026" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ympev.2006.04.026</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stockman</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> An Integrative Method for Delimiting Cohesion Species: Finding the Population-Species Interface in a Group of Californian Trapdoor Spiders with Extreme Genetic Divergence and Geographic Structuring.</article-title> <source>Systematic Biology </source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>628</fpage>-<lpage>646</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10635150802302443" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/10635150802302443</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Funk</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omland</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Species-level paraphyly and polyphyly: Frequency, causes, and consequences, with insights from animal mitochondrial DNA.</article-title> <source>Annual Review of Ecology, Evolution and Systematics </source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>397</fpage>-<lpage>423</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.34.011802.132421" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.34.011802.132421</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gertsch</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname> <given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1936</year>)<article-title> Notes on new and rare American mygalomorph spiders.</article-title> <source>American Museum Novitates </source> <volume>884</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Molecular phylogenetics of the spider infraorder Mygalomorphae using nuclear rRNA genes (18S and 28S): Conflict and agreement with the current system of classification.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution </source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>454</fpage>-<lpage>471</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2006.05.017" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ympev.2006.05.017</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendrixson</surname> <given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Molecular phylogeny and biogeography of an ancient Holarctic lineage of mygalomorph spiders (Araneae: Antrodiaetidae: Antrodiaetus).</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution </source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>738</fpage>-<lpage>755</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2006.09.010" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ympev.2006.09.010</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees.</article-title> <source>Bioinformatics </source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>754</fpage>-<lpage>755</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/17.8.754" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/17.8.754</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maddison</surname> <given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maddison</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Mesquite: a modular system for evolutionary analysis. Version 2.7.</source> doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btg180" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/btg180</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> MrBayes 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference under mixed models.</article-title> <source>Bioinformatics </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1572</fpage>-<lpage>1574</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frati</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckenbach</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crespi</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Evolution, Weighting, and Phylogenetic Utility of Mitochondrial Gene-Sequences and a Compilation of Conserved Polymerase Chain-Reaction Primers.</article-title> <source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America  </source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>651</fpage>-<lpage>701</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stamatakis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> RAxML-VI-HPC: Maximum Likelihood-based Phylogenetic Analyses with Thousands of Taxa and Mixed Models.</article-title> <source>Bioinformatics </source> <volume>22</volume> (<issue>21</issue>): <fpage>2688</fpage>-<lpage>2690</lpage>.  doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btl446" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/bioinformatics/btl446</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stockman</surname> <given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> A taxonomic review of the trapdoor spider genus Promyrmekiaphila Schenkel (Araneae, Mygalomorphae, Cyrtaucheniidae, Euctenizinae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1823</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Templeton</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Species and speciation: geography, population structure, ecology, and gene trees</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berlocher</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Endless Forms: Species and Speciation</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
        <app-group>
        	  <app><title/>
                <sec sec-type="Appendix 1">
                    <title>Appendix 1</title>
                    <p>Locality data for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
                    </p>
                    <p><bold>Explanation note:</bold> Locality data (CSV format) for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmekiaphila tigris</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens (doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.190.3011.app1)." xlink:type="simple">10.3897/zookeys.190.3011.app1).</ext-link> File format: Microsoft Excel comma delimited.
                    </p>
                    <p><bold>Copyright notice:</bold> This dataset is made available under the Open Database License (http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/odbl/1.0/). The Open Database License (ODbL) is a license agreement intended to allow users to freely share, modify, and use this Dataset while maintaining this same freedom for others, provided that the original source and author(s) are credited.
                    </p>
                </sec>
            </app>
        </app-group>
    </back>
</article>