<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.207.3419</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Three new species of 
                    <italic>Atopsyche</italic> Banks (Trichoptera, Hydrobiosidae) from Brazil
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Santos</surname>
                        <given-names>Allan P. M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:FDBB2390-430F-4769-A3A3-E8DD1CF36EBC</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Holzenthal</surname>
                        <given-names>Ralph W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:C27A1C49-F372-4232-A49C-B8B5F753CC70</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Departamento de Zoologia, Instituto de Biologia, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, P.O. box 68044, Rio de Janeiro, RJ 21941-971, Brazil
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>CAPES Foundation, Ministry of Education of Brazil, Brasília, DF 70040-020, Brazil
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Department of Entomology, University of Minnesota, 219 Hodson Hall, 1980 Folwell Ave., St. Paul, Minnesota, 55108, USA
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Allan P. M. Santos (<email xlink:type="simple">a.santos@ufrj.br</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Christy Geraci</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>11</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>207</issue>
            <fpage>65</fpage>
            <lpage>78</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>20</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Allan P. M. Santos, Ralph W. Holzenthal</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:F391D3A7-0F39-4818-87D7-5AFD9D920C3B</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Three new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name></italic> Banks (<tp:taxon-name>Hydrobiosidae</tp:taxon-name>) from Brazil are described and illustrated: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopscyhe (Atopsaura) blahniki</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsyche) parauna</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsaura) galharada</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> Additional illustrations of the male genitalia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche urumarca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schmid are provided, including its populational variation. Also, we provide new state records for 2 species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsyche) urumarca</tp:taxon-name></italic> from São Paulo, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsaura) plancki</tp:taxon-name></italic> Marlier from Santa Catarina.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Atlantic forest</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Atopsyche</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>Brazil</kwd>
                <kwd>caddisfly</kwd>
                <kwd>Hydrobiosidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Neotropics</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name></italic> Banks constitutes the most diverse genus in the family <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobiosidae</tp:taxon-name>, with over 120 described species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Holzenthal and Cressa 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Holzenthal et al. 2007</xref>). The genus occurs from the southwestern United States to northern Argentina, but it <!--PageBreak-->is replaced by other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobiosidae</tp:taxon-name> in the Chilean subregion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Holzenthal and Cressa 2002</xref>). Schimd (1989) provided a world revision of the family <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobiosidae</tp:taxon-name>, including comments on the classification and phylogeny of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name></italic> and descriptions of several new species. Currently, 19 species are recorded from Brazil, of which only 2 were recorded after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Schmid (1989)</xref>: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche chirihuana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schmid, originally described from Ecuador; and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche erigia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ross, originally described from Mexico (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Blahnik et al. 2004</xref>).  Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Schmid (1989)</xref>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name></italic> species are divided into three subgenera, based on features of the male genitalia: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsaura</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ross, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name></italic> Banks, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dolochorema</tp:taxon-name></italic> Banks.</p>
            <p>In this paper, we describe 3 new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name></italic> from southeastern Brazil. These additional species bring the number of known caddisflies species from Brazil to 569, but many species of this and other genera remain undescribed. In addition, we illustrate variations in the male genitalia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche urumarca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schmid, and provide new state distributional records of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche urumarca</tp:taxon-name></italic> from São Paulo and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche plancki</tp:taxon-name></italic> Marlier from Santa Catarina.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Morphological terminology used in this paper follows that presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Schmid (1989)</xref>. The lactic acid method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Blahnik et al. 2007</xref>) was used for specimen preparation. Genital structures were observed and illustrated with a compound microscope, equipped with a drawing tube. Pencil sketches were scanned and placed into an Adobe Illustrator (v. 13.0.0, Adobe Systems Inc.) document to produce a digital illustration. Descriptions provided for new species were made using the software DELTA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Dallwitz et al. 1999</xref>). Holotypes are deposited in the Museu de Zoologia, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil (MZSP). Paratypes and other material examined are deposited in the MZSP and also in the University of Minnesota Insect Collection, St. Paul, Minnesota, USA (UMSP), the National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington DC, USA (NMNH), and the Coleção Entomológica Prof. José Alfredo Pinheiro Dutra, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil (DZRJ).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        (<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subgenus">Atopsaura</tp:taxon-name-part>)
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">blahniki</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:17398E47-24AC-45A6-8FEF-CF2B3A9BBFE2</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atopsyche_blahniki</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">, 4</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">, 7</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This new species is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche zernyi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Flint, also described from Brazil. Both species have an apical process on the first article of the inferior appen<!--PageBreak-->dage as long as the second article, and a phallotheca with long paired processes, apically upturned and narrow. However, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche blahniki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche zernyi</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the narrower parapod, longer filipod (exceeding length of parapod), and in the apices of the paired processes from the phallotheca, which bear several spines on their lateral edges.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Male">
                    <title>Male.</title>
                    <p>Forewing length 5.5 mm (n=1). Overall body color brown; antennal scape brown, with long brown setae, pedicel brown, basal flagellomeres yellow, apical flagellomeres brown; setae of palps yellow; frons and vertex of head with long, erect brown and whitish setae; legs yellowish brown, coxae and femora of forelegs darker brown. Forewings brown; erect setae on veins forming irregular pattern of alternate dark brown and yellow setae; apex of wing with fringe of alternating patches of dark brown and yellow setae. Forewing venation complete (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>); R1 branched; stem of fork I about twice its length; fork II long, sessile; stem of fork III equal to its length; fork IV long, sessile; stem of M almost straight between m-cu crossvein and first fork of M; fork V long, narrow; Cu2 long, converging near fused anal veins; apex of fused anal veins very short. Hind wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>) with Sc and R1 fused apically; forks I, III, and V present, the first with a short stem, the last long with a short stem, stem of fork III equal to its length; forks II and IV absent; M3+4 not reaching wing margin; Cu2 long and almost straight; 1A long and sinuate. Nygmas indistinct in both wings. Tergum II with pair of prominent glands at posterolateral margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 7A</xref>); tergum III with pair of prominent gland at anterolateral margin, lined at opening with minute setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 7A, 7B</xref>). Sternum V with pair of small, rounded glands on anterolateral margins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 7C</xref>). Sterna VI and VII with prominent spine-like ventral processes on posteromesal margins.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Male genitalia">
                    <title>Male genitalia.</title>
                    <p>Segment IX, in lateral view, long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Parapod narrow, simple, with small dorsolaterally directed tooth-like projections and short, stout setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, 1B, 1C</xref>). Filipod long, slender, with elongate setae along length, apex attenuate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Preanal appendage short, rounded, setose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, 1C</xref>). Inferior appendage, first article long, slightly widened apically, otherwise relatively narrow and of uniform width, with subtriangular apical process, nearly equaling second article in length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, 1D</xref>); second article small, with subacute apex and small rounded carina ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, 1D</xref>). Proctiger, in lateral view, broadly widened apically, with truncate apical margin, covered with minute setae, apicodorsal margin with long setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Phallic apparatus complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E, 1F</xref>); phallotheca broadly rounded basally, with narrow ventral process articulating with inferior appendages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>); posteriorly divided into long, paired processes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref>); processes apically upturned and narrow, covered with minute setae and bearing spines on lateral edges (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E, 1F</xref>); aedeagus an elongate, stout, spine-like structure, with slight ventral curvature near base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsaura) blahniki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> parapod, lateral <bold>C</bold> parapod and preanal appendage, dorsal <bold>D</bold> inferior appendage, ventral <bold>E</bold> phallic apparatus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallic apparatus, dorsal. Abbreviations: <bold>aed</bold> aedeagus <bold>fil</bold> filipod <bold>inf app</bold> inferior appendage <bold>par</bold> parapod <bold>phal</bold> phallotheca <bold>pr app</bold> preanal appendage <bold>proc</bold> proctiger <bold>IX</bold> abdominal segment IX.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-207-065-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male">
                    <title>Holotype male.</title>
                    <p><bold>BRAZIL: Rio de Janeiro:</bold> Cachoeiras de Macacu, Rio Souza, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">16°26.567'S, 42°37.957'W</named-content>, 150 m, 16.iii.1996, Holzenthal, Rochetti &amp; Oliveira (pinned) (UMSP000031906) (MZSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes">
                    <title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p><bold>BRAZIL: Rio de Janeiro:</bold> same data as holotype, 23 females (pinned) (17 females, UMSP; 2 females, NMNH; 2 females, MZSP; 2 females, DZRJ).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>This new species is named in honor of Dr. Roger Blahnik, who identified this new species.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        (<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subgenus">Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name-part>)
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">parauna</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D90947CD-CF4E-44EA-9819-D47E65CCF7F6</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atopsyche_parauna</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">, 5</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">, 8</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This new species is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche jaba</tp:taxon-name></italic> Blahnik and Gottschalk, described from Costa Rica. These two species share a similar mesal process on the first article of the inferior appendage and the complex phallotheca, with paired processes posteriorly. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche parauna</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. can be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche jaba</tp:taxon-name></italic> and other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name></italic> species by the broad parapod, in lateral view, with the dorsolateral margin serrate and with a midlateral spinose projection, whereas in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche jaba</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the parapod has 2 prominent spines. In addition, the second article of the inferior appendage is shorter and slightly hooked in the new species, and the phallotheca is posteriorly divided into 2 long, paired processes, the dorsal one birfucate apically and the ventral one curved mesally.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Male">
                    <title>Male.</title>
                    <p>Forewing length 5.0–5.5 mm (n=10). Overall body color brown; antennal scape brown, with long stramineous setae, pedicel brown, basal flagellomeres yellow, apical flagellomeres brown; setae of palps yellow; frons and vertex of head with long, erect brown and whitish setae; legs yellowish brown, coxae of all legs darker brown. Forewings brown; erect setae on veins forming distinct mottled pattern of alternate dark brown and yellow setae, with dark brown setae along costal margin; apex of wing with fringe of alternating patches of dark brown and yellow setae. Forewing venation complete (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 5A</xref>); R1 branched; stem of fork I equal to its length; fork II long, sessile; stem of fork III equal to its length; fork IV long, sessile; stem of M slightly curved between m-cu crossvein and first fork of M; fork V long, narrow; Cu2 long, converging near fused anal veins, crossvein near apex forming small cell on posterior margin of wing; apex of fused anal veins very short. Hind wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 5B</xref>) with Sc and R1 fused apically; forks I, III, and V present, the first with a short stem, the last long with a short stem, stem of fork III longer than its length; forks II and IV absent; M3+4 reaching wing margin; Cu2 long and almost straight; 1A long and strongly curved, with row of elongate setae along its length. Nygmas indistinct in both wings. Terga III and IV with pair of prominent rounded glands at anterolateral margin, lined internally with minute setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 8A</xref>). Sternum V with pair of small rounded glands on anterolateral margins, with a keel-like projection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 8B</xref>). Sterna VI and VII with prominent spine-like ventral processes on posteromesal margins.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Male genitalia">
                    <title>Male genitalia.</title>
                    <p>Segment IX, in lateral view, short (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Parapod broad, with dorsolateral margin serrate, setose, and with small, midlateral spinose projection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A, 2B</xref>). Filipod long, slender, with elongate setae along length, apex somewhat capitate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Preanal appendage short, rounded, setose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A, 2B</xref>). Inferior appendage, first article long, slightly constricted mesally, otherwise relatively narrow and of uniform width, without apical process, but mesally with small process at midlength, bearing short spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A, 2C</xref>); second article small, slightly hooked apically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A, 2C</xref>). Proctiger, in lateral view, broadly widened apically, with angulate apical mar<!--PageBreak-->gin, covered with minute setae, apicodorsal margin with long setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Phallic apparatus complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2D, 2E</xref>); phallotheca broadly rounded basally, with short rounded ventral process articulating with inferior appendages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>); posteriorly divided into two long, paired processes, dorsal one longer and bifurcate apically, ventral one curved mesally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2D, 2E</xref>); aedeagus an elongate, stout, spine-like structure, with ventral curvature near base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsyche) parauna</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> parapod and preanal appendage, dorsal <bold>C</bold> inferior appendage, ventral <bold>D</bold> phallic apparatus, lateral <bold>E</bold> phallic apparatus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-207-065-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male">
                    <title>Holotype male.</title>
                    <p><bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Rio Paraúna, 3 km S Santana do Riacho, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">19°10.986'S, 43°43.485'W</named-content>, 650 m, 11.xi.2001, Holzenthal, Paprocki, Blahnik &amp; Amarante (pinned) (UMSP000080716) (MZSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes">
                    <title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p><bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> same data as holotype, 2 males, 3 females (pinned) (UMSP); Cardeal Mota, Cachoeira Véu da Noiva, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">19°18.912'S, 43°36.260'W</named-content>, 800 m, 12.xi.2001, Holzenthal, Paprocki, Blahnik &amp; Amarante, 2 males (pinned) (DZRJ); Rio Cipó, Cachoeira de Baixo, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">19°20.553'S, 43°38.531'W</named-content>, 750 m, 10.xi.2001, Holzenthal, Paprocki, Blahnik &amp; Amarante, 3 males (pinned) (2 males, NMNH; 1 male, UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>This species is named after the river where the holotype was collected, that means “black river” in the Tupi-guarani language.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        (<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subgenus">Atopsaura</tp:taxon-name-part>)
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">galharada</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4664284A-65D7-4F52-8ADB-8E66C1EAF4C2</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atopsyche_galharada</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">, 6</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">, 9</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This is a distinctive new species in the genus, belonging to the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche longipennis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ulmer group of the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsaura</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche galharada</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche ayahuaca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schmid and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche plancki</tp:taxon-name></italic> Marlier in the absence of filipods and in the simple phallotheca. The new species can be distinguished from the others by the broader parapod with 2 carinas bearing tooth-like processes. The new species and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche plancki</tp:taxon-name></italic> are similar in the short and broad first article of the inferior appendage, with an apical process, but in the new species this process is longer and the second article of the inferior appendage is broad in ventral view, and slightly hooked in lateral view. Also, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche galharada</tp:taxon-name></italic> has the proctiger with a broad lateral sclerotized projection, and the phallotheca posteriorly divided into long, paired flangelike processes, broadest subapically, in dorsal view.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Male">
                    <title>Male.</title>
                    <p>Forewing length 6.5–7.5 mm (n=23). Overall body color brown; antennal scape light brown, with long stramineous setae, pedicel brown, basal flagellomeres yellow, apical flagellomeres brown; setae of palps dark brown; frons and vertex of head with long, erect stramineous setae; legs yellowish brown, coxae of all legs darker brown. Forewings brown; erect setae on veins forming irregular pattern of alternate dark brown and yellow setae, with dark brown setae along costal margin; apex of wing with fringe of alternating patches of dark brown and yellow setae. Forewing venation complete (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 6A</xref>); R1 branched; stem of fork I equal to its length; fork II long, sessile; stem of fork III equal in length to stem of fork I; fork IV long, sessile; stem of M slightly curved between m-cu crossvein and first fork of M; fork V long, narrow; Cu2 long, converging near fused anal veins, crossvein near apex forming small cell on posterior margin of wing; apex of fused anal veins very short. Hind wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 6B</xref>) with Sc and R1 fused apically; forks I, III, and V present, the first with a short stem, the last long with a short stem, stem of fork III equal to its length; forks II and IV absent; M3+4 reaching wing margin; Cu2 long and almost straight; 1A long and sinuate. Nygmas <!--PageBreak-->indistinct in both wings. Sternum V with pair of small rounded glands on anterolateral margins, with a keel-like projection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 9</xref>). Sterna VI and VII with prominent spine-like ventral processes on posteromesal margins.<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Male genitalia">
                    <title>Male genitalia.</title>
                    <p>Segment IX, in lateral view, long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Parapod broad basally, narrow apically, with two carinas bearing tooth-like processes along dorsolateral edges and short, stout setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A, 3B</xref>). Filipod absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Preanal appendage short, rounded, setose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A, 3B</xref>). Inferior appendage, first article short, uniformly broad, with narrow apical process, nearly equaling second article in length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A, 3C</xref>); second article large, bulging basally and downturned apically, in ventral view, broad (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A, 3C</xref>). Proctiger, in lateral view, uniformly wide, with broad lateral sclerotized projection and truncate apical margin, covered with minute setae, apicodorsal margin with long setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Phallic apparatus simple (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3D, 3E</xref>); phallotheca broadly rounded basally, not articulating with inferior appendages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>); posteriorly di<!--PageBreak-->vided into long, paired flangelike processes, broadest subapically, in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref>); aedeagus an elongate, stout, spine-like structure, with strong basal loop (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 3.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsaura) galharada</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> parapod and preanal appendage, dorsal <bold>C</bold> inferior appendage, ventral <bold>D</bold> phallic apparatus, lateral <bold>E</bold> phallic apparatus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-207-065-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 4–6.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. n. Male wing venation: Figure <bold>4</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsaura) blahniki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>4A</bold> forewing <bold>4B</bold> hind wing. Figure <bold>5</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsyche) parauna</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>5A</bold> forewing <bold>5B</bold> hind wing. Figure <bold>6</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsaura) galharada</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>6A</bold> forewing <bold>6B</bold> hind wing.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-207-065-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 7–9.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. n. Abdominal glands: Figure <bold>7</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsaura) blahniki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>7A</bold> terga II and III, lateral <bold>7B</bold> tergum III, dorsal <bold>C</bold> sternum V, lateral. Figure <bold>8</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsyche) parauna</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>8A</bold> terga III and IV, dorsal <bold>8B</bold> sternum V, ventral. Figure <bold>9</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsaura) galharada</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., sternum V, lateral.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-207-065-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male">
                    <title>Holotype male.</title>
                    <p><bold>BRAZIL: São Paulo:</bold> Campos do Jordão, Parque Estadual de Campos do Jordão, Rio Galharada, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">22°41.662'S, 45°27.783'W</named-content>, 1530 m, 4–5.iii.1996, Holzenthal &amp; Guahyba (pinned) (UMSP000031880) (MZSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes">
                    <title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p><bold>BRAZIL: São Paulo:</bold> same data as holotype, 2 females (pinned) (MZSP); same data, except 22.i.1998, Holzenthal, Froehlich &amp; Paprocki,17 females (pinned) (UMSP); same data, except 13–15.ix.2002, Blahnik, Prather, Melo, Huamantinco, 1 male, 3 females (alcohol) (UMSP); Parque Estadual de Campos do Jordão, Campo do Meio, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">22°41.750'S, 45°29.448'W</named-content>, 1500 m, 21.i.1998, Holzenthal, Froehlich &amp; Paprocki, 2 females (pinned) (UMSP); same data, except 6.iii.1996, Holzenthal &amp; Guahyba, 1 male, 2 females (pinned) (NMNH); Rio Casquilho, 3.4 km NE Parque Estadual de Campos do Jordão, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">22°40.29'S, 45°27.87'W</named-content>, 1550 m, 23.1.1998, Holzenthal, Froehlich &amp; Paprocki, 18 males, 39 females (pinned) (15 males, 34 females, UMSP; 3 males, 5 females, DZRJ); Ribeirão do Casquilho, Bosque Vermelho, ca. 5 km Parque Estadual de Campos do Jordão, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">22°40'S, 45°27.5'W</named-content>, 1435 m, 16.ix.2002, Blahnik, Prather, Melo &amp; Huamantinco, 3 males (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>This species is named after the river where holotype was collected.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        (<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subgenus">Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name-part>)
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">urumarca</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atopsyche_urumarca</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">Schmid</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 10</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsaura) urumarca</tp:taxon-name><comment> Schmid, 1989: 131 [type locality: Brazil, Serra do Cipó, Rio Capivara; MZSP; male].</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche urumarca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schmid was described from Minas Gerais state, Brazil, and placed in the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche bolivari</tp:taxon-name></italic> Banks group. According to Schimid (1989), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche urumarca</tp:taxon-name></italic> is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche pachacutec</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schmid, especially in the form of the parapod and the apex of the phallotheca, but they differ in the structure of the second article of the inferior appendage. We have examined material from southeastern Brazil, including the type locality, and we found an interesting populational variation in the male genitalia structure. This variation is noticeable in the shape of the parapod and the apex of phallotheca. In all specimens, the parapod, in lateral view, is broad basally, with an oblique, mesal U-shaped incision, but this incision is deepest in specimens collected in Ipoema, Minas Gerais state, and shallow in specimens from São Paulo state; the parapod also can end in a narrow and rounded apex or bear a small, dorsal spine. The phallotheca is broadly rounded basally, with 3 paired processes posteriorly, the dorsal one long and broad, with small dorsal and ventral projections at its apex. Some specimens have a small, additional spine-like process on the posterior margin of this dorsal process, and the ventral margin can be rounded, slightly pointed, or pointed and hooked apically.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 10.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsyche) urumarca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schmd. Variation in male genitalia. <bold>A</bold> lateral, specimen from Ipoema, Minas Gerais <bold>B–D</bold> parapod, lateral <bold>B</bold> specimen from Serra do Cipó, Minas Gerais <bold>C</bold> specimen from Morro do Pilar, Minas Gerais <bold>D</bold> specimen from Altinópolis, São Paulo <bold>E–G</bold> phallic apparatus, lateral <bold>E</bold> specimen from Ipoema <bold>F</bold> specimen from Morro do Pilar <bold>G</bold> specimen from Altinópolis.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-207-065-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Serra do Cipó, Rio Capivara, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">19°20.553'S, 43°38.531'W</named-content>, 950 m, 11.ii.1998, Holzenthal &amp; Paprocki, 2 males (pinned) (UMSP); Serra do Cipó, trib. to Rio Capivara, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">19°14.396'S, 43°34.939'W</named-content>, 1000 m, 18.ii.1998, Holzenthal &amp; Paprocki, 3 males (pinned) (MZSP); Rio Tanque, ca. 12 km (rd) from Ipoema, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">19°32.208'S, 43°26.878'W</named-content>, 750 m, 16.v.1998, Holzenthal &amp; Paprocki, 2 males, 1 female (pinned) (DZRJ); Rio Santo Antônio, downstream from Morro do Pilar, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">19°08.134'S, 43°21.256'W</named-content>, 530 m, 17.x.2000, Paprocki &amp; Ferreira, 1 male (pinned) (UMSP); P.E. de São Gonçalo do Rio Preto, Rio Preto, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">18°07.841'S, 43°20.246'W</named-content>, 791 m, 12.x.2000, Paprocki, Amarante, Sal<!--PageBreak-->gado, 1 male (alcohol) (UMSP); <bold>São Paulo:</bold> Altinópolis, Cachoeira dos Macacos, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">20°55.390'S, 47°22.758'W</named-content>, 758 m, 18.xi.2003, Holzenthal, Paprocki &amp; Calor, 27 males, 15 females (pinned) (UMSP), 9 males, 1 female (alcohol) (DZRJ); Altinópolis, Fazenda São João da Mata, Rio Baguassu, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">21°00.588'S, 47°28.900'W</named-content>, 745 m, 19–21.xi.2003, Holzenthal, Paprocki &amp; Calor, 8 male, 17 females (pinned) (3 males, 5 females, NMNH; 5 males, 12 females, UMSP), 28 males (alcohol) (UMSP); Pedregulho, Sítio Bruninho, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">20°09.240'S, 47°30.704'W</named-content>, 630 m, 17.xi.2003, Holzenthal, Paprocki &amp; Calor, 1 male, 1 female (pinned) (UMSP); Pedregulho, Ribeirão São Pedro, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">20°09.113'S, 47°30.626'W</named-content>, 617 m, 16.ix.2003, Holzenthal, Paprocki, Calor, 1 male (alcohol) (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atopsyche</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        (<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subgenus">Atopsaura</tp:taxon-name-part>)
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">plancki</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atopsyche_plancki</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Marlier</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atopsyche (Atopsaura) plancki</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Marlier 1964</xref>: 2 [type locality: Brazil, São Paulo; IRSNB; male] - <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Blahnik et al. 2004</xref>: 4 [distribution; Brazil: Minas Gerais and Rio de Janeiro states]</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>BRAZIL: Santa Catarina:</bold> Parque Ecológico Spitzkopf, confl. Rio Ouro &amp; Rio Caeté, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">27°00.352'S, 49°06.693'W</named-content>, 140 m, 25.xi.2003, Holzenthal, Paprocki, Calor, 1 male (alcohol) (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>We are grateful to Dr. Roger Blahnik for assistance in the laboratory and important comments on this manuscript. We also are grateful to Adolfo Calor, Adriano Melo, Claudio Froehlich, and Henrique Paprocki for field assistance. APMS was supported by fellowship (PDSE 0085/12-0) from CAPES Foundation (Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior), Ministry of Education of Brazil. This material is based on work supported by National Science Foundation grant no. DEB 9971885.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blahnik</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paprocki</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> New distributional and species records of Trichoptera from southern and southeastern Brazil.</article-title> <source>Biota Neotropica </source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blahnik</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prather</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> The lactic acid method for clearing Trichoptera genitalia.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bueno-Soria</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barba-Alvarez</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Proceedings of the XIIth International Symposium on Trichoptera.</issue-title> <source>The Caddis Press, Columbus, Ohio</source>: <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dallwitz</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paine</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zurcher</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> User’s guide to the DELTA Editor. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://deltaintkey.com/">http://deltaintkey.com/</ext-link>  [accessed 4 May 2012]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flint</surname> <given-names>OS Jr</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> Studies of Neotropical caddisflies, X: <italic>Leucotrichia</italic> and related genera from North and Central America (Trichoptera: Hydroptilidae).</article-title> <source>Smithsonian Contributions to Zoology </source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5479/si.00810282.60">10.5479/si.00810282.60</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cressa</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> The Trichoptera, caddisflies, of Venezuela: three new species and records of <italic>Atopsyche</italic> Banks (Hydrobiosidae).</article-title> <source>Studies on Neotropical Fauna and Environment </source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>-<lpage>143</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1076/snfe.37.2.133.8578">10.1076/snfe.37.2.133.8578</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blahnik</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prather</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjer</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Order Trichoptera Kirby, 1813 (Insecta), Caddisflies.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1668</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>-<lpage>698</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Marlier</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<article-title> Sur trois Trichopteres nouveaux recueillis en Amerique du Sud par le Professeur J. Illies.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de l’Institut Royal des Sciences Naturelles de Belgique </source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<source> Les Hydrobiosides (Trichoptera, Annulipalpia). Bulletin de l’Institut Royal des Sciences Naturelles de Belgique 59 (supplement): 1–54.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>