<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.71.788</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
               Revision of the key characters for the Thricops nigrifrons species-group (Diptera, Muscidae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western"> 
                        <surname>Vikhrev</surname>
                        <given-names>Nikita</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"></xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>Zoological Museum of Moscow University, Bolshaya Nikitskaya 6, Moscow, 125009, Russia (ZMMU)</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Nikita Vikhrev (<email xlink:type="simple">hydrophorus@rambler.ru</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Martin Hauser</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>14</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>71</issue>
            <fpage>15</fpage>
            <lpage>22</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>24</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>8</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Nikita Vikhrev</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>An analysis of key characters for the separation of <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Muscidae</tp:taxon-name>) is given. A revised key for <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> and related species, including two species recently described from the Caucasus, is proposed.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><italic>Thricops nigrifrons</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Thricops longipes</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>Muscidae</kwd>
                <kwd>key</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> species-group is characterized by: long-plumose arista; dark body; holoptic head in male; absence of apical spur on <italic>t3</italic> and of apical spurs on <italic>t1</italic> in males; <italic>t2</italic> without <italic>pv</italic> or <italic>v</italic> seta(e); lower margin of face not projecting; 4 postsutural <italic>dc</italic>; unmodified fore tarsomeres in male; mid tarsomeres 3–4 each with a row of pale <italic>pv</italic> setulae in male (except <tp:taxon-name>Thricops dawkinsi</tp:taxon-name>); the male terminalia are similar (<tp:taxon-name>Thricops semicinereus</tp:taxon-name> - type).</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> (Robineau-Desvoidy, 1830) and <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> (Zetterstedt, 1845) are widespread in the Palearctic region. Nevertheless <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Hennig (1962)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">d’Assis-Fonseca (1968)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Gregor et al. (2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Savage (2003)</xref> have given different and often contradictory recommendations on how to separate these species. Recently two new related species have been described from the Russian Caucasus, <tp:taxon-name>Thricops tomkovichi</tp:taxon-name> Vikhrev, 2009 and <tp:taxon-name>Thricops dawkinsi</tp:taxon-name> Vikhrev, 2009 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Vikhrev and Sorokina 2009</xref>), and this has necessitated a revision of the characters for the separationof <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p><!--PageBreak-->The examined material is restricted to Eastern Europe, Transcaucasian region and Siberia, and do not include specimens collected in Western Europe. However, the proposed key characters are expected to be suitable for west-european specimens as well, because there is no gap in natural habitats of <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> in Europe. Another reason is the fact that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">d’Assis-Fonseca (1968)</xref> came to the same main conclusions based on the investigation of the material from British Islands.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>This analysis is based on the following material:</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Thricops dawkinsi</tp:taxon-name> Vikhrev, 2009 – 23 ♂♂ and ♀♀. <bold>Russia</bold>:Karachay-Cherkessia, Krasnodar, North Ossetia. Holotype in Zoological Museum of Moscow University, Moscow, (ZMMU), paratypes in ZMMU, Zoological Institute, St. Petersburg (ZIN), and the Natural History Museum, London (BMNH).</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> (Zetterstedt, 1845) – 140 ♂♂ and ♀♀. <bold>Estonia. Russia (European)</bold>: Arkhangelsk, Chelyabinsk, Karachay-Cherkessia, Karelia, Komi, Krasnodar, Moscow, Murmansk, Novgorod, St-Petersburg, Ulyanovsk. <bold>Russia (Asian)</bold>: Altai Rep (=Gorno-Altai), Khanty-Mansi, Krasnoyarsk, Novosibirsk, Tomsk, Yamalo-Nenets (ZMMU and ZIN).</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> (Robineau-Desvoidy 1830) – 150 ♂♂ and ♀♀. <bold>Estonia. Turkey:</bold> Bolu prov. <bold>Russia (European)</bold>: Chelyabinsk, Moscow, St Petersburg, Vladimir, Yaroslavl. <bold>Russia (Asian):</bold> Krasnoyarsk, Novosibirsk, Tomsk (ZMMU and ZIN).</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Thricops tomkovichi</tp:taxon-name> Vikhrev, 2009 – 62 ♂♂ and ♀♀. <bold>Russia</bold>:Karachay-Cherkessia, Krasnodar. Holotype in (ZMMU), paratypes in ZMMU, ZIN and BMNH.</p>
            <p>Morphological structures are abbreviated as: <italic>f1</italic>, <italic>t1</italic>, <italic>f2</italic>, <italic>t2</italic>, <italic>f3</italic>, <italic>t3</italic> = fore, mid, hind, femur or tibia; <italic>ac</italic> = acrostichal setae; <italic>dc</italic> = dorsocentral setae; <italic>a</italic>, <italic>p</italic>, <italic>d</italic>, <italic>v</italic> = anterior, posterior, dorsal, ventral seta(e).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Notes on the identification of Thricops nigrifrons and Thricops longipes"><title>Notes on the identification of <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></title>
            <p>On several occasions colleagues have expressed doubts that <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> could be reliably separated from <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name>. I have shared these doubts too, but currently I am convinced that a reliable (and rather easy) separation is possible. Let us first consider the identification characters proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Hennig (1962)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">d’Assis-Fonseca (1968)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Gregor et al. (2002)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Savage (2003)</xref>.</p>
            <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The longest aristal hairs distinctly longer than width of postpedicel</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The longest aristal hairs slightly longer than width of postpedicel</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This character was used as the main one by all the cited authors except for <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Gregor et al. (2002)</xref>, although the estimation of length and wording differ. <!--PageBreak--></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I agree that the aristal hairs are somewhat longer in <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name>, but I disagree with using this as the main character: the difference is very fine and the character is variable, with overlapping taking place. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Gregor et al. (2002)</xref> gave the following measurements: <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> – longest aristal hairs 1.05–1.30 times as long as width of postpedicel; <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> – 0,85–1.15 times. Instead of the length of aristal hairs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Gregor et al. (2002)</xref> proposed the following wording:</td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female: long aristal hairs reaching apical third of arista</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female: long aristal hairs not reaching apical third of arista</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I have not found this alternative to be more reliable or easier in use than the previous one.</td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male: upper frons with several proclinate setulae</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male: upper frons with all setulae reclinate</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Hennig (1962)</xref>, used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Gregor et al. (2002)</xref> as the only character for males, used as the main character by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Savage (2003)</xref>. I agree with this character, but these upper frontal setulae are fine and often partly or even completely broken, especially in specimens mounted from alcohol.</td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male with <italic>p</italic> and <italic>v</italic> setulose hairs on basal half of <italic>f3</italic> hardly longer than depth of femur</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male with <italic>p</italic> and <italic>v</italic> setulose hairs on basal half of <italic>f3</italic> quite twice as long as depth of femur</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">d’Assis-Fonseca (1968)</xref>, but the other authors excluded this character from their keys. According to the descriptions given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Savage (2003)</xref>: in <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> “<italic>f3</italic> … <italic>p</italic> and <italic>v</italic> surfaces covered with long hairs, longer than depth of femur”; in <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> “<italic>f3</italic> … <italic>p</italic> and <italic>v</italic> surfaces covered with setae of variable length, as long to much longer than depth of femur”. I suppose that the source of the misunderstanding is that the fine hairs on the <italic>p</italic> and <italic>v</italic> surface of <italic>f3</italic> are not homogeneous. In <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name>, these hairs really are evenly long, at least twice as long as femoral width, but in <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> the hairs on the <italic>p</italic> surface are rather long, usually about 1–1.5 times as long as femoral width, but on the <italic>v</italic> surface they are short, especially in basal half of femur where the hairs are 0.5–1 times as long as femoral width. Thus, the fine hairs on <italic>f3</italic> are distinctly longer in <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> than in <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name>, but the difference is the most obvious in a comparison of the <italic>v</italic> hairs in the basal half of <italic>f3</italic>, for which the hind femur needs only to be observed in lateral view. Among about 150 male specimens examined by me, this character was always reliable and correlated with other characters. No specimens with an intermediate development of <italic>f3</italic> setulae were found.</td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male <italic>t3</italic> with <italic>pv</italic> present in apical 1/2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male <italic>t3</italic> with <italic>pv</italic> present in apical 2/3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Hennig (1962)</xref>, but excluded by later authors. I agree with the exclusion of this variable character.</td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male notopleuron bare</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male notopleuron with a few setulae</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Savage (2003)</xref>. In fact the notopleuron is setulose on the anterior part in both species. The notopleuron on the surface between the anterior and posterior setae is almost always bare in <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> and usually setulose in <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name>, but bare in a quarter of the examined specimens. This may be used as an additional character only.</td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male: posterior part of scutum in posterior view densely dusted, without median vitta, with a pair of subshining narrow submedian vittae laterad to <italic>dc</italic> rows</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male: posterior part of scutum in posterior view mostly shining black, with a wide black median vitta</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Vikhrev and Sorokina (2009)</xref>, this character separates all examined specimens.</td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male abdomen with the median vitta on tergite 3 inconspicuous</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male abdomen with a conspicuous black median vitta on tergite 3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Vikhrev and Sorokina (2009)</xref>. The trace of a narrow and less dusted median vitta may be present in <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name>, but otherwise this character separates all examined specimens.</td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male body length usually 7–7.5 mm, rarely 6–8 mm</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male body length usually 8.5–9 mm, rarely 6.5–9.5 mm</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female body length usually 6.5–7.5 mm</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female body length usually 7.5–9 mm</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In spite of rare cases of overlapping, this character is at least as reliable as, and much easier to use than the width of the aristal hairs. The body size difference was also mentioned by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Hennig (1962)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Savage (2003)</xref>. It should be noted that this character works for the forest zone where both species are present, but not for the extreme northern populations of <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> from the tundra zone, where <italic>nigrifons</italic> has not been recorded. Specimens collected near Vorkuta (67.5°N) have a body size 6–8 mm only.</td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female: postsutural part of scutum in posterior view with the median vitta indistinct, or if more or less distinct then narrow, widened only posteriorly</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female: postsutural part of scutum in posterior view with the undusted median vitta distinct, uniformly wide throughout, occupying all the area between acrostichal rows</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">d’Assis-Fonseca (1968)</xref>, but with a misprint, so the indistinct vitta was wrongly ascribed to <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> and the distinct one to <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name>. Probably because of this, no one else has drawn attention to this reliable character, which separates all the females I have examined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
							        
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female abdomen with the median stripe narrow, often absent</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female abdomen with a broad median stripe</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Again proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">d’Assis-Fonseca (1968)</xref>, and again with the characters for <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> transposed. Usually present in <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name>, present or absent in <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name>. I think it is better to exclude this character.</td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female: <italic>t3</italic> with only 2 <italic>ad</italic> setae</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female: <italic>t3</italic> with 3–4 <italic>ad</italic> setae</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Hennig (1962)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Savage (2003)</xref>. Correct in the vast majority of specimens.</td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female: dusting on thorax and abdomen yellow with a slight brown tint</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female: dusting on thorax and abdomen grey with a slight yellow tint</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
											
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Savage (2003)</xref>. I agree that usually <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> has more yellowish dusting while <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> is more greyish, but the reverse situation may also occur. Personally I find this character difficult to use and prefer not to include it in the key.</td>
                        </tr>                    

                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
								<fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
									<label>Figure 1.</label>
								    <caption><p>Female scutum in posterior view. <bold>a</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> without median vitta <bold>b</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> with narrow median vitta <bold>c</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name>.</p></caption>
								    <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/603/supp/ZooKeys-071-015-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
								</fig>
            <sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution</title>
                <p> The distribution of these species in mountain areas seems sporadic and there aren’t enough reliable records. In the Austrian Alps, in the Oetz Valley, both species overlap at about 1500 m asl. Below this level, in the coniferous and broad-leaf for<!--PageBreak-->est zone, <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> is found; above it, in the upper forest zone and above the tree-line, only <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> is found (A.C. Pont, pers. comm.). In the Russian Caucasus (Krasnodarsky Kray and Karachay-Cherkessia) <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> is found at the altitudes 1800–2500 m asl., while <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> is not found. In the mountain area in Turkey, Bolu prov., 40.6N 31.8E <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> is found at the altitudes 1450–1950 m asl., while <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> is not found. In European Russia <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> is common in the area between Moscow and St. Petersburg (55–60°N), but absent or at least rare in Karelia at 65°N. The southern border of distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> seems to be the northern part of Moscow region (56°N), it is common in the northern coniferous forest zone (taiga) and is still the dominant species in the tundra around Vorkuta (67.5°N). In Abisko National Park (North Sweden, 68°N), with birch forest and mountain tundra (A.C. Pont, pers. comm.) and in birch-willow forest in Murmansk (69°N) only <tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> was found.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Key for the Thricops nigrifrons species-group"><title>Key for the <tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> species-group</title>
                <sec sec-type="Males"><title>Males</title>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
							
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>f2</italic> with a comb of 3–4 long and strong setae on <italic>p-pv</italic> surface at base and the fine setae in <italic>av</italic> and <italic>pv</italic> rows 1.5–2 times as long as <italic>f2</italic> width. Legs at least partly yellowish (tibiae) or both tibiae and femora yellow. <italic>t3</italic> with a comb of ventral consisting of 3–4 long curved setae. Caucasus</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
							
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>f2</italic> without such a comb of setae on <italic>p-pv</italic> surface at base and the setae in <italic>pv</italic> and <italic>av</italic> rows short, at most as long as femoral width. Legs entirely black. <italic>t3</italic> with 1–2 shorter ventral preapical setae. Palearctic, including Transcaucasian region</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
							
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Femora black, tibiae more or less darkened basally. Mid tarsomeres 3–4 each with a row of pale <italic>pv</italic> setulae. Fore tarsus on <italic>p</italic>-surface with fine hairs that are 1.5 times as long as tarsal width</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops tomkovichi</tp:taxon-name> Vikhrev</td>
                                </tr>
							
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All femora and tibiae yellow, at most fore femur slightly darkened. Mid tarsomeres 3–4 each with the row of pale <italic>pv</italic> setulae reduced. Fore tarsus with the <italic>p</italic>-hairs not longer than tarsal width</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops dawkinsi</tp:taxon-name> Vikhrev</td>
                                </tr>
							
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In lateral view, <italic>f3</italic> on basal half with fine hairs on <italic>v</italic> surface at most as long as femoral width, much shorter than the strong <italic>av</italic> setae (the hairs on <italic>p</italic> surface at most 1.5 times as long as femoral width). In posterior view postsutural part of scutum densely yellowish-grey dusted without a median vitta between acrostichals (a pair of vittae present laterad to <italic>dc</italic> rows). Abdomen with the median vitta on tergite 3 inconspicuous, at most a narrow trace of a vitta present. Frons with both pro- and reclinate setulae on upper half. Secondary characters: body length usually 7–7.5 mm, rarely 6–8 mm; ground setulae absent between the two notopleural bristles, longest aristal hairs 1.05–1.30 times as long as width of postpedicel</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> (Robineau-Desvoidy)</td>
                                </tr>
							
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In lateral view, <italic>f3</italic> on basal half with fine hairs on <italic>v</italic> surface about twice as long as femoral width, about as long as the strong <italic>av</italic> setae (these hairs on <italic>p</italic> surface<!--PageBreak--> at least twice as long as femoral width). In posterior view, postsutural part of scutum subshining black with only thin greyish dusting, consisting of two vittae restricted to areas between <italic>ac</italic> rows and slightly beyond <italic>dc</italic> rows, median vitta between <italic>ac</italic> rows always present. Abdomen with a black subshining median vitta on tergite 3 wide and distinct on at least anterior 2/3 of tergite. Frons with all setulae on upper half reclinate. Secondary characters: body length usually 8.5–9 mm, rarely 7.5–9.5 mm, ground setulae usually (in 75% specimens) present between the two notopleural bristles, longest aristal hairs 0.85–1.15 times as long as width of postpedicel</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> (Zetterstedt)</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </sec>
                <sec sec-type="Females"><title>Females</title>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
							
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Legs entirely black. Palearctic, including Transcaucasian region</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
							
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Legs partly or entirely yellow. Caucasus</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
							
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postsutural part of scutum in posterior view with the median vitta indistinct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>), or if more or less distinct then narrow, sometimes slightly widened posteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). <italic>t3</italic> with only 2 <italic>ad</italic> setae. Longest aristal hairs 1.05–1.30 times as long as width of postpedicel. Body length usually 6.5–7.5 mm</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops nigrifrons</tp:taxon-name> (Robineau-Desvoidy)</td>
                                </tr>
							
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postsutural part of scutum in posterior view with the undusted median vitta distinct, uniformly wide throughout, occupying all the area between <italic>ac</italic> rows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>). <italic>t3</italic> with 3–4 <italic>ad</italic> setae, the additional seta(e) often short. Longest aristal hairs 0.85–1.15 times as long as width of postpedicel. Body length usually 7.5–9 mm</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops longipes</tp:taxon-name> (Zetterstedt)</td>
                                </tr>
							
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Femora black, tibiae darkened basally</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops tomkovichi</tp:taxon-name> Vikhrev</td>
                                </tr>
							
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Femora and tibiae yellow</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Thricops dawkinsi</tp:taxon-name> Vikhrev</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </sec>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>I thank Oleg Kosterin (Novosibirsk), Adrian C. Pont (Oxford) and Andrey Ozerov (Moscow) who suggested several very useful corrections.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>d’Assis-Fonseca</surname><given-names>ECM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> Diptera Cyclorrhapha Calyptrata, Muscidae</article-title>. <source>Handbook for the Identification of British Insects 10, 4(b)</source>. <publisher-name>Royal Entomological Society</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>118</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregor</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rozkosny</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanhara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> The Muscidae (Diptera) of Central Europe.</article-title> <source>Folia Facultatis Scientiarum Naturalium Universitatis Masarykianae Brunensis, Biologia</source> <volume>107</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>280</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hennig</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1955–1964</year>) <article-title>Family Muscidae</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Die Fliegen der Palaearktischen Region 63b</source>. <publisher-name>E. Schweizerbart</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Stuttgart</publisher-loc>, <lpage>1110</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Revision of the genus Thricops Rondani (Diptera: Muscidae).</article-title> <source>Insect Systematics and Evolution Supplement</source> <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>143</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vikhrev</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorokina</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Faunistic records of Thricops Rondani (Diptera, Muscidae) from Russia with description of two new species.</article-title> <source>Euroasian Entomological Journal</source> <volume>8</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>341</fpage>-<lpage>350</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>