<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
<front>
		<journal-meta>
			<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
			<issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
			<issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
		</journal-meta>

<article-meta>
	<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.50.506</article-id>

	<title-group>
		<article-title>Parisognoriste, a new genus of Lygistorrhinidae (Diptera: Sciaroidea) from the Oise amber with redescription of Palaeognoriste Meunier
		</article-title>
	</title-group>
	
	<contrib-group>
	<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
	<surname>Blagoderov</surname>
	<given-names>Vladimir</given-names>
</name>
<aff>Department of Entomology, The Natural History Museum, Cromwell Road, London, SW7 5BD, UK</aff>
<uri content-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:EE802420-57F5-4285-89B3-282AB9F69894</uri>
	</contrib>
	<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
	<surname>Hippa</surname>
	<given-names>Heikki</given-names>
</name>
<aff>Swedish Museum of Natural History, P.O.Box 50007, S-10405 Stockholm, Sweden</aff>
<uri content-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:546524AD-3BD1-4830-842F-EEEE7DF4799B</uri>
	</contrib>
	<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
	<surname>Nel</surname>
	<given-names>André</given-names>
</name>
<aff>CNRS-UMR 7205, Entomologie, Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, 45 rue Buffon, F-75005 Paris, France</aff>
<uri content-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:98DF555A-16A0-4073-871C-E38BB506C676</uri>
	</contrib>
	</contrib-group>

<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="corresp"><p>Corresponding author: Vladimir Blagoderov (<email>v.blagoderov@nhm.ac.uk</email>).</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Academic editor: Chris Thompson</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
	<day>30</day>
	<month>6</month>
	<year>2010</year>
</pub-date>
<issue>50</issue>
<fpage>79</fpage>
<lpage>90</lpage>
<history>
	<date date-type="received">
		<day>1</day>
		<month>6</month>
		<year>2010</year>
	</date>
	<date date-type="accepted">
		<day>8</day>
		<month>6</month>
		<year>2010</year>
	</date>
</history>
<permissions>
	<copyright-statement>Copyright Vladimir Blagoderov et al.</copyright-statement>
	<license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
	</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:D3D0A515-1A8F-4F50-804D-B73DA4005731</self-uri>

<abstract>
	<label>Abstract</label>
	<p>A new genus and a new species of <tp:taxon-name>Lygistorrhinidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">eocenica</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> is described from the Eocene Oise amber of the Paris Basin. <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sciariforme</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> Meunier, 1904 and <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> Meunier, 1912 are re-described. Lectotypes are designated for both species of <tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name>. The phylogenetic positions of the new genus and <tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name> Meunier are discussed. The paper is an example demonstrating a new approach in cybertaxonomy including automatic generation of manuscript within Virtual Research Environment (Scratchpads), semantic enhancements, and parallel release of the publication on paper and on-line accompanied with registration of new taxa with ZooBank.</p></abstract>
	
	
	<kwd-group>
		<label>Keywords</label>
		<kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
		<kwd>new taxa</kwd>
		<kwd>phylogeny</kwd>
		<kwd>fossil resin</kwd>
		<kwd>Eocene</kwd>
	</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
		
	<body>
		<sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
			<p>The Le Quesnoy locality, near Houdancourt (Oise), has yielded fossiliferous amber associated with abundant plant remains and a diverse vertebrate fauna in sediments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Nel <!--PageBreak-->et al. 2004</xref>). Its age is lowermost Eocene and the infrared spectra (KBr) of Le Quesnoy and Baltic ambers are very different, with that of the former more similar to the Recent <tp:taxon-name>Hymenaea</tp:taxon-name> copal. Only a small fraction of the insect genera and even fewer species of the Oise amber (also known sometimes as Paris Basin amber) are also present in Baltic amber (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Nel et al. 2005</xref>). The palaeoclimate of Oise amber corresponds to the maximum global warming of the Palaeocene-Eocene boundary, which could partly explain the differences of it's fauna from the fauna of Baltic amber.</p>
			<p>A number of specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Sciaroidea</tp:taxon-name> were discovered in the Oise amber, of which perhaps the most interesting are several specimens of a lygistorrhinid fly. The purpose of the present paper is to describe this new taxon and discuss its systematic position. Superficially, it is similar to <tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name> Meunier, the two species of which were described from Baltic amber in the early 20th century. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Meunier (1904)</xref> described the first, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sciariforme</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, from the Königsberg collection of Baltic amber, based on a male and a female found in two separate pieces of amber, and erected a new genus, <tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name>, to accommodate it. Later, he described another species, <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, based on two specimens found in copula in a single piece of amber (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Meunier 1912</xref>). Unfortunately, both descriptions were very short and vague. To adequately describe the new genus from the Oise amber and to compare it with known fossil and recent taxa it was necessary to re-describe both species of <tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name> and designate lectotypes for both species.</p></sec>
			
		<sec sec-type="Material and methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
			<p>The piece of Oise amber containing three female specimens of the new species was cut in two for better observation and polished on a slab of diatomite. Type material of both species of <tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name> was also studied. Fortunately, the specimens were not lost during World War II, as many of Meunier’s other types were. The type of <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> was kept in Geowissenschaftlisches Zentrum der Georg-August-Universität, Göttingen. In 2007, VB found syntypes of <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sciariforme</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> in the Laboratory of Entomology, Muséum national d'Histoire naturelle, Paris, where they had been borrowed by the late Prof. L. Matile several years previously. Digital photography was undertaken using Zeiss Axioskop compound microscope and Canon EOS450D camera, the resulting images then being combined to increase depth of field using Helicon Focus v. 4.77 software. All images are available at Fungus Gnats Online website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciaroidea.info">www.sciaroidea.info</ext-link>).</p>
			<p>The descriptions of new taxa and redescription of known species were prepared on the Fungus Gnats Online Scratchpad as an initial stage of testing online taxonomic workflow as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Blagoderov et al. (2010)</xref>. The paper has been semantically tagged and enhanced using the Pensoft Mark Up Tool (PMT) which is based on the US National Library of Medicine’s DTD (Document Type Definitions) TaxPub extension (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/taxpub">http://sourceforge.net/projects/taxpub</ext-link>). The final XML output of the paper has been archived in PubMedCentral, a PDF uploaded in the Biodiversity Heritage Library (BHL), and all revised species registered in ZooBank (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Penev et al. 2010</xref>).</p></sec>
			
			
			


<!--PageBreak--><sec sec-type="Systematics">
	<title>Systematics</title>

<tp:taxon-treatment>
<tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name>Parisognoriste<object-id object-id-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D95A5DF3-9A27-474D-A504-AE90BD99F388</object-id></tp:taxon-name> <tp:taxon-status>gen. n.</tp:taxon-status></tp:nomenclature>
	
	<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title>
		<p> <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">eocenica</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, sp. n.</p></tp:treatment-sec>
		
		<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnostic description"><title>Diagnostic description.</title>
		<p> Small lygistorrhinid flies. Proboscis small, about 1/3 of the height of head, palpus four-segmented, much longer than proboscis. Ocelli three, median ocellus smaller than the lateral ocelli. Scutum moderately convex, laterotergite bare. Vestiture of tibiae in rows on apical part. Outer tibial spurs 2 and 3 shorter than inner. Hind leg much longer that fore and mid leg, but its tibia and tarsus only slightly expanded. Wing membrane without macrotrichia. Sc joining C. R1 short, approximately half of wing length. Rs distinct. Crossvein m-cu present, aligned with r-m. M1 and M2 fork base and M stem weak or reduced. M3+4 and CuA without a common stem. R1 setose, Sc, R5, M, and CuA bare.</p></tp:treatment-sec>
		
		<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
			<p> The genus name is compound word formed from parisos (Greek πάρǐσος, almost equal, just alike) and the genus name <tp:taxon-name>Gnoriste</tp:taxon-name>. The name is feminine.</p></tp:treatment-sec>
			
		<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion.</title>
		<p><tp:taxon-name>Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name> resembles <tp:taxon-name>Archaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name> from the Upper Cretaceous Burmese amber, but the latter has palpi longer than head height, frons membranous, all longitudinal wing veins setose, Sc ending free, R1 longer than half wing length, M stem and base of M1 and M2 fork distinct and the tibial spurs of equal length. <tp:taxon-name>Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name> is similar to <tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name> Meunier but the latter has a long proboscis, one-segmented palpus and club-shaped hind tibia (see also under Phylogenetic analysis).</p></tp:treatment-sec>
		
		
		<tp:taxon-treatment>
		<tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">eocenica</tp:taxon-name-part><object-id object-id-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FCFCCA94-9A88-4860-BF47-BBA30B83F761</object-id></tp:taxon-name> <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status></tp:nomenclature>
			
			<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined. </title>
			<p>Holotype: complete inclusion of female in transparent fossil resin, Oise amber, deposited in the Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle, Paris: MNHN A32914 (PA876).</p>
			<p>Type locality: France: Oise department: region of Creil, Chevrière, farm Le Quesnoy, 49°19.533'N, 2°40.833'E. Geological horizon: the lowermost Eocene, in amber, c. -53 My, Sparnacian, level MP7 of the mammal fauna of Dormaal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Nel et al. 2004</xref>).</p>
			<p>Paratypes: two inclusions of females in the same piece of amber (during preparation the piece was cut into two), deposited in the Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle, Paris: MNHN A32914 (PA876).</p></tp:treatment-sec>
			
			<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Morphology"><title>Morphology.</title>
			<p> Female. Measurements, mm: Length total 2.22–2.48 (holotype 2.48); wing 1.83–1.91 (holotype 1.91); antenna 0.44–0.49 (holotype 0.49); palpi 0.22.</p>
			<p>Head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) globular with short evenly distributed setae on occiput, face non-setose. Eye bare, rounded, not emarginated at antennae base, facets round and equal <!--PageBreak-->in size. Ocelli almost in a straight transverse line, the middle slightly smaller than the laterals, distance between lateral ocellus and middle ocellus 2.0x the distance between lateral ocellus and eye margin. Four palpomeres visible: ultimate one elongated, its length 3x the width; penultimate palpomere subglobular, slightly longer than wide; antepenultimate palpomere (the sensilliferous palpomere) about 2x longer than wide, much wider than the more apical ones; the palpomere basally from the penultimate one short, shorter than the penultimate one. Other mouthparts very short, ~ 1/3 of head height, labrum dark, triangular; labellum and hypopharynx light, narrow, sharply pointed. Antenna with 2+14 segments, apical segment secondarily divided into two. Scape and pedicel 2x wider than flagellomeres, globular. Flagellomeres subcylindrical, ca. 1.5x broader than long.</p>
			
			<fig id="F1">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption><p><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">eocenica</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, sp. n., head, lateral.</p></caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://sciaroidea.info//sites/sciaroidea.info/files/images/Parisognoriste_fig1.jpg"/>
    	</fig>
			
			<p>Thorax. Scutum uniformly setose with lateral and posterior setae being longer. Scutellum with 10 marginal setae, which are as long and strong as the setae on the posterior part of scutum. Anteprontum with five setae, proepisternum with three setae. Pleural pit inconspicuous. Anepimerone pointed ventrally, touching katepisternum in single point. Laterotergite not produced strongly laterally, bare. Mediotergite non-setose, not convex posteriorly. Metepisternum trapezoidal, with height almost equal to width.</p>
			<p>Legs. Procoxa longer than the others. Metacoxa with a row of long posterolateral setae. Protibia about the length of profemur. Tibial organ with a small lobe, but without any distinct setation. Metatibia not conspicuously expanded apically but steadily widening from base to apex, its apical width ca. 2x the basal width. The vestiture on the apical third of tibia in rows. Spur formula 1:2:2, mesotibia with inner spur 2x the outer, metatibia with inner spur 2.5x the outer. Claws 1–3 pointed.</p>
			<!--PageBreak--><p>Wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Costa extending beyond R5 tip at 3/5 distance between tips of R5 and M1. Sc joining C. Rs distinct, oblique. M stem and base of M1+2 fork inconspicuous. M3+4 reduced at base. Transverse vein connecting Rs and CuA with a distinct kink at the base of M3+4. R1 with 18–20 dorsal setae, Sc, R5, M, and CuA bare.</p><p>Abdomen. Cercus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) two-segmented, basal segment rounded, very short, apical segment oval, its length 2x the width. Sternite 8 wide, rounded apically.</p>
			
			<fig id="F2">
      <label>Figure 2</label>
      <caption><p><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">eocenica</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, sp. n., wing</p></caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://sciaroidea.info//sites/sciaroidea.info/files/images/Parisognoriste_fig2.jpg"/>
    	</fig>
    	
    	<fig id="F3">
      <label>Figure 3</label>
      <caption><p><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">eocenica</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, sp. n., female genitalia, lateral</p></caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="http://sciaroidea.info//sites/sciaroidea.info/files/images/Parisognoriste_fig3.jpg"/>
    	</fig>
    	
    	</tp:treatment-sec>
    			
			<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
			<p> The species name is an adjective in the nominative singular, derived from the Eocene period, referring to the temporal distribution of the species.</p></tp:treatment-sec>
			
			<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion.</title>
			<p> See under Parisognoriste above.</p></tp:treatment-sec>
			
			</tp:taxon-treatment></tp:taxon-treatment>
			
		
		
			<tp:taxon-treatment>
			<tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste<object-id object-id-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8E3217CC-0700-4934-8D2F-5C1F93552006 </object-id></tp:taxon-name>  <tp:taxon-authority>Meunier, 1904</tp:taxon-authority><tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
					<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Meunier 1904</xref>: 87; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Meunier 1912</xref>: 89; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Matile 1990a</xref>: 360; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Matile 1990b</xref>: 366, 373-376, 383, 409, 421, 554; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Hoffeins and Hoffeins 1996</xref>: 311; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Grimaldi and Blagoderov 2001</xref>: 55; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Hippa et al. 2005</xref>: 5, 11; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Blagoderov et al. 2009</xref>: 32, 33, 35, 37, 45.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation></tp:nomenclature-citation-list></tp:nomenclature>
				
				
				<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title><p> <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sciariforme</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Meunier 1904</xref>: 88, by monotypy.</p></tp:treatment-sec>
				
				<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnostic description"><title>Diagnostic description.</title>
				<p> Small lygistorrhinid flies. Proboscis medium length, about the length of fore tibia, palpus one-segmented, shorter than labellum. Three ocelli, median ocellus smaller than lateral ocelli. Scutum evenly setose with medium-length setae, laterotergite bare. Wing venation similar to Parisognoriste but Rs transverse (illustrated in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Grimaldi and Blagoderov 2001</xref>: fig. 5a): Sc joining C. R1 short, approximately half of wing length. Rs distinct. R5 setose. Base of fork M1 and M2 incomplete, but traceable. M3+4 and CuA without a common stem. Crossvein m-cu well developed and aligned with crossvein r-m. R1 setose, Sc, R5, M, and CuA bare. Hind leg much longer that both fore and mid leg, hind tibia enlarged apically. Tibial <!--PageBreak-->vestiture in rows. Basitarsomere 3 inflated. Male tergite 9 with aggregation of thickened setae at apex.</p></tp:treatment-sec>
				
				<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion.</title>
				<p> <tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name> is distinguished from all other described fossil taxa of <tp:taxon-name>Lygistorrhinidae</tp:taxon-name> by the structure of mouthparts and from all recent genera by, for example, a well-developed Rs and r-m (see below under Phylogenetic analysis).</p></tp:treatment-sec>
				
				
			<tp:taxon-treatment>
			<tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sciariforme</tp:taxon-name-part><object-id object-id-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B8A39907-AED8-4DC1-8231-351704E7A84D </object-id></tp:taxon-name>  <tp:taxon-authority>Meunier, 1904</tp:taxon-authority>
			<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" />
			<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Meunier 1904</xref>
			<tp:nomenclature-citation-list><tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sciariforme</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name><comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Meunier 1904</xref>: 88</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation></tp:nomenclature-citation-list></tp:nomenclature>
					
					<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
					<p> Lectotype: male, Baltic amber, Z6630, deposited in Geowissenschaftlisches Zentrum der Georg-August-Universität, Göttingen, Germany, here designated.</p>
					<p>Notes. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Meunier (1904)</xref> described the species based on two specimens, a male and a female, in two separate pieces of amber. The present study revealed that they were not conspecific. For the sake of nomenclatural stability, we designate the male specimen, Z6630, as lectotype. The female specimen, Z5125, most probably belongs to <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> (see under <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>). Both specimens come from the Königsberg collection of Baltic amber, which was moved after World War II to Geowissenschaftlisches Zentrum der Georg-August-Universität, Göttingen (and currently on loan in the Laboratory of Entomology, Muséum national d'Histoire naturelle, Paris).</p></tp:treatment-sec>
					
					<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Morphology"><title>Morphology.</title>
					<p> Male. Measurements, mm: Length total 3.8; wing 2.5; antenna 0.75; labellum 0.95; palpus 0.5.</p>
					<p>Head rounded, dichoptic, posteriorly with a row of short (40 μm) postoccipital bristles. Ommatidia round, equal in size. Interommatidial setae shorter than ommatidial diameter. Three ocelli, laterals 2x diameter of median, touching eye margin. Clypeus <!--PageBreak-->triangular, pointed. Palpus one-segmented, ~ 1/2 length of labellum, with a dorsal row of setae. Antenna 2+14 segmented. Flagellomeres slightly longer than wide.</p>
					<p>Thorax: Scutum uniformly setose, with supraalar setae longer than others. Scutellum with four longer subapical marginal setae and irregularly positioned shorter hairs. Antepronotum with three setae. Proepisternum with five setae. Suture between anepisternum and katepisternum distinct. Anepimeron separated from katepisternum with indistinct ridge. Pleural pit distinct, cut into a dorsoventral corner of katepisternum. Laterotergite produced strongly lateroventrally, with a row of seven long setae. Metepisternum trapezoidal, with stronger sclerotized anterior margin, separated from metepimeron with a strong ridge. Mediotergite evenly curved.</p><p>Legs: Metacoxa without basolateral depression. Tibial spurs 1:2:2, length 0.1: (0.25, 0.1): (0.35, 0.19), outer spur shorter. Tibial and tarsal vestiture in rows. Protibia without tibial organ. Mesotibia with a dorsal row of 7-8 dark setae on apical half, and a dense apical brush of 17-20 dark setae. Mid tarsus with a row of a few dark setae. Metatibia apically and hind basitarsomere entirely swollen. Hind tarsomeres 1–3 with strong dark ventral setae. Claws of fore and mid legs blunt, of hind leg pointed.</p>
					<p>Wing: Costa extending 3/5 of distance between tips of R5 and M1. Sc joining C. Rs and r-m weakened, but distinct. M stem and base of M1+M2 fork inconspicuous. M3+4 base much weakened, M3+4 and CuA without common stem. Distance between apices of R5, M1, M2, M3+4 and CuA: 2.4: 1.5: 1.2: 1.8: 1.0. M1 slightly arched, M2 curved backwards apically. R1 setose, Sc, R5, M, CuA bare. Wing membrane without macrotrichia.</p>
					<p>Abdomen: Tergite 9 broadly curved posteriorly, with numerous short dark spines directed posteriorly and longer light setae directed ventrally at apex. Gonostyli narrow, flattened, 4x longer than wide, each with two stout apical teeth and long dorsal mesial setae. Gonocoxite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>) in lateral view with an obtuse angle on dorsal edge, a setae near the angle and two long setae near the base on gonostylus; covered with long setae ventrally.</p>
					
					<fig id="F4">
						<label>Figure 4</label>
						<caption><p><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sciariforme</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> Meunier, 1904, male genitalia, lateral</p></caption>
						<graphic xlink:href="http://sciaroidea.info//sites/sciaroidea.info/files/images/Parisognoriste_fig4.jpg"/>
					</fig>
					</tp:treatment-sec></tp:taxon-treatment>
					
					<tp:taxon-treatment>
						<tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part><object-id object-id-type="lsid">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6F42E20F-5073-473E-8463-38881FB76D10</object-id></tp:taxon-name> <tp:taxon-authority>Meunier, 1912</tp:taxon-authority><tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
							<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Meunier 1912</xref>: 89</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation></tp:nomenclature-citation-list></tp:nomenclature>
							
						<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined. </title>
						<p>Lectotype: male, Baltic amber, G1848 (BST.03.382), deposited in the Geowissenschaftlisches Zentrum der Georg-August-Universität, Göttingen, Germany; here designated.</p><p>Paralectotype: female, Baltic amber, G1848 (BST.03.382), deposited in the Geowissenschaftlisches Zentrum der Georg-August-Universität, Göttingen, Germany; here designated.</p>
						<p>Other material: female, Baltic amber, Z5125 (syntype of <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sciariforme</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>), deposited in the Geowissenschaftlisches Zentrum der Georg-August-Universität, Göttingen<!--PageBreak-->, Germany (currently on loan in the Laboratory of Entomology, Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle, Paris).</p>
						<p>Notes. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Meunier (1912)</xref> described <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> from a male and a female in copula. We here designate the male as lectotype and the female as paralectotype.</p></tp:treatment-sec>
						
						<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Morphology"><title>Morphology.</title>
						<p> Male. Measurements, mm: length total 3.8; wing 2.5; antenna 0.75; labellum 0.95; palpus 0.5.</p>
						<p>Head rounded, dichoptic. Ommatidia densely set, almost hexagonal, becoming slightly smaller dorsally. Interommatidial setae inconspicuous. Three ocelli present, diameterer of medial one 0.6x of the lateral ones, lateral ocelli touching eye margin. Antennae 2+14 segmented; flagellomeres as wide as long, with one or two short dorsal setae and two short ventral spines each. Scape small, as long as wide, trapezoidal. Pedicel globular, slightly wider than flagellum. Clypeus triangular, pointed. Palpus one-segmented, 0.56x length of labellum, with a row of dorsal setae. Labellum lanceolate at apex. Hypopharynx wide and strongly sclerotized.</p>
						<p>Thorax. Scutum uniformly setose with supraalar setae slightly longer than others. Antepronotum and proepisternum with 7–8 short setae each. Suture between anepisternum and katepisternum distinct. Pleural pit inconspicuous. Laterotergite produced strongly lateroventrally, with a row of five long setae postero-ventrally. Metepisternum trapezoidal, separated from metepimeron with a strong ridge.</p>
						<p>Legs. Procoxa and mesocoxa with a few anteroapical setae. Metacoxa with deep lateral depression and 2 long posterolateral setae on apical 1/3. Tibial spurs 1:2:2, length 0.08: (0.17, 0.11): (0.25, 0.12), outer spur shorter. Protibia without tibial organ. Tibial and tarsal vestiture in rows. Metatibia gradually expanding apically, with a row of 10 long dorso-lateral setae and 7–8 light apical inner setae not arranged in dense brush. First tarsomere of metatarsus inflated, with nine short setae in lateral row and 14 in ventral. Claws of fore leg blunt, of mid and hind legs pointed.</p>
						<!--PageBreak--><p>Wing. Costa extends beyond R5 on 0.5x distance between R5 and M1. Sc short, joins Costa. Rs, r-m, M stem inconspicuous. Base of M1 and M2 fork traceable. M1 slightly arched, M2 almost straight apically. Ratio of distances between R1, R5, M1, M2, M3+4 and CuA 2.0:1.5:0.8:1.6:1.0.</p>
						<p>Abdomen. Tergite 9 with a dense patch of short setae apically, without longer light setae. Dorsal margin of gonocoxites in lateral view evenly curved. Gonocoxites and gonostyli covered with long setae laterally; dorsal edge evenly curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
						
						<fig id="F5">
							<label>Figure 5</label>
							<caption><p><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> Meunier, 1912, male genitalia, lateral</p></caption>
							<graphic xlink:href="http://sciaroidea.info//sites/sciaroidea.info/files/images/Parisognoriste_fig5.jpg"/>
						</fig>
						
						<p>Female 1 (paralectotype). Measurements, mm: length total 3.8, wing 2.5, antenna 0.75, proboscis 0.95, palpus 0.5. As male, except: Compound eye smaller, not reaching lateral ocelli. All ommatidia equal in size to dorsal ommatidia of male. Interommatidia setae slightly longer than diameter of ommatidia. Ocelli in wide triangle, diameter of lateral ocellus 2x the medial ocellus, distance from lateral ocellus to eye slightly longer than to medial ocellus. Scape a little smaller than pedicel, trapezoidal. Pedicel wide, trapezoidal, 2x the width of flagellum; flagellomeres slightly shorter than wide, with numerous irregularly placed setae. Palpus 0.53x the labellum. Labellum widely rounded apically. Hypopharynx weak. Scutellum with 4 pairs of long subapical marginal setae. Antepronotum and proepisternum with 3–4 long setae each. Procoxa with long anterior setae, mesocoxa and metacoxa with long lateral setae on apical half. All claws pointed. Setae on fore basitarsomere shorter and less numerous than in male. Hind tibia with a 13–15 thin dorsal setae. Tibial spur lengths 0.11: (0.22, 0.12): (0.27, 0.13). Cercus two-segmented, basal segment globular, apical obovate, length 2x the basal one, with a few short setae laterally and ventrally.</p>
						<p>Female 2 (syntype of <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sciariforme</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>, Z5125, see under <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sciariforme</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>). Measurements, mm: length total 2.9; wing 2.0; antenna 0.55; proboscis 0.75; palpi 0.4. Lateral ocelli almost touching compound eye. Flagellomeres shorter than wide. Pedicel large, round. Hind tibia with an anteriodosral row of seven thin dark setae. Hind basitarsomere <!--PageBreak-->with a few weak dark setae. Laterotergite with four long setae. M1 arched, M2 almost straight apically. Base of M1 and M2 fork apparent, slightly proximad of level of R1 tip. Antepronotum with 4-5 short setae, proepisternum with seven setae. All claws pointed. Cercus two-segmented, length of apical segment 2x the basal one, basal segment trapezoidal, apical elliptic with numerous long setae at apex.</p></tp:treatment-sec>
						
						<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion.</title>
						<p> <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> differs from <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sciariforme</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> in having the male mid tarsal claws pointed, not blunt, base of M fork weak but distinguishable, M2 straight, not curved, at apex, weaker and fewer ventral setae on hind tarsomeres 1 and 2 (11 and four pairs contra 16 and six), dorsal margin of gonocoxites evenly curved, gonocoxites setose dorsally as well as ventrally, tergite 9 without longer apical setae. It is possible that the female specimen Z5125 is not conspecific with the paralectotype of <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>. However, we consider the differences rather small, and they may be a result of post-embedding distortion, and until new material become available we prefer to refer the specimen to <tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name>.</p></tp:treatment-sec>
						</tp:taxon-treatment></tp:taxon-treatment>
						
					
						</sec>
						
						<sec sec-type="Phylogenetic analysis"><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title>
						<p>Phylogenetic analysis was based on characters from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Blagoderov et al. (2009)</xref>. The data matrix was created and edited in Mesquite ver. 2.6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Maddison and Maddison 2009</xref>) and analysed in WinNona version 2.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Goloboff 1999</xref>). The search parameters used were ’hold100000; hold/1000; mult*1000; mult*max’. All characters were equally <!--PageBreak-->weighted and multistate characters treated as non-additive. Cladograms and character distribution were analysed in WinClada verson 1.00.08 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Nixon 2002</xref>).</p>
						<p>Cladistic analysis yielded four equally most parsimonious cladograms of 174 steps (CI = 0.44, RI = 0.58). The strict consensus tree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>) is congruent with previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Hippa et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Blagoderov et al. 2009</xref>). <tp:taxon-name>Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name> forms a monophyletic group together with the clade comprising <tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name> + recent <tp:taxon-name>Lygistorrhinidae</tp:taxon-name>; this group has the following synapomorphies: medial ocellus smaller than lateral (char. 8), proximal position of Rs base (char. 25), and non-setose R5 (char. 32). The taxa of the clade of <tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name> + recent <tp:taxon-name>Lygistorrhinidae</tp:taxon-name> have long proboscis (char. 1), maxillary palpus shorter than labellum (char. 2), one palpomere (char. 3), ocelli almost in transverse line (char. 9), and hind tibiae club-shaped (char. 47). Although both species of <tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name> form a well-defined clade, the genus has no unambiguous synapomorphies, all three supporting characters undergoing similar changes elsewhere: R5 setose (char. 35); basitarsomere 3 inflated (char. 50); tarsal claws 1 blunt (char. 51); Rs base transverse (in <tp:taxon-name>Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name> and some Cretaceous taxa – oblique).</p>
						
						<fig id="F6">
							<label>Figure 6</label>
							<caption><p>Strict consensus cladogram of four most parsimonious cladograms (176 steps, CI = 0.43, RI = 0.57). Black dots = unique character changes, open circles = homoplastic changes</p></caption>
							<graphic xlink:href="http://sciaroidea.info//sites/sciaroidea.info/files/images/Parisognoriste_fig6.png"/>
						</fig>
						
						<p><tp:taxon-name>Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name> belong to the base of a clade of modern <tp:taxon-name>Lygistorrhinidae</tp:taxon-name>, different from the Mesozoic taxa. This replacement corresponds to significant changes of environment in the Upper Cretaceous and Palaeocene. Thus, we can hypothesise that gradual increase on length of the proboscis in Cainozoic taxa of <tp:taxon-name>Lygistorrhinidae</tp:taxon-name> reflects wider distribution of nectar-bearing angiosperms in Palaeocene-Eocene.</p></sec>
						

</body>


<back>
	<ack>
		<label>Acknowledgements</label>
		<p>This research received support from the SYNTHESYS Project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.synthesys.info">http://www.synthesys.info</ext-link>) which is financed by European Community Research Infrastructure Action under the FP6 “Structuring the European Research Area” Programme (projects No. SE-TAF 5109, FR-TAF-3001). Prototype of the interface between Scratchpads and ZooKeys journal allowing rapid publication of taxonomic papers was created within the EDIT IRG grant “Streamlining Fungus Gnats Taxonomy”. Authors are grateful to Dr Ian Kitching of the Department of Entomology, the Natural History Museum, London for valuable comments and checking English language of the manuscript.</p></ack>

<ref-list><title>References</title>

			<ref id="B1"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Blagoderov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Brake</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgiev</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Penev</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rycroft</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Agosti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Catapano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Streamlining taxonomic publication: a working example with Scratchpads and ZooKeys.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.50.539">10.3897/zookeys.50.539</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B2"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Blagoderov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hippa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ševčík</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Asiorrhina, a new Oriental genus of Lygistorrhinidae (Diptera: Sciaroidea) and its phylogenetic position.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2295</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2009/f/z02295p045f.pdf">http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2009/f/z02295p045f.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B3"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Goloboff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> NONA, version 2.0.</source> <publisher-loc>Tucuman, Argentina.</publisher-loc> <publisher-name>Fundacion e Instituto Miguel Lillo.</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<!--PageBreak--><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Grimaldi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Blagoderov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> A new genus of Lygistorrhinidae from Vietnam (Diptera: Sciaroidea), and phylogenetic relationships in the family.</article-title> <source>Studia Dipterologica</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B5"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Hippa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattsson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilkamaa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> New taxa of the Lygistorrhinidae (Diptera: Sciaroidea) and their implications for a phylogenetic analysis of the family.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>960</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2005f/z00960f.pdf">http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2005f/z00960f.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B6"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Hoffeins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffeins</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Palaeognoriste sp. Ungewöhnliche Pilzmücke im Baltischen Bernstein. [Palaeognoriste sp., an unusual fungus gnat in Baltic amber.].</article-title> <source>Fossilien</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>314</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B7"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source>Mesquite: a modular system for evolutionary analysis. Version 2.6</source> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mesquiteproject.org">http://mesquiteproject.org</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B8"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Matile</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990a</year>)<article-title> Les Lygistorrhinidae de la region afrotropicale (Diptera: Mycetophiloidea).</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société Entomologique de France </source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B9"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Matile</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990b</year>)<article-title> Recherches sur la systématique et l'évolution des Keroplatidae (Diptera, Mycetophiloidea).</article-title> <source>Mémoires du Muséum national d'Histoire naturelle, serie A Zoologie</source> <volume>148</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>682</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B10"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Meunier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1904</year>)<article-title> Monographie des Cecidomyidae, des Sciaridae, des Mycetophilidae et des Chironomidae de l'ambre de la Baltique &lt;part&gt;.</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société Scientifique de Bruxelles</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/bibliography/8565">http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/bibliography/8565</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B11"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Meunier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>)<article-title> Un nouveau Mycetophilidae de l'ambre de la Baltique &lt;Dipt.&gt;.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Société Entomologique de France</source> <volume>1912</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B12"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Nel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>De Ploëg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Menier</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> The French ambers: a general conspectus and the Lowermost Eocene amber deposit of Le Quesnoy in the Paris Basin.</article-title> <source>Geologica Acta</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geologica-acta.com/MostrarAbstractAC.do?abstract=gav0201a02">http://www.geologica-acta.com/MostrarAbstractAC.do?abstract=gav0201a02</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B13"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Nel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prokop</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>De Ploëg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Millet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> New Psocoptera (Insecta) from the Lowermost Eocene amber of Oise, France.</article-title> <source>Journal of Systematic Palaeontology</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S1477201905001598">10.1017/S1477201905001598</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B14"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<source>Winclada, Version 1.00.08. </source><publisher-loc>Ithaca, New York.</publisher-loc> <publisher-name>Published by author.</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref>
			
			<ref id="B15"><mixed-citation><person-group><name><surname>Penev</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Agosti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgiev</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Catapano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Blagoderov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brake</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryrcroft</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sautter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Remsen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoev</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Parr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Semantic tagging of and semantic enhancements to systematics papers: ZooKeys working examples.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href=" http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.50.538">10.3897/zookeys.50.538</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>



</ref-list>

<sec sec-type="Supplementary material"><title>Supplementary material</title>
	<p>The Scratchpad version of this publication is available on the Fungus Gnats Online website at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sciaroidea.info/node/44428">http://sciaroidea.info/node/44428</ext-link></p>
	<p>Character matrix used for the analysis is available on Fungus Gnats Online website at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sciaroidea.info/sites/sciaroidea.info/files/Parisognoriste_matrix.txt">http://sciaroidea.info/sites/sciaroidea.info/files/Parisognoriste_matrix.txt</ext-link></p>
	<p>Additional images:</p>
	<p><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Parisognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">eocenica</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sciaroidea.info/taxonomy/47895">http://sciaroidea.info/taxonomy/47895</ext-link></p>
	<p><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">affine</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sciaroidea.info/taxonomy/41600">http://sciaroidea.info/taxonomy/41600</ext-link></p>
	<p><tp:taxon-name><tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Palaeognoriste</tp:taxon-name-part> <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sciariforme</tp:taxon-name-part></tp:taxon-name> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sciaroidea.info/taxonomy/41601">http://sciaroidea.info/taxonomy/41601</ext-link></p>
</sec>
</back></article>