<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.160.2108</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>New genus and species of broad-nosed weevils from Baltic amber and notes on fossils of the subfamily Entiminae (Coleoptera, Curculionidae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Yunakov</surname>
                        <given-names>Nikolai N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:62A12A2F-F00D-4E7C-88BA-252EA7A1DEB9</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Kirejtshuk</surname>
                        <given-names>Alexander G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:D63E800C-87F6-4281-8658-C3C032FE8628</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Natural History Museum, University of Oslo, P.O. Box 1172 Blindern NO-0318 Oslo, Norway
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Zoological Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences, Universitetskaya nab. 1, St. Petersburg, 199034, Russia
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, CP 50, Entomologie, 45 Rue Buffon, F- 75005 Paris, France
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Nikolai N. Yunakov (<email xlink:type="simple">n.yunakov@gmail.com</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: M. Alonso-Zarazaga</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>29</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>160</issue>
            <fpage>73</fpage>
            <lpage>96</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>16</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>7</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Nikolai N. Yunakov, Alexander G. Kirejtshuk</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:C7EF821A-79AF-4DB0-A059-E59CCCE93DBC</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis groehni</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>gen. et sp. n.</bold> is described from Baltic amber and temporarily placed in the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name>. It differs from all recent <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name> genera with open corbels by very short and flattened scape, distinct lateral carina of the pronotum and elytra, and the rostrum distinctly narrower than the head capsule. The shape of head in the extinct genus is somewhat similar to that of the extant <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name> genera with enclosed corbels (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Platyomus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sahlberg, 1823 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aptolemus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schoenherr, 1842), but differs in the slender body, open corbels, very short antennal scape and epifrons without a median sulcus (only a longitudinal depression is slightly visible). It is also similar to the Tanymecine genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pandeleteius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schoenherr, 1834 in general appearance, but distinct by the straight anterior edge of the pronotum, lack of postocular spurs, lobes, and vibrissae, a slightly sloping elytral declivity, lateral ridges on the pronotum, subflattened antennal scape, elongate rostrum, and sparsely setose epistome. A new synonymy of the generic names <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Zherikhin, 1971 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wanat &amp; Borowiec, 1986, <bold>syn. n.</bold>, is established. The Madagascan genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Corecaulus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fairmaire, 1903 is transferred from the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name> to the <tp:taxon-name>Brachyderini</tp:taxon-name> because of its connate claws and the similarity in chaetotaxy of the epistomal area with African and Madagascar <tp:taxon-name>Brachyderini</tp:taxon-name> genera. A key to the identification of known Baltic amber genera of <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> is proposed. A checklist of the prepleistocene fossil <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name>, based on V.V. Zherikhin’s data, with remarks and corrections, is presented.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>new genus and species</kwd>
                <kwd>new synonymy</kwd>
                <kwd>fossil Entiminae</kwd>
                <kwd>Naupactini</kwd>
                <kwd>Baltic amber</kwd>
                <kwd>key</kwd>
                <kwd>checklist</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Having examined the Baltic amber weevils from the collection of Mr. Carsten Gröhn, a new genus and species belonging to the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> is described. However its tribal attribution was questioned because of the aberrant shape of the head capsule and inaccessibility of structures normally used for diagnostics (e.g. genitalia). In studying the various characters of <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> weevils, it became readily apparent that one of the most useful diagnostic features at the suprageneric level is the structure of the mandibular processes. They show some variability within <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> in general, but within certain tribes is usually rather stable. Besides, the mandibular process of fossils can be used, if available, as an additional character for identification of tribes.</p>
            <p>In the course of the current study, mandibular processes of 35 extant genera in 17 tribes, including 6 genera of the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name> Gistel, 1848, were examined (results of this comparison will be published in a forthcoming paper).</p>
            <p>In addition, non-American genera treated in the <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name> were also examined. As a result, the Madagascar genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Corecaulus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fairmaire, 1903 (type, female examined, MNHN) was transferred from the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name> to <tp:taxon-name>Brachyderini</tp:taxon-name>, as its claws are connate in the basal third and similar to those in the genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Podionops</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schoenherr, 1847 (South Africa) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lagocaulus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fairmaire, 1903 (Madagascar) with the long median sulcus at the vertex and chaetotaxy of the epistomal area.</p>
            <p>The type specimens of some poorly known taxa were re-examined. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phyllobius sobrinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Voss, 1972 was placed in the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Wanat and Borovec 1986</xref>). A redescription of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is provided and a new taxonomic placement is proposed for this genus in accordance with the current knowledge of the Tertiary <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> fauna (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Zherikhin 1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">1992</xref>; and original data). This new information is included in the online catalogue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Ponomarenko et al. 2011</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Historical review of fossil Entiminae"><title>Historical review of fossil <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name></title>
            <p>The earliest descriptions of fossils from the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> Schoenherr, 1823 were published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Heer (1847)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Germar (1849)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Giebel (1856)</xref> in their reviews of “Tertiary” insects. One of the preceding publications includes a brief note on unrecognizable “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Naupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic>” species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Serres 1829</xref>). These authors assigned fossil species to recent genera. The oldest species treated as <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitonites melanarius</tp:taxon-name></italic>) was dated from the Upper Jurassic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Heer 1864</xref>), but this assignment with the broad-nosed weevils is rather doubtful and it is not considered reliable. The fossil specimens reliably identified as <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> originated from the Middle Eocene<!--PageBreak--> (Green River and Roan Mountain), the boundary between the Eocene and Oligocene, and also from the Lower Oligocene (Florissant and White River) (Scudder 1893). Exclusively rich American deposits with 47 genera and European deposits with 11 genera demonstrate the level of the Caenozoic diversity of this subfamily. The Middle Eocene deposits contain taxa resembling <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> but bear no mandibular processes, such as in <tp:taxon-name>Aterpini</tp:taxon-name> Lacordaire, 1866, usually assigned to the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Cyclominae</tp:taxon-name> Schoenherr, 1826 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Oberprieler 2010</xref>). Some advanced genera of <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> have also been found with well developed postocular vibrissae and mandibles bearing mandibular processes, which are usually treated as members of the tribes <tp:taxon-name>Tanymecini</tp:taxon-name> Lacordaire, 1863 and <tp:taxon-name>Ophryastini</tp:taxon-name> Lacordaire, 1863. A rather large number of the taxa with free claws in the Caenozoic fossil weevils could be regarded as remarkable. Unfortunately, poor preservation of weevils from the Green River and most other American sediments make it difficult to determine generic or even tribal attributions, as most important characters (particularly legs and thin structures of the rostrum) seem to be rarely available for study. On the other hand, good preservation of some compression remnants makes it possible to provide precise systematic interpretations. In particular, the inprints of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Geralophus fossicius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Scudder, 1893 from Florissant, initially treated as <tp:taxon-name>Alophini</tp:taxon-name> LeConte, 1874, have the distinct transverse sulcus at the base of the epifrons, and the latter was transferred to <tp:taxon-name>Cylydrorhinini</tp:taxon-name> Lacordaire, 1863 or <tp:taxon-name>Aterpini</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Cyclominae</tp:taxon-name>) (see Scudder 1893: plate II, Figs 16, 17 and 24); however, a more precise placement is scarcely possible due to the masking of fine structures of the mouthparts and epistomal area of the rostrum. Most <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> described from the Upper Eocene resin of Denmark, Poland and Russia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Voss 1953</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Zherikhin 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Wanat and Boroviec 1986</xref>) are in quite good condition.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Baltic amber Entiminae and their systematic and biographic links"><title>Baltic amber <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> and their systematic and biographic links</title>
            <p>The Baltic amber weevils apparently share more similarity with recent groups occurring mostly in the Indo-Malayan (Oriental) and Neotropical Regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Zherikhin 1971</xref>). The biotic similarity could be due to the more homogeneous Paleogene Euro-Asian biota which now mostly remains in the recent “Himalayan-Burmanian-Yunannian block” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Takhtajan 1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Kirejtshuk and Kurochkin 2010</xref>), but the link between this Paleogene biota with the recent Neotropical fauna is still unclear. Nevertheless, the Baltic amber fauna of <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> comprises two fossil genera, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Voss, 1953 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Zherikhin, 1971, linked to the Neotropics, versus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wanat &amp; Boroviec, 1986, linked to the Indo-Malayan Region. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polydrusus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Germar, 1817, is the only confirmed recent genus known from Baltic amber. It was established by the paleoendemic, monotypic subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Palaeodrosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Zherikhin, 1971, and is highly diverse in the recent fauna of the warm-temperate zone of the Palaearctic where it comprises 204 species. Another recent Palaearctic genus recorded from Baltic amber may be <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachyphloeus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Germar, 1824 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Klebs 1910</xref>), but this data is still not confirmed.</p>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Voss, 1953 is monotypic and it is considered as a member of the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name> Champion, 1911 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal 1999</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Zherikhin, 1971 is also monotypic and it was originally placed in the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name> Gistel, 1856). The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wanat &amp; Boroviec, 1986 was proposed for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phyllobius sobrinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Voss, 1972 and another species (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wanat &amp; Boroviec, 1986) was also described in it. According to the recent catalogue of weevil genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal 1999</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic> belongs to the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerini</tp:taxon-name> Lacordaire, 1863. Preliminary study and a comparison of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophylobius</tp:taxon-name></italic> with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerus</tp:taxon-name></italic> reveals that the characters of the head and prothorax make it questionable if <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic> belongs within the subtribe <tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerina</tp:taxon-name> (see further discussion below under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
            <p>The usual optic equipment was used for descriptions, including a Leica MZ 16.0 microscope provided with a CCD camera and camera lucida. Morphological terms mostly follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Thompson (1992)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Emden (1944)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Doyen (1966)</xref>. Special terms related to the rostrum structure follow Oberprieler 1988 and details of the epistomal area follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Morimoto et al. (2006)</xref>.</p>
            <p><italic>Measurements.</italic> All measurements were taken with an ocular-micrometer. Body length was measured from the anterior margin of the eyes to the apex of the elytra, and rostrum length from the rostrum apex to the anterior margin of the eyes. Width of the rostrum is the maximum distance between the lateral edges of the pterygia.</p>
            <p><italic>Imaging.</italic> All outline illustrations were drawn using a camera-lucida and modified with a Wacom Graphire 4 Classic XL A5 tablet in Corel Draw (version 11.633) Corel®. Merging of layers was done with Helicon Focus (version 5.0) HeliconSoft®. Amber samples were photographed as under normal conditions as well as in sugar syrup to provide more suitable light refraction.</p>
            <p><italic>Abbreviations of depositories</italic>. <bold>GPIH</bold> Institute of Geology and Palaeontology and Museum (Geologo-Paläontologisches Institut u. Museum), University of Hamburg; <bold>MNHN</bold> National Museum of Natural History (Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle), Paris; <bold>ZMUC</bold> Zoological Museum (Zoologisk Museum), University of Copenhagen.</p>
            <p><italic>Abbreviations of morphological terms</italic>. <bold>cb</bold> corbel, <bold>es</bold> epistomal setae, <bold>ed</bold> elytral declivity, <bold>fr</bold> frons, <bold>hp</bold> humeral prominence, <bold>ibt</bold> intero-basal tooth, <bold>ma</bold> mandibular process, <bold>lr</bold> lateral ridge of pronotum, <bold>pep</bold> parepistome.</p>
            <p><italic>Abbreviations in table.</italic> <bold>Agri</bold> Agriento (=Girgenti), Sicilia, Italy, Upper Miocene; <bold>Aix</bold> Aix-en-Province, France, Lower Oligocene; <bold>BalJ</bold> Baltic Amber, Baltic and North Sea coast, Upper Eocene; <bold>Boet</bold> Böttinger Marmors, Germany, Miocene; <bold>Cere</bold> Céreste, west to Apt, Alpes-de-Haute, Basses Alp Department, Provence, France, Lower Oligocene; <bold>Cela</bold> Célas, railway Uzés - Saint-Julien-de-Casignac, Fumades, Corents, Bassein Ales, Gard Dept., France, Upper Eocene, previously Lower Oligocene (Sannosien)<!--PageBreak-->; <bold>Dece</bold> Lava Camp Mine, Jumachuk River Valley, Seward peninsula, Alaska, Pleocene-Pleistocene (5.7 mln - 27 000 - Deceit Formation); <bold>DomJ</bold> Dominican amber, Dominican Republic and Haiti; Lower Miocene; <bold>CerG</bold> Cerro Guido, Ultima Esperanza, Magallanes, Upper Cretaceous; <bold>Core</bold> Corent, Gergovia Plateu, south of Clermon-Ferran, Puy-de-Dom Department, France, Upper Oligocene; <bold>Flor</bold> Florissant, south fork of Twin Creek, Front Range near Pike’s Peak, Colorado, U.S.A., Lower Oligocene. <bold>GreR</bold> Green-River, 3-4 km western rail-way crossing of Green River; Utah, U.S.A, Middle Eocene; <bold>N1</bold> Neogene, Miocene; <bold>N11</bold> Neogene, Lower Miocene; <bold>N13</bold> Neogene, Upper Miocene; <bold>N2</bold> Neogene, Pliocene; <bold>K2</bold> Upper Cretaceous; <bold>Dece</bold> Lava Camp Mine, Jumachuk River Valley, Seward peninsula, Alaska, Pleocene-Pleistocene site (5.7 mln - 27 000 - Deceit Formation); <bold>Oeni</bold> Oeningen, near Baden lake, Baden-Württemberg, Germany, Upper Miocene; <bold>Pg12</bold> Paleogene, Middle Paleocene; <bold>Pg2</bold> Paleogene, Eocene; <bold>Pg22</bold> Paleogene, Middle Eocene; <bold>Pg23</bold> Paleogene, Upper Eocene; <bold>Pg31</bold> Paleogene, Lower Oligocene; <bold>Pg33</bold> Paleogene, Upper Oligocene; <bold>RoaM</bold> Roan Mountain, Colorado, USA, Middle Eocene; <bold>Rott</bold> Siebengebirge, Germany; Lower Miocene, Aquitanian or Upper Oligocene; <bold>Sunc</bold> Sunchal, La Mendieta, Jujuy Prov., northern Argentina; Upper Paleocene (Lower Eocene); <bold>WhiR</bold> White River Badlands, South Dakota, boundary Eocene and Oligocene.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomic treatment"><title>Taxonomic treatment</title>
            <p><bold>Order <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name></bold> Linnaeus, 1758</p>
            <p><bold>Family <tp:taxon-name>Curculionidae</tp:taxon-name></bold> Latreille, 1802</p>
            <p><bold>Subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name></bold> Schoenherr, 1823</p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:24BF76B1-8ADA-44BA-B111-FEED72EB7A05</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Arostropsis</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Yunakov &amp; Kirejtshuk</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status>gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis groehni</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yunakov &amp; Kirejtshuk, sp. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> The name of the new genus is formed from the Greek negative prefix “a”, “rōstron” (beak, bill, snout) and “opsis” (resembling a (specified) thing). Gender feminine.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> Body elongate, in general appearance similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pandeleteius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schoenherr, 1834. Antenna with scape short, as long as pedicel (first funicular article; term after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Doyen 1966</xref>) and 2<sup>nd</sup> funicular article (antennomere 3) together, reaching anterior margin of eye, strongly widened and flattened dorso-ventrally along apical third. Rostrum distinctly elongate and slender, about half as thick as frons. Vertex with small frontal fossa anterior of eyes. Buccal cavity completely covered by prementum; transverse sulcus absent. Epistome sparsely setose: only two pairs of short (internal) and long (external) setae (such composition of setae is not found among groups of <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name>); parepistome (term after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Morimoto et al. 2006</xref>) weakly acute and <!--PageBreak-->gently extending beyond contour of rostrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 14</xref>). Antennal scrobes entirely lateral, just swinging fossa (term after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Morimoto et al. 2006</xref>) slightly visible from above, pterygia scarcely pronounced. Mandibular process resembling that in other <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name> (this structure was examined for six genera of <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name>), weakly curved inward, with distinct dorsal carina, without inner basal tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 18</xref>). Eyes strongly asymmetrically convex. Pronotal and elytral disk distinctly depressed dorsally. Pronotum with distinct lateral ridges; its posterior edge bisinuate. Elytra subparallel-sided, with humeral and distinct subapical prominences, elytral declivity gently sloping. Femora obtuse, weakly swollen. Metatibiae with open corbels. Claws free.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">groehni</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:25FBCC0C-8376-41C7-A86E-F024B1541EEC</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Arostropsis_groehni</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Yunakov &amp; Kirejtshuk</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">–16</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p> <italic>Holotype</italic> “C 7968, GPIH 4516”, male (GPIH); the complete beetle with a clear integument is included in an irregular parallelepiped with the largest plane about 18.0 × 14.0 mm and the smallest one 11.0 × 7.0 mm; amber matter on right side from the beetle is rather homogeneous, but that from the left side of the inclusion consists of some layers, in which between the borders is a fine net of dark (almost blackish) organic matter.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> The epithet of the new species is formed from the name of Carsten Gröhn, collector of its holotype.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type strata"><title>Type strata.</title>
                    <p> Baltic Amber; Upper Eocene, Prussian Formation.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality"><title>Type locality.</title>
                    <p> Baltic Sea coast and Amber quarry Jantarny near Kaliningrad (formerly Koenigsberg), Kaliningrad region, Russia.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Length 6.4, width 1.8, height 1.3 mm. Body slender, distinctly depressed from above. Pronotum and elytra strongly carinate at sides. Integument densely covered with small, apparently metallic, lanceolate (apparently green) scales at both sides of body and legs.</p>
                    <p><italic>Head</italic>. Rostrum 1.5 times as long as wide, narrow, distinctly narrower than head capsule, laterally depressed. Pterygia weakly extending beyond lateral contour of rostrum. Epistomal area not depressed. Lateral edges of epifrons at middle convex, narrowed towards middle, then parallel-sided, without basal, transverse depression or sulcus. Median sulcus shallow, extending towards pit between eyes, not continuing towards vertex. Head capsule not constricted beyond eyes. Frons distinctly convex, almost twice as wide as epifrons at level of antennal insertions. Maximum width of head at posterior part of eyes. Scape comparatively short, about 1/4 as long as funicle, strongly expanded apically, somewhat compressed dorsoventrally, not extending beyond anterior third of eyes, directed obliquely downwards in folded state. Funicle slender; all segments elongate, funicular segment 1 about three times as long as wide, 2<sup>nd</sup> about two times as long as wide, 3<sup>rd</sup> about 1.5 times as long as wide; 4<sup>th</sup>-5<sup>th</sup> about two times as long as wide, segments<!--PageBreak--> 6-7 about 1.5 times as long as wide. Club spindle-shaped and comparatively thin, with distinctly separated segments, about as long as funicular segments 1-7 together. Mandibles entirely bare (without scales), moderately extended beyond buccal cavity. The only remaining left mandibular process knife-shaped, in apical third slightly curved inward, without internal prominences, about 1.5 times as long as protruding part of mandibles.</p>
                    <p><italic>Pronotum</italic> elongate, almost parallel-sided, with anterior and posterior constrictions widely expressed, weakly and evenly convex at sides, with disc weakly convex transversely<!--PageBreak--> and anterior edge curving upward; posterior edge slightly bisinuate; posterior angles widely rounded and somewhat projecting posteriorly; anterior edge nearly straight.</p>
                    <p><italic>Elytra</italic> elongate, about 4.5 times as long as wide, parallel-sided, humeral prominences distinct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>, <bold>hp</bold>), basal edge of elytra biconvex opposite the posterior pronotal depressions. Elytral declivity gently sloping (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>).</p>
                    <!--PageBreak-->
                    <p><italic>Legs</italic> slender. Femora slender, elongate, obtuse, weakly swollen in apical third. Tibiae slender and elongate. Protibiae gently curved inwards in apical third; with anterior row of thin spines. Metatibiae subflattened and with inner edge sinuate at apical third. Corbels open (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 6</xref>, <bold>cb</bold>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>), without additional row of spines. Tarsi slender, setaceous, pelma well-developed (term after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Doyen 1966</xref>). Tarsomere 1 almost as long as <!--PageBreak-->tarsomeres 2–3 combined. Ultimate tarsomere extended beyond lobes of tarsomere 3 by length of last one. Claws free. Procoxae comparatively small, situated in middle of prothorax (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–6.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis groehni</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. et sp.n. <bold>1</bold> body, dorsal view <bold>2</bold> body, lateral view <bold>3</bold> body, ventro-lateral view <bold>4</bold> head, dorsal view <bold>5</bold> protarsi <bold>6</bold> metatibia apex. Abbreviations: <bold>cb</bold> – corbel, <bold>ma</bold> – mandibular process. Body length: 6.4 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-160-073-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 7–8.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis groehni</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. et sp.n. <bold>7</bold> body outline, lateral view <bold>8</bold> idem, ventro-lateral view (anterior and middle limbs removed). Abbreviations: <bold>ed</bold> elytral declivity, <bold>hp</bold> humeral prominence, <bold>lr</bold> lateral ridge, <bold>ma</bold> mandibular process. Body length: 6.4 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-160-073-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 9–12.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis groehni</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. et sp.n. <bold>9</bold> head, antero-lateral view <bold>10</bold> idem, antero-dorsal view <bold>11</bold> head and prothorax, lateral view <bold>12</bold> antenna, lateral view. Abbreviations: <bold>lr</bold> lateral ridge, <bold>ma</bold> mandibular process. Scale bar: 1 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-160-073-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 13–18.</label>
                        <caption><p>Species of<italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepropus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Naupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, details. Figs 17 and 18 (modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Thompson 1992</xref>). <bold>13</bold>–<bold>16</bold>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis groehni</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>13</bold> base of pronotum and elytra <bold>14</bold> epistome <bold>15</bold> epipleural margin of elytra <bold>16</bold> protarsus <bold>17</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepropus rutilans</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier, 1807) (<tp:taxon-name>Tanymecini</tp:taxon-name>), mandibular processes dentate <bold>18</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Naupactus fatuus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Boheman, 1833, mandibular processes simple (<tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name>). Abbreviations: <bold>dc</bold> dorsal carina of mandibular process, <bold>ibt</bold> interobasal tooth of mandibular process, <bold>es</bold> epistomal setae, <bold>ma</bold> mandibular process. Scale bar: 1 mm (Figs <bold>13, 15</bold>); 0.5 mm (Figs <bold>14, 16</bold>); not in scale (Figs <bold>17, 18</bold>).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-160-073-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <!--PageBreak-->
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comparison with recent genera"><title>Comparison with recent genera.</title>
                    <p> The new genus differs from all recent genera of <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name> with open corbels and procoxae not completely separated from the prosternum (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Mesagroicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schoenherr, 1840, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eurymetopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schoenherr, 1840, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanocyphus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Jekel, 1875, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hustache, 1939 ) in the following characters: short and depressed scape, rostrum narrow, epistomal area weakly setose, epifrons with a weakly developed median depression and vertex with very small fossa, not continuing to occiput.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comparison with Baltic amber entimine genera"><title>Comparison with Baltic amber entimine genera.</title>
                    <p> Since <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n. has free claws, only two other fossil genera, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Voss, 1953 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Zherikhin, 1971, share the same character state and can be compared with the new genus. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n. strongly differs from both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the following characters given in the key below.</p>
                    <sec sec-type="Key to Baltic amber genera of Entiminae with free claws"><title>Key to Baltic amber genera of <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> with free claws</title>
                        <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape short, reaching middle of eyes, strongly thickened apically; pedicel 1.5 times as long as or 2<sup>nd</sup> funicular article; 1<sup>st</sup> article of club similar in shape and size with 7<sup>th</sup> funicular article. Eyes irregularly convex, lateral, located significantly below level of frons (in lateral view). Epifrons without transverse sulcus before eyes. Lateral carina of prothorax developed. Pronotal disc depressed. Procoxae situated in middle of prosternum. Body length 6.4 mm</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape long, reaching anterior edge of prothorax, not strongly thickened at apex; pedicel 0.7 time as long as 2<sup>nd</sup> funicular article; 1<sup>st</sup> article of club significantly different in shape from 7<sup>th</sup> funicular article. Eyes evenly convex, dorso-laterally, located almost at level of frons and somewhat extended above level of frons (in lateral view). Epifrons with more or less developed, transverse sulcus before eyes. Sides of prothorax evenly swollen, without carina. Pronotal disc moderately convex. Procoxae are closer to the anterior than to the posterior edge of prosternum. Body length 4.0-4.8 mm</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennal club oval. 4.5-4.8 mm.</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Zherikhin, 1971</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennal club spindle-shaped. 4 mm.</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Voss, 1953</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Systematic position"><title>Systematic position</title>
                        <p>This new genus is undoubtedly a member of <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> due to the presence of mandibular processes. Due to structural characters: mandibular processes long, knife-shaped (<bold>ibt</bold> not developed) - claws free, vertex and epifrons combined in uniform structure without transverse sulcus before eyes, the new genus could be assigned to the tribes <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name> or <tp:taxon-name>Geonemini</tp:taxon-name> Gistel, 1848. Emden separated these groups from other ‘brachyderoid’ tribes of <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> with free claws (<tp:taxon-name>Tanymecini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name>) by the following characters (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
                        <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Table 1.</label>
                            <caption><p> Basic morphological characters of ‘brachyderoid’ tribes of <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> with free claws in comparison with the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen.n.</p></caption>
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Geonemini</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Tanymecini</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Postocular vibrissae</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">absent</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">absent</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">present</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">absent</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">absent</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Claws</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">free</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">free</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">free/connate</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">free</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">free</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Transverse sulcus</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">absent</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">present/absent</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">present/&lt;br/&gt; absent</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">present/&lt;br/&gt; obsolete</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">absent</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. Eyes position</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">dorso-lateral</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lateral</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">dorso-lateral</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">dorso-lateral</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lateral</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Mentum covers maxillae</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">yes/no</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">unknown</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6. Metatibial corbels</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">open/enclosed</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">open/enclosed</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">open/enclosed</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">open</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">open</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7. Mandibular processes </td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">without ibt</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">without ibt</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">with ibt</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">unknown</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">without ibt</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8. Procoxae position</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">anterior</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">anterior/median</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">median</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
												
                        <p>The position of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is tested following the table:</p>
                        <p>Presumption 1 (<tp:taxon-name>Geonemini</tp:taxon-name>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen.n. lacks the key characters of <tp:taxon-name>Geonemini</tp:taxon-name> such as: evenly sloping lateral edges of epifrons, very narrow vertex and anterior position of procoxae. Consequently this genus cannot be assigned to this tribe..</p>
                        <p>Presumption 2 (<tp:taxon-name>Tanymecini</tp:taxon-name>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n. could not be considered in the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Tanymecini</tp:taxon-name>, due to absence of postocular vibrissae at the prothorax. The amount of vibrissae varies from genus to genus within <tp:taxon-name>Tanymecini</tp:taxon-name> but at least a few vibrissae are present (some <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pandeleteius</tp:taxon-name></italic>). We do not know any case in which vibrissae are completely absent, so it is unlikely that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> belongs to <tp:taxon-name>Tanymecini</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                        <p>Presumption 3 (<tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name>). Due to absence of transverse sulcus between vertex and epifrons and U-shaped epistome in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> it is impossible to consider this genus within <tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                        <p>Presumption 4 (<tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name>). The strictly lateral position of the eyes, flattened epifrons and very broad vertex resembles that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> within <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name>, however, the shape of the rostrum is very different from that of any known member of this tribe. This transformation of rostrum probably resulted in reduction of the frontal fossa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>) that is normally (in genera with broad rostrum) deep, long and continuing from the anterior portion of epifrons to the occiput. Such head shape together with the unusual slender body makes it difficult to recognize <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arostropsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> as a member of the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                        <p><bold>Probable bionomy</bold>. The long legs and well developed tarsal pelma (term after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Doyen 1966</xref>) of the new species suggests that this beetle was capable of running swiftly between leaves and, therefore, it was likely a canopy-dweller.</p>
                    </sec>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature><label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Zherikhin, 1971</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius</tp:taxon-name><comment> Wanat &amp; Borowiec, 1986: 243, syn. n. Type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wanat &amp; Boroviec, 1986</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus microphthalmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Zherikhin, 1971</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Included species"><title>Included species:</title>
                    <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus microphthalmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Zherikhin, 1971, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Wanat &amp; Boroviec, 1986), comb. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus sobrinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Voss, 1972), comb. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sobrinus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Protonaupactus_sobrinus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Voss, 1972)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status>comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 19</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">–34</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Phyllobius sobrinus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Voss 1972</xref>: 174</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius sobrinus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Wanat &amp; Borowiec 1986: 243</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p> <bold>Holotype:</bold> ZMUC903847, male (ZMUC); the complete beetle is included in a nearly regular amber piece, parallelepiped, with facets 14.0, 10.0 and 5.0 mm; one thin layer with wavy, light organic matter, small gas bubbles and small cracks located beneath the beetle.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type strata"><title>Type strata.</title>
                    <p> Baltic Amber; Upper Eocene, Prussian Formation.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality"><title>Type locality.</title>
                    <p> Denmark “Bernschteinschluss, Versterhavet bei Thisted, 17.xii.1895, Madsen leg.”.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Redescription"><title>Redescription.</title>
                    <p> Length 4.5, width 1.75, and height 1.65 mm. Beetle densely covered with metallic, shining scales (apparently green).</p>
                    <p><italic>Head</italic>. Rostrum 1.5 times as long as wide at level of pterygia. Epifrons subparallel-sided, at level of antennal insertions abruptly widened anteriorly, weakly convex longitudinally, separated from frons by a distinct depression indicating a transverse sulcus hidden by dense scales. Pterygia strongly extending beyond lateral contour of rostrum. Epistome well-defined by U-shaped keel. Epistomal setae grouped in dense bunches at anterior epistomal angles. Each bunch bearing at least 5 setae. Epistomal angles pronounced apically. Anterior edge of pterygia densely setose. Antennal furrows distinct only in their basal half and not continuing obliquely to underside of rostrum, their dorsal and ventral edges somewhat divergent posteriorly. Eyes dorso-lateral, round and evenly convex. Frons slightly convex, as wide as epifrons between antennal insertions. Frontal fossa not visible because masking by scales. Antennae long. Scape straight, evenly thickened apically, reaching anterior constriction of pronotum. Funicle thin: pedicel about 0.7 time as long as 2<sup>nd</sup> funicular article; 2<sup>nd</sup> article about 3.5 times as long as wide; 3<sup>rd</sup> –7<sup>th</sup> articles weakly oblong, about 1.5 times as long as wide. Club ovoid, about 2.3 times as long as wide, its 1<sup>st</sup> article significantly different in shape from 7<sup>th</sup> funicular article.</p>
                    <p><italic>Pronotum</italic> transverse; evenly convex at sides and disc, strongly constricted anteriorly and posteriorly. Its base slightly bisinuate. Anterior edge of pronotum straight, without postocular lobes, spurs or vibrissae. Scutellum significantly pronounced, subquadrate.</p>
                    <p><italic>Elytra</italic> subparallel, hardly widened in apical half, with pronounced humeral prominences. Epipleural edge weekly but distinctly S-shaped. Wings well-developed, beetle apparently capable of flying. Elytral declivity abruptly sloping. Anterior edge of anal ventrite (hypopygidium) emarginate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 30</xref>).</p>
                    <!--PageBreak-->
                    <p><italic>Legs</italic> thin. Femora obtuse, weakly swollen in middle part. Protibiae straight at external edge, not widened at external apical angle. Metatibiae spatulate apically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 33</xref>), with open corbel but without additional setal row. Setal comb of all tibiae weakly-developed. Tarsi with well-developed setaceous pelma (term after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Doyen 1966</xref>). Tarsomere 1 about as long as tarsomeres 2 and 3 combined. Tarsomere 3 with well-developed lobes. Ultimate tarsomere by 0.7 extending beyond lobes of tarsomere 3. Claws free.</p>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 19–24.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus sobrinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Voss, 1972), holotype, male. <bold>19</bold> body, dorsal view <bold>20</bold> elytral declivity, posterior view <bold>21</bold> head and pronotum, dorsal view <bold>22</bold> body, lateral view <bold>23</bold> rostrum, dorsal view (transverse sulcus, indicated by dashed line, hidden by dense scale vestiture) <bold>24</bold> antennal club. Abbreviations: <bold>es</bold> epistomal setae, <bold>ts</bold> transverse sulcus. Body length: 4.5 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-160-073-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 25–30.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus sobrinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Voss, 1972), holotype, male. <bold>25</bold> head with antennal scape, dorsal view <bold>26</bold> idem, lateral dorsal view <bold>27</bold> epistomal area of rostrum <bold>28</bold> pronotum and elytral base, dorsal view <bold>29</bold> anterior right leg, dorsal view <bold>30</bold> elytral apex with pygidium and anal ventrite. Abbreviations: <bold>ts</bold> transverse sulcus, <bold>es</bold> epistomal serae, <bold>ep</bold> epistome, <bold>fr</bold> frons, <bold>pep</bold> parepistome. Scale bar: 1 mm (Figs 25, 26, 28, 30); 0.5 mm (Figs <bold>27, 29</bold>).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-160-073-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 31–34.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus sobrinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Voss, 1972), holotype, male. <bold>31</bold> metatibial apex and tarsus lateral view, and claws dorsal view <bold>32</bold> mesotarsus ventral view <bold>33</bold> posterior leg <bold>34</bold> antenna. <bold>Remark</bold>. Setose pelma (term after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Doyen 1966</xref>) indicated by grey color. Scale bar: 0.25 mm (Figs 31, 32); 0.5 mm (Figs <bold>33, 34</bold>).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-160-073-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <!--PageBreak-->
                    <!--PageBreak-->
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Differential diagnosis"><title>Differential diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> This species is distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus microphthalmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the metatibiae being strongly spatulate apically. The re-examination of the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phyllobius sobrinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Voss, 1972 demonstrates the particular structure of the head, which is very similar to some genera of <tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name> (mostly from tropical America) and <tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerini</tp:taxon-name> (mostly from Old World tropics, distinctly separated groups): epistome U-shaped, convex, weakly sinuate anteriorly, and claws free (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 27</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">31</xref>). This species also shares a well-developed, transverse sulcus on the rostrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 25, 26</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">35–39</xref>) with other groups of <tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 35–39.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name>, details. 35, 38 body, lateral view; 36, 39 body, dorsal view; 37 head, dorsal view. <bold>35</bold>–<bold>37</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anypotactus exilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Boheman, 1840, female (Venezuela); length 3,3 mm <bold>38</bold>, <bold>39</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyphantus buccifer</tp:taxon-name></italic> Germar, 1824, female (Brazil); length 8,2 mm. Abbreviations. <bold>isc</bold> incrustation scales, <bold>ep</bold> epistome, <bold>fr</bold> frons, <bold>ts</bold> transverse sulcus.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-160-073-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes on synonymy"><title>Notes on synonymy.</title>
                    <p> The comparison of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius sobrinus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus microphthalmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> shows they are closely related species of the same genus. <!--PageBreak-->They share almost the same characters of the rostrum, with moderately defined U-shaped epistome having apically pronounced angles, long and slender antennae with the scape extending behind the anterior margin of the pronotum, funicular article 1 about 0.7 × as long as article 2, and article 2 about 3.5 × as long as wide.</p>
                    <sec sec-type="Systematic position of Protonaupactus"><title>Systematic position of <tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></title>
                        <p><tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerini</tp:taxon-name> are the only tribes of <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> whose relationships with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> still need to be tested. Both tribes contain genera with the following characters: (1) claws free, (2) epistome deeply sinuate, parepistome distinctly<!--PageBreak--> protruding and bearing dense bunches of long setae, (3) swinging fossae long, fully visible in dorsal view, (4) pterygia strongly extended beyond rostrum.</p>
                        <p>The tribe <tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerini</tp:taxon-name> consists of rather diverse genera which may be divided into two subgroups by the structure of the prothorax and underside of the head: (<bold>1</bold>) <bold>a</bold> prosternum subflattened with straight anterior edge; <bold>b</bold> pronotum with straight anterior edge; <bold>c</bold> rostrum and head united in a consolidated structure; <bold>d</bold> underside of rostrum densely covered with scales, its sculpture uniform; <bold>e</bold> rostrum directed forwards (<tp:taxon-name>Mylacorrhinina</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Myllocerina</tp:taxon-name>) or (<bold>2</bold>) <bold>a</bold> prosternum with anterior edge sinuate; <bold>b</bold> pronotum with distinct postocular lobes; <bold>c</bold> head and rostrum distinctly separated by transverse constriction; <bold>d</bold> basal area of underside of rostrum with glabrous integument which has a bare stripe reaching the eyes; <bold>e</bold> rostrum directed downwards (<tp:taxon-name>Acanthotrachelina</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerina</tp:taxon-name>, and <tp:taxon-name>Phytoscaphina</tp:taxon-name>).</p>
                        <p><tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name> include a group of genera that share a character set characteristic of the subgroup I of <tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerini</tp:taxon-name> and distinct from this subgroup in the transverse sulcus on the rostrum. However, this tribe displays an enormous variety in rostrum shape, and also shows both dorsal and lateral positions of the antennal scape which is normally folded above the eyes, along the rostrum, or folded obliquely downwards in the scrobe if developed. Both the antennal scape and funicle are quite slender, hence the antennae resemble a brachyderoid rather than otiorhynchoid type, like in <tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerini</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anypotactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schoenherr 1840, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polydacrys</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schoenherr, 1833 and other genera with short rostrum and large pterygia belong to <tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name> subgroup 1, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Prepodellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kirsch, 1867, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyphantus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Germar, 1824 and other genera with long rostrum with very small pterygia belong to <tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name> subgroup 2.</p>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> combines both character sets, <tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerini</tp:taxon-name>. Nevertheless, it can be easily distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerini</tp:taxon-name> subgr. 2 in sharing the basic character set of <tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerini</tp:taxon-name> subgr. 1 and <tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name> subgr. 1. From <tp:taxon-name>Cyphicerini</tp:taxon-name> subgr.1 <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs particularly in the transverse sulcus on the rostrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 25, 26</xref>). The new data on this fossil genus show that the distinctness between these tribes is not very clear and needs a further investigation.</p>
                    </sec>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>The authors are pleased to express their gratitude to Carsten Gröhn (GPIH), who provided material for study. They also express sincere thanks to Lars Vilhelmsen and Alexey Solodovnikov (ZMUC) for the opportunity to examine the Baltic amber collection. Wolfgang Weitschat (GPIH) assisted to the authors in their attempts to seek the types of E. Voss which should be deposited in GPIH but now are missing. Steven R. Davis (University of Kansas, Lawrence), George Poinar Jr. (Oregon State University, Corvallis), and two anonymous referees made an essential contribution in improving the English and the content of the manuscript. The use of the data after Vladimir V. Zherikhin (published in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Ponomarenko et al. 2011</xref>) greatly contributed to the fulfillment of this study. The first <!--PageBreak-->co-author was supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft grant: KL 1162/4-1, AOBJ 554623. The second co-author was supported by the Program of the Presidium of the Russian Academy of Sciences ‘Origin of Biosphere and Evolution of Geo-Biological Systems’ and Russian Foundation of Basic Research (grant 09-04-00789-a). The second co-author have also a pleasant duty to express his recognition to the Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle for providing him a possibility to work in this museum according to the program of visiting professors. The authors’ work with the collection of ZIN was supported by the Russian Ministry of Education and Science.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Zarazaga</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyal</surname><given-names>ChHC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> A world catalogue of families and genera of Curculionoidea (Insecta: Coleoptera) (excepting Scolytidae and Platypodidae) Entomopraxis, Barcelona, 315 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Burmeister</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1831–1832</year>)<source> Handbuch der Entomologie. Band I. G. Reimer, Berlin, xvi + 696 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Emden</surname><given-names>F van</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1944</year>)<source> A key to the genera of Brachyderinae of the world. Annals and Magazine of Natural History 11(11): 503–532, 559–586. </source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222934408527452" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1080/00222934408527452</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1966</year>)<article-title> The Skeletal Anatomy of <italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic> (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae).</article-title> <source>Miscellaneous publications of the Entomological Society of America </source> <volume>5</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>103</fpage>-<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Germar</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1849</year>)<article-title> Über einige Insekten aus Tertiargebildungen.</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift der Deutschen geologischen Gesellschaft </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>52</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Giebel</surname><given-names>CGA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1856</year>)<article-title> Analyse von Berendt, Die im Bernstein befindlichen organischen Reste der Vorwelt. Band 2.</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift für die gesamte Naturwissenschaft </source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>619</fpage>-<lpage>624</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1847</year>)<source> Die Insektenfauna der Tertiärgebilde von Oeningen und von Radoboj in Croatien. Erste Abtheilung: Käfer. Neue Denkschriften der Allgemeinen Schweizerischen Gesellschaft für die gesamten Naturwissenschaften 8: 1–229 + index + 8 pl. [own pag.]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1864–1865</year>)<source> Die Urwelt der Schweiz. Parts l to 11. Druck und Verlag von Friedrich Schulthess, Zürich, xxix + 622 pp. + 11 pl. + l map. [Published in parts; according to Evenhuis, 1997–352, these are: (1–2): pp. 1–96, pi 1–6, before 30-III-1864; (3–4): pp. 97–192, pl. 7, 30-III-1864; (5–6): pp. 193–288, pl. 8, between 31-III and 17-VIII-1864; (7–11): pp. 289–496, pl. 9–10, 18-VIII-1864; (12–13): pp. i–xxix + 497–622 + pl. 11, between I and VI-1865]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hieke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pietrzeniuk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Die Bernstein-Käfer des Museums für Naturkunde, Berlin (Insecta, Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen aus dem Zoologischen Museum in Berlin </source> <volume>60</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>297</fpage>-<lpage>326</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hundsdoerfer</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rheinheimer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Towards the phylogeny of the Curculionoidea (Coleoptera): Reconstructions from mitochondrial and nuclear ribosomal DNA sequences.</article-title> <source>Zoologischer Anzeiger </source> <volume>248</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jcz.2008.09.001" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/j.jcz.2008.09.001</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirejtshuk</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurochkin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> New Species of Sap Beetles (Coleoptera: Nitidulidae: Nitidulini) from the Baltic and Bitterfeld Ambers.</article-title> <source>Paleontological Journal</source> <volume>44</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kissinger</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>)<article-title> A new weevil genus from America north of the Arctic Circle and notes of fossils from Pliocene and Pleistocene sediments (Coleoptera: Curculionidae).</article-title> <source>Coleopterists Bulletin </source> <volume>27</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>200</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1134/S0031030110010089" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1134/S0031030110010089</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Klebs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1910</year>)<article-title> Über Bernstein einschlüsse im allgemeinen und die Coleopteren meiner Bernsteinsammlung.</article-title> <source>Schriften der Physikalisch-Ökonomischen Gesellschaft zu Königsberg </source> <volume>51</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>217</fpage>-<lpage>242</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyakawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> The insects of Japan. Volume 3. Curculionoidea: general introduction and Curculionidae: Entiminae (part 1). Phyllobiini, Polydrusini and Cyphicerini (Coleoptera). Touka Shobo Co. Ltd., Fukuoka, iv + 406 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberprieler</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> A reclassification of the weevil subfamily Cyclominae (Coleoptera: Curculionidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2515</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poinar</surname><given-names>G Jr.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of a broad-nosed weevil (Eudiagogini: Curculionidae) and false ladybird beetle (Nilionini: Nilionidae) in Dominican amber.</article-title> <source>Historical Biology, </source> <volume>23</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>235</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/08912963.2010.527159" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1080/08912963.2010.527159</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ponomarenko</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zherikhin</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirejtshuk</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> Catalogue of fossil Coleoptera. http://www.zin.ru/Animalia/Coleoptera/rus/paleosys.htm [accessed 1.III.2011]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Serres</surname><given-names>M de</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1829</year>)<source> Gèognosie des Terrains Tertiaires, ou Tableau des principaux animaux invertébrés des terrains marins tertiaires, du midi de la France.</source> <publisher-name>Pomathio-Durville</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris-Montpellier</publisher-loc>, <lpage>277</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Spahr</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<article-title> Systematischer Katalog der Bernstein- und Kopal-Käfer (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Stuttgarter Beiträge zur Naturkunde </source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Takhtajan</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<source> Proiskhozhdenie i rasprostranenie zvetkovykh rasteniy [Origins and Dispersion of Flowering Plants]. Nauka, Leningrad, 1–146. </source>[in Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Observations on the morphology and classification of weevils (Coleoptera, Curculionoidea) with a key to major groups.</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History </source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>835</fpage>-<lpage>891</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222939200770511" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1080/00222939200770511</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1953</year>)<article-title> Einige Rhynchophoren der Bernsteinfauna (Col.).</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen aus dem Geologischen Staatsinstitut in Hamburg </source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Voss</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Einige Rüsselkäfer der Tertiarzeit aus Baltischem Bernstein (Coleoptera, Curculionoidea).</article-title> <source>Steenstrupia </source> <volume>2</volume> (<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>181</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boroviec</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> New genus of weevil (Coleoptera, Curculionidae) from Baltic amber.</article-title> <source>Polskie Pismo Entomologiczne </source> <volume>56</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>243</fpage>-<lpage>247</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zherikhin</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<article-title> O dolgonosikach (Insecta, Coleoptera) Baltiyskogo Jantarja [On the weevils (Insecta, Coleoptera) from the Baltic Amber].</article-title> <source>Trudy Palaeontologicheskogo Instituta </source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>-<lpage>209</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zherikhin</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Tertiary weevils (Insecta, Coleoptera: Curculionoidea), identified from the collections of the Senckerberg Museum.</article-title> <source>Senckerbergiana Lethaea </source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>-<lpage>178</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zherikhin</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Egorov</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<source> Weevils (Coleoptera, Curculionidae) of the USSR Far East (a review of the subfamilies with description of new taxa).</source> <publisher-name>Institute of Biology and Soil science</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Vladivostok</publisher-loc>, <lpage>164</lpage> pp.[in Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
        <!--PageBreak-->
				<app-group>
        <app id="app1"><title>Appendix</title>
            <p><bold>Checklist of prepleistocene fossil weevils of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name></bold></p>
            <p>(according to the taxonomic interpretation in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Zherikhin and Egorov 1991</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Ponomarenko et al. 2011</xref>)</p>
            <p>V.V. Zherikhin analyzed all available sources mentioning fossil <tp:taxon-name>Curculionoidea</tp:taxon-name> (Jurassic-Paleogene). Later the results of his analysis were published in the catalogue by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Ponomarenko et al. (2011)</xref>. In the list below (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) the authors mostly follow his subdivisions pertaining to the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name>. Many references in the list provided here need to be checked re-examining the fossils. Most accounts regarded as doubtful Zherikhin were removed from the following list. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Ponomarenko et al. (2011)</xref> treated them as ‘Subfamilia incerta’ or ‘Familia incerta’.</p>
            <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Table 2.</label>
                <caption><p>Checklist of prepleistocene fossil <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name>.</p><p><bold>Subfamilia <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name></bold> Schoenherr, 1823</p></caption>
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NN</bold></th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Species</bold></th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>age and site of finding</bold></th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Aterpini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Lacordaire, 1863 (<bold>see note 1 below this table</bold>)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>fossicius</italic> Scudder, 1893:75 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Geralophus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Tropiphorini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Marseul, 1863</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vitavitus thulius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kissinger, 1973</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2, Dece</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhytideres sexsulcatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Heer, 1856) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cleonus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) (= <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hipporhinus reynesii</tp:taxon-name></italic> Oustalet, 1874; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Brachycerus annosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Oustalet, 1874)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31st, Aix N13, Agri</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Cylydrorhinini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Lacordaire, 1863</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Dorotheus guidensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kuschel, 1959</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">K2, CerG</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Sitonini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Gistel, 1848</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitona</tp:taxon-name></italic> (subgenus incertus) <italic>lata</italic> Théobald, 1937</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?Pg31, unknown</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitona</tp:taxon-name></italic> (subgenus incertus) sp. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Hieke and Pietrzeniuk 1984</xref>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg23, BalJ</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Entimini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Schoenherr, 1823</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Geralophus antiquarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Scudder, 1893</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Geralophus occultus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Scudder, 1876) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Eurhinus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Geralophus lassatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Scudder, 1893</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Geralophus scudderi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wickham, 1911</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Eudomus robustus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Scudder, 1893</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Eudomus pinguis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Scudder, 1893</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hipporhinops sternbergi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cockerell, 1926</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg12, Sunc</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>saxatilis</italic> Scudder, 1876 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Eudiagogus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, GreR</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>effossus</italic> Scudder, 1876 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Eudiagogus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, GreR</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>compactus</italic> Scudder, 1878: 765 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Ophryastes</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, GreR</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>heeri</italic> Germar, 1849 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Hipporhinus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) (= <italic>matheroni</italic> Nicolas, 1891; <italic>similis</italic> Nicolas, 1891; <italic>intermedius</italic> Nicolas, 1891; <italic>marioni</italic> Nicolas, 1891; <italic>pertonii</italic> Nicolas, 1891 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Hipporhinus</tp:taxon-name></italic>))</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Aix </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>brevis</italic> Giebel, 1856 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Hipporhinus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Aix</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>schaumi</italic> Heer, 1856 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Hipporhinus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Aix</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>pumiceus</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Geralophus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>repositus</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Geralophus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>atavus</italic> Oustalet, 1870 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Bagous</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg33, Core</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Tanymecini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Lacordaire, 1863 (<bold>see note 2 below this table</bold>)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>rugosus</italic> Deichmüller, 1881 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Thylacites</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg3, Kucl</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protainophthalmus asperulus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Heer, 1856) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cleonus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) (including Théobald, 1937) (= <italic><tp:taxon-name>Brachyderes aquisextanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Oustalet, 1874, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Brachyderes longipes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Heer in Oustalet, 1874, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cleonus marcelli</tp:taxon-name></italic> Oustalet, 1874)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Aix, Cere</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protainophthalmus margarum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Germar, 1849) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitona</tp:taxon-name></italic>)&lt;br/&gt; (=<italic>antiqua</italic> Giebel, 1856) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitona</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Aix</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protainophthalmus punctulatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Nicolas, 1891) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Desmidophorus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Aix</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protainophthalmus regularis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Nicolas, 1891) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Hipporhinus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Aix</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protainophthalmus rugicollis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Heer, 1847) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Lixus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N13, Oeni</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protainophthalmus thaisi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Nicolas, 1891 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Desmidophorus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Aix</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protainophthalmus tuberculatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Nicolas, 1891 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Desmidophorus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31,Aix</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepropus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. (Zherikhin, 1992)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N13, Agri</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>nudus</italic> Wickham, 1912 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pandeleteius</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>secunda</italic> Wickham, 1912 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Paussopsis</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Phyllobiini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Schoenherr, 1826</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Phyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Spahr 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Hieke and Pietrzeniuk 1984</xref> etc.)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg23, BalJ</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Polydrusini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Schoenherr, 1823 (<bold>see note 3 below this table</bold>)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Polydrusus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Palaeodrosus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) <italic>archetypus</italic> Zherikhin, 1971</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg23, BalJ</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Polydrusus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Subgenus incertus) sp. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Burmeister 1832</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Hieke and Pietrzeniuk 1984</xref>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg23, BalJ</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Anypotactini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Champion, 1911</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paonaupactus sitonitoides</tp:taxon-name></italic> Voss, 1953 (<italic>=Polydrusus scheelei</italic> Voss, 1953; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Otiorhynchus pellucidipes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Voss, 1972)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg23, BalJ</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paonaupactus cephalotes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Voss, 1972) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Phyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg23, BalJ</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus microphthalmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Zherikhin, 1971</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg23, BalJ</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus sobrinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Voss, 1972) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Phyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sbg. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Subphyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic>); Wanat et Borowiec, 1986 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg23, BalJ</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protonaupactus viridis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Wanat et Borowiec, 1986) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sucinophyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg23, BalJ</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Hormorini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Horn, 1876 (see note 4 below this table)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hormorus undulatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Uhler, 1855) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Chlorophanus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal 1999</xref>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1, USA</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Pristorhynchini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Heer, 1847 (Pristorhynchiden)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pristorhynchus ellipticus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Heer, 1847</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N13, Oeni</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Naupactini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Gistel, 1856</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>florissantensis</italic> Wickham, 1914 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyphus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>subterraneus</italic> Wickham, 1911 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyphus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Otiorhynchini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Schoenherr, 1826</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Otiorhynchus boettingensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> van Emden in Zeuner, 1931</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N13, Boet </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Trachyphloeini</tp:taxon-name></bold> Lacordaire, 1863</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachyphloeus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. (Klebs, 1910)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg23, BalJ </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Eudiagogini</tp:taxon-name></bold> LeConte, 1874</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Promecops tumidirostris</tp:taxon-name></italic> Poinar &amp; Brown, 2011</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N11, DomJ</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="3"><bold>Tribe uncertain</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Laccopygus nilesii</tp:taxon-name></italic> Scudder, 1893</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Evopes veneratus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Scudder, 1893</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Oligocryptus sectus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Scudder, 1893) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Eucryptus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>atavina</italic> Heer, 1847 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitona</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N13, Oeni</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>crassirostris</italic> Heer, 1864 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Naupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N13, Oeni</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>dilapsus</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Phyxelis</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, GreR</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>durus</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cryptorhynchus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, RoaM</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>eradicatus</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Phyxelis</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, RoaM</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>evanidus</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Omileus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>evigoratus</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Phyxelis</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, WhiR</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>exanimis</italic> Scudder, 1876 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Eudiagogus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epicaerus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, GreR </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>fortis</italic> Cockerell, 1909 (?<italic><tp:taxon-name>Syntomostylus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, GreR</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>manderstjernai</italic> Heyden et Heyden, 1866 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tychius</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N11, Rott</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>margarum</italic> Theobald, 1937 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitona</tp:taxon-name></italic>) [HN]</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg23, Cela</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>obdurefactus</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Exomias</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, RoaM</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>occubatus</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Evopes</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>perditus</italic> Scudder, 1876 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Otiorhynchus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, GreR</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>petrarum</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Ophryastes</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, RoaM </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>recuperatus</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Lachnopus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Flor </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>rhenanus</italic> Meuner, 1923 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Laccopygus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N11, Rott </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>subteractus</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Otiorhynchus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, RoaM </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>subterraneus</italic> Scudder, 1893 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Scythropus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, GreR, WhiR </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>terrosus</italic> Scudder, 1878 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Eudiagogus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg22, RoaM, WhiR </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus <italic>venustulus</italic> Heyden et Heyden, 1866 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitona</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N11, Rott </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus incertus sp. (Serres, 1829) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Naupactus</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg31, Aix</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <p>Notes to table 2.</p>
            <p><bold>1</bold>. In contrast to the interpretations of Zherikhin, the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Aterpini</tp:taxon-name> is traditionally treated as belonging to the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Cyclominae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Oberprieler 2010</xref>, Bouchard et al. 2011) [in the classification proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Zherikhin and Egorov (1991)</xref> it is considered in ‘<tp:taxon-name>Tropiphorinae</tp:taxon-name>’]. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal (1999)</xref> consider the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hipporhinops</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Cyclominae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p><bold>2</bold>. According to V.V. Zherikhin’s unpublished data, genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protainophthalmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Zherikhin, 1992 comprises 7 species originally described within ‘<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cleonus</tp:taxon-name></italic>’, ‘<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitona</tp:taxon-name></italic>’, ‘<italic><tp:taxon-name>Desmidophorus</tp:taxon-name></italic>’, ‘<italic><tp:taxon-name>Hipporhinus</tp:taxon-name></italic>’ and <italic>‘Lixus’</italic> from the Late Paleogene of France and Germany. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protainophthalmus asperulus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Heer, 1856) known by three type prints (see Oustalet 1874: 259–263 + plate 3: Figs 20 and 21), two of them (from Aix) are types. We consider they belong to different species or even different genera: since the first print (see Oustalet 1874: Fig. 20) has a transverse sulcus behind the epifrons, but the second print (Oustalet 1874: Fig. 20) does not have such a transverse sulcus. The original description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protainophthalmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Zherikhin 1992</xref>: 174) also includes two prints <!--PageBreak-->(SMF VI 218 and SMF VI 220, Senckenberg Museum) from Agrigento (Italy) which are not types of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protainophthalmus asperulus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <p><bold>3</bold>. The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phyllobius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Germar, 1824 could not be placed in <tp:taxon-name>Polydrusini</tp:taxon-name> because of significant differences in head structure: long and closed swinging fossae, antennal scrobes not developed (foveiform) and scape not folding while in rest. V.V. Zherikhin, proposed that the tribes <tp:taxon-name>Polydrusini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Phyllobiini</tp:taxon-name> are synonyms. He considered that the number of mandibular setae is constant and may be used for discrimination of suprageneric groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Zherikhin and Egorov 1991</xref>). Further study of <tp:taxon-name>Polydrusini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Phyllobiini</tp:taxon-name> genera showed a great variety of the number of mandibular setae. Recent molecular analysis based on two genes 16S rDNA and 18S rDNA, showed that <tp:taxon-name>Polydrusini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Phyllobiini</tp:taxon-name> are nested in different branches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Hundsdoerfer et al. 2009</xref>).</p>
            <p><bold>4</bold>. According to the current interpretation, the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Hormorini</tp:taxon-name> is assigned to <tp:taxon-name>Entiminae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alonso-Zarazaga and Lyal 1999</xref>). This opinion corresponds to the results of our examination of mandibles, which revealed similarity between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hormorus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and the North-Pacific genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Byrsopages</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schoenherr, 1842. The abnormal shape of the mandibles, subflattened dorso-ventrally along the anterior edge and ventral position of the mandibular processes, led Zherikhin to refuse this opinion, and he treated <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hormorus</tp:taxon-name></italic> without subfamily placement as ‘subfamilia incerta’.</p>
        </app>
				</app-group>
    </back>
</article>