<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.93.1159</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>The millipede genus <italic>Caucasodesmus</italic> Golovatch, 1985, with the description of a new species from the Crimea, Ukraine (Polydesmida, Diplopoda, Trichopolydesmidae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Sergei I.</surname> 
                        <given-names>Golovatch</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"></xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:71532F45-BDD5-415D-BC54-86256E5D5D4A</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label></label>Institute for Problems of Ecology and Evolution, Russian Academy of Sciences, Leninsky pr. 33. Moscow 119071, Russia</aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Sergei I. Golovatch (<email xlink:type="simple">sgolovatch@yandex.ru</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Robert Mesibov</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
            	    <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>29</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>93</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>8</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>21</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>5</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Sergei I. Golovatch</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:974E31F2-ED39-454A-809D-BE6C64E6B140</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The hitherto monotypic genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is new to the Ukrainian list due to the discovery of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus tauricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> in a cave in the Crimea. The new species is easily distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Golovatch, 1985, the type, and only other, known species of this genus, in the abundantly setose collum and following metaterga, and more elaborate gonopods. The status of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, which shows in the superfamily Trichopolydesmoidea where it definitely belongs such evident generic-level apomorphies as the absence of bacilliform sensilla on antennomeres 5 and 7, of a cannula on the gonocoxite, and of a seminal groove on a biramous gononod telopodite (apparently, both latter characters are functionally correlated to each other), is refined by formally reassigning it to the family Trichopolydesmidae.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>millipede</kwd>
                <kwd>Trichopolydesmidae</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>cave</kwd>
                <kwd>Crimea</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The millipede fauna of the Crimea has recently been reviewed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Golovatch 2008</xref>), with only 14 species from 11 genera, seven families and six orders being involved. Of these, only two or three species are possibly Crimean endemics, whereas most show more or less widely (Euro-)Mediterranean distributions.</p>
            <p>The more so important is the present discovery of still another new millipede in a cave in the Crimea. Unlike all other faunal elements, this new species might prove to represent the first truly relict, palaeoendemic in the diplopod list of that peninsula.</p>
            <p>Material serving as the basis for the present contribution was captured with pitfall traps, later transferred into 75% alcohol and is currently deposited in the collection of the Zoological Museum, State University of Moscow, Russia. Specimens were studied and illustrated using standard stereomicroscopic, photographic and drawing equipment.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics"><title>Systematics</title>
            <p><bold><tp:taxon-name>Trichopolydesmidae</tp:taxon-name> Verhoeff, 1910</bold></p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Caucasodesmus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Golovatch, 1985</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Golovatch, 1985: 40.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species:</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Golovatch, 1985, by original designation.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Caucasodesmus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">tauricus</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:66FEBC49-89EC-432E-A0E2-561179B19B24</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Caucasodesmus_tauricus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">8</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material:</title>
                    <p>Holotype ♂, Ukraine, Crimea, Mt Villya-Burun, Cave Villyaburunskaya, pitfall traps, 12.05.2008–12.10.2010, leg. A. Koval. – Paratype: 1 ♀, same locality, 19.07.2004–17.07.2006, leg. A. Koval.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis:</title>
                    <p>Easily distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Golovatch, 1985, the type, and only other, known species of this genus, by the abundantly setose metaterga and more elaborate gonopods.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description:</title>
                    <p>Length of both sexes ca 8 mm, width of midbody pro- and metazona 0.8 and 1.5 mm, respectively. Coloration in alcohol from uniformly pallid to light yellowish.</p>
                    <p>Body with 20 segments. Tegument mainly dull, at most slightly shining, texture very delicately alveolate. Head densely pilose throughout; epicranial suture distinct<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> but thin; isthmus between antennae ca 1.5 times broader than length of antennomere 1, still broader than diameter of antennal socket. Antennae rather short, evidently clavate due to a considerably enlarged antennomere 6, slightly overreaching segment 2 dorsally; antennomeres 2, 3 and 6 longest, subequal in length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>, <!--PageBreak--><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">2</xref>); only antennomere 6 with a large, compact, roundish, distodorsal group of bacilliform sensilla.</p>
                    <p>In width, collum &lt; segment 2 = 3 &lt; head = 4 &lt; 5=16 (♂) or head = collum = segment 2 = 4 &lt; 5=16 (♀), thereafter body gradually tapering towards telson. Paraterga moderately developed, starting from collum, subhorizontal to slightly declivous, set high but always lying slightly below a faintly convex dorsum, devoid of shoulders frontally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–3</xref>). Caudal corner of postcollum paraterga invariably spiniform, pointed, starting from segment 4 extending increasingly further than rear tergal margin. Lateral edge of paraterga with neither marginal groove nor thickening, with 5–6 clear setigerous indentations. Pore formula normal, ozopores evident, round, located laterally in front of caudalmost incision. Collum and following metaterga beset with numerous medium-sized setae set on minute knobs, polygonal bosses missing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–3</xref>). Stricture between pro- and metazona wide, shallow and smooth. Limbus very thin, microdenticulate. Pleurosternal carinae absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>). Epiproct short, conical, directed caudoventrally; preapical papillae small (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>). Hypoproct subtrapeziform, setiferous papillae at caudal corners evident, rather well separated.</p>
                    <p>Sterna without modifications, poorly setose. Epigynal ridge very low. Legs rather short (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">5</xref>), ca 1.2–1.3 (♂) or 0.9–1.0 (♀) times as long as midbody height; ♀ legs slightly slenderer; ♂ legs with clearly enlarged prefemora and femora; tarsi especially long and slender, claw long, ca 1/4 length of tarsus; sphaerotrichomes missing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Gonopod aperture large, transversely oblong-oval, taking up nearly all of ventral part of metazonite 7. Gonopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 6–8</xref>) with large, globose, medially fused coxae carrying rather numerous setae laterally, but no trace of a cannula. Telopodite subfalcate, distally of a rather short prefemoral (= setose) portion split into two branches: exomere (<bold>ex</bold>) largest and longest, more simple, whereas endomere (<bold>en</bold>) shorter, more complex in shape; an evident, tooth-like, mesal process (<bold>d</bold>) at base between both <bold>ex</bold> and <bold>en</bold>; no trace of a seminal groove.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–4.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus tauricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype. <bold>1, 2</bold> anterior half of body, dorsal and lateral views, respectively <bold>3, 4</bold> posterior portion of body, dorsal and ventral views, respectively. Photographed not to scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-093-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 5–8.</label>
                        <caption><p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus tauricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype. <bold>5</bold> leg 9 (setae not shown) <bold>6</bold> rightgonopod, anteromesal view <bold>7, 8</bold>,left gonopod, mesal, and lateral views, respectively. Scale bar: 0.4 (<bold>5</bold>) and 0.2 mm (<bold>6–8</bold>).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-093-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>This species is an unquestioned relict troglobite and, based on its zoogeographical traits, might well represent the first palaeoendemic in the diplopod fauna of the Crimea.</p>
                    <p>Only one species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has hitherto been known: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Cave Nyvjin Lagat (= Nyvdzhinlagat, = Tagardonskaya) in North Ossetia, central Caucasus Major (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Golovatch 1984/85</xref>). The second congener, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus tauricus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., shares with the type species such remarkable, clearly generic-level apomorphies as the absence of bacilliform sensilla on antennomeres 5 and 7, of a cannula on the gonocoxite, and of a seminal groove on a biramous gononod telopodite. Apparently, both latter characters are functionally correlated to each other, differing from the loss of a cannula alone which is observed in the families <tp:taxon-name>Dalodesmidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Rhachodesmidae</tp:taxon-name>. The differences lie in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> showing a far more moniliform body, only three transverse rows of setae on the collum and following metaterga, and less strongly elaborate gonopod telopodites.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematic position of Caucasodesmus"><title>Systematic position of Caucasodesmus</title>
            <p>Originally, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was treated as a genus of the small Holarctic family <tp:taxon-name>Macrosternodesmidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Golovatch 1984/85</xref>). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Shear and Shelley (2007)</xref>, in their recent reassessment of the <tp:taxon-name>Macrosternodesmidae</tp:taxon-name>, have ejected <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> from that family, leaving it unclassified. These authors have also advanced a new terminology of the various parts of a polydesmidan gonopod. This has been further refined even more recently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Shear et al. 2009</xref>), in particular in accepting such denominations as exo- and endomere.</p>
            <p>The superfamily <tp:taxon-name>Trichopolydesmoidea</tp:taxon-name> can be defined by its gonopod prefemoral (= setose) part orientated mostly transversely to the body’s main axis, extending mesally across the entire width of the coxae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Hoffman 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Simonsen 1990</xref>). Within this superfamily, where <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> undoubtedly belongs, there are several, mainly small families in addition to <tp:taxon-name>Macrosternodesmidae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Trichopolydesmidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Neoarctodesmidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Furhmannodesmidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Mastigonodesmidae</tp:taxon-name>. To find a new, more suitable place for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, their diagnoses must briefly be reiterated, especially as regards their gonopod conformation.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Macrosternodesmidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Shear and Shelley 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Shear et al. 2009</xref>): In this Holarctic family, the gonopod aperture is large, transversely oval. The coxae completely fill the respective halves of the aperture, excavated mesad to accommodate the telopodites; the prefemora are horizontal or angling ventromesad, giving rise to the acropodite and often, but not always, to an additional projection; the acropodite part distal to the origin of a solenomere (distal zone) variably configured, sometimes folded, flattened, and not recognizable as such; the solenomere is long and narrow, arising subterminally, with neither a hairpad nor an accessory seminal chamber (= ampulla); the seminal groove opens terminally.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Nearctodesmidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Shelley 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Shear et al. 2009</xref>): This small Nearctic group shares basically the same gonopod conformation with <tp:taxon-name>Macrosternodesmidae</tp:taxon-name>. No wonder it has sometimes been treated as only a subfamily or even a possible synonym of the latter family.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Trichopolydesmidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Ceuca 1958</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Mauriès 1983</xref>): This small, mainly Mediterranean family shows basically the same gonopod structure as the previous two groups, except in the prefemoral part sometimes being shortened (e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Galliocookia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ribaut, 1955, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Occitanocookia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mauriès, 1980 and a few others), i.e. rather strongly resembling the condition observed in the family <tp:taxon-name>Polydesmidae</tp:taxon-name> (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Hoffman 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Simonsen 1990</xref>), while the telopodite is bi- or uniramous, far less elaborate, often with a long flagelliform solenomere. Yet I am inclined to follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Mauriès (1983)</xref> in treating such somewhat deviating genera as representing rather peculiar <tp:taxon-name>Trichopolydesmoidea</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Mastigonodesmidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Mauriès 1980</xref>, 1982): This very small, purely western Mediterranean group of polydesmidean millipedes is sometimes regarded as only one of the numerous genera of <tp:taxon-name>Polydesmidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Hoffman 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Simonsen 1990</xref>), apparently because the gonopod prefemoral part in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mastigonodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Silvestri, 1898, is also shortened, but, due to its globose gonocoxae and a peculiar, parabasal, long and coiled solenomere, it seems more similar to trichopolydesmoids. So I am again inclined to<!--PageBreak--> follow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Mauriès (1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">1982</xref>) in regarding this group as representing rather peculiar <tp:taxon-name>Trichopolydesmoidea</tp:taxon-name> as well.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Fuhrmannodesmidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Golovatch 1994</xref>): This profoundly diverse, pantropical group of small polydesmideans shows a wide range of situations transitional in gonopod conformation between the typical <tp:taxon-name>Polydesmoidea</tp:taxon-name> and the typical <tp:taxon-name>Trichopolydesmoidea</tp:taxon-name>. At least in the Neotropical fauna, the gonopod coxae can be small and devoid of a gonocoel, with (sub)erect telopodites, yet more often the coxae are enlarged and deeply excavate for the accommodation of more stout, usually elaborate telopodites that can have a shortened to medially stretched prefemoral part supporting either crossing or parallel acropodites, the latter with or without a distinct solenomere. This highly heterogeneous assemblage certainly merits splitting into several natural families, but such a task is by necessity to be deferred because of the numerous genera and species involved, many of which still require revision.</p>
            <p>Based on the above diagnoses and distributions, it appears to be quite difficult to unequivocally reallocate <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The correlated absence of both a cannula and a seminal groove is probably a sufficiently strong apomorphy to erect still another family of <tp:taxon-name>Trichopolydesmoidea</tp:taxon-name> for the accommodation of solely this genus, but I refrain here from doing so pending more information becomes available. New taxa are still being regularly described, new synonymies established, and old types revised. Instead I reassign <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caucasodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> to <tp:taxon-name>Trichopolydesmidae</tp:taxon-name> as a family not only representing the oldest taxon in the superfamily, but also one which shows the same basic traits of gonopod structure and a coherent distribution pattern.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>I am most grateful to Alexandr Koval, St Petersburg, Russia, who has kindly allowed me to study his invaluable material, as well as to deposit it entirely in the Moscow Museum. I am also deeply obliged to Kirill Makarov, Moscow, Russia who skillfully took the pictures, and to Igor Muratov, Pietermaritzburg, Republic of South Africa for his kind technical assistance.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceuca</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>)<article-title> Contribuţii la cunoaşterea diplopodelor din fauna Republicii Populare Romîne. III. Diplopode cavernicole.</article-title> <source>Studii şi Cercetări de Biologie (Cluj)</source> <volume>2</volume> (<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>335</fpage>-<lpage>343</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Golovatch</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984/85</year>) <article-title>Two new genera of cave-dwelling millipedes (Diplopoda), with remarks on the millipede fauna of West Caucasian caves.</article-title> <source>International Journal of Speleology</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Golovatch</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Further new Fuhrmannodesmidae from the environs of Manaus, Central Amazonia, Brazil, with a revision of <italic>Cryptogonodesmus</italic> Silvestri, 1898 (Diplopoda, Polydesmida).</article-title> <source>Amazoniana</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1/2</issue>): <fpage>131</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
          	<ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Golovatch</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> On three remarkable millipedes (Diplopoda) from the Crimea, Ukraine.</article-title> <source>International Journal of Myriapodology</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/187525408X316767" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1163/187525408X316767</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<source> Classification of the Diplopoda.</source> <publisher-name>Muséum d’histoire naturelle</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Genève</publisher-loc>, <lpage>237</lpage>pp. (for 1979).</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<article-title> Diplopoda.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Synopsis and classification of living organisms 2</source>. <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>New York &amp; St Louis</publisher-loc>, <fpage>689</fpage>–<lpage>724</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mauriès</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Description d’une nouvelle espèce et d’un genre nouveau de diplopodes polydesmides hypogés récoltés dans l’arrondissement de Béziers (Héraults).</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Société d’Histoire Naturelle de Toulouse</source> <volume>116</volume>(<issue>3/4</issue>): <fpage>228</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mauriès</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<article-title> Un nouveau diplopode polydesmide cavernicole du Département du Gard : <italic>Manstigonodesmus fagniezi</italic> n. sp. (Polydesmidea, Mastigonodesmidae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Société d’Histoire Naturelle de Toulouse</source> <volume>118</volume>:<fpage>141</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mauriès</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> Le genre <italic>Galliocookia</italic> Ribaut, 1954. Deux espèces nouvelles des grottes de l’Ardèche et du Gard (Myriapoda, Diplopoda, Polydesmida).</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Société d’Histoire Naturelle de Toulouse</source> <volume>119</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Shear</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shelley</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> The milliped genus <italic>Tidesmus</italic> Chamberlin, 1943 (Polydesmida: Macrosternodesmidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1656</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Shear</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wynne</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krejca</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title>Cave millipeds of the United States. VIII. New genera and species of polydesmidan millipeds from caves in the southwestern United States (Diplopoda, Polydesmida, Macrosternodesmidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2151</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Shelley</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> The milliped family Nearctodesmidae in northwestern North America, with accounts of <italic>Sakophallus</italic> and <italic>S. simplex</italic> Chamberlin (Polydesmida).</article-title> <source>Canadian Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>470</fpage>–<lpage>495</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1139/z94-066" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1139/z94-066</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simonsen</surname><given-names>Å</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<source> Phylogeny and biogeography of the millipede order Polydesmida, with special emphasis on the suborder Polydesmidea.</source> <publisher-name>Institute of Zoology, University of Bergen</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Bergen</publisher-loc>, 114pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>