<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
	      				<journal-title>ZooKeys</journal-title>
    				</journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.100.1522</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    <italic>Calleida desenderi</italic>, new species from Ecuador (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Lebiinae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Casale</surname>
                        <given-names>Achille</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7488DBB2-9447-4698-8613-5E90D5C7228D</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Università di Sassari, Dipartimento di Zoologia e Genetica Evoluzionistica, Via Muroni 25, 07100 Sassari (Italy)
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Achille Casale (<email xlink:type="simple">casale@uniss.it</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: T. Erwin</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>20</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>100</issue>
            <fpage>47</fpage>
            <lpage>54</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>11</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>24</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Achille Casale</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:2A9D9ABB-AF4B-4CFF-812C-460358480B2D</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida desenderi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Casale, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, is described from Ecuador, Napo Province, surroundings of San Rafael. The new taxon is mostly characterized by the head and appendages rufous, the disc of elytra with marked metallic green reflection, the median lobe of aedeagus ring-like, and the endophallus with a long, twisted flagellum. A key for identification of the closer Neotropical species described so far is also provided.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Coleoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Carabidae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Calleida desenderi</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>Ecuador</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>As I recently noted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Casale 2008</xref>), Ecuador, in spite of its small surface area (283,561 square kms), is a South American country that includes a surprising variety of environments. Thanks to its geographical position crossed by the Equator, the occurrence of some of the highest peaks of Southern America, and the presence of tropical rain and cloud forests on both the Pacific and Amazon sides of the Andes, Ecuador is currently cited as one of the main hot-spots of biodiversity and endemism in the world, but also <!--PageBreak-->as one of the areas more threatened by deforestation. However, its mainland insect fauna, with some exceptions (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Moret 2005</xref>), is little known at present. Amongst carabid beetles, the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dejean 1825 (in the widest sense of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Chaudoir 1972</xref>), including nice, arboreal species mostly tied to wet forests, can be cited as a good example of scarce knowledge.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, the Galapagos islands and their biodiversity offer a fantastic place for any student familiar with evolutionary biology, and have been investigated for many decades. Several contributions from these investigations include beetles (for a synopsis see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Peck 2006</xref>).</p>
            <p>Konjev Desender and Jean Pierre Maelfait contributed greatly to the knowledge of the arthropod fauna of the Galapagos Islands: thanks to many travels, they had the opportunity to produce a series of highly interesting scientific contributions dedicated to this archipelago (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Lövei 2011</xref> for a list of Konjev’s publications).</p>
            <p>Thanks to Konjev, I had the opportunity to describe the only <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida</tp:taxon-name></italic> species known so far in Galapagos (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida migratoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> Casale in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Desender et al. 2002</xref>), a species introduced from Peru and now widely spread on several islands. Therefore, this is for me an honour – but also a great sadness - to dedicate to him this paper, and a very fine and interesting <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida</tp:taxon-name></italic> species from Ecuador, in memory of pleasant days spent with him in congresses, in the field, and at his Institute in Brussels.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The following data come from many specimens of Neotropical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida</tp:taxon-name></italic> species examined so far (including type series), most of them received from different museums, institutes and colleagues. The type material of the new species here described has been offered to me for study by my good friend Giovanni Onore, former professor of Entomology at the Pontificia Universidad Catolica del Ecuador in Quito.</p>
            <p>Male genitalia were dissected, dehydrated in ethanol, cleared in cold KOH, examined and illustrated, using standard techniques before their definitive inclusion on microscope slides. Line drawings were made using a camera lucida attached to stereomicroscopes Wild M-3 and Wild M-5, and a microscope Leitz Orthoplan. The photograph of habitus was obtained using a digital camera Canon G6 attached to stereomicroscope Zeiss Stemi 2000.</p>
            <sec sec-type="Acronyms:">
                <title>Acronyms:</title>
                <p><abbrev xlink:type="simple">TL<def><p>	body Total Length, from the anterior margin of clypeus to the apex of elytra, measured along the suture.</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev xlink:type="simple">L<def><p>	overall Length, from apex of mandibles to apex of elytra, measured along the suture.</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev xlink:type="simple">PL/PW<def><p>	ratio Length of Pronotum, as linear distance from the anterior to the basal margin, measured along the midline/maximum Width of Pronotum, as greatest transverse distance.<!--PageBreak--></p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev xlink:type="simple">EL/EW<def><p>	ratio Length of Elytra, as linear distance from the basal ridge to the apex, measured along the suture/maximum Width of Elytra.</p></def></abbrev></p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Collections:">
                <title>Collections:</title>
                <p><abbrev xlink:type="simple">QCAZ<def><p>	Zoology Museum, Departamento de Biologia, Pontificia Universidad Catolica del Ecuador, Quito (Ecuador)</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev xlink:type="simple">CCa<def><p>	Casale collection, University of Sassari (Italy)</p></def></abbrev></p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomic treatment and morphological terms">
            <title>Taxonomic treatment and morphological terms</title>
            <p>In this contribution, the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida</tp:taxon-name></italic> is treated in the narrow sense, i.e. as a unit including only American species, and excluding African and Asiatic taxa (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Callidiola</tp:taxon-name></italic> Jeannel, 1949, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Stenocallida</tp:taxon-name></italic> Jeannel, 1949, of authors), currently treated at subgeneric rank of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see, among others: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Lorenz 2005</xref>). In spite of this choice, the limits of these generic groups are not yet defined.</p>
            <p>The median lobe of aedeagus is a synonym of phallus of some authors. Endophallus is synonym of inner sac of authors.</p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Calleida</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">desenderi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D9A8E5CC-04AB-4F26-AB9E-BAB0216BD3F8</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Calleida_desenderi</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Casale</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis.">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>With the character states of the Neotropical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida</tp:taxon-name></italic> species (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Erwin 2004</xref>), but markedly characterised by the peculiar combination of the following morphological features: medium sized (L: 9.0–9.5 mm; TL: 8.5–9.0 mm); body and appendages rufous, contrasting in colour with the translucent, metallic green disc of elytra; pronotum slightly transverse, with lateral margins slightly sinuate in the basal fourth; elytra moderately elongate, depressed, with marked pre-apical callosity and apical margin not beaded, bent and prominent at the sutural angle. Abdominal sternum VII with two setae on each side in males, three setae in females.</p>
                    <p>Male genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 3–5</xref>: median lobe of aedeagus ring-like, depressed at sides; apex short; endophallus with a long, twisted flagellum.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida desenderi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female paratype, habitus, dorsal aspect.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-100-047-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <p>Close to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida scyntillans</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bates, 1883 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida schumacheri</tp:taxon-name></italic> Steinheil, 1875, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida desenderi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is distinguishable from the closest Neotropical species for the features stressed below (see Key, in Relationships).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality.">
                    <title>Type locality.</title>
                    <p>Ecuador, Napo: San Rafael, 1400 m.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material.">
                    <title>Type material.</title>
                    <p>Holotype ♂: Ecuador, Napo: Reventador, San Rafael 1400 m, 10 Jan 1998 F. Maza, at light trap (QCAZ); paratype ♀: Ecuador, Sucumbios, Cascada San Rafael, 1150 m, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">77°33'30"W, 00°2'44"S</named-content>, 30 Apr 2004, D. Cisneros (CCa).</p>
                    <p>Note: the male holotype presents some malformations (elytral intervals wrinkled, metatibiae asymmetrically curved). For this very reason, the female paratype is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology and dedication.">
                    <title>Etymology and dedication.</title>
                    <p>It is a great honor for me to dedicate this new Ecuadorian species to the memory of Konjev Desender, the Belgian carabidologist who contributed greatly to the knowledge of carabids of the Galapagos Islands, the famous archipelago belonging to the Republic of Ecuador</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description.">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>General features as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>. Medium sized: L: 9.0 mm (male holotype) – 9.5 mm (female paratype); TL: mm 8.5 mm (male holotype) – 9.0 mm (female paratype).</p>
                    <p><italic>Colour:</italic> Head, base of antennae, prothorax, pterothorax, abdomen, basal and lateral margins of elytra, and legs, concolorous pale rufous; apex of mandibles, apical half of antennomere 4, and antennomeres 5–11 markedly infuscated; disc of elytra translucent, light metallic golden green (but reddish at oblique light), with cupreous-purple reflections at apex and on the sutural interval.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p><italic>Lustre and microsculpure:</italic> Head and pronotum shiny, with highly effaced microsculpture; elytra shiny, translucent, with fine, hardly visible reticulate sculpture and marked metallic lustre.</p>
                    <p><italic>Head:</italic> wide, with moderate neck constriction; genae short, moderately swollen and regularly curved to the neck constriction, not contiguous with the posterior margin of eyes; frontal furrows sparsely punctuate; eyes very large and prominent; two supraorbital setae on each side.</p>
                    <p><italic>Prothorax:</italic> subquadrate, slightly wider than long (ratio PL/PW: 0.9), with lateral sides shortly sinuate in the basal fourth. Lateral reflection moderate, more evident basally; lateral furrows wide, depressed, each with a series of deep punctures. Disc moderately depressed, with marked transversal wrinkles. Anterior angles rounded, not prominent; basal angles obtuse. Basal margin markedly oblique <!--PageBreak-->at the extreme lateral sides. One paramedial seta and one basolateral seta on each side present.</p>
                    <p><italic>Elytra:</italic> moderately elongate (ratio EL/EW: 1.7), slightly widened at the apical third; disc depressed, with evident concavity at the middle on each elytron; striae superficial, shallowly punctuate; intervals flat. Post-humeral sinuation shallow, pre-apical outer callosity evident on intervals 7–8. Apical margin obliquely bent, markedly prominent at the sutural angle, not beaded. Interval 3 with two small discal and one apical setiferous pores; umbilicate series of 13 pores along stria 8.</p>
                    <p><italic>Hind wings:</italic> fully developed.</p>
                    <p><italic>Legs:</italic> femora robust, tibiae elongate, tarsomeres of slender form; only metatarsomere 1 grooved dorsally; metatarsomere 4 deeply bilobed, its lobes short, widened and truncate at apex. Tarsal claws denticulate, each with six long teeth on the inner side.</p>
                    <p><italic>Abdominal sterna:</italic> sternum VII with two setae on each side in males, three setae in females; male abdominal segment IX as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2-5.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida desenderi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype <bold>2</bold> abdominal segment IX, ring sclerite <bold>3</bold> male genitalia, median lobe of aedeagus and inner sac, dorsal-right aspect <bold>4</bold> male genitalia, median lobe of aedeagus and inner sac, lateral left aspect <bold>5</bold> male genitalia, left paramere.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-100-047-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <p><italic>Male genitalia:</italic> median lobe of aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 3–4</xref>) ring-like, depressed at sides; apex short, distally rounded; endophallus with a long, twisted flagellum. Left paramere as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>.</p>
                    <p><italic>Female genitalia:</italic> not examined, owing to the fact that the abdominal sterna, in the only female specimen known so far, were not fully sclerotized.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Geographical distribution and ecology.">
                    <title>Geographical distribution and ecology.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida desenderi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.is known so far from Ecuador (Napo Province), surroundings of San Rafael, on the Amazon side of the Andes. The two specimens of the type series were obtained in January and April, in two different years, in secondary humid premontane forests at 1150–1400 m.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Relationships.">
                    <title>Relationships.</title>
                    <p>The most interesting and curious fact is that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida desenderi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is very similar in external features to the sympatric species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida vignai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Casale, 2008, this also known so far from only two individuals sampled in two different years. This datum confirms the well known occurrence, in arboreal canopies of tropical forests, of apparently rare sibling species belonging to different species groups, markedly isolated by pre-zygotic barriers thanks to different phenologies, habitat choices, and by completely different morphological features in genitalia.</p>
                    <p>In fact, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida vignai</tp:taxon-name></italic>, for the character state of male genitalia (median lobe of aedeagus elongate and slender, endophallus with copulatory lamella composed by two pieces connected at the base), belongs to a group of taxa that I indicated as <italic>lindigii</italic> species group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Casale 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2008</xref>).</p>
                    <p>On the contrary, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida desenderi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. belongs to another group of Neotropical species, that here I will indicate as <italic>cupreocincta</italic> species group. Diagnostic features of this group are: body and appendages rufous, elytra in part or fully metallic green; elytra moderately elongate, depressed, with apical margin not beaded. Abdominal sternum VII with two setae on each side in males, three setae in females. Male genitalia: median lobe of aedeagus ring-like, depressed at sides; endophallus with a long, twisted flagellum.</p>
                    <p>The group includes some not yet described species from Central and Southern America. The species described so far can be distinguished by the following key:</p>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genae markedly swollen, abruptly constricted to the neck. Elytral disc mostly dark rufous, with metallic green reflection only at base and on outer intervals 7–9. Elytral pre-apical callosity slightly distinct. Metatarsomeres 1–3 deeply grooved dorsally. Range: Brazil, Atlantic coast (Pernambuco, Rio de Janeiro)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida cupreocincta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chaudoir, 1848</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genae swollen but regularly curved, not abruptly constricted to the neck. Elytral disc with metallic reflection extended to all intervals. Elytral pre-apical callosity markedly distinct on intervals 7–8. Metatarsomere 3 not grooved dorsally</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum elongate, constricted in front. Elytral disc with marked metallic green reflection, but with distinct reddish patch on the inner intervals, more evident at oblique light. Metatarsomeres 1–2 superficially grooved dorsally. Range: Central America (Panama)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida scyntillans</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bates, 1883</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum subquadrate or slightly transverse. Elytral disc fully metallic green or golden green. Only metatarsomere 1 grooved dorsally</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apical half of antennomere 1, and following antennomeres, markedly infuscated. Apical margin and sutural interval of elytra with metallic cupreous-purple reflection. Range: Ecuador (Napo)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida desenderi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Casale, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennae fully rufous. Sutural interval of elytra bright metallic green; apical margin of elytra yellow reddish, as the base and lateral margins. Range: Colombia</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calleida schumacheri</tp:taxon-name></italic> Steinheil, 1875</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>For the loan or gift of material on which this description is based, and for his constant help in Ecuador, I am particularly indebted to my good friend Giovanni Onore (Quito).</p>
            <p>I highly appreciated the support of Dr Thierry Deuve (Paris, France) for the loan of type material from the collections in the National Natural History Museum, Department of Systematics (Entomology) (Paris).</p>
            <p>For their valuable assistance with the preparation of illustrations, I thank very much my co-operators Ivo Manca and Paolo Marcia (Department of Zoology, University of Sassari).</p>
            <p>The author is also indebted to an anonymous reviewer for the linguistic revision of the text.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Casale</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny and biogeography of Calleidina (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Lebiini): a preliminary survey, pp. 381–428.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname> <given-names>G E</given-names></name> <name name-style="western"><surname>Casale</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name> <name name-style="western"><surname>Vigna Taglianti</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>), <source>Phylogeny and classification of Caraboidea.</source> <publisher-name>Atti Museo regionale di Scienze naturali</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Torino</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Casale</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> The genus <italic>Calleida</italic> Dejean, 1825 in Ecuador (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Lebiini), with eight new species. Biodiversity of South America I.</article-title> <source>Memoirs on Biodiversity</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudoir M</surname> <given-names>de</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1872</year>)<article-title> Monographie des Callidides.</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société entomologique de Belgique</source> <volume>15</volume> (<issue>1871–1872</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>-<lpage>204</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Desender</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casale</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baert</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maelfait</surname> <given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verdyck</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> <italic>Calleida migratoria</italic> Casale, new species (Coleoptera: Carabidae), a newly introduced ground beetle in the Galapagos Islands, Ecuador.</article-title> <source>The Coleopterists Bulletin</source> <volume>56</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>71</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1649/0010-065X(2002)056[0071:CMCNSC]2.0.CO;2">10.1649/0010-065X(2002)056[0071:CMCNSC]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Erwin</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> The beetle family Carabidae of Costa Rica: The genus <italic>Epikastea</italic> Liebke of the Plochionida Group, with new Neotropical species and notes on their way of life (Insecta: Coleoptera, Lebiini, Agrina).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>790</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenz</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Systematic list of extant ground beetles of the world (Insecta, Coleoptera «Geadephaga»: Trachypachidae and Carabidae, incl. Paussinae, Cicindelinae, Rhysodinae).</source>Tutzing, iv + <lpage>530</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lövei</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> In memoriam: Konjev Desender (1956–2008) and Jean-Pierre Maelfait (1950–2009). In: Kotze DJ, Assmann T, Noordijk J, Turin H, Vermeulen R (Eds) Carabid Beetles as Bioindicators: Biogeographical, Ecological and Environmental Studies.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys</source> <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moret</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Los coleópteros Carabidae del páramo en los Andes del Ecuador. Sistemática, ecología y biogeografia.</source> Pontificia Universidad Católica del Ecuador, Centro de Biodiversidad y Ambiente, Quito, Monografia 2, <lpage>306</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Peck</surname> <given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> The Beetles of the Galapagos Islands, Ecuador: Evolution, ecology and diversity (Insecta: Coleoptera).</source> National Research Council Canada, Research Press, Ottawa, xiii + <lpage>313</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>