<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.166.2387</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new species of 
                    <italic>Rhopalosiphum</italic> (Hemiptera, Aphididae) on 
                    <italic>Chusquea tomentosa</italic> (Poaceae, Bambusoideae) from Costa Rica
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Hidalgo</surname>
                        <given-names>Nicolás Pérez</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:B40B43A8-D339-499A-9370-C9D200D9F94C</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Martínez-Torres</surname>
                        <given-names>David</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:75388FFF-B033-4864-9CA5-455DE4FD9E15</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Collantes-Alegre</surname>
                        <given-names>Jorge Mariano</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:C2DA0012-1F1B-4A88-8082-20FFC13DD034</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Muller</surname>
                        <given-names>William Villalobos</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:FE514A95-E56A-4B81-9E57-BCA5504F530C</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Nafría</surname>
                        <given-names>Juan M. Nieto</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:81F0702F-538F-4AB4-92A9-74580A562221</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Departamento de Biodiversidad y Gestión Ambiental, Universidad de León, E-24071, León, Spain
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Institut Cavanilles de Biodiversitat i Biologia Evolutiva, Universitat de València, E-46071, Valencia, Spain
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Centro de Investigación en Biología Celular y Molecular, Universidad de Costa Rica, 11501-2060, San José, Costa Rica
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Nicolás Pérez Hidalgo (<email xlink:type="simple">nperh@unileon.es</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: R. Blackman</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>20</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>166</issue>
            <fpage>59</fpage>
            <lpage>73</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>18</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>13</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Nicolás Pérez Hidalgo, David Martínez-Torres, Jorge Mariano Collantes-Alegre, William Villalobos Muller, Juan M. Nieto Nafría</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:A898677B-81F5-49C5-9380-20A699FF571B</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The new species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum chusqueae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pérez Hidalgo &amp; Villalobos Muller, is described from apterous viviparous females caught on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chusquea tomentosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Cerro de la Muerte (Costa Rica). The identity of the species is supported both by the morphological features and by a molecular phylogenetic analysis based on a fragment of the mitochondrial DNA containing the 5’ region of the cytochrome c oxidase 1 (COI) and on the nuclear gene coding for the Elongation factor-1 alpha (EF1α). The taxonomic position of the new species is discussed. An identification key to the <tp:taxon-name>Aphidinae</tp:taxon-name> species living on plants of <tp:taxon-name>Bambusoideae</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>) is presented.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><italic>Rhopalosiphum</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>aphids</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>molecular</kwd>
                <kwd>Costa Rica</kwd>
                <!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The high diversity of organisms in Costa Rica has been referred to as a product of diverse ecosystems resulting from the interaction between complex microclimates, soils, topography, and a variety of biological processes, as well as the position of the country in the land-bridge between North and South America. Costa Rica’s biodiversity comprises more than 500,000 species of organisms, approximately 84% of which are yet to be described. This percentage is even higher (90%) if we take insects, fungi, bacteria and viruses into account (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Sánchez-Azofeifa et al. 2001</xref>). As for the number of aphid species present in Costa Rica, the list was recently extended (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Pérez Hidalgo et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Zamora Mejías et al. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Villalobos Muller et al. 2010</xref>) and research is ongoing.</p>
            <p>During an expedition in 2008 in the area of Cerro de la Muerte (Cordillera de Talamanca), Costa Rica, three apterous viviparous females and several nymphs were collected on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chusquea tomentosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). At first, they were assigned to the subtribe <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphina</tp:taxon-name> Mordvilko, 1914 (<tp:taxon-name>Aphidini</tp:taxon-name> Latreille, 1802). This identification was confirmed in the laboratory when it was verified that the marginal papillae on abdominal segments I and VIII were in dorsal position to the corresponding stigmata. The morphological characters of the specimens resembled those of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Koch, 1854, though the length of the setae were reminiscent of species in the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paraschizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hille Ris Lambers, 1947 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Börner, 1931).</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p><bold>A</bold>View of the area where the types of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosipum chusqueae</tp:taxon-name></italic> were captured, in Cerro de la Muerte (Costa Rica), with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chusquea tomentosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>B</bold> view of the plant <bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold> details of the area where the aphids were located.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-166-059-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Valenzuela et al. (2009)</xref>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> form a monophyletic group with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> van der Goot, 1917, the separation between them being unclear. The vein structure of the wings separates <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, however, as there were no alates available, molecular analyses were carried out to verify the relationship with the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> through qualitative and quantitative characters. Molecular analyses are normally used to determine species and resolve taxonomic problems in the family <tp:taxon-name>Aphididae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Lozier et al. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Foottit et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Lee et al. 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Pike et al. 2010</xref>).</p>
            <p>A microscopic morphotaxonomic study of the specimens enabled the hypothesis that they could not be assigned to any known species, and strengthened the hypothesis that they be assigned to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Molecular phylogenetic analysis based (1) on a fragment of the mitochondrial DNA containing the 5’ region of the cytochrome c oxidase 1 (COI) and (2) on the nuclear gene coding for the Elongation factor-1 alpha (EF1α) were used to verify both hypotheses.</p>
            <p>Several species included in the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Aphidinae</tp:taxon-name> are known living on plant species of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Bambusoideae</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>), but only two belong to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name>Aphidini</tp:taxon-name>): <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum arundinariae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Tissot, 1933) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum rufiabdominale</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Schrank, 1899), and none to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <!--PageBreak-->
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="material|methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <sec sec-type="Material studied"><title>Material studied</title>
                <p>Three apterous viviparous female and several nymphs (sample CRI-235) were recorded on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chusquea tomentosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Y. Widmer et L. G. Clark (<tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Bambusoideae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Bambuseae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Chusquinae</tp:taxon-name>) in Ojo de Agua (Cerro de la Muerte, Cordillera de Talamanca, Costa Rica) (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">9°36'N, 83°47'W</named-content>), 2968 m, 26.ii.2008.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Morphological study"><title>Morphological study</title>
                <p>Thirty-three quantitative characteristics and the qualitative features of shape, sclerotization, pigmentation and cuticular ornamentation, were considered. The method used for measurements is that normally employed in our studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Nieto Nafría and Mier Durante 1998</xref>). A camera lucida fitted to the microscope was used for the drawings and the microphotographs were taken with a Leica DC digital camera with IM 1000 version 1.10 software.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="DNA extraction and PCR amplification"><title>DNA extraction and PCR amplification</title>
                <p>Total DNA was extracted separately from two samples, one of them containing a single nymph and the second the contents of the abdomen of 3 apterous adults, all kept in 96% ethanol. We followed the HotSHOT (Hot Sodium Hydroxide and Tris) method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Truett et al. 2000</xref>).</p>
                <p>PCR amplification of the two gene fragments analyzed was carried out on 3 µl of the extracted DNA. A 710 bp fragment of the 5’ region of the mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit 1 (COI) was amplified using primers LCO1490 and HCO2198, described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Folmer et al. (1994)</xref>. PCR conditions for COI amplification were as follows: 94°C for 1 min; 35 cycles of 94°C for 30 s, 48°C for 1 min and 68°C for 1 min; a final extension step of 7 min at 68°C was included after cycling. Amplification of the Elongation factor-1 alpha (EF1α) gene fragment was performed using two consecutive PCR reactions with primers Efs175 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Moran et al. 1999</xref>) and Efr1 (5’GTGTGGCAATSCAANACNGGAGT3’) in the first reaction and then primers Efs175 and Efr2 (5’TTGGAAATTTGACCNGGGTGRTT3’) in the second hemi-nested reaction. PCR conditions used in the first reaction were: 94°C for 1 min; 40 cycles of 94°C for 30 s, 50°C for 1 min and 68°C for 1.5 min; a final extension step of 7 min at 68°C was included after cycling. The hemi-nested PCR was done similarly but using 52°C for the annealing step and using 1 µl of the first PCR product.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Sequencing and analysis of DNA sequences"><title>Sequencing and analysis of DNA sequences</title>
                <p>PCR products were purified by ammonium precipitation and reconstituted in 10 μL of LTE buffer (10mM Tris, 0,1mM EDTA). Direct sequencing of amplified fragments was done in both directions using PCR primers (Efr2 was used as reverse primer for sequencing the EF1α fragment). Sequencing was conducted using the Big Dye Terminator v3.1 Cycle Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems) following the manufacturer’s instructions, and samples were loaded onto an ABI 3700 automated sequencer.</p>
                <p>Chromatograms were revised and sequences corresponding to each sample assembled using the Staden package v1.6.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Staden et al. 2000</xref>). Multiple alignments were carried out with Clustal X v1.81 (Thompson et al. 2002) with gap opening and gap extension penalties of 10.0 and 0.2, respectively, and subsequently manually revised.</p>
                <p>Phylogenetic analysis of COI sequences were done using <italic>MEGA</italic> version 4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Tamura et al. 2007</xref>). For EF1α sequences ModelTest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Posada and Crandall 1998</xref>) was used to find the evolutionary model that best fitted sequence data and phylogenetic reconstruction was done using RAxML (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Stamatakis et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results"><title>Results</title>
            <sec sec-type="Morphological data"><title>Morphological data</title>
                <p>A study of the qualitative and quantitative (metric and meristic) characters of the specimens enabled us to establish the hypothesis that they belong to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> as, apart from the above-mentioned character of the marginal papillae on the abdomen, (1) when alive they are ovoid and when preserved the body is not very long and the margins are curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A, 2B</xref>), (2) the dorsal cuticle of the thorax and abdomen is membranous, except for the presence of intersegmental sclerites and a pair of large sclerites on abdominal segment VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A, 2B</xref>), (3) the dorsal cuticle has a more or less regular reticulate area formed by coalescent spinules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2Ba, 2Bb, 2F, 2G</xref>), (4) the siphunculi are longer than the cauda and clearly constricted underneath the apical edge (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A, 2B, 2D</xref>), and (5) there are few setae on the cauda.</p>
                <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 2.</label>
                    <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum chusqueae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A, B</bold> <italic>Habitus</italic> <bold>C</bold> antennal segment III <bold>D</bold> siphunculus <bold>E</bold> cauda. <bold>F</bold> (and <bold>B-a</bold>) detail of the cuticule of abdominal segment 3 <bold>G</bold> (and <bold>B-b</bold>) detail of cuticule of abdominal segment 8.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-166-059-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <p>A comparison of the characters of these specimens with those of apterae in other species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> also strengthened the hypothesis that they could not be assigned to any known species.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Molecular data"><title>Molecular data</title>
                <p>A 710 bp DNA fragment containing a portion of the mitochondrial COI gene was amplified through PCR from the two samples analysed. Useful sequences obtained<!--PageBreak--> from each sample consisted of 658 nucleotides. Identical sequences were obtained for both samples so that a single sequence was finally assigned and deposited in Genbank (accession number HE604204). The online identification engine available at the Barcode of Life Data Systems (BOLD) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Ratnasingham and Hebert 2007</xref>) using the COI <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->species database, failed to find any record corresponding to any identified species that matched our sequence. After a BLASTN search against the non-redundant nucleotide database at the NCBI, sequences from different <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> species were most similar to our sequence (93–94% identical) followed by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sequences (92–93% identical). We then aligned our sequence with sequences from all <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> species available at the NCBI database and from species representative of closely related genera (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, etc.) that we had previously retrieved from the database, and built a phylogenetic tree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). The tree shows that the sequence from our unknown species groups with relatively high support within a monophyletic clade that contains all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> COI sequences occupying a rather basal position within that clade.</p>
                <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 3.</label>
                    <caption><p><bold>A</bold> Neighbour joining tree based on Kimura 2P distances obtained for the COI sequences from our new species (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum chusqueae</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and different <tp:taxon-name>Aphidini</tp:taxon-name> representatives obtained from the NCBI database. <bold>B</bold> Maximum Likelihood tree obtained for the EF1α sequences for our new species (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum chusqueae</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and different <tp:taxon-name>Aphidini</tp:taxon-name> representatives obtained from the NCBI database. Bootstrap support values obtained after 1000 replicates in A and 100 in B are indicated above branches if higher than 50%. Initials for genera are as follows: A, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; As, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Asiphonaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; B, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Braggia</tp:taxon-name></italic>; H, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalopterus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, M, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; P, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paradoxaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; R, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic>; S, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic>); S. (E.), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Euschizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic>); S. (P.), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Paraschizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic>); T, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Toxoptera</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-166-059-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <p>For the Elongation factor-1 alpha (EF1α) gene fragment, we obtained an identical sequence from the two analyzed samples of 987 bp which was deposited in the Genbank with accession number HE604205. Using sequences available for EF1α in NCBI for different <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and closely related species within <tp:taxon-name>Aphidini</tp:taxon-name>, an ML tree was built that included the sequence obtained for our unknown species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). As with the COI sequence, our unknown species grouped with strong support within a monophyletic clade that also included sequences from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Euschizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However, unlike the COI tree, both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic>-related sequences separated into two distinct clades, though with very low bootstrap support.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion and conclusion"><title>Discussion and conclusion</title>
            <p>Molecular data using both mitochondrial COI and nuclear EF1α gene sequences confirmed that the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum chusqueae</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens belong to the same monophyletic clade as other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> species occupying a rather basal position in the group likely closely related to other divergent <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> species such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum nymphaeae</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Both trees revealed the close relationship between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> genera. Although COI sequences are widely used in taxonomy, their utility for phylogeny reconstructions seems rather limited as their phylogenetic signal is somewhat weak in comparison with other markers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Wilson 2010</xref>). Contrarily, EF1α is widely used in phylogenetic reconstructions and its use in insect phylogeny has been shown to be informative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Simon et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Wilson 2010</xref>). In this respect, although the COI analysis did not recover the monophyly of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name></italic> genera separately, ML analysis of EF1α separated both genera and clearly <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum chusqueae</tp:taxon-name></italic> grouped within the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> clade, which, along with our morphometric data discussed above, supports its assignation to the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> genus.</p>
            <p>Approximately 15 species are classified in the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Remaudière and Remaudière 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Zhang and Qiao 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Eastop and Blackman 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Blackman and Eastop 2006</xref>) associated with arboreal <tp:taxon-name>Rosaceae</tp:taxon-name> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Prunus</tp:taxon-name></italic> or <tp:taxon-name>Pyroidea</tp:taxon-name>) as the primary host and with <tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Cyperaceae</tp:taxon-name> or, less frequently, other plants as the secondary<!--PageBreak--> host if their cycle is dioecious, or only with one of them if their cycle is monoecious. Most of the species probably originate in North America, with a subsidiary centre of dispersal in Central Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Blackman and Eastop 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Halbert and Voegtlin 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Blackman and Eastop 2006</xref>). Five of its species have an exclusively Nearctic distribution: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum arundinariae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Tissot), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum cerasifoliae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fitch), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum enigmae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hottes &amp; Frison, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum laconae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Taber, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum nigrum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Richards, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum padiformis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Richards; and another four Nearctic species have been introduced in other parts of the world: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum parvae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hottes &amp; Frison and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum rufulum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Richards in Europe, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum musae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Schouteden has been recorded in areas of Europe, Central Asia, Africa and Australia, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum oxyacanthae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Schrank) is known in Central- and South-America, Europe, Asia and Australia. To date, only four species, linked mainly to crops, have been recorded in Central American countries: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum maidis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (throughout Central America), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum nymphaeae</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Panama, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum padi</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Costa Rica and Panama, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum rufiabdominale</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Honduras, Costa Rica and Panama (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Evans and Halbert 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Quirós et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Villalobos Muller et al. 2010</xref>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum oxyacanthae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is also known in Central America, without country (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Blackman and Eastop 2006</xref>).</p>
            <p>Species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> most resembling the new species due to their morphological characters are <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum rufiabdominale</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum padiformis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The former originated from East Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Blackman and Eastop 2006</xref>) and is currently widely distributed. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum padiformis</tp:taxon-name></italic> originates from North America. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum chusqueae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. nov. coincides with both species in the length of the setae, with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum padiformis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the number of antennal segments and shape of the cauda, and with specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum rufiabdominale</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the 4 setae on abdominal segment VIII (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum rufiabdominale</tp:taxon-name></italic> has 3 to 8 setae on this segment). It is easily distinguished from them because the antennae in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum rufiabdominale</tp:taxon-name></italic> are five-segmented and the dorsal setae in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum padiformis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are not pointed and abdominal segment VIII only has 2 setae. Bamboo species are the host plants of the mentioned <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum rufiabdominale</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum arundinariae</tp:taxon-name></italic>; this last species can be easily differentiated from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum chusqueae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the shape of the cauda (short and more or less triangular or rounded) and siphunculus (more or less tapering) and by much shorter setae on body dorsum and appendages.</p>
            <p>In view of the above, a new species can be established, the description of which follows.</p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">chusqueae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D3A0466B-3858-46A8-A4BB-4618BDD956D3</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Rhopalosiphum_chusqueae</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Pérez Hidalgo &amp; Villalobos Muller</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype"><title>Holotype.</title>
                    <p>Apterous viviparous female number 1 of measurement series, caught on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chusquea tomentosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, Pérez Hidalgo &amp; Villalobos Muller <italic>leg</italic>., deposited in the Aphidological Collection of the University of León (CZULE), sample CRI-235.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p>2 apterous viviparous females (in separated slides) caught with the holotype.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific epithet, <italic>chusqueae</italic> is the genitive singular of the generic name of the aphid’s host plant.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Apterous viviparous females"><title>Apterous viviparous females</title>
                    <p>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). When alive globular oval and brown with white spots of wax on abdomen. Mounted 2.20–2.72 mm and pale in general with head, antennae, legs, siphunculi and cauda dark-brown.</p>
                    <p>Antennae 0.63–0.79 times body length. Antennal segment III (0.32–0.43 mm) shorter than segment IV (0.21–0.25 mm) plus V (0.20–0.26 mm); with setae 55–65 μm long and 1.8–2.6 times the articular diameter of the segment. Terminal process of segment VI (0.44–0.47 mm) 3.9–4.4 times the base (0.32–0.43 mm). Rostrum 0.52–0.61 mm long, reaching middle coxae, 0.19–0.27 times the body length. Ultimate rostral segment 0.13–0.15 mm long, approximately 1.7 times its basal width and 1.1 second segment of hind tarsus; it carries two accessory setae. Marginal papillae present on prothorax, on the abdominal segment 1 and 7, which are dorsally placed to the respective spiracles, and sometimes on segments 3 and 6. Dorsum of the abdomen with spinules forming reticulate ornamentation. Dorsal setae on abdominal segment 3 with delicate, pointed and 25–30 μm long and 3.0–3.9 times the articular diameter of antennal segment III and shorter than ventral ones, which are 90–110 μm long. Siphunculi slightly swollen with marked narrowing below the flange, 0.41–0.45 mm long, 0.16–0.20 times the body length and 2.1–2.2 times cauda. Abdominal segment 8 with two sclerites and four setae 90–110 μm long, delicate and pointed. Genital plate with 2 discal setae and near 26 posterior ones. Cauda finger-like, 0.19–0.21 mm long and carrying 5 setae.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution and host-plant.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Chusquea tomentosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Bambusoideae</tp:taxon-name>) is the only known host of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum chusqueae</tp:taxon-name></italic>. This bamboo is endemic to the country and can be found in several areas of the Cordillera de Talamanca at an altitude of between 2450 and 3000 m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Widmer 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Hammel et al. 2003</xref>). Species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chusquea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (approximately 120 described) can be found at between 800 and 3800 m in dry and humid forests from Mexico to Chile and Argentina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Clark 1989</xref>). As species in the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name></italic> are not strictly stenophagous, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum chusqueae</tp:taxon-name></italic> may also live on other species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chusquea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, or even on other bamboos and live in other parts of America.</p>
                    <p>On the plant, the aphids live close to the nodes well protected by the leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1C, 1D</xref>) and not easily detectable, as shown by fruitless efforts to locate other colonies.</p>
                    <p>So far, only one aphid species had been recorded on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chusquea</tp:taxon-name></italic>: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hysteroneura setariae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thomas) on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chusquea abietifolia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Griseb, in Cuba (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Holman 1974</xref>).</p>
                    <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Blackman and Eastop (1994)</xref> present two identification keys to the aphid species living on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arundinaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> and on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bambusa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, genera that include arboreal bamboos; several of these aphid species belong to the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Aphidinae</tp:taxon-name>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Blackman and Eastop (2006)</xref> report the presence of aphid species on several genera of non-arboreal bamboos such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chusquea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudosasa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sinoarundinaria</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thamnocalamus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thysanolaena</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and also <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arundinaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> (other bamboo genera are included but no <tp:taxon-name>Aphidinae</tp:taxon-name> species have been recorded on them), and for the identification of these species the reader is forwarded to the “keys [of 1994] to aphids on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arundinaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bambusa</tp:taxon-name></italic>”, or to the “keys [of 2006]<!--PageBreak--> to apterae on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Digitaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> and other genera of herbaceous <tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>”. To make the identification work easier, it seems useful to present one compendium-key to the identification of apterous viviparous females of <tp:taxon-name>Aphidinae</tp:taxon-name> species recorded on species of <tp:taxon-name>Bambusoideae</tp:taxon-name> in the World.</p>
                    <p>This key has been prepared using the general structure and several couplets in all of those keys by Blackman and Eastop; thirteen <tp:taxon-name>Aphidinae</tp:taxon-name> species and subspecies have been included, and are: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hysteroneura setariae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thomas, 1878), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis arundinariae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Takahashi, 1937), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis bambusae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fullaway, 1910), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis meghalayensis bengalensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Raychaudhuri [D.N.] and Banerjee [C.], 1974, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis meghalayensis meghalayensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Raychaudhuri [D.N.] and Banerjee [C.], 1974, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis pahanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Takahashi, 1950), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis sacchari</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Zehntner, 1897), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum arundinariae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Tissot, 1933) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum rufiabdominale</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Schrank, 1899) (<tp:taxon-name>Aphidinae</tp:taxon-name> <tp:taxon-name>Aphidini</tp:taxon-name> <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphina</tp:taxon-name>), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitobion bambusicola</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Ghosh [L.K.], 1986), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitobion fragariae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Walker, 1848), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitobion miscanthi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Takahashi, 1921) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitobion papillatum subnudum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Remaudière, 1985 (<tp:taxon-name>Aphidinae</tp:taxon-name> <tp:taxon-name>Macrosiphini</tp:taxon-name>).</p>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculus without apical zone of polygonal reticulation. Abdominal segments I and VII with marginal tubercles (papillae) placed dorsally to the respective spiracular apertures. Cuticle of dorsum of the abdomen membranous, a sclerotized patch absent</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculus with apical zone of polygonal reticulation (at least two rows of cells). Abdominal segments I and VII usually without marginal tubercles (papillae), but if they are present then spinal papillae present on head and several abdominal segments. Dorsum of the abdomen with a sclerotized patch more or less extended and pigmented</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aphids spindle-shaped, green when alive. Siphunculus very small (less than 0.7 times cauda), thin, cylindrical and narrow-based, flangeless, and with not functional aperture</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalopterus pruni</tp:taxon-name></italic> [and other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalopterus</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp.]</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aphids broad oval-shaped. Siphunculus 0.5–2.5 times cauda (if less than 0.6 times then less than 2 times longer than its basal width), shaped differently and with functional aperture</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculus short, usually thick or rather thick, less than (often much less than) 2.4 times longer than its basal width, 0.4–1.2 times cauda, and usually with a well-developed, rather swollen flange</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculus usually longer than cauda (if less than 1.2 times cauda then it is more than 2.4 times its basal width and/or has a small flange), tapering, cylindrical or swollen</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Setae on antennal segment III at most 1.5 times the basal diameter of the segment. [Alatae viviparous females with wing veins dark bordered]</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Setae on antennal segment III at least 2.0 times the basal diameter of the segment. [Alatae viviparous females with wing veins not dark bordered]</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cauda with only 4-6 setae. Coxae dark</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis bambusae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cauda with 7-20 setae. Coxae pale</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis sacchari</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennae five-segmented. Siphunculus 1.5 times its basal width at least</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis arundinariae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennae six-segmented. Siphunculus 1.4 times its basal width at most</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculus 1.1–1.4 times its basal width. Terminal processus of antennal segment VI at most 2.3 times the base</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis pahanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculus 0.8–0.9 times its basal width. Terminal processus of antennal segment VI at least 2.2 times the base</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis meghalayensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>] 8</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cauda with 4–6 setae and anterior half of the genital plate with 4–7 setae</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis meghalayensis meghalayensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cauda with 7–10 setae and anterior half of the genital plate with 2 setae</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanaphis meghalayensis bengalensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Setae on antennal segment III shorter than the basal width of the segment</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Setae on antennal segment III longer than the basal width of the segment</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cauda at least 1.5 times its basal width, finger-shaped, with basal constriction, paler than cauda, and usually with 4 setae. [Alate viviparous females with only one oblique vein in hindwing]</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hysteroneura setariae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cauda a little longer that its basal width, cone-shaped, without basal constriction, as dark as siphunculi, and with approximately 8 setae. [Alate viviparous females with two oblique veins in hindwing]</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum arundinariae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennae usually five-segmented. Setae on antennal segment III 3.0–5.0 times the basal width of the segment. Abdominal segment VIII with 3–8 setae. Ultimate rostral segment 1.3–1.8 times second segment of the hind tarsus. Terminal processus of antennal segment VI 4.0–6.5 times the base</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum rufiabdominale</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennae six-segmented. Setae on antennal segment III 1.8–2.6 times the basal width of the segment. Abdominal segment VIII with 4 setae. Terminal processus of antennal segment VI 3.9-–4.4 times the base</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum chusqueae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spinal tubercles (papillae) present on the head and abdominal segments (V)VI-VIII; marginal ones present on prothorax and abdominal segments (I)II–V and infrequently on VII</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitobion papillatum subnudum</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spinal tubercles (papillae) absent; marginal ones on abdominal segment II–V usually absent, and always absent on abdominal segments I and VII</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cauda dusky (but not as dark as siphunculi) and with a rather pointed apex. Siphunculus 2.0–2.1 times cauda. Aphids yellowish when alive</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitobion bambusicola</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cauda pale (very contrasted with siphunculi) with a variably shaped apex. Siphunculus 1.4–2.7 times cauda. Aphids variable in colour when alive</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi 1.75–2.25 times cauda, which has a rather rounded apex</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitobion fragariae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi 1.4–1.9 times cauda, which has a rather pointed apex</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sitobion miscanthi</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                    <!--PageBreak-->
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>The authors thank the <italic>Agencia Española de Cooperación Internacional para el Desarrollo</italic> (AECID) [joint project of the universities of León and Costa Rica, number D/010523/07] for supporting this research and to the <italic>Universidad de Costa Rica</italic> for the scientific visit of W. Villalobos (July 2009) to <italic>Universidad de León</italic> and <italic>Institut Cavanilles de Biodiversitat i Biología Evolutiva</italic>. Work partially funded by MICINN project CGL2010-22043 to D. Martínez-Torres (Universitat de València). The authors also acknowledge the suggestions made by the academic editor and the reviewer S. Halbert.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastop</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<source> Aphids on the World’s Trees. An Identification and Information Guide. CAB International, Wallingford, 8 + 987 pp. + 16 pl.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastop</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> Aphids on the World’s Herbaceous Plants and Shrubs. J. Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, Two volumes, 8 + 1439 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Systematics of <italic>Chusquea</italic> section <italic>Swallenochloa</italic>, section <italic>Verticillatae</italic>, section <italic>Serpentes</italic>, and section <italic>Longifoliae</italic> (Poaceae-Bambusoideae).</article-title> <source>Systematic Botanic Monographs </source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>127</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/25027724" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.2307/25027724</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastop</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Some new synonyms in Aphididae (Hemiptera: Sternorrhyncha).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1089</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halbert</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> A checklist of the aphids of Honduras (Hemiptera: Aphididae).</article-title> <source>Florida Entomologist </source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>518</fpage>-<lpage>523</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1653/0015-4040(2007)90[518:ACOTAO]2.0.CO;2" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1653/0015-4040(2007)90[518:ACOTAO]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Folmer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeh</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrijenhoek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> DNA primers for amplification of mitochondrial cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase subunit I from diverse metazoan invertebrates.</article-title> <source>Molecular Marine Biology and Biotechnology </source> <volume>3</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>294</fpage>-<lpage>299</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Foottit</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maw</surname><given-names>HEL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Dohlen</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Species identification of aphids (Insecta: Hemiptera: Aphididae) through DNA barcodes.</article-title> <source>Molecular Ecology Resources </source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1189</fpage>-<lpage>1201</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-0998.2008.02297.x" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1111/j.1755-0998.2008.02297.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Foottit</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maw</surname><given-names>HEL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> DNA barcodes to explore diversity in aphids (Hemiptera: Aphididae and Adelgidae).</article-title> <source>Redia </source> <volume>92</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Halbert</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Voegtlin</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<source> Evidence for the North American origin of <italic>Rhopalosiphum</italic> and Barley Yellow Dwarf Virus. In: Aphids in natural and managed ecosystems. Nieto Nafría JM, Dixon AFG (Eds), Universidad de León (Secretariado de Publicaciones), León, 351–356.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammel</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grayum</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamora</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<source> Manual de Plantas de Costa Rica, Vol. III. Monocotiledóneas. Missouri Botanical Garden Press, 884 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<source> Los áfidos de Cuba.</source> <publisher-name>Instituto Cubano del Libro</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>La Habana</publisher-loc>, <lpage>304</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H-R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foottit</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Barcoding aphids (Hemiptera: Aphididae) of the Korean Peninsula: updating the global data set.</article-title> <source>Molecular Ecology Resources </source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-0998.2010.02877.x" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1111/j.1755-0998.2010.02877.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozier</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foottit</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roderick</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Molecular and morphological evaluation of the aphid genus <italic>Hyalopterus</italic> Koch (Insecta: Hemiptera: Aphididae), with a description of a new species.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1688</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelsey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholes</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Phylogenetics and evolution of the aphid genus <italic>Uroleucon</italic> based on mitochondrial and nuclear DNA sequences.</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology </source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-3113.1999.00076.x" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1046/j.1365-3113.1999.00076.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieto Nafría</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mier Durante</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<source> Hemiptera, Aphididae I. In: Ramos MA et al. (Eds) Fauna Ibérica Volumen 11.</source> <publisher-name>Museo Nacional de Ciencias Naturales, C.S.I.C</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Madrid</publisher-loc>, <lpage>424</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez Hidalgo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villalobos Muller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mier Durante</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> <italic>Greenidea psidii</italic> (Hemiptera: Aphididae: Greenideinae) new invasive aphid in Costa Rica.</article-title> <source>Florida Entomologist </source> <volume>92</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>396</fpage>-<lpage>398</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1653/024.092.0233" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1653/024.092.0233</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foottit</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maw</surname><given-names>HEL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pantoja</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagerty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emmert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Molecular and biometric assessment of <italic>Myzodium mimulicola</italic> (Hemiptera: Aphididae), with new synonymy and host and distribution data.</article-title> <source>Canadian Entomologist </source> <volume>142</volume>: <fpage>448</fpage>-<lpage>457</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/n10-034" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.4039/n10-034</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crandall</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> Modeltest: testing the model of DNA substitution.</article-title> <source>Bioinformatics </source> <volume>14</volume> (<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>817</fpage>-<lpage>818</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/14.9.817" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/14.9.817</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Quirós</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remaudière</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieto Nafría</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Contribución al conocimiento de Aphididae y Phylloxeridae (Hemiptera, Sternorrhyncha) de Panamá.</article-title> <source>Neotropical Entomology </source> <volume>38</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>791</fpage>-<lpage>800</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnasingham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> BOLD: the barcode of life data system (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.barcodinglife.org" xlink:type="simple">www.barcodinglife.org</ext-link>).</article-title> <source>Molecular Ecology Notes </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>364</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1471-8286.2007.01678.x" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1111/j.1471-8286.2007.01678.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Remaudière</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remaudière</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<source> Catalogue des Aphididae du Monde / Catalogue of the World’s Aphididae.</source> <publisher-name>Homoptera Aphidoidea. INRA Editions</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Versailles</publisher-loc>, <lpage>478</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sánchez-Azofeifa</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harriss</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skole</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Deforestation in Costa Rica: A Quantitative Analysis Using Remote Sensing Imagery.</article-title> <source>Biotropica </source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>378</fpage>-<lpage>384</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schierwater</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadrys</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> On the value of Elongation factor-1alpha for reconstructing pterygote insect phylogeny.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution </source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>651</fpage>-<lpage>656</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2009.09.029" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1016/j.ympev.2009.09.029</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Staden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonfield</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> The Staden Package. Computer Methods in Molecular Biology Volume 132.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bioinformatics Methods and</surname><given-names>Protocols</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Misener</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krawetz</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>The Humana Press Inc.</issue-title> <source>, Totowa, NJ</source>: <fpage>115</fpage>-<lpage>130</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1385/1-59259-192-2:115" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1385/1-59259-192-2:115</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rougemont</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> A Rapid Bootstrap Algorithm for the RAxML Web-Servers.</article-title> <source>Systematic Biology </source> <volume>75</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>758</fpage>-<lpage>771</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10635150802429642" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1080/10635150802429642</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0.</article-title> <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution </source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1596</fpage>-<lpage>1599</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msm092" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1093/molbev/msm092</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plewniak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeanmougin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> The ClustalX windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis tools.</article-title> <source>Nucleic Acids Research </source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>4876</fpage>-<lpage>4882</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/25.24.4876" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1093/nar/25.24.4876</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Truett</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warman</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Truett</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heeger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mynatt</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Preparation of PCR-quality mouse genomic DNA with Hot Sodium Hydroxide and Tris (HotSHOT).</article-title> <source>BioTechniques </source> <volume>29</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>52</fpage>-<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastop</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ridland</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Molecular and Morphometric data indicate a new species of the aphid genus <italic>Rhopalosiphum</italic> (Hemiptera: Aphididae).</article-title> <source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America </source> <volume>102</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>914</fpage>-<lpage>924</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1603/008.102.0602" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1603/008.102.0602</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Villalobos Muller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez Hidalgo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mier Durante</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieto Nafría</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Aphididae (Hemiptera: Sternorhyncha) from Costa Rica, with new records for Central America.</article-title> <source>Boletín de la Asociación Española de Entomología </source> <volume>34</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>): <fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>182</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Widmer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Life history of some <italic>Chusquea</italic> species in old-growth oak forest in Costa Rica.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>The bamboos.</issue-title> <source>Academic Press, New York</source>: <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source> Assessing the value of DNA Barcodes and other priority gene regions for molecular phylogenetics of Lepidoptera. PLoS ONE 5 (5): e10525. </source>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0010525.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamora Mejías</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez Hidalgo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mier Durante</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> First report of <italic>Idiopterus nephrelepidis</italic> (Hemiptera: Aphididae) in Central America.</article-title> <source>Florida Entomologist, </source> <volume>93</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>460</fpage>-<lpage>463</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1653/024.093.0325" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1653/024.093.0325</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G-x</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>G-x</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Homoptera: Aphidinea: Pemphigidae, Anoeciidae, Lachnidae and Aphididae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XK</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>Insects of the Three Gorge Resevoir Area of Yangtze River (2 volumes): Chongqing Publishing House.</issue-title> <source>Chongqing</source>: <fpage>374</fpage>-<lpage>384</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>