<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
	
    <front>

        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>

        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.56.528</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    First records of Xyleborinus octiesdentatus(Murayama) (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Scolytinae) from North America
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
	
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>J. Rabaglia</surname>
                        <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <aff>
                        USDA Forest Service, 1601 N. Kent St, RPC–7, Arlington, VA 22209, USA 
                    </aff>
                </contrib>

                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Knížek</surname>
                        <given-names>Miloš</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <aff>
                        Forestry and Game Management Research Institute, Jíloviště - Strnady, CZ-156 04 Praha 5 - Zbraslav, Czech Republic
                    </aff>
                </contrib>

                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Johnson</surname>
                        <given-names>Wood</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <aff>
                        USDA Forest Service, 2500 Shreveport Hwy, Pineville, LA 71360, USA
                    </aff>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>

            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Robert J. Rabaglia (<email xlink:type="simple">brabaglia@fs.fed.us</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: M. Yu. Mandelshtam</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>

            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>17</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>56</issue>
            <fpage>219</fpage>
            <lpage>226</lpage>

            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>8</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2009</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>21</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
            </history>

            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>R.J. Rabaglia, M. Knížek, W. Johnson</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name> (Murayama), an ambrosia beetle native to Asia, is reported for the first time in North America based on specimens from Alabama and Louisiana. This is the twenty-first species of exotic <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborina</tp:taxon-name> documented in North America. A re-description of the female and a key to the four North American species of <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus</tp:taxon-name> are presented.</p>
            </abstract>
	
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Coleoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Curculionidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Scolytidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Xyleborina</kwd>
                <kwd>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</kwd>
                <kwd>new North American record</kwd>
                <kwd>exotic species</kwd>            	
            </kwd-group>

        </article-meta>
    </front>

    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>In 1977, Steve Wood documented the introduced and exported North and Central American scolytines known at that time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Wood 1977</xref>). He also pointed out that many of the recent introductions into North America were species with sib-mating systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Wood 1982</xref>). Since then there have been many papers citing the numerous species and increasing rate of introductions of non-native scolytines into North America. The number of non-native scolytines known to be established in North America has more than doubled since 1977. Whereas more than half of the species reported prior to 1977 were in the twig and seed infesting genera <tp:taxon-name>Hypothenemus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Coccotrypes</tp:taxon-name>, most of the recently established species are ambrosia beetles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Hoebeke and Rabaglia 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Rabaglia et al. 2009</xref>).</p><!--PageBreak-->
            <p>Ambrosia beetles in the <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborina</tp:taxon-name> are commonly transported in dunnage and crating, and readily establish in new environments due to their cryptic nature and sib-mating behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Wood 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Atkinson et al. 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Brockerhoff et al. 2006</xref>). Since 1980, there have been 13 non-native xyleborines found to be established in North America. As of 2009, there were 42 species of <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborina</tp:taxon-name> known from north of Mexico, and 21 of these are non-native (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Rabaglia et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Hoebeke and Rabaglia 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Rabaglia et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Okins and Thomas 2010</xref>). This paper reports the first occurrence of the 22nd non-native xyleborine, <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name> (Murayama), documented from North America, provides a key and description for its identification, and presents recent collection and taxonomic data.</p>
            <p>The USDA Forest Service has been pilot testing and later implementing on an operational basis, an early detection and rapid response (EDRR) project for bark and ambrosia beetles since 2001 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Rabaglia et al. 2008</xref>). This project utilizes Lindgren funnel traps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Lindgren 1983</xref>) and lures which target non-native scolytines that are at high risk of introduction into the United States. As part of this project, in 2008 a study was conducted on the Kisatchie National Forest near Winnfield, Louisiana to determine the effects of lure release rates on beetle response. On April 24, 2008 a sample containing an unidentified xyleborine ambrosia beetle was collected, and images were sent to RJR. The beetle was recognized as a new, non-native species and images were forwarded to MK who suggested it was identical with <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name> (Murayama, 1931). The identification was then confirmed by RJR after comparison with Murayama’s type specimen of at the US National Museum. This was the first record of this species in North America. An additional specimen was collected on August 14, 2008 in Vance, Alabama also as part of the EDRR project. In 2009, WJ collected additional specimens on the Kisatchie National Forest as part of a delimiting survey in Louisiana. Further collection details are in the Distribution section below.</p>
        </sec>
        
        <sec sec-type="Systematics"><title>Systematics</title>
            <p>The <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborina</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Xyleborini</tp:taxon-name> sensu Wood &amp; Bright, 1992) is a large and complex group containing more than 1,200 species. Until <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Wood’s (1986)</xref> reclassification, most species in the tribe were placed in the polyphyletic genus <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborus</tp:taxon-name>. Recent molecular (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Jordal 2002</xref>) and morphological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hulcr et al. 2007</xref>) methods have helped create a more stable classification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hulcr and Cognato 2009</xref>). The genus <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus</tp:taxon-name> was established by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Reitter (1913)</xref>, and has at times been considered a synonym of <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborus</tp:taxon-name>. Since <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Wood (1986)</xref>, it has been recognized as a distinct genus. The main character used to distinguish the two genera is the somewhat hidden, conical scutellum in <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus</tp:taxon-name> and the visible, flat scutellum in <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborus</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <p>Most publications on <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name>, including the original description from Korea by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Murayama (1931)</xref>, placed it in <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborus</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Murayama 1934</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Yin et al. 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Nobuchi 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Wood and Bright 1992</xref>). A study by R. A. Beaver (pers. comm.) and MK of Murayama’s type collection at the US National Museum in 2003 indicated that the species should be placed in <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Beaver et al. 2008</xref>)</p>
            
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Xyleborinus</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Murayama, 1931: 46)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name> can be easily distinguished from other members of <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus</tp:taxon-name> occurring in North America by the sulcate shape of the elytral declivity, and the elevated lateral declivital margins which bear four pairs of long, narrow, sharply pointed spines, increasing in length approaching the posterior margin.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Revised Key to Xyleborinus in America north of Mexico"><title>Revised Key to <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus</tp:taxon-name> in America north of Mexico.</title>
                    <p>The following key, modified from the key to <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus</tp:taxon-name> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Rabaglia et al. (2006)</xref>, will enable the identification of the five species of <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus</tp:taxon-name> known from America north of Mexico. It includes the recently established <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus andrewsi</tp:taxon-name> in Florida (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Okins and Thomas 2010</xref>).</p>
										
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior margin of elytra strongly convergent</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus andrewsi</tp:taxon-name> (Blandford)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior margin of elytra broadly rounded</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(1)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Declivital interstriae 1 with small granules, 1 and 3 equally, weakly elevated</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Declivital interstriae 1 without granules and not elevated</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(2)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Granules on declivital interstriae 1 and 3 larger, those on 3 pointed, spine-like, slightly incurved; granules on ventrolateral area large, sharply pointed, spine-like, curved slightly downwards and to the suture; declivital interstriae 2 flattened; 2.5–2.8 mm</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus alni</tp:taxon-name> (Niisima)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Granules on declivital interstriae 1 and 3 smaller, obtusely pointed; granules on ventrolateral areas small, less pointed; declivital interstriae 2 slightly impressed; 2.0–2.4 mm</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus saxesenii</tp:taxon-name> (Ratzeburg)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(2)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Declivity flattened, declivital interstriae 3 slightly elevated with 3 pairs of small denticles, the pair near the posterior margin largest and often blunt; 1.6–1.9 mm</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus gracilis</tp:taxon-name> Eichhoff</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Declivity sulcate, declivital interstriae 3 strongly elevated with 4 pairs of long, narrow, pointed spines increasing in size approaching posterior margin, 2.1–2.4 mm</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name> Murayama</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
										
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p>Lateral view of <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name> adult female.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/528/supp/ZooKeys-056-219-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
										
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p> Declivity of <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name> adult female.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/528/supp/ZooKeys-056-219-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
										
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 3.</label>
                        <caption><p>Scutellum of <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name> adult female.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/528/supp/ZooKeys-056-219-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>

                </tp:treatment-sec>
                
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> The species was redescribed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Nunberg (1982)</xref></p>
                    <p>Female. Length 2.1–2.4 mm (from anterior margin of pronotum to posterior margin of elytra, excluding spines), 2.5× as long as wide; color brown to dark brown, matt. Frons convex, strongly reticulate, with large, shallow, rather dense punctures. Antennal club round with two round sutures on its anterior side and one strongly apically displaced suture on posterior side. Pronotum cylindrical, 1.2× as long as wide, frontal edge broadly rounded bearing small tubercles as continuation of very fine asperities on anterior half, posterior half finely shagreened, with minute, shallow punctures. Scutellum typical for the genus, conical, visible between the emarginated bases of the elytra. Elytra cylindrical 1.5× as long as wide, 1.3× as long as pronotum, side straight on anterior half, narrowed on posterior half; striae on the disk very shallowly impressed, regularly and rather densely punctured; interstriae flat, finely and regularly punctured; interstriae 1, 2 and 3 with small tubercles just before the upper margin of the declivity. Elytral declivity long, nearly from the middle of elytra, sulcate, sutural interstriae weakly elevated on upper part, not elevated below, without granules; lateral edges formed by strongly elevated continuation of 3rd interstriae, which bears four pairs of long, narrow, posteriorly directed sharply pointed spines, which increase in length approaching posterior margin, the last two pair exceeding outline of the elytral edge; several small, fine spines on the lateral raised margin of declivity. Vestiture consisting of moderately long, fine setae in uniseriate rows on interstriae, longer on declivity. Legs yellowish, brown.</p>
                    <p>Male. Not examined.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p> China, Japan, South Korea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Wood and Bright 1992</xref>). United States (all records new to North America, numbers of specimens collected at each location shown in parentheses.): ALABAMA, Tuscaloosa County: Vance, 14 August 2008, ethanol-baited funnel trap (1);LOUISIANA, Winn Parish: Kisatchie National Forest, 6 miles w. of Winnfield, 24 April 2008, α-β-pinene (70:30) and ethanol-baited funnel trap (1); 23 March 2009, α-β-pinene (70:30) and ethanol-baited funnel trap (3), ethanol-baited funnel trap (3), phoebe oil-baited funnel trap (2) ; 9 April 2009, α-β-pinene (70:30) and ethanol-baited funnel trap (1),: ethanol-baited funnel trap (2); 21 April 2009, α-β-pinene (70:30) and ethanol-baited funnel trap (7), ethanol-baited funnel trap (4); 29 April 2009, α-β-pinene (70:30) and ethanol-baited funnel trap (3), ethanol-baited funnel trap (6),: phoebe oil-baited funnel trap (2); 21 May 2009,: α-β-pinene (70:30) and ethanol-baited funnel trap (1); 3 June 2009, trap on girdled yaupon (14); 9 June 2009,: trap on girdled yaupon (3); 15 June 2009, trap on girdled yaupon (3); 14 July 2009, trap on girdled yaupon (2); 4 August 2009,: trap on girdled yaupon (2). All specimens collected in North America are females.</p><!--PageBreak-->
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology, habits, and host"><title>Biology, habits, and host.</title>
                    <p> In its native Asian range, the known hosts for <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name> are <tp:taxon-name>Carpinus laxiflora</tp:taxon-name> (Siebold and Zuccarini) Blume (<tp:taxon-name>Corylaceae</tp:taxon-name>), <tp:taxon-name>Cleyera</tp:taxon-name> sp., <tp:taxon-name>Eurya japonica</tp:taxon-name> Thunberg (<tp:taxon-name>Theaceae</tp:taxon-name>) and <tp:taxon-name>Illicium religiosum</tp:taxon-name> Siebold (<tp:taxon-name>Illiaceae</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Wood and Bright 1992</xref>), and <tp:taxon-name>Illex rotunda</tp:taxon-name> Thunberg (<tp:taxon-name>Aquifoliaceae</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Murayama 1934</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Although this species is certainly established in the Winnfield area of Louisiana (Winn Parish) and probably in Alabama (Tuscaloosa Co.), it has not been collected from any host trees. In May, 2009, on the Kisatchie National Forest, <tp:taxon-name>Ilex vomitoria</tp:taxon-name> Aiton (yaupon), <tp:taxon-name>Ilex opaca</tp:taxon-name> Aiton (American holly) (<tp:taxon-name>Aquifoliaceae</tp:taxon-name>) and <tp:taxon-name>Carpinus caroliniana</tp:taxon-name> Walter (ironwood) (<tp:taxon-name>Corylaceae</tp:taxon-name>) were girdled and a sticky band placed on the trees to act as attractant/trap trees for the beetle. These species were selected because known hosts of the beetles belonging to these genera occur in Asia. During the month following this treatment 27 specimens were collected on the sticky band on the girdled yaupon whereas no specimens were collected from the other species. No specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name> were found boring into the yaupon tree.</p><!--PageBreak-->
                    <p>The impact <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name> will have in North America is still uncertain. All species of xyleborines carry symbiotic ambrosia fungi that are usually benign to hosts in their native range. However, as recently discovered with <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborus glabratus</tp:taxon-name> Eichhoff, 1877, another ambrosia beetle introduced from Asia, certain ambrosial fungi may prove to be very pathogenic on new, novel hosts in North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Fraedrich et al. 2008</xref>). Future studies with <tp:taxon-name>Xyleborinus octiesdentatus</tp:taxon-name> will attempt to identify fungal associates, and test their pathogenicity against North American host trees.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <label>Acknowledgements</label>
            <p>We express our appreciation to the following people: Tessa Bauman (formerly with USDA Forest Service) for first recognizing the specimen as a species unknown in the US; Brian Strom (USDA Forest Service) for conducting the field test of lures which detected the species in Louisiana; Erich Vallery for taking the images for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>; Valli Peacher, Saul Petty, Billy Bruce, Chris Steiner, Jacob Hudson, Jim Meeker (all with USDA Forest Service) for field assistance in the delimiting survey; Dana McReynolds, Alabama Forestry Commission for setting up survey traps in Alabama. This work was partly supported by the Ministry of Agriculture of the Czech Republic, Project No. MZe 002070203 Stabilization of forest functions in anthropicly disturbed and changing environmental conditions. USDA Forest Service, Forest Health Protection, Early Detection and Rapid Response project provided funding for the trapping study and delimiting survey.</p><!--PageBreak-->
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
							<ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname> <given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabaglia</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bright</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> Newly detected exotic species of Xyleborus (Coleoptera: Scolytidae) with a revised key to species in eastern North America.</article-title> <source>Canadian Entomologist</source> <volume>122</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>104</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaver</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kajimura</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goto</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Taxonomic changes and new records of Japanese bark and ambrosia beetles (Coleoptera: Curculionidae: Scolytinae).</article-title> <source>Elytra, Tokyo</source> <volume>36</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>239</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brockerhoff</surname> <given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bain</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimberley</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knižek</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Interception frequency of bark and ambrosia beetles (Coleoptera: Scolytinae) and relationship with establishment in New Zealand and worldwide.</article-title> <source>Canadian Journal of Forest Research</source> <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>289</fpage>-<lpage>298</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraedrich</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrington</surname> <given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabaglia</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulyshen</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayfield III</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanula</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eickwort</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> A fungal symbiont of the redbay ambrosia beetle causes wilt in redbay and other Lauraceae in the southeastern USA.</article-title> <source>Plant Disease</source> <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>-<lpage>224</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoebeke</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabaglia</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Xyleborus seriatus Blandford (Coleoptera: Curculionidae: Scolytinae), an Asian ambrosia beetle new to North America.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington</source> <volume>110</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>470</fpage>-<lpage>476</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordal</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Elongation Factor 1 alpha resolves the monophyly of the haplodiploid ambrosia beetles Xyleborini (Coleoptera: Curculionidae).</article-title> <source>Insect Molecular Biology</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>453</fpage>-<lpage>465</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulcr</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dole</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaver RA Cognato</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Cladistic review of taxonomic characters in Xyleborina (Coleoptera: Curculionidae: Scolytinae).</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology</source> <volume>32</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>568</fpage>-<lpage>584</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulcr</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cognato</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Three new genera of oriental Xyleborina (Coleoptera: Curculionidae: Scolytinae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2204</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindgren</surname> <given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> A multiple funnel trap for scolytid beetles (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Canadian Entomologist</source> <volume>115</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>302</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murayama</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1931</year>)<article-title> Révision des familles des Ipides et Platypides (Coléoptères) de l’île de Quelpart.</article-title> <source>Annot Zool Japonenses</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murayama</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1934</year>)<article-title> Notes on the Ipidae (Coleoptera) from Kyushu.</article-title> <source>Annual Zool Japonenses</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>287</fpage>-<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nobuchi</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Check-list of Coleoptera of Japan. Family Scolytidae.</article-title> <source>Studies on Scolytidae XXVI.</source> <publisher-name>The Coleopterists’ Association of Japan</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc>, <lpage>32</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunberg</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Die Gattung Xyleborus Eichhoff (Coleoptera, Scolytidae). Erganzungen, Berichitigungen und Erwieterungen der Diagnosen, V. Teil.</article-title> <source>Annales Zoologici Warszawa.</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>–<lpage>446</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Okins</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> A new North American record for Xyleborinus andrewesi (Coleoptera: Curculionidae: Scolytinae).</article-title> <source>Florida Entomologist</source> <volume>93</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>133</fpage>-<lpage>134</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabaglia</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dole</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cognato</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Review of American Xyleborina (Coleoptera: Curculionidae: Scolytinae) occurring north of Mexico, with an illustrated key.</article-title> <source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</source> <volume>99</volume> (<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1034</fpage>-<lpage>1056</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabaglia</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duerr</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acciavatti</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ragenovich</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Early detection and rapid response for non-native bar and ambrosia beetles.</source> <publisher-name>USDA Forest Service, Forest Heath Protection</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc>. <lpage>12</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rabaglia</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenberg</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acciavatti,</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> First records of Anisandrus maiche Stark (Coleoptera: Curculionidae: Scolytinae) in North America.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2137</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><!--PageBreak-->
							<ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Reitter</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1913</year>)<article-title> Bestimmungs-tabelle der Borkenkäfer (Scolytidae) aus Europa und den angrenzenden Ländern.</article-title> <source>Wiener Entomologische Zeitung</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>)<article-title> Introduced and exported American Scolytidae (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Great Basin Naturalist</source> <volume>37</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Bark and Ambrosia Beetles of North and Central America (Coleoptera: Scolytidae), a taxonomic monograph.</article-title> <source>Great basin Naturalist Memoirs No. 6</source>, <publisher-name>Brigham Young University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Provo, Utah</publisher-loc>, <lpage>1359</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>A reclassification of the genera of Scolytidae (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Great basin Naturalist Memoirs No. 10</source>, <publisher-name>Brigham Young University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Provo, Utah</publisher-loc>, <lpage>126</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bright Jr.</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>A catalog of Scolytidae and Platypodidae (Coleoptera), part 2: Taxonomic index, Volume A.</article-title> <source>Great basin Naturalist Memoirs No. 13</source>, <publisher-name>Brigham Young University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Provo, Utah</publisher-loc>, <lpage>833</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
							<ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname> <given-names>HF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>ZL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <source>Economic insect fauna of China. Fasc. 29. Coleoptera: Scolytidae.</source> <publisher-name>Science Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>, x + <lpage>205</lpage> pp., XVII Tab.</mixed-citation></ref>        
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>