<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>

        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.59.510</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    Aleocharine rove beetles (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae) associated with Leptogenys
                     Roger, 1861 (Hymenoptera, Formicidae) I. Review of three genera associated with L. distinguenda
                     (Emery, 1887) and L. mutabilis
                     (Smith, 1861)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
	
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Maruyama</surname>
                        <given-names>Munetoshi</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <aff>
                        The Kyushu University Museum, Fukuoka, 812-8581 Japan
                    </aff>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:2F8BEE60-1C25-42BB-8D59-AA71D7EB7141</uri>
                </contrib>
                
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>von Beeren</surname>
                        <given-names>Christoph</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <aff>
                        Department Biologie II, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München, Großhaderner Straße 2, 82152 Planegg-Martinsried, Germany
                    </aff>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:73672394-9A6F-4182-85F2-008063E1898C</uri>
                </contrib>

                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Hashim</surname>
                        <given-names>Rosli</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <aff>
                        Institute of Biological Science, Faculty of Science, University of Malaya, 50603 Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia
                    </aff>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:9CB22ADA-5803-4D0E-B673-53F868A1EF1B</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>

            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Munetoshi Maruyama (<email xlink:type="simple">dendrolasius@gmail.com</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Jan Klimaszewski</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>

            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>1</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>59</issue>
            <fpage>47</fpage>
            <lpage>60</lpage>

            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>17</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>22</day>
                    <month>7</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
            </history>

            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Munetoshi Maruyama, Christoph von Beeren, Rosli Hashim</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:B453B953-88E2-466A-AB98-37E5A51DD422</self-uri>

            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Three myrmecophilous genera of <tp:taxon-name>Aleocharinae</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Staphylinidae</tp:taxon-name>) associated with <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> (Emery, 1887) and <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys mutabilis</tp:taxon-name> (Smith, 1861) are reviewed with descriptions of new taxa: <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name> Kistner, 1989, <tp:taxon-name>Togpelenys</tp:taxon-name> Kistner, 1989 and <tp:taxon-name>Witteia</tp:taxon-name> Maruyama &amp; von Beeren, gen. n. (type species: <tp:taxon-name>Witteia dentilabrum</tp:taxon-name>Maruyama &amp; von Beeren, sp. n.). The following new combinations are proposed: <tp:taxon-name>Zyras</tp:taxon-name> (s. lat.) aenictophila (Kistner, 1997),comb. n. (ex <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name>), <tp:taxon-name>Zyras</tp:taxon-name> (s. lat.) dichthadiaphila (Kistner in Kistner et al., 2003), comb. n. (ex <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name>), <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia derougemonti</tp:taxon-name> (Pace, 1984), comb. n. (ex <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name> Wasmann, 1899), <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia watanabei</tp:taxon-name> (Maruyama, 2004), comb. n. (ex <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name>), <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia dilatata</tp:taxon-name> (Pace, 2005), comb. n. (ex <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name>), <tp:taxon-name>Witteia borneensis</tp:taxon-name> (Pace, 1986), comb. n. (ex Wroughtonilla). These genera belong to the <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name> genus group of the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Lomechusini</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            </abstract>
	
            <kwd-group>
		            
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Myrmecophily</kwd>
                <kwd>Maschwitzia</kwd>
                <kwd>Togpelenys</kwd>
                <kwd>Witteia gen. n.</kwd>
                <kwd>Wroughtonilla genus group</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>new combination</kwd>
                <kwd>Malaysia</kwd>
                <kwd>new host record</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>

    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The ant genus <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> Roger, 1861 belongs to the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Ponerinae</tp:taxon-name>. Some of its members show army ant-like behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Maschwitz et al. 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Kronauer 2009</xref>). Many <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> species harbor various groups of myrmecophilous insects comparable to the myrmecophile richness of the classic army ants of the subfamilies <tp:taxon-name>Dorylinae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Aenictinae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Ecitoninae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Witte et al. 2008</xref>). Rove beetles associated with <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> ants have been studied by several authors based on the material collected by ant researchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Wasmann 1899</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Kistner 1975</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Kistner et al. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hlaváč and Janda 2009</xref>). The rove beetles associated with <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> ants show strict host-species specificity, i.e. one rove beetle species is associated with only one host ant species (Maruyama, unpublished data; von Beeren and Witte, personal observations). In this article we present the first known exception to this rule, with <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia ulrichi</tp:taxon-name> Kistner, 1989 occurring in two closely related <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> host species. The already described species, <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia ulrichi</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Togpelenys gigantea</tp:taxon-name> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kistner 1989</xref> were recorded from colonies of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> (Emery, 1887) at Ulu Gombak in Peninsular Malaysia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kistner 1989</xref>). Although the former species was recorded from a <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys borneensis</tp:taxon-name> colony (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Kistner et al. 2008</xref>), this is most probably based on a misidentification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Maruyama et al. 2010</xref>). Recently, the junior author (CvB) collected a series of rove beetles from <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> colonies and from one <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys mutabilis</tp:taxon-name> (Smith, 1861) colony in Peninsular Malaysia. The material included an unknown species with an autapomorphy, which did not allow it to be assigned to any known genus.</p>
            <p>In the present article, we revise some of the rove beetle genera associated with <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> ants. This first part of the series reviews the genera which are associated with <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys mutabilis</tp:taxon-name>, including descriptions of some new taxa and some new combinations.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods"><title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>The rove beetles were collected in spring and autumn 2008 and 2009 in a well regenerated dipterocarp rainforest in the Field Studies Centre of the University of Malaya in Ulu Gombak, Malaysia (03°19.4796N; 101°45.1630E, altitude 230 m) and near the Institute of Biodiversity in Bukit Rengit, Malaysia (03°35.779N; 102°10.814E, altitude 72 m). Nests of the nocturnal host ants were located during the night by back-tracking <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> raiding trails. Since all rove beetles follow the host ant migrations, we detected them on these occasions and collected them with aspirators (for further information see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Witte et al. 2008</xref>). The specimens were put in 1.5 ml plastic tube containing 80 % ethanol for morphological studies.</p>
            <p>The methods of dissecting and line drawings followed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Maruyama (2006)</xref>. Dissected genitalia and mouthparts were mounted in Euparal on a small glass plate (10 × 5 mm), and subsequently glued onto a paper card (6 × 5 mm) and pinned under the<!--PageBreak--> respective specimen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Maruyama 2004</xref>). Photographs were taken with a Canon EOS Kiss X1 with a macro lens MP-E 65, and then combined by the automontage software CombineZM. Specimens are deposited in the senior author’s collection in the Kyushu University Museum (KUM) and in the Bavarian State Collection of Zoology (Munich, Germany). Measurements are given in millimeters and are abbreviated as follows: antennal length (AL); body length (BL); fore body length, from front margin of head to apices of elytra (FBL); hind tibial length (HTL); head length (HL); head width (HW); pronotal length (PL); pronotal width (PW).</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> is sometimes treated as a subspecies of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys processionalis</tp:taxon-name> Jerdon, 1851 known from India (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Emery 1911</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bolton 1995</xref>). However, the taxonomy of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> species in Asia has been poorly studied, and identifications of the known species remain confusing (Ito pers. comm.). We tentatively follow the current papers citing <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> as a distinct species (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Witte and Maschwitz 2000</xref>), until a revisional study of all Asian <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> species is completed. Both of the antspecies in the present paper are illustrated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–4</xref>) to specify our identifications of the species.</p>

				</sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>

            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figures 1–4.</label>
                <caption><p>Host ants. 1 <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name>, lateral view 2 ditto, head 3 <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys mutabilis</tp:taxon-name>, lateral view 4 ditto, head.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/510/supp/ZooKeys-059-047-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>

            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Kistner, 1989</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kistner 1989</xref>: 301 (original description).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia ulrichi</tp:taxon-name> Kistner, 1989.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> This genus is closely allied to <tp:taxon-name>Witteia</tp:taxon-name> in general appearance, especially pronotal shape, but may easily be distinguished from it by having a generalized labrum, not strongly sclerotized and without projections; the simple mandibles, their inner edges not emarginate at middle; the straight lateral projections of the labial apodeme; the much smaller eyes; the shorter antennae; and the shorter legs.</p>

                <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figures 5–8.</label>
                    <caption><p>Type species of the genera <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Togpelenys</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Witteia</tp:taxon-name> 5 <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia ulrichi</tp:taxon-name>, dorsal habitus 6 <tp:taxon-name>Togpelenys gigantea</tp:taxon-name>, dorsal habitus 7 <tp:taxon-name>Witteia dentilabrum</tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. n., dorsal habitus 8 ditto, head and pronotum, dorsal view.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/510/supp/ZooKeys-059-047-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>

                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                    <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Kistner et al. (2008)</xref> transferred <tp:taxon-name>Trachydonia aenictophila</tp:taxon-name> Kistner, 1997 and <tp:taxon-name>Trachydonia dichthadiaphila</tp:taxon-name> Kistner, 2003 to <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name>. However, they are apparently not members of <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name>, nor even closely related in view of the absence of the autapomorphies of <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name> Wasmann, 1899 and its allied genera (see Discussion). Though the genus <tp:taxon-name>Zyras</tp:taxon-name> Stephens, 1835 is heterogeneous, apparently non-monophyletic and not well defined yet, they can be placed in <tp:taxon-name>Zyras</tp:taxon-name> (s.lat.) by sharing the general diagnostic features of the genus (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Fenyes 1920</xref>) and excluded from <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name>, as follows:</p>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Zyras</tp:taxon-name> (s. lat.) aenictophila (Kistner in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Kistner et al. 1997</xref>),comb. n.</p>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Zyras</tp:taxon-name> (s. lat.) dichthadiaphila (Kistner in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Kistner et al. 2003</xref>), comb. n.</p>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Trachydonia</tp:taxon-name> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bernhauer 1928</xref> has been placed as a subgenus of <tp:taxon-name>Zyras</tp:taxon-name>, but <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Kistner et al. (2003)</xref> raised it to generic status. At least <tp:taxon-name>Zyras aenictophila</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Zyras dichthadiaphila</tp:taxon-name> are not members of <tp:taxon-name>Trachydonia</tp:taxon-name>. They are also not members of the subgenus <tp:taxon-name>Zyras</tp:taxon-name>. The genus <tp:taxon-name>Zyras</tp:taxon-name> should be subdivided into several genera based on a phylogenetic analysis, and then adequate systematic affiliation of these two species may be found.</p>
                    <p>The following four species are known in <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">ulrichi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Kistner, 1989</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia ulrichi</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kistner 1989</xref>: 307 (original description).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
														
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Trachydonia leptogenophila</tp:taxon-name><comment> Kistner in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Kistner et al. 2003</xref>: 386 (original description); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Maruyama 2004</xref>: 96 (synonymized with <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia ulrichi</tp:taxon-name>).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality"><title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p> Ulu Gombak, Selangor, Malaysia.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Additional records"><title>Additional records.</title>
                        <p> Ulu Gombak (University Malaya Field Studies Centre, 03°19.479N; 101°45.170E, 220–250 m alt.), Selangor, Malaysia, VIII 2008, C. von Beeren from the colony of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> (10); same data, but III 2009, C.<!--PageBreak--> von Beeren and V. Witte (12); same data, but VIII 2009, C. von Beeren (10); same data, but IX 2009, Y. Nakase (6); same data, but III 2010, C. von Beeren from the colony of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys mutabilis</tp:taxon-name> (2); Bukit Rengit, Pahang, Malaysia (03°35.779N; 102°10.814E, altitude 72 m): C. von Beeren and V. Witte (8).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Peninsular Malaysia.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Symbiotic hosts"><title>Symbiotic hosts.</title>
                        <p><tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys mutabilis</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>This species is closely similar to <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia watanabei</tp:taxon-name> in general appearance, but is distinguished from it by the pronotum being narrower around the posterior margin and the aedeagus being different in shape, especially with the apical part of the median lobe being strongly widened apically and not excavated paramerally.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>Two specimens were collected for the first time from the end of a migration column of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys mutabilis</tp:taxon-name> (new host record).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">derougemonti</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>(Pace, 1984)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla derougemonti</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Pace 1984</xref>: 460 (original description).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality"><title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p> Kalaw, Myanmar</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Myanmar.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Symbiotic host"><title>Symbiotic host.</title>
                        <p>Unknown.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>The aedeagal shape is clearly different from the other congeners in particular the parameral crest is larger and the apical lobe longer.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>Only the holotype and one paratype are known. The original description by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Pace (1984)</xref> agrees well with the characteristics of the other congeners. The symbiotic host is probably, <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> or its related species. However, Asian species of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> are in need of revision, and distributions of most known species, including <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name>, are still uncertain.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">watanabei</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>(Maruyama, 2004)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla watanabei</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Maruyama 2004</xref>: 92 (original description).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality"><title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p>Bolikhamsai (Borikhamxay), Laos.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Laos.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Symbiotic host"><title>Symbiotic host.</title>
                        <p>Unknown.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>This species is closely similar to <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia ulrichi</tp:taxon-name> in general appearance, but is distinguished from it by the pronotum being wider around the posterior margin and by the different shape of the aedeagus, especially the apical part of the median lobe being less widened apically and largely excavated paramerally.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>Only the holotype is known. The symbiotic host is probably <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> or a related species, although <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> is not recorded from Laos at present.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">dilatata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>(Pace, 2005)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla dilatata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Pace 2005</xref>: 147 (original description).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality"><title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p>Umran, East Khasi Hills, Meghalaya, India.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Meghalaya, India.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Symbiotic host"><title>Symbiotic host.</title>
                        <p>Unknown.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>This species is closely similar to <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia ulrichi</tp:taxon-name> in general appearance, but is distinguished from it by the pronotum being wider around the posterior margin and by the different shape of aedeagus, especially the apical part of the median lobe being less widened apically and largely excavated paramerally.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>Only the holotype has been known. The original description by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Pace (2005)</xref> agrees well with the characteristics of the other congeners and he noted that this species is allied to <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia derougemonti</tp:taxon-name>. The symbiotic host is probably <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> or a related species.</p>
										
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
								
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
						
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Togpelenys</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Kistner, 1989</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Togpelenys</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kistner 1989</xref>: 308 (original description).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
	              
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title>
	                  
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Togpelenys gigantea</tp:taxon-name> Kistner, 1989.</p>
	              
                </tp:treatment-sec>
	              
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
	                  
                    <p>This genus is clearly distinguished from the other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name> group by the combination of the following character states: eyes extremely large; pronotum without superior marginal line of the pronotal hypomeron; pronotal disc quite convex, with a shallow and large longitudinal depression; pronotum and elytra covered with long, suberect macrosetae; and abdomen large, expanded, much wider than elytra.</p>
	              
                </tp:treatment-sec>
	              
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
	                  
                    <p>Peninsular Malaysia.</p>
	              
                </tp:treatment-sec>
	              
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
	                  
                    <p> Only the type species <tp:taxon-name>Togpelenys gigantea</tp:taxon-name> Kistner, 1989 has been known in the genus. Probably further species will be found from the regions around Peninsular Malaysia, e.g., Sumatra, Borneo and Java.</p>
	              
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Togpelenys</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">gigantea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Kistner, 1989</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Togpelenys gigantea</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kistner 1989</xref>: 312 (original description).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality"><title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p> Ulu Gombak, Selangor, Malaysia.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Additional record"><title>Additional record.</title>
                        <p>Bukit Rengit (03°35.779N; 102°10.814E; 72 m alt.), Pahang, Malaysia, III 2009, C. von Beeren and V. Witte (2 males).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Peninsular Malaysia.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Symbiotic host"><title>Symbiotic host.</title>
                        <p><tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>This species is easily distinguished from the other species of <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name> as well as its allied genera by the generic diagnosis.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                        <p> Rare species, newly recorded from Pahang. In the type locality, Ulu Gombak, Selangor, no additional specimen has been collected despite more than 40 colonies having been examined in the last few years (von Beeren and Witte, <!--PageBreak-->personal observations; the type series were collected in 1982). We are not sure whether this is due to environmental changes in Ulu Gombak or simply due to rarity of this species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Witteia</tp:taxon-name-part>
		                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B3D89EA2-4867-40F5-9817-E6E108D0BA2B</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Maruyama &amp; von Beeren</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">18</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Witteia dentilabrum</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> Dedicated to Dr. Volker Witte for his contribution to the biology of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> ants and their symbionts. Gender, feminine.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This genus is similar to <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name> Kistner, 1989 in body shape and punctation of body surface, but may easily be distinguished from it by the labrum being strongly sclerotized and with a pair of spines; the inner margins of the mandibles emarginate at middle; the lateral projections of the labial apodeme curved apically; the extremely large eyes; the longer antennae; and the longer legs.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>) elongate, flattened; surface of fore body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>) weakly rugose, reticulated, somewhat matte.</p>
                    <p>Head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–8</xref>) transverse, with eyes extremely large, somewhat shorter than head, with a round depression above; clypeus truncate apically. Labrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 8</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">9</xref>) strongly sclerotized, with a pair of projections laterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 9</xref>: arrow). Mandibles asymmetrical, strongly curved, each apex acutely pointed; inner margin of left mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>) shallowly emarginate; that of right (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 11</xref>) rather largely emarginated. Mentum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 12</xref>) trapezoidal, with several thick setae, with sparse pseudopores. Labium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 13</xref>) broad; prementum with a setal pore and 2 real pores near base, with several pseudopores around inner ridges; apodeme without median projection, with lateral projection curved apically; ligula long, each lobe with a large setulum and three small setula; labial palpus with segment I long and apically dilated; segment II half as long as I; segment III thin, parallel-sided, slightly shorter than II.</p>
                    <p>Pronotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–8</xref>) with disc well margined, slightly convex, with a narrow longitudinal groove medially and a pair of depressions postero-laterally. Mesocoxal cavity well margined; process of metaventrite narrow, pointed at apex.</p>
                    <p>Elytra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>) apically widened, laterally with a pair of rather high carinae, that are slightly curved inwards.</p>
                    <p>Legs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>) very long, thin; femora slightly narrowed apically near apex; tibiae somewhat widened around middle to basal 1/3, their bases constricted; tibiae very thin, filiform.</p>
                    <p>Abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>) fusiform, flattened, widest around apex of segment III; surface smooth, sparsely punctured, shining. Median lobe of aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 16–17</xref>) with long and narrow apical part, with a small projection near base of apical part (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 16</xref>: arrow). Paramere with apical lobe slightly widened apically.<!--PageBreak--></p>

                <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figures 9–13.</label>
                    <caption><p>Mouthparts of <tp:taxon-name>Witteia dentilabrum</tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. n. 9 labrum, left side, dorsal view 10 left mandible, dorsal view 11 right mandible, dorsal view 12 mentum, ventral view 13 labium, ventral view.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/510/supp/ZooKeys-059-047-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>

                <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figures 14–18.</label>
                    <caption><p>Terminalia of <tp:taxon-name>Witteia dentilabrum</tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. n. 14 Male tergite VIII, dorsal view 15 male sternite VIII, ventral view 16 median lobe of aedeagus, lateral view 17 ditto, apical part 18 spermatheca.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/510/supp/ZooKeys-059-047-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>

                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Witteia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">dentilabrum</tp:taxon-name-part>
		                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:EF84731E-0E8D-486B-859B-DBD89510FC8A</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Maruyama &amp; von Beeren</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">18</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Referring to the lateral projections on the labrum which is a unique character state in <tp:taxon-name>Witteia</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type series"><title>Type series.</title>
                        <p> Holotype, male, Ulu Gombak (University Malaya Field Studies Centre, 03°19.479N; 101°45.170E, 220–250 m alt.), Selangor, Malaysia, III 2009, C. von Beeren and V. Witte, from a colony of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> (KUM). Paratypes: same data as holotype (2 males, 1 female); same data, but VIII 2008, C. von Beeren (10); same data, but VIII 2008, C. von Beeren (8); same data, but IX 2009, Y. Nakase (2).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality"><title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p>Ulu Gombak, Selangor, Malaysia.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Peninsular Malaysia.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Symbiotic host"><title>Symbiotic host.</title>
                        <p><tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>This species is closely similar in general appearance to <tp:taxon-name>Witteia borneensis</tp:taxon-name> (Pace, 1986), comb. n., from Sabah, Borneo, but is distinguished from it by the larger body and the smaller apical part of the spermatheca.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p> Body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>) color reddish brown, but head completely black, mouthparts, legs, apex of abdomen lighter, medial areas of abdominal segments V and VI infuscate. Head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–8</xref>) sparsely covered with setae; surface finely reticulated. Antennae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–8</xref>) long, filiform; all segments longer than wide; segments III-X almost twice as long as wide; segment XI elongate. Pronotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–8</xref>) subquadrate, subparallel-sided, slightly wider than long (width/length = 1.11–1.18); surface moderately covered with minute setae, with some minute macrosetae laterally. Abdomen with anterior margins of sternites IV-VI produced medially; tergite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 14</xref>) crenulate apically, with 8 macrosetae; sternite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 15</xref>) rounded apically.</p>
                        <p>Male: sternite VIII with 11–12 macrosetae. Median lobe of aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 16–17</xref>) with large parameral crest; apical part roundly convex paramerally; apical lobe slightly trilobed; copulatory piece with a short flagellum.</p>
                        <p>Female: sternite VIII with 8–9 macrosetae. Spermatheca (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 18</xref>) with basal part dilated apically, coiled near base, curved near apex; apical part short.</p>
                        <p>Measurements: BL, ≈ 4.2–5.1; FBL, ≈ 1.8–2.0; HL, 0.660–0.738; HW, 0.887–0.988; AL, ≈ 2.8–3.1; PL, 0.806–0.950; PW, 0.725–0.800; HTL, 1.238–1.438.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                        <p> Commonly found in <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> colonies together with <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia ulrichi</tp:taxon-name>, but less frequent than the latter species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Witteia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">borneensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>(Pace, 1986)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla borneensis</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Pace 1986</xref>: 204.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality"><title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p>Pangi, Sabah, Malaysia.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>This species is closely similar in general appearance to <tp:taxon-name>Witteia dentilabrum</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. from Selangor, Malaysia, but is distinguished from it by the smaller body (3.0 mm) and the larger apical part of the spermatheca.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p> Sabah, Borneo; Burma.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                        <p> This species was described based on a single specimen from Sabah, Borneo. In the original description <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Pace (1986)</xref> illustrated the habitus and spermatheca. The habitus illustration shows the labrum with a pair of projections that is an autapomorphy of <tp:taxon-name>Witteia</tp:taxon-name>. This species is probably associated with <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name>.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
	              
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            	<p>The genera <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Togpelenys</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Witteia</tp:taxon-name> are closely allied to <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name> (one species from India, Sri Lanka, Malaysia) and they belong to the <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name> genus-group (here proposed) of the subtribe <tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonina</tp:taxon-name> of the tribe Lomechusi<!--PageBreak-->ni, together with the genera <tp:taxon-name>Aenictonia</tp:taxon-name> Wasmann, 1900 (10 species from tropical Africa, one species from Thailand), <tp:taxon-name>Anommatochara</tp:taxon-name> Wasmann, 1915 (one species from tropical Africa), <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenoxenus</tp:taxon-name>, 1975 (one species from Philippines) and <tp:taxon-name>Neowroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name>, 1989 (one species from Malaysia). All members of this genus-group are associated with <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> ants as far as known, except for species of <tp:taxon-name>Aenictonia</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Anommatochara</tp:taxon-name>  which are associated with <tp:taxon-name>Dorylus</tp:taxon-name> Fabricius, 1793 and/or <tp:taxon-name>Aenictus</tp:taxon-name> Shuckard, 1840 ants. The genera of this group share the following apomorphic character states: head with “neck”, a constricted postoccipital suture; pronotum with a longitudinal median groove; elytra with a pair of carinae laterally; and apical lobe of aedeagal median lobe elongate.</p>
            	<p>When Hlaváè and Janda (2009) described the genus <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenopapus</tp:taxon-name> (species from Papua New Guinea, associated with <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys breviceps</tp:taxon-name> Viehmeyer, 1914), they stated that it is closely related to <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenoxenus</tp:taxon-name>. However, <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenopapus</tp:taxon-name> does not share the character states mentioned above. Because the type species <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenopapus mirabilis</tp:taxon-name> is in its general appearance extremely modified for myrmecomorphy, it is possible that the apomorphic character states in the <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name> group cited above have been secondarily lost or modified in this species. However, the aedeagal shape, which is normally not modified along with modification of external morphology to the myrmecophilous habitat, of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenopapus mirabilis</tp:taxon-name> is very different from those of the <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name> group. <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenopapus</tp:taxon-name> does not belong to the <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name> genus-group.</p>
            	<p><tp:taxon-name>Witteia</tp:taxon-name> is established as a new genus due to a strong autapomorphy, the presence of the projections on the labrum, by which it is clearly distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name> which is similar overall in general appearance. This character state is unique in the <tp:taxon-name>Lomechusini</tp:taxon-name>, possibly not present in any other aleocharine genera. Several other character states further distinguish <tp:taxon-name>Witteia</tp:taxon-name> from <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia</tp:taxon-name> (see Diagnosis of both the genera), though their polarities remain uncertain. We were reluctant to establish <tp:taxon-name>Witteia</tp:taxon-name> based on this single autapomorphy. However, considering generic concepts of the <tp:taxon-name>Wroughtonilla</tp:taxon-name> genus-group, which seem relatively narrow, the present establishment of the new genus seems reasonable at present. Phylogeny-based, ideally molecular phylogeny-based systematic revisions will be needed in the future.</p>
            	<p><tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> has been known as the only host of <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia ulrichi</tp:taxon-name>. However, it was collected also from colonies of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys mutabilis</tp:taxon-name> (new record above). This is the only confirmed example of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name>-associated aleocharine species that parasitizes more than one species of <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> ants. <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys distinguenda</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys mutabilis</tp:taxon-name> are morphologically very similar which suggests their close phylogenetic relationships, and this probably allows <tp:taxon-name>Maschwitzia ulrichi</tp:taxon-name> to parasitize both species. In other myrmecophilous aleocharine species of <tp:taxon-name>Lomechusini</tp:taxon-name>, some of the Asian species of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Pella</tp:taxon-name> Stephens, 1835 have been known to host more than one ant species of <tp:taxon-name>Lasius</tp:taxon-name> spp. that are also very closely related, i.e., they belong to the same subgenus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Maruyama 2006</xref>).<!--PageBreak--></p>
        		</sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <label>Acknowledgments</label>
            <p>We thank Mr. Peter Hlaváč (Košice), Dr. Alfred F. Newton (Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago) and Dr. Volker Witte (Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München) for their comments on the manuscript and Dr. Fuminori Ito for information on <tp:taxon-name>Leptogenys</tp:taxon-name> ants. This paper is supported by a Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research from JSPS (Start-up 20870031) as well as a grant of the Deutsche Forschungsgesellschaft (Project WI 2646/3).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernhauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1928</year>) <article-title>Zur Kenntnis der Staphyliniden-Gattung Zyras Steph. (17. Beitrag zur Staphylinidenfauna Afrikas)</article-title>. <source>Archiv für Naturgeschichte 92, Abreilung A</source> (<volume>7</volume>): <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1995</year>) <source>A New General Catalogue of the Ants of the World</source>. <publisher-name>Harvard University Press.</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1887</year>)<article-title> Catalogo delle formiche esistenti nelle collezioni del Museo Civico di Genova. Parte terza. Formiche della regione Indo-Malese e dell’Australia (continuazione e fine) [part].</article-title> <source>Annali del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale Genova</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>427</fpage>-<lpage>432</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1911</year>)<article-title> Hymenoptera, Fam. Formicidae, subfam. Ponerinae.</article-title> <source>In P Wytsman (ed) Genera Insectorum Fasc</source> <volume>118</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>124</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabricius</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1793</year>) <source>Entomologia Systematica emendata et aucta. Secundum classes, ordines, genera, species adjectis synonimis, locis, observationibus, descriptionibus 2</source>. <publisher-name>Hafniae</publisher-name>, <lpage>519</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenyes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1920</year>) <source>Coleoptera: Fam. Staphylinidae, subfam. Aleocharinae. Genera Insectorum, fasc. 173b</source>: <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>414</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hlaváč</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2009</year>)<article-title> New genus of Lomechusini (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae, Aleocharinae) from Papua New Guinea associated with Leptogenys Roger.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2062</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jerdon</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1851</year>)<article-title> A catalogue of the species of ants found in Southern India.</article-title> <source>Madras Journal of Literature and Science</source> <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>-<lpage>127</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1975</year>)<article-title> Myrmecophilous Staphylinidae associated with Leptogenys Roger (Coleoptera, Hymenoptera, Formicidae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1989</year>)<article-title> New genera and species of Aleocharinae associated with ants of the genus Leptogenys and their relationships (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae; Hymenoptera: Formicidae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology</source> <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>323</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berghoff</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maschwitz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Myrmecophilous Staphylinidae (Coleoptera) associated with Dorylus (Dichthadia) laevigatus (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) in Malaysia with studies of their behavior.</article-title> <source>Sociobiology</source> <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>264</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Beeren</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Redescription of generitype of Trachydonia and a new host record for Maschwitzia ulrichi (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology</source> <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>497</fpage>-<lpage>524</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissflog</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rościszewski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maschwitz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1997</year>)<article-title> New species, new genera, and new records of myrmecophiles associated with army ants (Aenictus sp.) with the description of a new subtribe of Staphylinidae (Coleoptera; Hymenoptera, Formicidae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>221</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kronauer</surname><given-names>DJC</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2009</year>)<article-title>. Recent advances in army ant biology (Hymenoptera: Formicidae).</article-title> <source>Myrmecological News</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Two new species of the Lomechusini (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae: Aleocharinae) from Laos.</article-title> <source>Entomological Review of Japan</source> <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Revision of the Palearctic species of the myrmecophilous genus Pella (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Aleocharinae).</article-title> <source>National Science Museum Monographs</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Beeren C and Witte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Aleocharine rove beetles (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae) associated with Leptogenys Roger, 1861 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) II. Two new genera and species associated with L. borneensis Wheeler, 1919.</article-title> <source>Zookeys</source> <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maschwitz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steghaus-Kovac</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaube</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hänel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1989</year>)<article-title> A Southeast Asian ponerine ant of the genus Leptogenys (Hym., Form.) with army ant life habits.</article-title> <source>Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology</source> <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>305</fpage>-<lpage>316</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Aleocharinae della Thailandia e della Birmania riportate da G. de Rougemont (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Bolletino Museo Civico Storia Naturale Verona</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>427</fpage>-<lpage>468</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1986</year>)<article-title> Aleocharinae dell’Asia sudorientale raccolte da G. de Rougemont (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Bolletino Museo Civico Storia Naturale Verona</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>-<lpage>237</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Nuovo contributo alla conoscenza delle Aleocharinae dell’India (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae). Nouvelle Revue d’Entomologie (N.S.</article-title> <source>)</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>141</fpage>-<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1861</year>)<article-title> Die Ponera-artigen Ameisen. (Schluss.</article-title> <source>) BerlinerEntomologische Zeitschrift 5</source>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Shuckard</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1840</year>)<article-title> Monograph of the Dorylidae, a family of the Hymenoptera Heterogyna. (Continued from p. 201.</article-title> <source>) Annals of Natural History; or Magazine of Zoology, Botany and Geology</source> <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>-<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1861</year>)<article-title> Catalogue of hymenopterous insects collected by Mr. A. R. Wallace in the islands of Ceram, Celebes, Ternate, and Gilolo [part].</article-title> <source>Journal of Proceedings of the Linnean Society of London</source> <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1835</year>) <source>Illustrations of British Entomology; or, a synopsis of indigenous insects; containing their generic and specific distinctions; with an account of their metamorphoses, times of appearance, localities, food, and economy,as far as practicable. Mandibulata</source>. Vol. <volume>5</volume>. <publisher-name>Baldwin and Cradock</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Viehmeyer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1914</year>)<article-title> Neue und unvollständig bekannte Ameisen der alten Welt.</article-title> <source>Archiv fur Naturgeschichte</source> <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wasmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1899</year>) <article-title>Neue Termitophilen und Myrmecophilen aus Indien</article-title>. <source>Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift 1899</source>: <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wasmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1900</year>) <article-title>Neue Dorylinengäste aus dem neo-tropischen und dem aethiopischen Fraunengebiet</article-title>. <source>Zoologische Jahrbücher: Zeitschrift für Systematik, Geographie und Biologie der Thiere</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>, 2 pls.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wasmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1915</year>) <article-title>Revision der Gattung Aenictonia Wasm. (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae) (211. Beitrag ...)</article-title>. <source>Entomologische Mitteilungen</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>, pl. 2.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Witte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leingärtner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabaß</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashim</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foitzik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Symbiont microcosm in an ant society and the diversity of interspecific interactions.</article-title> <source>Animal Behaviour</source> <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>1477</fpage>-<lpage>1486</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Witte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maschwitz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Raiding and emigration dynamics in the ponerine army ant Leptogenys distinguenda (Hymenoptera: Formicidae).</article-title> <source>Insectes Sociaux</source> <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>-<lpage>83</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>