<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.251.3986</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Parasitoids of 
                    <italic>Monochamus galloprovincialis</italic> (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae), vector of the pine wood nematode, with identification key for the Palaearctic region
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Petersen-Silva</surname>
                        <given-names>Ricardo</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Pujade-Villar</surname>
                        <given-names>Juli</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Naves</surname>
                        <given-names>Pedro</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Edmundo Sousa</surname>
                        <given-names></given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Belokobylskij</surname>
                        <given-names> Sergey</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Instituto Nacional de Investigação Agrária e Veterinária, Quinta do Marquês, 2780–159 Oeiras, Portugal
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Departament de Biologia Animal, Facultat de Biologia, Universitat de Barcelona, Avda. Diagonal 645, 08026, Barcelona, Spain
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Museum and Institute of Zoology, Polish Academy of Sciences, Wilcza 64, Warszawa 00–679, Poland
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Ricardo Petersen-Silva (<email xlink:type="simple">rnpetersen@netcabo.pt</email>)
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: C. van Achterberg</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>18</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>251</issue>
            <fpage>29</fpage>
            <lpage>48</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>11</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Ricardo Petersen-Silva, Juli Pujade-Villar, Pedro Naves, Edmundo Sousa,  Sergey Belokobylskij</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The parasitoid complex associated with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier), vector of the pine wood nematode, is discussed. Four species of the family <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name> and one <tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name> were found associated with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Portugal, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus denigrator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus ivanowi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kokujev), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Doryctes striatellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Nees) (<tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name>), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xorides depressus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Holmgren) (<tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus ivanowi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus denigrator</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Doryctes striatellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xorides depressus</tp:taxon-name></italic> are new species for Portugal fauna, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is recorded as a new host of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xorides depressus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. A key for determination of the ichneumonoid parasitoids of the pine sawyer is provided for the Palaearctic fauna.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Braconinae</kwd>
                <kwd>Ichneumonidae</kwd>
                <kwd>parasitoids</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Monochamus galloprovincialis</italic>
                </kwd>
                <kwd>Cerambycidae</kwd>
                <kwd>key to species</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Worldwide, beetles of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dejean (1821) (<tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>; <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name>) are the most important vectors of the pine wood nematode <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bursaphelenchus xylophilus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Steiner and Buhrer 1934) (Nematoda, Tylenchida, <tp:taxon-name>Aphelenchoididae</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Linit 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Kishi 1995</xref>). This nematode is native to North America, where it’s not <!--PageBreak-->considered a primary pathogen of indigenous pines, although in countries where it has been introduced it is an important agent of mortality for susceptible pines. In Portugal, where the nematode has been present for over a decade now, the pine sawyer <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier 1795) is it’s sole vector (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Sousa et al. 2001</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>The pine sawyer <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is widely distributed in Europe (except in the United Kingdom, Ireland and Cyprus), and is also present in Caucasus, Russia, North Africa, China and Mongolia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hellrigl 1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Francardi and Pennacchio 1996</xref>). The <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus</tp:taxon-name></italic> beetles do not breed on healthy trees, and are attracted only to stressed, dying or recently killed trees and freshly felled timber for egg laying (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Linsley 1959</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hellrigl 1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Linit 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Hanks 1999</xref>). Before the introduction of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bursaphelenchus xylophilus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Portugal, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> was considered a secondary forest pest and nothing was known about the most important aspects of its biology and ecology. In the rest of Europe there is also an absence of detailed studies on its biology, with the exception of the classic paper of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hellrigl (1971)</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>The most efficient way to control wilt disease is to decrease the population levels of the vector <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus</tp:taxon-name></italic> beetles. However, the different methods to control these insects usually have success only in localized, small-dimension areas, but are difficult to implement at low cost and have reduced efficiency over large forested areas. In Portugal, the most important management and control strategy consists in the elimination of symptomatic trees during late autumn, winter and early spring, while the insect vector is inside the host as late-instar larvae or pupae. The vector’s populations can also be diminished during the beetle´s flight season with the use of traps baited with attractive lures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Naves et al. 2008</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>Specific and efficient natural enemies (bio-control) would be an interesting and environmental-friendly option, but until now there are no adequate species for such control program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Naves et al. 2005</xref>). A few studies have already dealt with the parasitoids of this pine pest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Francardi and Pennacchio 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Francardi et al. 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Naves et al. 2005</xref>), although the information is scarce and disperse. In this paper we report on the diversity of parasitoids associated with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Portugal, their frequency and revise all previous information on ichneumonoids parasitoids of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the Palaearctic Region, resulting in a key for their identification.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>For the parasitoid surveys, two different approaches were employed:</p>
            <p>I – Field surveys were made in five main pine regions in Portugal, selected by their different environmental characteristics, between April and October 2011. The areas where the study was made were:</p>
            <p>Monção: (Lat: 42.075801, Lon: -8.517426)</p>
            <p>Marinha Grande, Leiria: (Lat: 39.751677, Lon: -8.9977)</p>
            <p>Comporta: (Lat: 38.35808, Lon: -8.772995)</p>
            <p>Vale Feitoso, Idanha-a-Nova: (Lat: 40.064935, Lon: -6.987579)<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <p>In each location two dead <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pinus pinaster</tp:taxon-name></italic> Aiton, trees were felled, the wood sections colonized by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> were divided into 60 cm logs, and taken to the INIAV (Instituto Nacional de Investigação Agrária e Veterinária) laboratories in Oeiras to be stored in wood boxes prepared with a wire mesh. The boxes were completely covered with a black plastic, leaving two holes with transparent containers to collect emerged insects. Boxes were analyzed every two days for insects, which were collected and stored in alcohol for posterior identification. Additionally, the boxes were opened frequently for the evaluation of the content and to collect other emerged insects. The logs were kept inside the boxes until no emergences were registered for a period of two months, and then debarked and opened (with a vertical chain saw) to detect the hosts and life stages attacked by the parasitoids.
            </p>
            <p>II – Complementary to the previous approach, artificial trap-trees were also prepared, consisting of living maritime pine trees which were cut into logs and given to adult <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> to lay eggs under laboratory controlled conditions. Each log had a medium length of 40 cm and a medium diameter of 10 cm. subsequently, the logs were taken to the terrain to be colonized by parasitoids, and in each log a hole was made to allow passing a rope to hang them in the trees, at the branches height.
            </p>
            <p>A total of 96 logs were divided according to the insect´s life stages (eggs, phloem larvae, xylem larvae and pupae), with 24 replicates each. Trials were made in Monção, Marinha Grande (Leiria), Comporta and Vimeiro, Alcobaça (Lat: 39.477811, Lon: –9.022316). In each location, six trap-trees were taken to the terrain four times during the year (pupae: April; eggs: July; phloem larvae: August; xylem larvae: October), in synchrony with the natural life cycle of the insect, and hanged in a healthy adult pine tree for a period of ten days. Subsequently, the logs were taken to the INIAV laboratory, and kept in wooden boxes (similarly to the previous experiment) to allow for emergencies. All emerged insects were identified and prepared to be photographed in the stereomicroscopy and environmental scanning electron microscopy (Serveis Científico-Tècnics de la Universitat de Barcelona). The field-emission gun environmental scanning electron microscope (FEI Quanta 200 ESEM) was used for high-resolution imaging without gold-coating with the purpose of not damaging the specimens.</p>
            <p>All the collected material was stored in INRB Forestry Entomology Collection, Oeiras, Portugal. The insects collected with the trap-tree were labeled “Artificial” and the ones from the dead trees were labeled “Natural”. Terminology employed in the key for morphological features, sculpture and measurements as well as wing venation nomenclature follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Belokobylskij and Maeto (2009)</xref>.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <p>Besides <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the following insects emerged from the wood and logs: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arhopalus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. (<tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Orthotomicus erosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Wollaston 1857) (<tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Scolytidae</tp:taxon-name>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thanasimus formicarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus 1758) (<tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Cleridae</tp:taxon-name>), <!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sirex noctilio</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fabricius (1793) (<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Siricidae</tp:taxon-name>), and some species of the family <tp:taxon-name>Anobiidae</tp:taxon-name>. Other bark beetles (<tp:taxon-name>Scolytidae</tp:taxon-name>) were also present in the dead tree material, although they were not analyzed.
            </p>
            <p>No parasitoids emerged from the trap trees with eggs, xylem larvae and pupae of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Parasitism was only found in the sub-cortical larvae, corresponding to the host´s first instars. A total of 27 specimens, belonging to five species, were recovered solely from Marinha Grande and Vale Feitoso, seven of which (all <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic>) from the trap-trees, while the remaining species were all obtained from the dead trees. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius)and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus ivanowi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kokujev)were found in Vale Feitoso, and in Marinha Grande the following ichneumonids and braconids were recovered: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus denigrator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (L.); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Doryctes striatellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Nees) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xorides depressus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Holmgren).
            </p>
            <p>By far, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic> was the most abundant species with a total of 15 specimens from Marinha Grande and Vale Feitoso. Cocoons of this species were found in the xylem galleries of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, alongside with mandibles of the dead larvae.
            </p>
            <p>The other cocoons found were in the inner bark associated with the larval galleries of the pine sawyer. The number of cocoons found matches exactly the number of parasitoids obtained from this surveys, and no other cocoons were found parasitizing any of the species previously mentioned. The parasitized species emerged between May and September under laboratory conditions and the precise dates are recorded in the labels of each specimen.</p>
            <p>The following hymenoptera emerged from the wood, with both <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name> (4) and <tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name> (1):
            </p>
            <sec sec-type="Family Braconidae">
                <title>Family <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name>
                </title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atanycolus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">denigrator</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atanycolus_denigrator</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>(Linnaeus 1758)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figures 7a, e</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Portugal: 1 female, “Leiria, 1/6/2011”, “Ensaio Pupas Natural”, “Col. Estação Florestal Nacional”; 1 male, “Leiria, 1/6/2011”, “Ensaio Pupas Natural”, “Col. Entomologica, est. Florestal”.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><bold>Palaearctic</bold>: Austria, Bulgaria, China, Croatia, former Czechoslovakia, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Israel, Italy, Kazakhstan, Korea, Mongolia, Norway, Poland, Russia, Sweden, Switzerland, Turkey, United Kingdom. <bold>Afrotropical</bold>: Niger (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Wang et al. 2009</xref>). This species is here recorded for Portugal for the first time.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Hosts">
                        <title>Hosts.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthaxia morio</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fabricius, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysobothris chrysostigma</tp:taxon-name></italic> Linnaeus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysobothris solieri</tp:taxon-name></italic> Laporte &amp; Gory, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lampra rutilans</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Poecilonota variolosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Paykull) (<tp:taxon-name>Buprestidae</tp:taxon-name>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acanthocinus aedilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Linnaeus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acanthocinus griseus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arhopalus syriacus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Reitter), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Oliver), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus sutor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhagium indagator</tp:taxon-name></italic> <!--PageBreak-->Fabricius, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhagium inquisitor</tp:taxon-name></italic> Linnaeus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhagium mordax</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Degeer), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Saperda populnea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetropium castaneum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetropium fuscum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetropium gabrieli</tp:taxon-name></italic> Weise (<tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ips sexdentatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Boerner) (<tp:taxon-name>Scolytidae</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Wang et al. 2009</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology">
                        <title>Biology.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus denigrator</tp:taxon-name></italic> is an ectoparasitoid of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> attacking <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pinus pinaster</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The species was found parasitizing the first larval instars under the bark of the tree.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus denigrator</tp:taxon-name></italic> was already recorded in Italy as parasitoid of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Campadelli and Scaramozzino 1994</xref>). We additionally studied this reared Italian material in Hungarian Natural History Museum in Budapest (1 female, “Italia, Ravenna, 14.IV.1992, Campadelli”, “Pinus picea”, “ex larva <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ol., 21.IV.1992”, “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus</tp:taxon-name></italic> ♀ <italic>denigrator</italic> L. det. Papp J. 2000”; 1 female, same first label, but “21.IV.1992”, second and third labels are the same ones) and confirmed present determination.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atanycolus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">ivanowi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atanycolus_ivanowi</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>(Kokujev 1898)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4c</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5b</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6d</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Portugal: 4 females, “Vale Feitoso II, Maio 2011”, “Col. Entomologica, est. Florestal”; 1 female, same labels, but 12.VI.2011; 1 male, “Vale Feitoso II, Maio 2011”.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><bold>Palaearctic</bold>: Armenia, Austria, Azerbaijan, Croatia, Czechia, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Italy, Japan, Kazakhstan, Russia, Slovakia, Switzerland, Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, Ukraine, Uzbekistan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>) and Turkey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bolu et al. 2009</xref>). This species is here recorded for Portugal for the first time.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Hosts">
                        <title>Hosts.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthaxia aurulenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthaxia deaurata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Gmelin), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chrysobothris solieri</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Laporte &amp; Gory), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ovalisia mirifica</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Mulsant), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanophila picta decastigma</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphenoptera tappesi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Marseul (<tp:taxon-name>Buprestidae</tp:taxon-name>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Arhopalus syriacus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Reitter), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Stictoleptura rubra</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetropium fuscum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetropium gabrieli</tp:taxon-name></italic> Weise (<tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bolu et al. 2009</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology">
                        <title>Biology.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus ivanowi</tp:taxon-name></italic> was found to be an ectoparasitoid of first larval stages of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> living under the bark of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pinus pinaster</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remark">
                        <title>Remark.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> was already recorded by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Campadelli and Scaramozzino (1994)</xref> as a host of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus ivanowi</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Italy.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cyanopterus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">flavator</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cyanopterus_flavator</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>(Fabricius 1793)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1d</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7b, d, g</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Portugal: 1 female, “Leiria, 14/6/2011”, “Ensaio Pupas Natural”, “Col. Entomologica, est. Florestal”, “13”; 1 female, same labels, 17.VI.2011, N 12. <!--PageBreak-->“Leiria, Larvas Artificial”: 1 female, N 26; 1 female, N 27. “Leiria, Posturas Artificial”: 1 female, 31.VIII.2011, N 25; 1 female, N 27. “Leiria, Ensaio, Posturas Artificial”: 1 male, 31.VIII.2011, N 21. “Vale Feitoso”: 1 female, N 9; 1 female, N 10; 1 male, N 11; 1 female, N 14; 1 female, N 15; 1 female, N 16; 1 female, N 17.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><bold>Palaearctic</bold>: Algeria, Croatia, Cyprus, former Czechoslovakia, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Israel, Italy, Japan, Kazakhstan, Korea, Latvia, Morocco, Netherland, Poland, Romania, Russia, Spain, Switzerland, Syria, Tunisia, Ukraine, United Kingdom, former Yugoslavia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>) and Portugal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Naves et al. 2005</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Hosts">
                        <title>Hosts.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bostrichus capucinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus) (<tp:taxon-name>Bostrichidae</tp:taxon-name>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acanthocinus griseus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acanthoderes clavipes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Schrank), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hesperophanes pallidus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus sartor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Morimus asper</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Sulzer), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phymatodes testaceus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pogonochaerus fasciculatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Degeer), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pogonochaerus hispidus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhagium inquisitor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Saperda scalaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus) (<tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus rosenmulleri</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Cederhjelm) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Watanabe 1937</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology">
                        <title>Biology.</title>
                        <p>The biology of this parasitoid is poorly known, but in this study all the specimens emerged from cocoons from the xylemic galleries of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, which were not completely sealed with frass, as it is normal. Considering the length of the ovipositor of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic>, it is apparent that only first larval instars of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (found beneath the bark) are parasitized, which subsequently enter the wood carrying the parasitoid. Only the mandibles of the host larvae were found in galleries with cocoons.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remark">
                        <title>Remark.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> as a host of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic> was already recorded by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Campadelli and Scaramozzino (1994)</xref> for Italy and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Naves et al. (2005)</xref> for Portugal.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Doryctes</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">striatellus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Doryctes_striatellus</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>(Nees 1834)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1b</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4b, d</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Portugal: 1 female, “Leiria, 12/8/11”, “Ensaio Pupas Natural”, 1 male, same labels, but 9.VIII.2011; 1 male, same label, but 29.VII.2011.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><bold>Palaearctic</bold>: Austria, Belgium, Bulgaria, China, Czechia, Finland, France, Germany, Hungary, Italy, Japan, Lithuania, Poland, Russia, Slovakia, Sweden, Switzerland, Ukraine, United Kingdom (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>). This species is here recorded for Portugal for the first time.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Hosts">
                        <title>Hosts.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ernobius mollis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dorcatoma dresdensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Herbst (<tp:taxon-name>Anobiidae</tp:taxon-name>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthaxia quadripunctata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phaenops cyanea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phaenops guttulata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Gebler) (<tp:taxon-name>Buprestidae</tp:taxon-name>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acanthocinus aedilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agapanthia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callidium</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callidium violaceum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Clytus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Exocentrus lusitanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mesosa curculionoides</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Molorchus minor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus sutor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phymatodes pusillus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phymatodes testaceus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Poecilium alni</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pogonocheru</tp:taxon-name></italic>s sp., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pogonocheru hispidus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhagium inquisitor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Li<!--PageBreak-->nnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Semanotus undatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Stenostola ferrea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Schrank), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetropium castaneum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetropium gabrieli</tp:taxon-name></italic> Weise, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetropium fuscum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetropium gracilicorne</tp:taxon-name></italic> Reitter (<tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pissodes harcyniae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Herbst), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pissodes notatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhynchaenus fagi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhynchaenus pilosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhynchaenus quercus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhynchaenus testaceus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Müller), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Magdalis violacea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Magdalis rufa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Germar), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyerges salicis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), (<tp:taxon-name>Curculionidae</tp:taxon-name>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hylurgops palliatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Gyllenhal), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ips typographus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ips sexdentatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Boerner), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ips subelongatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Motschulsky, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pityogenes bidentatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Herbst), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tomicus piniperda</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus) (<tp:taxon-name>Scolytidae</tp:taxon-name>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xyphidria prolongata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Geoffroy) (<tp:taxon-name>Xyphidriidae</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remark">
                        <title>Remark.</title>
                        <p>This species was already recorded in Italy on the name <italic><tp:taxon-name>Doryctes mutillator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thunberg) as parasitoid of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Campadelli and Scaramozzino 1994</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Family Ichneumonidae&gt;">
                <title>Family <tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name>
                </title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Xorides</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">depressus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Xorides_depressus</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>(Holmgren 1860)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1c</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b, e</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Portugal: 1 female, “Leiria, Pupas Natural”, 19.VII.2011; 1 female, “Leiria, 29/7/11, Ensaio Pupas Natural”; 1 female, N 19.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><bold>Palaearctic</bold>: Austria, former Czechoslovakia, Finland, France, Germany, Hungary, Latvia, Poland, Romania, Russia, Spain, Sweden (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>). This species is here recorded for Portugal for the first time.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Hosts">
                        <title>Hosts.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanophila cyanea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius) (<tp:taxon-name>Buprestidae</tp:taxon-name>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nothorhina punctata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius) (<tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier) is a new host of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xorides depressus</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Portugal.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Considering the literature data and information presented in this study, the following key identifies the species of parasitoids attacking this pine sawyer in the Palaearctic Region. Only species that are reliably confirmed as parasitoids of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> were considered for the key. Some species of parasitoids were excluded from this list and discussion about this decision is present in the final section. A key to species of <tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name> parasitoids of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is presented:
            </p>
            <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second recurrent vein of fore wing present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref>). In hind wing, second longitudinal cubital vein always present and arising near middle of nervellus. Second and third metasomal tergites movable, not fused (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2g</xref>) (Fam. <tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name>). – Spiracles of first metasomal tergite placed on or before its middle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2e–f</xref>) 
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second recurrent vein of fore wing absent (Figuress 1b, 4e, 5d). In hind wing, second longitudinal cubital vein absent. Second and third metasomal tergites immovable, fused (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a–c</xref>) (Fam. <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name>)
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First metasomal sternite distinctly separated from tergite, this tergite with glymma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2e</xref>), and/or propodeum without transverse basal carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>). Claws of leg in female with teeth or basal lobe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2c</xref>) (<tp:taxon-name>Pimplinae</tp:taxon-name>) – Second metasomal tergite with pair of oblique furrows running from almost middle of its base to spiracles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2g</xref>). Lower valva of ovipositor apically with lateral lobes covered partly upper valva; dorsal lobe of lower valva with six–seven furrows. Ovipositor sheath 1.2–1.3 times longer than body. Body entirely black (including corner of pronotum); tegula brownish yellow; pterostigma dark; legs red, hind tibia and tarsus brownish red. Body 10.0–22.0 mm
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Dolichomitus tuberculatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Geoffroy)
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First metasomal sternite fused with tergite, this tergite without glymma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2f</xref>); propodeum always at least with track of transverse basal carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>). Claws of leg in female simple, without teeth or basal lobe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2d</xref>) (<tp:taxon-name>Xoridinae</tp:taxon-name>)
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hind femur wide, with strong median ventral tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3a</xref>). Temple distinctly punctuate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3d</xref>). – Middle tibia posteriorly without deep oblique groove. Second metasomal tergite transverse and finely punctuate. Ovipositor sheath about as long as body. Body blackish; flagellum of antenna rufous; legs mainly reddish, coxae blackish. Body length 5.0–9.0 mm
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Odontocolon quercinum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thomson)
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hind femur narrow, without ventral tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3b</xref>). Temple finely obliquely striate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3e</xref>). – First metasomal tergite beyond middle without dorsal longitudinal carinae, about twice longer than wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1c</xref>). Ovipositor sheath about as long as body. Antennae brownish, without white band; hind leg brownish, but tarsus rufous; first and second metasomal tergites reddish. Body length 6.0–11.0 mm
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Xorides depressus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Holmgren)
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypoclypeal depression absent; middle of ventral margin of clypeus situated close to upper level of mandibles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4a</xref>). Brachial cell of fore wing open in distal posterior part, brachial vein absent. Second radiomedial cell of fore wing short (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4e</xref>). (<tp:taxon-name>Euphorinae</tp:taxon-name>). – Second metasomal tergite striate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3c</xref>). Body mainly black. Body length 6.0–8.0 mm
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Meteorus corax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Marshall
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypoclypeal depression deep and wide; middle of ventral margin of clypeus situated distinctly above upper level of mandibles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b</xref>). Brachial cell of fore wing closed by brachial vein in distal posterior part. Second radiomedial cell of fore wing usually long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>)
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occipital and prepectal carinae present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4d</xref>). First tergite with distinct dorsope and without median area delineated by furrows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5a</xref>). Recurrent vein of hind wing present. Submedial cell of hind wing long. (<tp:taxon-name>Doryctinae</tp:taxon-name>). Body length 3.0–6.5 mm
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Doryctes striatellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Nees) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Doryctes mutillator</tp:taxon-name></italic> auct.)<!--PageBreak-->
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occipital and prepectal carinae absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4c</xref>). First tergite without dorsope and with median area delineated by furrows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5b, c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7a-c</xref>). Recurrent vein of hind wing absent. Submedial cell of hind wing short (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5d</xref>). (<tp:taxon-name>Braconinae</tp:taxon-name>)
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pedicel of antenna almost as long as first flagellar segment. First and second flagellar segments not longer than median segments of flagellum and concave below (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6a</xref>). Second metasomal tergite without mediobasal triangle area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5c</xref>). – Ovipositor short, its sheath 1.0–1.3 times as long as metasoma, 0.60–0.65 times as long as fore wing. Second metasomal tergite about as long as third tergite, without or with fine oblique lateral furrows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5c</xref>). Body length 2.5–5.0 mm
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coeloides sordidator</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ratzeburg
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pedicel of antenna distinctly shorter than first flagellar segment. First and second flagellar segments longer than median segments of flagellum and not concave below (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7d</xref>). Second metasomal tergite usually with mediobasal triangle area separated by furrows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figures 5b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7a, c</xref>)
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second metasomal tergite without mediobasal triangle area separated by furrows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6c</xref>). Upper valva of ovipositor enlarged, distinctly larger than lower valva. Antenna setiform, longer than body. Body crimson-red with black spots. Body length 5.0–12.0 mm
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Iphiaulax impostor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Scopoli)
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second metasomal tergite usually (except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic>) with mediobasal triangle area separated by furrows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figures 5b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7a, c</xref>). Upper valva of ovipositor not enlarged, not larger than lower valva. Antenna more or less filiform, not longer than body. Body never crimson-red, usually black with yellowish brown spots or areas on head and always on most part of metasoma
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape of antenna with strong basal constriction and with apical collar. Pedicel distinctly projected behind scape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7e, f</xref>). Furrow between antennal socket and eye present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7f</xref>)
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scape of antenna without basal constriction and without apical collar. Pedicel weakly projected behind scape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7d</xref>). Furrow between antennal socket and eye absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7g</xref>)
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second–fourth metasomal tergites of female coarsely rugose-striate at least medially (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5b</xref>). Head often more or less depressed dorso-ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6d</xref>). Body length 5.0–9.0 mm
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus ivanowi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kokujev)
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second–fourth metasomal tergites of female smooth (except sculptured furrows) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7a</xref>), rarely second tergite partly with rugosity. Head never depressed dorso-ventrally
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head mainly brownish yellow or light reddish brown, only dorsally black and usually in large wedge-shaped black spot. Body length 7.0–10.0 mm</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus genalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thomson) (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus initiator</tp:taxon-name></italic> auct.)
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head mainly black, sometimes paler only near base of mandible, always with reddish stripes along inner side of eye. Body length 5.0–9.0 mm.</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus denigrator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus)
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral margin of scape (lateral view) not shorter than dorsal margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7d</xref>). Second tergite without basomedian area delineated by furrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7b</xref>). Metasoma brownish yellow, behind first tergite entirely smooth. Wings strongly infuscate. Body length 6.0–10.0 mm
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus (Cyanopterus) flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius)
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral margin of scape (lateral view) shorter than dorsal margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6b</xref>). Second tergite with distinct basomedian area delineated by sculptured furrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7c</xref>). Metasoma mainly dark brown or black, behind first tergite sculptured in furrows and suture. Wings faintly infuscate. Body length 4.0–5.0 mm
                            </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus (Ipobracon) tricolor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Ivanov)
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>With the exception of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus ivanowi</tp:taxon-name></italic> collected from Vale Feitoso, all the other species were collected in Marinha Grande. This location is near Portugal´s oldest managed pine forest, in a pine stand with about 1700 square km and which was first planted in the XIII century. This stable and managed environment may have created favorable conditions for the establishment of a diverse entomofauna in the region. In fact, the larger number of parasitoids found in the region, and the low population levels of the vector insect suggest that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> may be locally well controlled by its natural enemies. Further studies in the Leiria pine stand should confirm this hypothesis.
            </p>
            <p>There is no obvious reason for the absence of parasitoids in the other sampled locations, although factors such as the local density of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (and other insect hosts), and differences in the local edapho-climatic conditions may explain the absence of the natural enemies.
            </p>
            <p>Despite <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus</tp:taxon-name></italic> genus being the most diverse,<italic> Cyanopterus</italic> is the genus were the most specimens were found. Each parasitoid was reared from one specific location, except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens which were found in two very distanced sites, which present completely different edapho-climatic conditions.
            </p>
            <p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Watanabe (1937)</xref>, the cocoons of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic> occurred in the trunk of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Picea jezoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Siebold et <tp:taxon-name>Zuccarini</tp:taxon-name> shut in by a thick corky lid at the end of the tunnel made by the larva of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus rosenmulleri</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a conclusion which completely supports the suggested hypothesis for the parasitizing activity in Portugal.
            </p>
            <p>Worldwide and including this study, there is now a total of 14 species of parasitoids associated with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, being six <tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name> and eight <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name>. Previous reliable records (confirmed rearing from the larvae of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic>) in the literature include references from Portugal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Naves et al. 2005</xref>), Italy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Campadelli and Scaramozzino 1994</xref>), and Siberia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Tobias and Belokobylskij 2000</xref>), among other locations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kenis and Hilszczanski 2004</xref>, Tobias et al. 1986; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>). Although not detected in this study, other groups, such as the braconids of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Helconinae</tp:taxon-name> (namely species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Helcon</tp:taxon-name></italic> Nees 1812 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Helconidea</tp:taxon-name></italic> Viereck 1914), will also likely parasitized larvae of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> as they have been found to develop in larvae of other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species (Tobiaset al. 1986, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>).<!--PageBreak-->
            </p>
            <p>Other records are more dubious and need further confirmation. Among these, three records of <tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name> are possibly erroneous, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhyssa persuasoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus) (<tp:taxon-name>Pimplinae</tp:taxon-name>),<italic> Perithous divinator</italic> (Rossi) (<tp:taxon-name>Pimplinae</tp:taxon-name>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Stenarella domator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Poda) (<tp:taxon-name>Cryptinae</tp:taxon-name>). The first species is a specialized parasitoid of <tp:taxon-name>Siricidae</tp:taxon-name> larvae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Yu et al. 2005</xref>), and its rearing from <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name> is probably inaccurate. Likewise, the other two species are specialized parasitoids of vespoid and sphecoid wasps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Kasparyan 2010</xref>), and their associations with <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name> is quite doubtful. Therefore, in the identification key only three ichneumonids were included, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Odontocolon quercinum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thomson), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xorides depressus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Holmgren) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dolichomitus tuberculatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Geoffroy). On the other hand, as all species of <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name> were directly reared from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, they were included in our key.
            </p>
            <p>Despite the relatively high diversity of parasitoids associated with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus galloprovincialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> worldwide, all species are mainly idiobiont ectoparasitoids (except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus corax</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and seem to be generalists attacking a vast array of other insects living in dead and dying trees. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic>, which had already been found parasitizing young larval stages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Naves et al. 2005</xref>), appears to be the most frequent and promising candidate for studies aiming the biological control of the pine sawyer, despite its generalist habits. As mentioned, the disperse distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be considered as a major adaptation two the diverse edapho-climatic conditions characteristic for Portugal. Other options, such as the introduction of exotic natural enemies would create new parasite-host interactions, which usually offer greater changes of success for biological control than the promotion of already established associations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hokkanen and Pimentel 1984</xref>). Nevertheless, such measures require rigorous pre-release risk assessment of the economic and environmental costs and benefits of the introduction, to evaluate its potential effectiveness, host specificity, acclimatisation and viability for mass-production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">van Lenteren et al. 2006</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>Detailed studies on the effect of the parasitoid guild found in Portugal on the pine sawyer´s population and the suitability of the species for biological control are being planned, with the final objective of eventually establishing an integrated bio-control program against the vector of the pine wilt disease in Europe.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Figure plates">
            <title>Figure plates<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></title>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Forewing of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dolichomitus tuberculatus</tp:taxon-name></italic>(<bold>a</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Doryctes striatellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>b</bold>); metasoma in dorsal view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xorides depressus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>c</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>d</bold>).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-029-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 2.</label>
                <caption><p>Propodeum in dorsal view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dolichomitus tuberculatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>a</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Odontocolon quercinum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>b</bold>); tarsal claws of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dolichomitus tuberculatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>c</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Odontocolon quercinum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>d</bold>); first metasomal tergite in lateral view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dolichomitus tuberculatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>e</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Odontocolon quercinum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (f); dorsal view of metasoma of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dolichomitus tuberculatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>e</bold>); sp – spiracle.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-029-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 3.</label>
                <caption><p>Lateral view of hind femur of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Odontocolon quercinum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>a</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xorides depressus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>b</bold>); first and second metasomal tergites in dorsal view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meteorus corax</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>c</bold>);head in lateral view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Odontocolon quercinum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>d</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xorides depressus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>e</bold>).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-029-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 4.</label>
                <caption><p>Face in frontal view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Meteorus corax</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>a</bold>)and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Doryctes striatellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>b</bold>); head in dorsal view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus ivanowi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>c</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Doryctes striatellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>d</bold>); detail of forewing of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Monochamus corax</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>e</bold>).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-029-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 5.</label>
                <caption><p>Metasoma in dorsal view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Doryctes striatellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>a</bold>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus ivanowi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>b</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coeloides sordidator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>c</bold>); forewing of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coeloides sordidator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>d</bold>); ma – mediobasal area.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-029-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 6.</label>
                <caption><p>Basal segments of antenna in lateral view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coeloides sordidator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>a</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus tricolor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>b</bold>); metasoma in dorsal view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Iphiaulax impostor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>c</bold>); face of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus ivanowi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>d</bold>).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-029-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 7.</label>
                <caption><p>Metasoma in dorsal view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus denigrator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>a</bold>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>b</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus tricolor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>c</bold>); scape and pedicel in lateral view of C.<italic> flavator</italic> (<bold>d</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus denigrator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>e</bold>); space of head between antennal socket and eye in laterofrontal view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atanycolus genalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>f</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyanopterus flavator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<bold>g</bold>).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-029-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgement</title>
            <p>We are grateful to Mr. Adérito Matos for his assistance both in the field surveys and laboratory handling, to Drª Rita Matos Gomes and to the team from the AFN Marinha Grande for all the conditions and support provided during this study, to Eng. Teixeira and his team from Alcobaça, to Mr. Alfredo and his colleagues from Monção and to Engºs António Moreira and Pedro Serrasqueiro of Herdade da Comporta for allowing the trails to take place in the private estate. We are also very thankful to Dr Dmitri R. Kasparyan (St. Petersburg, Russia) for determination of the ichneumonid parasitoid and valuable consultation.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Belokobylskij</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeto</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Doryctinae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) of Japan. Fauna Mundi Volume 1.</source> <publisher-name>Natura optima dux Foundation</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Warsaw</publisher-loc>, <lpage>806</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beyarslan</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yildirim</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aktürk</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Two new host records of Atanycolus ivanowi(Kokujev, 1898) (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) from Turkey.</article-title> <source>Türkiye Entomoloji Dergisi </source> <volume>33</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>287</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Campadelli</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scaramozzino</surname> <given-names>EPL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Imenotteri parassitoidi di insetti xilofagi in in Romagna.</article-title> <source>Bollettino dell’Istituto di Entomologia della Universita degli Studi di Bologna</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Francardi</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pennacchio</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Note sulla bioecologia di Monochamus galloprovincialis galloprovincialis (Olivier) in Toscana e in Liguria (Coleoptera Cerambycidae).</article-title> <source>Redia</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Francardi</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pennacchio</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Silva</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> Attack distribution on maritime pine bole by longhorn beetles in Tuscany (Coleoptera Cerambycidae).</article-title> <source>Redia </source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>-<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanks</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Influence of the larval host plant on reproductive strategies of cerambycid beetles.</article-title> <source>Annual Review of Entomology</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>-<lpage>505</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ento.44.1.483" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.ento.44.1.483</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hellrigl</surname> <given-names>KG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<article-title> The bionomics of the European genera of Monochamus (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae) and their significance to the forest and lumber economy.</article-title> <source>Redia </source> <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>-<lpage>509</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hokkanen</surname> <given-names>HMT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pimentel</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> New approach for selecting biocontrol agents.</article-title> <source>Canadian Entomologist</source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>1109</fpage>-<lpage>1121</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/Ent1161109-8" xlink:type="simple">10.4039/Ent1161109-8</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasparyan</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Parasitism on aculeates (Hymenoptera: Aculeata) as important direction in the evolution of ichneumon-flies of the tribe Cryptini (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae, Cryptinae).</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Russian Entomological Society</source> <volume>81</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>112</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>. [<comment>In Russian</comment>]</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenis</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilszczanski</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Natural enemies of Cerambycidae and Buprestidae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieutier</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Battisti</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregoire</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>European bark and wood boring insects in living trees: a synthesis.</source> <publisher-name>Kluwer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>, <fpage>484</fpage>–<lpage>498</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4020-2241-8_21" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/978-1-4020-2241-8_21</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kishi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<source> The pine wood nematode and the Japanese pine sawyer.</source> <publisher-name>Thomas Company Limited</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc>, <lpage>302</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>van Lenteren</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bale</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bigler</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hokkanen</surname> <given-names>HMT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loomans</surname> <given-names>AJM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Assessing risks of releasing exotic biological control agents of arthropod pests.</article-title> <source> Annual Review of Entomology </source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>609</fpage>-<lpage>634</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ento.51.110104.151129" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.ento.51.110104.151129</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Linit</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<source> The insect component of pine wilt disease in the United States. In Wingfield MJ (ed.), Pathogenicity of the pine wood nematode.</source> <publisher-name>American Phytopathological Society Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>St. Paul</publisher-loc>, <fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Linit</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> Nematode-vector relationships in the pine wilt disease system.</article-title> <source>Journal of Nematology </source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>-<lpage>235</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Linit</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> Transmission of pinewood nematode through feeding wounds of Monochamus carolinensis (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of Nematology </source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>236</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Linsley</surname> <given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>)<article-title> Ecology of Cerambycidae.</article-title> <source>Annual Review of Entomology </source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>138</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.en.04.010159.000531" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.en.04.010159.000531</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Naves</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenis</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Parasitoids associated with Monochamus galloprovincialis (Olivier) (Coleoptera: Cerambycidae) within the pine wilt nematode-affected zone in Portugal.</article-title> <source>Journal of Pest Science </source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10340-004-0068-z" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10340-004-0068-z</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Naves</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Biology of Monochamus galloprovincialis (Coleóptera: Cerambycidae) in the pine wilt disease affected zone, Southern Portugal.</article-title> <source>Silva Lusitana</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pires</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naves</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penas</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonifácio</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mota</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Bursaphelenchus xylophilus (Nematoda; Aphelenchoididae) associated with Monochamus galloprovincialis (Coleoptera; Cerambycidae) in Portugal.</article-title> <source>Nematology </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/156854101300106937" xlink:type="simple">10.1163/156854101300106937</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobias</surname> <given-names>VI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belokobylskij</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotenko</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Family Braconinae</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Medvedev</surname> <given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed.</role>) <source>Key to the insects of the European part of the USSR.</source> Volume 3 Hymenoptera, Part 4, New Dehli, 500 pp. [<comment>Translation, original in Russian was published in 1986</comment>]</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobias</surname> <given-names>VI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belokobylskij</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Fam. Braconidae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehr</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed.</role>) <source>Key to insects of the Russian Far East. Neuropteroidea, Mecoptera, Hymenoptera.</source> <publisher-name>Dal’nauka</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Vladivostok</publisher-loc>, 4(4), <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>571</lpage>. [<comment>In Russian</comment>]</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Achterberg</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horstmann</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> World Ichneumonoidea, Taxonomy, Biology, Morphology and Distribution.</source> <publisher-name>Vancouver</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Taxapad</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> The genus AtanycolusFoerster (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Braconinae) in China, with description of one new species.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys </source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1937</year>)<article-title> A contribution to the knowledge of the Braconid fauna of the Empire of Japan (Hymenoptera).</article-title> <source>Journal of the Faculty of Agriculture Hokkaido Imperial University </source> <volume>42</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>