<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.207.3339</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new genus and species of Metopiinae  (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae) from Mexico</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Khalaim</surname>
                        <given-names>Andrey I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:ACF2AF20-5723-4507-AABB-CC7445B7A44A</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Ruíz-Cancino</surname>
                        <given-names>Enrique</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:81FACC41-6193-4C59-92E0-7AB89FCD037E</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Coronado-Blanco</surname>
                        <given-names>Juana M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:CB508630-E90E-42AD-B7CE-8AB40ED02AF7</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>División de Estudios de Postgrado e Investigación, Facultad de Ingeniería y Ciencias, Universidad Autónoma de Tamaulipas, Cd. Victoria 87149, México
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Zoological Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences, Universitetskaya nab. 1, St. Petersburg 199034, Russia
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Andrey I. Khalaim (<email xlink:type="simple">ptera@mail.ru</email>)
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Gavin Broad</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>11</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>207</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>10</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>6</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Andrey I. Khalaim, Enrique Ruíz-Cancino, Juana M. Coronado-Blanco</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:1FFDF406-8FD6-4BDF-9292-3136AFE50BC4</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new genus of <tp:taxon-name>Metopiinae</tp:taxon-name>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khalaim, <bold>gen. n.</bold>, with a single species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos juachicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khalaim &amp; Ruíz-Cancino, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, is described from Jalisco Province in central Mexico. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos</tp:taxon-name></italic> belongs to the group of three genera (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cubus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Townes &amp; Townes, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Colpotrochia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Holmgren and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triclistus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Förster) having a high lamella separating the antennal sockets and reaching the median ocellus (this lamella possesses a dorsal groove in it, just below the median ocellus), but differs from these genera primarily by 1) face and clypeus not convex in lateral view, 2) face separated from clypeus by a shallow transverse impression, 3) mandible with lower tooth very strongly reduced, 4) flagellomeres of antenna strongly transverse, and 5) dorsal carinae of propodeum reduced. A portion of the key to the genera of <tp:taxon-name>Metopiinae</tp:taxon-name> is provided to distinguish the new genus.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>North America</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Ojuelos</italic>
                </kwd>
                <kwd>new genus</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy
<!--PageBreak--></kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Metopiinae is a moderately large subfamily with over 750 described extant species distributed in 25 genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Yu et al. 2005</xref>). The subfamily is well represented in all parts of the World, occurs from the Arctic to the tropics, and some large genera (e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Exochus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Gravenhorst, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metopius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Panzer) are almost worldwide. Species of <tp:taxon-name>Metopiinae</tp:taxon-name> can be collected in various habitats but generally are most abundant in forests. All known <tp:taxon-name>Metopiinae</tp:taxon-name> are solitary endoparasitoits of <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name>. Oviposition is into the exposed or concealed host larva, and emergence is always from the pupa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Townes 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Gauld and Sithole 2002</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>Most <tp:taxon-name>Metopiinae</tp:taxon-name> species are easily recognized by their face and clypeus which are confluent and not separated by a groove and moderately to strongly convex in lateral view (except that the face of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metopius</tp:taxon-name></italic> is flat and with a large shield-shaped area bounded by a sharp carina). Most have the upper margin of the face produced dorsally between the antennal insertions into a triangular flange. The body and legs are usually robust, the metasoma is more or less cylindrical, and the ovipositor is thin and very short (not projecting beyond the apex of metasoma). Some <tp:taxon-name>Orthocentrinae</tp:taxon-name> [Orthocentrus group of genera sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Wahl and Gauld (1998)</xref>] have a similar structure of the face and clypeus (confluent and strongly convex) but these may be distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Metopiinae</tp:taxon-name> primarily by the long cylindrical scape of antenna and because the upper edge of the face lacks the triangular interantennal projection. In addition, <tp:taxon-name>Orthocentrinae</tp:taxon-name> parasitize <tp:taxon-name>Mycetophiloidea</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Townes 1971</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>A list of Mexican <tp:taxon-name>Metopiinae</tp:taxon-name> was prepared by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Ruíz-Cancino et al. (2002)</xref> and included only 17 species from 7 genera. Some more metopiine species and genera were mentioned from Mexico in the book on Costa Rican <tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name> published in the same year by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Gauld and Sithole (2002)</xref>. Five new records of metopiine species were recently recorded from southern Mexico by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">González-Moreno et al. (2011)</xref>, and a review of the Mexican species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Colpotrochia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Holmgren (five species of this genus are recorded for the first time) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cubus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Townes &amp; Townes was published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Khalaim and Ruíz-Cancino (2011)</xref>. Nevertheless at present, the Mexican <tp:taxon-name>Metopiinae</tp:taxon-name> are very poorly studied, and only a small part of the real Mexican metopiine fauna is described. For comparison, the fauna of America north of Mexico comprises about 145 species from 19 genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Townes and Townes 1959</xref>), and 130 species from 14 genera were recorded from Costa Rica (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Gauld and Sithole 2002</xref>). Here a new metopiine genus with a new species is described from central Mexico.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Wing venation and morphological terms predominantly follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Gauld and Sithole (2002)</xref>. Photographs were taken at the Zoological Institute of the Russian Academy of Science (St. Petersburg, Russia) with a DFC 290 digital camera attached to a Leica MZ16 stereomicroscope, and images were combined using Helicon Focus software.<!--PageBreak--> Generic identification was checked through the keys to world genera of <tp:taxon-name>Metopiinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Townes 1971</xref>), genera of America north of Mexico (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Townes and Townes 1959</xref>), genera of Costa Rica (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Gauld and Sithole 2002</xref>) and genera of Australia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Fitton 1984</xref>). The only specimen of the new genus was collected on herbs in a dry area above 2200 m in central Mexico. The holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos juachicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is deposited at the Insect Museum of Universidad Autónoma de Tamaulipas, Cd. Victoria, Mexico (UAT).
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <sec sec-type="Key to world genera of Metopiinae (modified from Gauld and Sithole 2002, Townes 1971)">
                <title>Key to world genera of <tp:taxon-name>Metopiinae</tp:taxon-name> (modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Gauld and Sithole 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Townes 1971</xref>)
                </title>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Face with a large shield-shaped area bounded by a sharp carina. Tergites 1 and 2 fused (clearly visible in lateral view). Laterotergite 1 broad</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Metopius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Panzer
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Face more or less convex, without a concave shield-shaped area. Tergites 1 and 2 separated by a flexible membrane</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interantennal process of face produced dorsally into a high longitudinal lamella separating the antennal sockets; this lamella with a longitudinal groove in the dorsal surface, just below the median ocellus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interantennal process of face not produced dorsally as a longitudinal lamella, or if a weak, short lamella present, it does not have groove in the dorsal surface</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other genera of Metopiinae</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propleuron almost cubical in profile, resembling fore coxa in shape. Mesosternal region with a pair of flattened finger-like processes projecting backwards over bases of mid coxae. Upper half of mesopleuron strongly inflated</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cubus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Townes &amp; Townes
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propleuron not cubical in profile. Mesosternal region smooth or with a weak lamella before mid coxae, without finger-like processes. Mesopleuron laterally usually not strongly inflated</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Face and clypeus not especially convex in lateral view, separated by weak and broad transverse impression. Mandible with lower tooth strongly reduced, represented as a small tubercle; upper tooth large, chisel-shaped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>). Propodeum with only area posteroexterna bounded by carinae, otherwise ecarinate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>). Flagellomeres of antenna very short, mid flagellomeres almost twice as broad as long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>)
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khalaim, gen. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Face and clypeus moderately to very strongly convex in lateral view; clypeus not separated from face. Mandible with lower tooth shorter, subequal to or longer than upper tooth, not especially reduced, and upper tooth more or less pointed, not chisel-shaped. Propodeum with carinae not as above. Flagellomeres of antenna more or less elongate</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><!--PageBreak-->5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First metasomal segment weakly to quite strongly tapered anteriorly, but always evenly so, thus the anterior 0.4 is not parallel sided; its spiracle near its anterior 0.3. Sternite 1 short, at most reaching about 0.3 of length of tergite. Mandible with lower tooth much shorter than upper tooth</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Triclistus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Foerster
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First metasomal segment petiolate anteriorly, the anterior 0.4 slender and parallel sided; its spiracle near, at or behind the centre. Sternite 1 long, reaching more than 0.5 of length of tergite. Mandible with teeth subequal or with lower tooth longer than upper tooth</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Colpotrochia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Holmgren
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ojuelos</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6A8BDDD3-BF85-458A-A5F4-9850741A1819</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Ojuelos</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Khalaim</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">13</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                        <title>Type species:</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos juachicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khalaim &amp; Ruíz-Cancino, sp. n.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Composition">
                        <title>Composition.</title>
                        <p>The new genus contains only the type species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos juachicus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, described below.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>The new genus belongs to the group of three genera (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cubus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Colpotrochia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triclistus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) having a characteristic lamella separating the antennal sockets and reaching the median ocellus (this lamella possesses a longitudinal groove in it, just below the median ocellus) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>), and can be distinguished from these genera by the characters given in the key above. Besides characters mentioned in the key, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Colpotrochia</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the first metasomal segment not petiolate and evenly tapered anteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 11</xref>), and lower tooth of mandible very small (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>), and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triclistus</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the subgenital plate of female without a deep V-shaped invagination posteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 13</xref>) (some species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triclistus</tp:taxon-name></italic> also have hypopygium only weakly emarginate).
                        </p>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from all other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Metopiinae</tp:taxon-name> by combination of the following characters: 1) frons with a medial, longitudinal lamella that possesses a groove in dorsal surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>); 2) face very weakly convex in profile and separated from clypeus by a weak groove; 3) first metasomal tergite in dorsal view gradually widening posteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 11</xref>) (not petiolate as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Colpotrochia</tp:taxon-name></italic>); 4) mesosternum without a pair of flattened, finger-like processes projecting posteriorly over bases of mid coxa (projections present in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cubus</tp:taxon-name></italic>); 5) propodeum lacks most carinae, only the area posteroexterna is bounded by carinae, whereas the longitudinal carinae are absent anteriorly.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Fore wing length 9.5 mm, body length about 12.6 mm. Body and legs predominantly black, flagellum yellowish brown, wings yellow with distal margin broadly infuscate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p><bold>Head:</bold> Mandibles stout, not twisted, with lower tooth strongly reduced (very small and inconspicuous) and upper tooth broad and chisel-shaped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>). Labrum<!--PageBreak--> exposed, short and apically truncated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>). Malar space half as long as basal width of mandible. Clypeus 3.0 times as broad as high, more or less flat in lateral view, separated from face by weak and broad transverse impression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>). Face and upper 0.8 of clypeus very densely and coarsely punctate (punctures partly merging). Face very weakly convex, with upper part produced dorsomedially into a triangular projection that extends posteriorly as a thin, longitudinal lamella between bases of antennae; this lamella reaching to the median ocellus, and dorsally with a conspicuous groove (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>). Ocelli not enlarged. Back of head steeply declivous behind the posterior ocelli. Occipital carina dorsally close to foramen magnum, almost complete but obliterated ventrally before hypostomal carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>). Hypostomal carina strong, raised into a high flange (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>). Flagellum of antenna rather short and thick; all flagellomeres, excepting three basal and one apical flagellomere, distinctly transverse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p><bold>Mesosoma:</bold> Propleuron not enlarged. Epomia very sharp and strongly raised, close to anterior margin and extending upwards (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>). Notauli completely absent. Mesopleuron strongly inflated (lateral sides of mesopleuron conspicuously protuberant in dorsal view). Epicnemial carina reaching almost margin of pleuron immediately below the subalar prominence, with a secondary carina extending from pleural margin near lower corner of pronotum, to join the subtegular ridge. Sternaulus absent. Posterior transverse carina of mesopleuron present laterally and absent ventrally. Propodeum rather short, convex, almost ecarinate, with only area posteroexterna clearly bounded by carinae, and with weak and short longitudinal carina extending anteriorly from anterior margin of area posteroexterna (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>). Propodeal spiracle large and oval (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>). Pleural carina between propodeum and metapleuron complete. Submetapleural carina complete, strongly raised anteriorly.
                        </p>
                        <p><bold>Wings:</bold> Fore wing with stalked rhombic areolet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>), vein <italic>cu-a</italic> strongly inclivous and distad <italic>Rs</italic>&amp;<italic>M</italic>. Vein 2<italic>m-cu</italic> slightly S-curved, with one long bulla. Hind wing with distal abscissa of <italic>Cu</italic>1 distinct, meeting cu-a much closer to 1<italic>A</italic> than to <italic>M</italic>.
                        </p>
                        <p><bold>Legs:</bold> Robust, all femora thickened. Fore tibia without apical tooth. Hind and mid tibiae with two spurs; inner spur of hind tibia longer than outer spur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 12</xref>). Apical tarsomeres not swollen. Tarsal claws large, simple but with long hairs.
                        </p>
                        <p><bold>Metasoma:</bold> Tergites 1 and 2 of metasoma separated. First tergite 1.6 times as long as posteriorly broad (length measured from hind margin of propodeum), evenly tapered anteriorly in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 11</xref>), with spiracle near its anterior 0.35 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 9</xref>); dorsomedian carinae virtually absent, dorsolateral carinae distinct only at base of the tergite, completely absent behind spiracle; sternite 1 reaching about 0.33 of length of tergite. Tergites 2 and 3 with neither dorsal nor dorsolateral carinae. Laterotergites 2 and 3 narrow, separated by a sharp crease. Laterotergite 4 separated from tergite by weak crease only anteriorly. Subgenital plate of female roundly truncated and very weakly concave at apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 13</xref>). Ovipositor thin and short, slightly upcurved, without dorsal subapical notch, slightly projecting beyond apex of subgenital plate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 12</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Named after the type locality, Ojuelos de Jalisco. Gender masculine.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ojuelos</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">juachicus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2F287E7F-CF27-4383-BDF4-3DF74EA9EB43</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Ojuelos_juachicus</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Khalaim &amp; Ruíz-Cancino</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">13</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Female.</p>
                        <p><bold>Head:</bold> Mandibles mostly densely and coarsely punctate, very finely shagreened at apex. Labrum 6.3 times as long as basally broad (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>). Maxillary and labial palpi slender and moderately long. Clypeus with lower margin truncated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>), smooth in lower 0.2. Face with weak median tubercle in its upper part. Inner eye orbits moderately concave at level of antennal insertions. Vertex and genae with dense and sharp punctures (distance between punctures mostly equal to or slightly longer than diameter of puncture), smooth between punctures; punctures in lower part of genae sparser. Gena, in dorsal view, rounded, about as long as eye width (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>). Lateral ocellus separated from eye margin by distance equal to maximum diameter of ocellus. Flagellum of antenna with 46 flagellomeres; the basal flagellomere about 2.5 times as long as broad; flagellomeres 4+ distinctly transverse, mid flagellomeres almost twice as broad as long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p><bold>Mesosoma:</bold> Pronotum mediodorsally smooth, laterally deeply concave. Mesoscutum weakly convex, posterolaterally with a sharp flange, entirely densely and sharply punctate, smooth between punctures. Scutoscutellar groove deep and smooth. Scute<!--PageBreak-->llum moderately convex in lateral view, smooth, with sharp punctures and with lateral carinae only at its extreme base. Mesopleuron mostly densely and sharply punctate, smooth and impunctate only posteriorly. Propodeum dorsally polished, laterally and posteriorly finely punctate to coriaceous. Metapleuron smooth, in dorsoposterior 2/3 with sparp punctures, in ventroanterior 1/3 impunctate.
                        </p>
                        <p><bold>Metasoma:</bold> Tergite 2, in dorsal view, slightly transverse; laterotergite 2 parallel-sided, 3.8 times as long as broad. Tergite 3 with laterotergite rather narrow and parallel-<!--PageBreak-->sided. Tergite 1 dorsally predominantly finely and densely punctate, smooth and shining between punctures. Tergites 2–6 dorsally mostly finely and very densely punctate, weakly polished between punctures. Subgenital plate finely punctate.
                        </p>
                        <p><bold>Coloration:</bold> Body and legs almost entirely black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Flagellum yellowish brown with the basal and the apical flagellomeres fuscous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Mouth parts blackish. Wings yellow with distal margin broadly infuscate, pterostigma and most of veins pale brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>). Legs predominantly black; fore leg with femur yellowish brown apically, tarsus yellowish brown, partly infuscate; mid leg with femur apically, tibia basally and basitarsus basally yellowish brown; hind leg with tibia with broad subbasal yellowish brown band and basitarsus basally yellowish brown. Tergite 1 with broad posterior brownish yellow band; tergite 2 laterally yellowish brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 11</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Male unknown.</p>
                        <p><bold>Material examined.</bold> Holotype female, México, Zacatecas Prov., 20 km S Ojuelos de Jalisco, Juachí, La Papa de Arriba, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">21°42.104'N, 101°36.791'W</named-content>, 2275 m, sweeping, 21.IX.2011, coll. A.I. Khalaim (UAT).
                        </p>
                        <p><bold>Distribution.</bold> Central Mexico (Jalisco).
                        </p>
                        <p><bold>Etymology.</bold> Named after the type locality, Juachí.<!--PageBreak-->
                        </p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos juachicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khalaim &amp; Ruíz-Cancino, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, habitus, female holotype.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-207-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figures 2–8.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos juachicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khalaim &amp; Ruíz-Cancino, <bold>sp. n.</bold> <bold>1</bold> antenna, dorsal view <bold>2</bold> head, dorsal view <bold>3</bold> head, latero-ventro-posterior view (OC – occipital carina, HC – hypostomal carina) <bold>5</bold> head, latero-ventro-anterior view <bold>6</bold> head, frontal view <bold>7</bold> head and anterior part of mesosoma, dorsolateral view <bold>8</bold> fore wing, dorsal view.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-207-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figures 9–13.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos juachicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khalaim &amp; Ruíz-Cancino, <bold>sp. n.</bold> <bold>9</bold> propodeum, metapleuron and metasomal segments 1–2, lateral view <bold>10</bold> propodeum and metapleuron, lateral view <bold>11</bold> propodeum and metasomal segments 1–2, dorsal view <bold>12</bold> metasoma and hind leg, lateral view <bold>13</bold> apex of metasoma, latero-ventro-posterior view.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-207-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a distinct member of the <tp:taxon-name>Metopiinae</tp:taxon-name> as it has a characteristic stout body and legs, cylindrical metasoma with short first segment, face weakly separated from clypeus and with the dorsally projecting triangular interantennal flange, lack of sternaulus and tooth on apex of fore tibia, and having a short and very slender ovipositor.
            </p>
            <p>We place <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos</tp:taxon-name></italic> to the group of three genera, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cubus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Colpotrochia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Triclistus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (all occur in Mexico), based on the putative synapomorphy of the interantennal lamella that bears a dorsal, longitudinal groove. The genus is distinguished from other genera of the subfamily primarily by the rather unusual structure of the head which has the face and clypeus only slightly convex in lateral view and separated by a weak impression. Within the subfamily similar head present only in two small genera, the predominantly Holarctic <italic><tp:taxon-name>Periope</tp:taxon-name></italic> Haliday (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Kusigemati 1968</xref>) and the Holarctic and Neotropical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Scolomus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Townes &amp; Townes (= <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apolophys</tp:taxon-name></italic> Townes) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Gauld and Wahl 2006</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ojuelos</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Periope</tp:taxon-name></italic> by having a hind tibia with two robust spurs (one slender spur in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Periope</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and a strongly reduced lower tooth of the mandible, from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Scolomus</tp:taxon-name></italic> by having the triangular interantennal projection of face (in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Scolomus</tp:taxon-name></italic> face without triangular projection dorsally), a shorter malar space (1.2–1.8 times as long as basal width of mandible in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Scolomus</tp:taxon-name></italic>), a strongly transverse clypeus (subquadrate, about as broad as long in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Scolomus</tp:taxon-name></italic>), a fore wing with vein <italic>cu-a</italic> strongly distad <italic>Rs</italic>&amp;<italic>M</italic> (opposite to slightly distad in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Scolomus</tp:taxon-name></italic>), and from both genera by having a reduced longitudinal carinae of the propodeum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 10, 11</xref>) (propodeum with complete medial longitudinal carinae in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Periope</tp:taxon-name></italic> and more or less developed basal and apical transverse carinae in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Scolomus</tp:taxon-name></italic>).
            </p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We are thankful to Dmitry R. Kasparyan (Zoological Institute of Russian Academy of Sciences, St. Petersburg, Russia), Ilari E. Sääksjärvi (University of Turku, Finland) and Gavin R. Broad (Natural History Museum, London, UK) for their valuable comments and suggestions. We also wish to thank the anonymous referee for his important suggestions and language corrections. This work was supported by the Russian Foundation for Basic Research (grant no. 10-04-00265) and the PROMEP Project “Taxonomía y ecología de fauna y micobiota en comunidades forestales y cultivos”.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitton</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Subfamily Metopiinae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>An introduction to the Ichneumonidae of Australia.</issue-title> <source>Natural History Museum, London</source>: <fpage>353</fpage>-<lpage>363</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sithole</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Subfamily Metopiinae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sithole</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ugalde-Gómez</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godoy</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <issue-title>The Ichneumonidae of Costa Rica, 4.</issue-title> <source>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 66</source>: <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> The relationship and taxonomic position of the genera <italic>Apolophus</italic> and <italic>Scolomus</italic> (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1130</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>González-Moreno</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bordera</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delfin-González</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Metopiinae (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae) de la reserva especial de la biosphera Ríz Lagartos, México.</article-title> <source>Entomología mexicana </source> <volume>9</volume> (<issue>2010</issue>): <fpage>212</fpage>-<lpage>215</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalaim</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruíz-Cancino</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Mexican species of <italic>Colpotrochia</italic> Holmgren, 1856 and <italic>Cubus</italic> Townes &amp; Townes, 1959 (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae: Metopiinae).</article-title> <source>Russian Entomological Journal </source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>-<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kusigemati</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> A revision of the genus <italic>Periope</italic> Haliday with description of a new species (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae).</article-title> <source>Insecta Matsumurana </source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruíz-Cancino</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasparyan</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coronado-Blanco</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> 37. Ichneumonidae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Llorente-Bousquets</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrone</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Biodiversidad, Taxonomía y Biogeografía de Artrópodos de México: Hacia una síntesis de su conocimiento.</issue-title> <source>Conabio-Ecosur-Bayer, México</source>: <fpage>631</fpage>-<lpage>646</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Townes</surname> <given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<article-title> The genera of Ichneumonidae, Part 4.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute </source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>372</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Townes</surname> <given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Townes</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>)<article-title> Ichneumon-flies of America north of Mexico: 1. Subfamily Metopiinae.</article-title> <source>United States National Museum Bulletin </source> <volume>216</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>318</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5479/si.03629236.216.1" xlink:type="simple">10.5479/si.03629236.216.1</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> The cladistics and higher classification of the Pimpliformes (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae).</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology </source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>-<lpage>298</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-3113.1998.00057.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1046/j.1365-3113.1998.00057.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Achterberg</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horstmann</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> World Ichneumonoidea 2004. Taxonomy, biology, morphology and distribution. CD/DVD</source>. <publisher-name>TAXAPAD</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Vancouver, Canada</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>