<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
	
    <front>
		
        <journal-meta>
			
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
			
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
			
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
			
            <publisher>
				
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
				
            </publisher>
		
        </journal-meta>

        <article-meta>
	
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.53.493</article-id>

	
            <title-group>
	
                <article-title>
                    A new species of Myrmedonota Cameron from eastern Kansas (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Aleocharinae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
	
	
            <contrib-group>
		
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
			
                    <name name-style="western">
				
                        <surname>Eldridge</surname>
				
                        <given-names>K. Taro</given-names>
			
                    </name>
			
                    <aff>
                        Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, and Division of Entomology, Biodiversity Institute, 1501 Crestline Dr., Suite 140, University of Kansas, Lawrence, KS 66045-2811, USA
                    </aff>
			
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:682046BE-35EB-4228-807A-D6888BE7081C</uri>
		
                </contrib>

            </contrib-group>

            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: K. Taro Eldridge (<email xlink:type="simple">taroeldredge@ku.edu</email>).
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Jan Klimaszewski</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
	
                <day>27</day>
	
                <month>8</month>
	
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>53</issue>
            <fpage>17</fpage>
            <lpage>24</lpage>
            <history>
	
                <date date-type="received">
		
                    <day>4</day>
		
                    <month>6</month>
		
                    <year>2010</year>
	
                </date>
	
                <date date-type="accepted">
		
                    <day>20</day>
		
                    <month>7</month>
		
                    <year>2010</year>
	
                </date>
            </history>

            <permissions>
	
                <copyright-statement>K. Taro Eldridge</copyright-statement>
	
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
	
                </license>
            </permissions>

            <abstract>
	
                <label>Abstract</label>
	
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota heliantha</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is described from eastern Kansas (USA). All specimens were collected from dung. A modified new key to the species of <tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota</tp:taxon-name> of America north of Mexico is provided.
                </p>
	
            </abstract>
	
	
	
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Lomechusini</kwd>
                <kwd>myrmecophily</kwd>
                <kwd>termitophily</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>Nearctic region</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota</tp:taxon-name> Cameron (Aleocharinae: Lomechusini) currently contains 25 species, mostly described from the Old World (23 species), including Borneo (one species), Malay Peninsula (two species), New Guinea (19 species) and Sulawesi (one species) (Hlaváč personal communication). Recently, two new Nearctic species, <tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota aidani</tp:taxon-name> Maruyama &amp; Klimaszewski and <tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota lewisi</tp:taxon-name> Maruyama &amp; Klimaszewski were described from the states of Ohio and Indiana (USA), respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Maruyama et al. 2008</xref>). Life histories of most species are not known, but some have been collected in the presents of ants or termites; these species are presumed to be myrmecophilous or termitophilous, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bourguignon and Roisin 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Kistner 2003</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>Recently, the author collected specimens of an undescribed <tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota</tp:taxon-name> species from dung. This species is treated as new and described along with a new key to separate North American species.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
            <p>Dry specimens were observed using an Olympus SZX7 stereomicroscope. Dissected structures were observed with the stereomicroscope and an Olympus BX51 compound microscope. Illustrations were made using a camera lucida, Olympus U-DA, mounted on the compound scope. Scale bars were drawn using an Olympus slide micrometer. Body measurements were made using a stereomicroscope ocular micrometer.
</p>
            <p>All specimens examined were mounted using water soluble fish glue; all dissected body parts were cleared, preserved in Euparal mounting medium and are pinned under appropriate specimens.
</p>
            <p>Terminology follows the work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Gusarov (2002</xref>; aedeagal orientation), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Maruyama (2006</xref>; epipharyngeal surface), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Sawada (1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">1972</xref>; chaetotaxy, mouthpart and median lobe morphology) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Seevers (1978</xref>; parameral morphology).
            </p>
            <p>Abbreviations applied in this paper are as follows: HW = head width; HL = head length; HW/HL = head width over head length; OL = ocular length; OL/HL = ocular length over head length; CKTE = private collection of K. Taro Eldredge; SEMC = Snow Entomological Collection, University of Kansas.
</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics"><title>Systematics</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Myrmedonota</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Cameron, 1920</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name></tp:taxon-name><comment>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Kistner (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Pace (2009)</xref> for references and keys to species.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota cingulata</tp:taxon-name> Cameron, 1920, by monotypy (pp. 272–273).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> Members of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota</tp:taxon-name> may be separated from other genera of Lomechusini by the following combination of characters (partially adopted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Maruyama et al. 2008</xref>): 1) head dorsally subcircular, excluding mouth parts; 2) head lacking neck; 3) occipital suture complete; 4) antennae generalized, clavate and slightly laterally compressed; 5) pronotum with complete marginal line; 6) pronotum without depressions or macrosculpture; 7) body surface finely punctate; 8) abdomen with no horn-like ornamentation; 9) dorsal abdominal surface with sparse to moderate setation but never with dense setal cover, nor with thick macrosetae creating a bristle-like texture; 10) cardo partially overlapping stipes, ventrally; 11) lacinia and<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> galea extremely elongate and parallel sided; 12) labial palpomeres I and III subequal in length and longer then palpomere II; 13) glossa bifid with each lobe housing two sensillate elements; 14) mentum trapeziform and almost as long as wide; 15) labrum with lateral apices rounded and extending apically beyond maximum midpoint; 16) apical lobe of paramere short; 17) vellum and velar sac of paramere large and extending past the maximum reach of apical lobe and partially concealing it.
                    </p>
                    <p>In North America <tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota</tp:taxon-name> most closely resembles the genus <tp:taxon-name>Pella</tp:taxon-name>, but can be separated from the later by the following combination of characters: 1) smaller size (&lt; 3.5 mm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Maruyama et al. 2008</xref>]); 2) extremely elongate lacinia and galea; 3) mentum almost as long as wide.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="New key to Myrmedonota species of America north of Mexico"><title>New key to Myrmedonota species of America north of Mexico</title>
										
                    <p>.
                    </p>	
										
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                	
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                	
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of body at least 3.0 mm, ranging up to 3.2 mm; pronotum reddish brown or black in color; spermatheca with proximal end not curved atop itself (Fig. 12 &amp; 21 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Maruyama et al. 2008</xref>)
                                    </td>
                                	
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
																
                                <tr>
																	
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
																	
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of body less then 3.0 mm, on average 2.6 mm; pronotum yellowish in color; spermatheca with proximal end curved atop itself (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 20</xref>)
                                    </td>
																	
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M. heliantha sp. n.
                                    </td>
																
                                </tr>
																
                                <tr>
																	
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
																	
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum reddish brown in color; elytra uni-colored reddish light brown; abdomen bi-colored with tergites II-IV light brown and V-VIII brown; spermatheca S-shaped (Fig. 12 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Maruyama et al. 2008</xref>); athetine bridge wide in lateral view (Fig. 8 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Maruyama et al. 2008</xref>)
                                    </td>
																	
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M. aidani Maruyama &amp; Klimaszewski
                                    </td>
																	
                                </tr>
																
                                <tr>
																	
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
																	
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum black in color; elytra bi-colored with at least distal margin cream colored and rest grey to black in color; abdomen uni-colored black; spermatheca V-shaped (Fig. 21 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Maruyama et al. 2008</xref>); athetine bridge narrow in lateral view (Fig. 17 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Maruyama et al. 2008</xref>)
                                    </td>
																	
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M. lewisi Maruyama &amp; Klimaszewski
                                    </td>
																
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>

                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Myrmedonota</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">heliantha</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:91552887-E437-4D63-88FB-80AAF8630A11</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Eldredge</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">20</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–2</xref>) length with a mean of 2.6 mm (n = 4), color yellowish to black. Head and abdominal tergites V-VII (segment V can be lighter or approaching yellowish grey) grey to black; pronotum and elytra yellowish light brown; abdominal tergites II–IV and VIII yellowish light brown to yellowish; mouthparts and legs yellowish; antennae dark brown, segments I–III and apex of segment XI may be yellow ish light brown to yellow ish brown.
                    </p>
                    <p>Head subcircular (HW = 0.47 mm; HL = 0.42 mm; HW/HL = 1.11; n = 4) with apex narrowing to receive labrum and mouthparts; eyes large, occupying half of head (OL = 0.21 mm; OL/HL = 0.5; n = 4); setae of vertex growing posteromedially; labrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>) with apex broadly margined, apicomedially with paired emargination to receive seta b; epipharynx (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>) with relatively short seta a, six to seven lateral setae equally spaced apart, mesolateral area with relatively little sculpture; maxilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>) with galea and lacinia extremely elongate, galea with preapical margin with a row of spinose setae that are uninterrupted by confused setation, palpomere IV long, with filamentous sensillae, and greater then half the length of palpomere III; labium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>) with palpomere I and III subequal in length and palpomere II short, setula β and δ absent, glossa with a pair of apical and basolateral-epipharyngeal sensillate elements, mentum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 14</xref>) trapeziform with apex approximately half as wide as base and length almost equally width at base.
                    </p>

											
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
												
                        <label>Figure 1–2.</label>
                        <caption>
													<p><tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota heliantha</tp:taxon-name>. 1 habitus 2 elytra.</p>
													
                        </caption>
													
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/493/supp/ZooKeys-53-017-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
											
                    </fig>
											
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
												
                        <label>Figure 3–6.</label>
                        <caption>
													<p><tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota heliantha</tp:taxon-name>. 3 right maxilla, ventral view 4 labium, ventral view 5 labrum 6 epipharynx. Scale bars: I Figs 5–6 II Fig. 3 III Fig. 4.</p>
													
                        </caption>
													
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/493/supp/ZooKeys-53-017-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
											
                    </fig>
											
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
												
                        <label>Figure 7–14.</label>
                        <caption>
													<p><tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota heliantha</tp:taxon-name> male (7–9, 10–13) and female (10–11). 7 tergite VIII 8 holotype tergite VIII, outline of apical margin 9 tergite VIII 10 holotype sternite VIII 11 sternite VIII 12 genital segments excluding sternite IX, dorsal view 13 sternite IX, ventral view 14 mentum, ventral view. Scale bars: I Figs 7–13 II Fig. 14.</p>
													
                        </caption>
													
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/493/supp/ZooKeys-53-017-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
											
                    </fig>
											
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
												
                        <label>Figure 15–20.</label>
                        <caption>
													<p><tp:taxon-name> Myrmedonota heliantha</tp:taxon-name>. 15 median lobe, lateral view 16 median lobe, parameral view 17 copulatory piece, oblique arameral view 18 paramere, outer lateral view 19 apical lobe of paramere, outer lateral view 20 spermatheca. Scale bars: I Fig. 19 II Figs 17, 20 III Figs 15–16, 18.</p>
													
                        </caption>
													
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/493/supp/ZooKeys-53-017-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
											
											
                    </fig>

                    <p>Pronotum flattened, transverse (PW = 0.57 mm; PL = 0.39 mm; PW/PL = 1.46; n = 4), widest subapically and narrowest sub-basally, general form trapeziform (“approximately shield-shaped” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Klimaszewski et al. 2005</xref>, p. 709]), anterolateral corners rounded and slightly receding posterior for most of apical edge, posterolaterally with obtuse angles, posterior edge broadly rounded, lateral margins evenly arcuate, setae growing posterolaterally with no distinct midline.
                    </p>
                    <p>Elytra together, transverse (EW = 0.73 mm; EL = 0.49 mm; EW/EL = 1.49; n = 2), longer then pronotum (EL/PL = 1.55) and acutely emarginated at suture.
</p>
                    <p>Abdomen with dorsal surface relatively glabrous with tergites II-V with basal transverse impressions.
</p>
                    <p>Male tergite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 7–8</xref>) apicomedially emarginate with lateral angles of emargination slightly produced and intermarginal edge variably serrate, with five pairs of macrosetae; sternite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>) with eight pairs of macrosetae; genital segments as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 12</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">13</xref>; aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 15–16</xref>) relatively elongate with complete athetine bridge; copulatory piece (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 17</xref>) long, occupying most of median lobe; paramere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 18–19</xref>) with apical lobe partially visible on outer surface, internal velar pad present (stippled area), vellum large and extending apically, partially obscuring apical lobe in outer view, apical lobe with chaetotaxy as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 19.</xref>
                    </p>
                    <p>Female tergite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 9</xref>) truncate with five pairs of macrosetae; sternite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 11</xref>) with seven pairs of macrosetae (one fewer then males); genital segments with same macrochaetotaxy as in males; spermatheca (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 20</xref>) in shape of the letter S with proximal end curved atop itself, internal cone with circumventral sculptural grooves.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota heliantha</tp:taxon-name> most closely resembles <tp:taxon-name>Myrmedonota aidani</tp:taxon-name>, but can be distinguished by the following combination of characters: 1) pronotum widest subapically; 2) internal sac with distinctive configuration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 15</xref>); 3) spermatheca without an apical process extending from internal cone and with proximal end curved atop itself.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>HOLOTYPE, ♂: “USA: KANSAS: Douglas Co.,/Lawrence, Baker Wetlands, N 38.92737°; W 95.23278°//ex. human dung baited pitfall trap (SEMC). PARATYPES, 2♀ and 1♂: same data as holotype (1♀, terminalia dissected<!--PageBreak--> but spermatheca not recovered, SEMC; 1♂, completely disarticulated permanent slide mount [additional label data “Euparal slide#007, K.T. Eldredge 2009”], CKTE); same locality data, differing data reads “13.ix.2009”, “ex. mammal dung” (1♀, terminalia dissected, SEMC).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Bionomics"><title>Bionomics.</title>
                    <p> All specimens were collected off dung at Baker Wetlands, a 573 acre tract of restored wetland and prairie habitat, approximately 250 meters in elevation and two miles south of the University of Kansas campus.
</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> Derived from the generic nomen <tp:taxon-name>Helianthus</tp:taxon-name>, in dedication to the sunflower state Kansas, where the type series was collected.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <label>Acknowledgments
            </label>
            <p>The author would like to thank Dr. A.E.Z. Short and Dr. M. Maruyama for thoughtful comments on drafts.
</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>Reference

            </title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourguignon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roisin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2006</year>)<article-title>A New Genus and Three New Species of Termitophilous Staphylinids (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae) Associated with Schedorhinotermes (Isoptera: Rhinotermitidae) in New Guinea.</article-title><source>Sociobiology</source><volume>48</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1920</year>) <article-title> New species of Staphylinidae from Singapore. Part III.</article-title><source>The Transactions of the Entomological Society of London, 1920, parts 1–2</source>:<fpage>212</fpage>-<lpage>284</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gusarov</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title> A revision the Nearctic species of the genus Geostiba Thomson, 1858 (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Aleocharinae).</article-title><source>Zootaxa</source><volume>81</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2003</year>) <article-title> A New Species of Myrmedonota from Papua-New Guinea with the First Specific Host Record (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae, Lomechusini).</article-title><source>Sociobiology</source> <volume>42</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>519</fpage>-<lpage>532</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Klimaszewski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hlaváč</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2005</year>)<article-title>Canadian species of the Zyras group of genera and review of the types from America north of Mexico (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Aleocharinae).</article-title><source>Revue Suisse de Zoologie</source><volume>112</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>703</fpage>-<lpage>733</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2006</year>) <source> Revision of the Palearctic species of the myrmecophilous genus Pella (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Aleocharinae)</source>. <publisher-name>National Science Museum</publisher-name> 32, <publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc>, iii + <lpage>207</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klimaszewski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2008</year>) <article-title> First record of the genus Myrmedonota Cameron (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae) from North America, with descriptions of two new species.</article-title><source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1716</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Aleocharinae dell’Irian Jaya (Nuova Guinea) al Naturkundemuseum di Erfurt (Insecta: Coleoptera: Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Vernate</source> <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>329</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1970</year>)<article-title> Aleocharinae (Staphylinidae, Coleoptera) of the IBP-Station in the Shiga Heights, Central Japan, II.</article-title><source>Contributions from the Biological Laboratory, Kyoto University</source><volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sawada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Methodological Research in the Taxonomy of Aleocharinae.</article-title><source>Contributions from the Biological Laboratory, Kyoto University</source><volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Seevers</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1978</year>)<article-title>A generic and tribal revision of the North American Aleocharinae (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Fieldiana: Zoology</source><volume>71</volume>: vi + <lpage>275</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>