<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.67.705</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    A new <italic>Tithaeus</italic> species from Hainan Island, China (Arachnida, Opiliones, Laniatores, Epedanidae), with a key to the Chinese species
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Zhang</surname>
                        <given-names>Chao</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7BF197AF-0B03-4F35-81C7-1E4AD1DE77EE</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Zhang</surname>
                        <given-names>Feng</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:904C4445-AAEA-40BC-B418-502053EF39B8</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            				<aff id="A1">College of Life Sciences, Hebei University, Baoding Hebei 071002, China</aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Feng Zhang(<email xlink:type="simple">zhangfeng@hbu.cn</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Dmitry Logunov</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
            	    <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>10</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>67</issue>
            <fpage>65</fpage>
            <lpage>72</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>13</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>5</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Chao Zhang, Feng Zhang</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:8AF8B895-A6E8-4C07-A9BE-1203952E3BCB</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new species of the harvestmen <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus calyptratus</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold> (<tp:taxon-name>Epedanidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Opiliones</tp:taxon-name>) from Hainan Island (China) is diagnosed, described and illustrated. A key to the two Chinese species of <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name> is provided.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Opiliones</kwd>
                <kwd>Laniatores</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Tithaeus</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>Hainan Island</kwd>
                <kwd>China</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The family <tp:taxon-name>Epedanidae</tp:taxon-name> Sørensen, 1886 is represented by 188 species in 73 genera worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Kury 2003</xref>). The genus <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name> was described on the basis on the type species, <tp:taxon-name>Tithaenus laevigatus</tp:taxon-name> Thorell, 1891, from Malaysia. At present, the genus includes 34 valid species mainly distributed in South East Asia. Among them, the only species, <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus drac</tp:taxon-name> Lian, Zhu &amp; Kury, 2008, known from both sexes, has been reported from China (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). However, the majority of the <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name> species remain poorly known, es<!--PageBreak-->pecially as far as their genital morphology concern. Therefore, the diversity of <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name> reported from south China (2 species) and neighbouring countries of SE Asia, such as Myanmar (1 species), Vietnam (1 species), Singapore (2 species), and Thailand (4 species), is much lower that that in Indonesia (7 species) or Malaysia (18 species) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Thorell 1891</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Loman 1905</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Roewer 1912</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">1923</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">1927</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1949</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Banks 1930</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Suzuki 1969a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">1969b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Lian et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
            <p>During a 2009 faunal survey of tropical Hainan Island, a few specimens of the Laniatores were collected. Among them, one species of <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name> was identified as new to science and is described in this paper.</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
            	<label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Tithaenus drac</tp:taxon-name> (black circles) and <tp:taxon-name>Tithaenus calyptratus</tp:taxon-name> (black triangle) in China</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-067-065-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Marterials and methods"><title>Marterials and methods</title>
            <p>Two males and one female were collected from Hainan Island in south China (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). All type specimens are deposited in the Museum of the Hebei University (MHBU), Baoding, China. Specimens were preserved in 75% ethanol, examined and drawn using a Leica M165c stereomicroscope equipped with a drawing apparatus. The genitalia were first placed in hot lactic acid then moved to distilled water in order to expand them for observation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Schwendinger and Martens 2002</xref>). All measurements are in mm.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Tithaenus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Thorell, 1891</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Thorell 1891: 371</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Banks 1930: 66</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Lian et al., 2008: 53–54</xref>.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Sinis</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Loman 1892: 12</xref>.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Sinniculus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Loman 1902: 198</xref>.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species:</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus laevigatus</tp:taxon-name> Thorell, 1891, by original designation.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis and distribution"><title>Diagnosis and distribution:</title>
                    <p> see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Lian et al. (2008)</xref>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to species of Tithaeus known in China"><title>Key to species of <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name> known in China</title><p>.</p>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carapace flat between its anterior margin and ocularium</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Tithaenus drac</tp:taxon-name> (Lian, Zhu &amp; Kury, 2008)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carapace with a low hump situated between its anterior margin and ocularium</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Tithaenus calyptratus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">calyptratus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                      <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E8C66900-F2DD-4852-A753-4B54459832CB</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">17</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                    <p> The ♂ holotype (MHBU) from China, Hainan Province, Mt. Diaoluo [18.67° N, 109.92° E], 5 June 2009, C. Zhang leg.</p>
                    <p>Paratypes: 1♀ (MHBU), together with the holotype; 1♂ (MHBU), China, Hainan Province, Mt. Qixianling [18.77° N, 109.68° E], 9 June 2009, C. Zhang leg.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> The specific name is derived from the Greek word “calyptra” meaning a cap or hat, referring to the straw-hat type stylar lobe of the penis.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> The new species is similar to <tp:taxon-name>Tithaenus kokutnus</tp:taxon-name> Suzuki, 1985, recorded from northern Thailand (Suzuki, 1985: fig. 4), but can be easily distinguished from it by the following characters: (1) Cheliceral proximal segment armed with a large tooth and two smaller ones, situated medially on the ventral surface and the second segment is covered with granules on its frontal surface; (2) Both the dorsal margin of pedipalpal femur and its ventral margin between two setiferous tubercles are finely serrated; (3) Penis with a straw-hat shaped stylar lobe.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Tithaenus calyptratus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. has various morphological characters that support its placement in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name>: viz., scutal region with five areas, eye tubercle without a median spine, pedipalpus relatively short and thick, tarsi III and IV without scopulae and distitarsus I with two tarsalia. Furthermore, the genital characters (such as, the distal margin of the penial ventral plate with a deep cleft, glans with simple mem<!--PageBreak-->branous lobe and each lobe of the ovipositor with two ventral and two dorsal setae) are also in agreement with to the generic disagnosis of <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name> (as per <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Lian et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Male (holotype) habitus as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2–3</xref>. Coloration: body rusty yellow; carapace and ocularium with yellow-brown reticulation; lateral margins and opisthosomal areas of scutum, and free tergites banded with blackish brown; all coxae and genital plate yellowish, free sternites somewhat clouded; chelicerae and pedipalpus yellowish, with brown reticulate markings above; trochanters of legs yellowish; femora to tarsi slightly darker.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p>Body from above as a trapezoid, wider posteriorly than anteriorly. Ocularium ovoid, only with a few granules. A low hump, lower than the ocularium, is situated between it and the anterior margin of carapace. Abdominal scutum, as well as each free tergite, with a transverse row of very small tubercles, and with a longitudinal row of granules on their lateral margins. Anal plate with scattered tubercles. Each of the free sternites with a row of obsolete granules. Coxa I with irregular hair-tipped granules, coxae II-IV smooth. Dorsal surface of coxa IV with several rather coarse granules. Coxa III with a few humps along the frontal and rear margins. Tracheal stigma clearly visible.</p>
                    <p>Chelicera (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–9</xref>). Proximal segment disto-dorsally visibly swollen, armed with a large tooth and two smaller ones, situated medially on the ventral surface. Second segment with some hair-tipped tubercles on frontal surface. Fingers relatively short but stout; inner edges toothed as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>.</p>
                    <p>Pedipalpus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 4–5</xref>) short and robust, trochanter with a ventral setaceous tubercle. Femur ventrally with three strong and a small setiferous tubercles; on the prolateral distal side with a setiferous tubercle. Femur dorsally with a minutely serrate margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>). Such a margin also between the two ventral setiferous tubercles. Patella disto-medially with a setiferous tubercle. Tibia ventro-laterally with two small and two prominent setiferous tubercles, ventro-medially with two stout and two reduced setiferous tubercles. Tarsus ventrally with three setiferous tubercles on each side.</p>
                    <p>Legs slender and relatively elongated. All segments unarmed, smooth. Femora I-IV straight. Tarsi III-IV with simple double claws, no scopulae. Tarsal formula: 5/11/5/6. Distitarsi of first and second tarsi each with two tarsalia.</p>
                    <p>Penis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">11–17</xref>). Shaft slender and long, distal portion swollen. Ventral plate with a wide median cleft, setae arranged as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 11–13</xref>. Basal sac oval, well developed, immovable and sunken into truncus. Glans with complex structures, twisted when at rest. Stylar lobe shaped somewhat like a straw hat and surrounding the stylus.</p>
                    <p>Female. Similar to male in general appearance but with a slightly larger body.</p>
                    <p>Ovipositor as illustrated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>). Each lobe with two ventral and two dorsal setae.</p>
                    <p>Measurements: Male holotype (female paratype). Body 4.13 (4.44) long, 2.91 (3.06) wide at the widest portion, scutum 3.42 (3.52) long; eye tubercle 0.40 (0.38) long, 0.93 (0.85) wide. Pedipalpus claw 0.50 (0.63) long. Penis 1.78 long. Measurements of left pedipalpus and right legs as in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    	<label>Figures 2–10.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus calyptratus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <bold>2</bold> Male body, lateral view <bold>3</bold> Same, dorsal view <bold>4</bold> Left pedipalpus, male, posterior view <bold>5</bold> Same, anterior view <bold>6</bold> Minute serrate margin on the ventral side of femur, left pedipalpus, male <bold>7</bold> Left chelicera male, anterior view <bold>8</bold> Distal segment of the left chelicera, male, above view <bold>9</bold> Left chelicera, male, posterior view <bold>10</bold> Ovipositor. Scale bars: 1mm (1–2); 0.5mm (3–4, 6–8); 0.25mm (5, 9).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-067-065-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    	<label>Figures 11–17.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus calyptratus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <bold>11</bold> Entire penis <bold>12</bold> Penis tip, ventral view <bold>13</bold> Ditto, lateral view <bold>14</bold> Ditto, dorsal view <bold>15</bold> Expanded penis, ventral view <bold>16</bold> Ditto, lateral view <bold>17</bold> Ditto, dorsal view. Abbreviations: <bold>BS</bold> basal sac <bold>S</bold> stylus <bold>SL</bold> stylar lobe <bold>VP</bold> ventral plate. Scale bars: 0.5 mm (10); 0.25mm (11–16).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-067-065-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <caption><p><bold>Table 1.</bold> Pedipalpus and leg measurements of the male holotype (female paratype). </p></caption>
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Trochanter</italic></th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Femur</italic></th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Patella</italic></th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tibia</italic></th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Metatarsus</italic></th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tarsus</italic></th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Total</italic></th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pedipalpus</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35(0.38)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00(0.90)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70(0.68)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75(0.68)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00(0.90)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80(3.54)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leg I</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56(0.51)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70(2.35)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77(0.71)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19(1.89)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21(2.86)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68(1.73)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.11(10.05)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leg II</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77(0.77)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32(5.30)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28(0.92)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.97(4.74)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.45(6.22)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.28(4.34)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.07(22.29)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leg III</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77(0.61)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.57(2.91)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02(1.02)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40(2.09)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.88(3.57)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04(2.04)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.68(12.24)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leg IV</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71(0.71)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00(4.18)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12(1.02)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26(2.86)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.61(5.20)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.81(2.55)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.51(16.52)</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>       
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Habitat"><title>Habitat.</title>
                    <p> Collected under fallen logs in the humid tropical forest.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p> Hainan Province, China.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>The opilionids genus <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name> was established by Thorell in 1891 (type species: <tp:taxon-name>Tithaenus laevigatus</tp:taxon-name> Thorell, 1891). Later, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Roewer (1912</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">1923</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">1927</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1949</xref>) placed it in the subfamily Phalangodinae of Phalangodidae and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Suzuki (1969a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">1969b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">1985)</xref> supported this assignment. However, recently <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Kury (2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2010)</xref> transferred <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name> to the <tp:taxon-name>Epedanidae</tp:taxon-name>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Lian et al. (2008)</xref> further considered the taxonomic status of the <!--PageBreak-->genus reasoning both from its somatic and from male genital morphology. Having compared <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus similis</tp:taxon-name> Suzuki, 1985 with representatives of two subfamilies, the phalangodid and the epedanid, they found out that its male genitalia could be evidence of its relationship with the epedanid. We follow Kury’ opinion and consider <tp:taxon-name>Tithaeus</tp:taxon-name> a member of the <tp:taxon-name>Epedanidae</tp:taxon-name> on the basis of its genital characters, such as, a well developed immovable sac and the absence of complex introverting structures in the penis.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We wish to express our sincere gratitude to Dr. J. MacDermott for reading of the manuscript and for valuable comments on it. Thanks are due to two anonymous referees for valuable comments. This work was supported by the Ministry of Science and Technology of the People’s Republic of China (MOST Grant No. 2006FY110500).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1930</year>)<article-title> Phalangida from Borneo.</article-title> <source>The Sarawak Museum Journal</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kury</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Annotated catalogue of the Laniatores of the New World (Arachnida, Opiliones). Revista Iberica de Aracnología, Zaragoza, vol.</article-title> <source>especial monográfico, nº</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>337</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kury</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source>Checklist of valid genera of Opiliones of the World</source>. <publisher-name>Museu Nacional/UFRJ website</publisher-name>. Online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.museunacional.ufrj.br/mndi/Aracnologia/checklaniator.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://www.museunacional.ufrj.br/mndi/Aracnologia/checklaniator.htm
            </ext-link> [access October 2010]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kury</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> A new species of the genus <italic>Tithaeus</italic> from China (Arachnida: Laniatores: Epedanidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1841</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Loman</surname><given-names>JCC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1892</year>)<article-title>Opilioniden von Sumatra, Java und Flores</article-title>. In <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Max</surname><given-names>Weber</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>ed.</role>) <source>Zoologische Ergebnisse einer Reise in Niederländisch Ost-Indien</source>. <publisher-loc>Leiden</publisher-loc>, <lpage>476</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Loman</surname><given-names>JCC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1902</year>)<article-title> Neue aussereuropäische Opilioniden.</article-title> <source>Zoologische Jahrbücher, Jena, Abteilung für Systematik, Ökologie und Geographie der Tiere</source> <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>-<lpage>216</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Loman</surname><given-names>JCC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1905</year>)<article-title> Opilioniden aus Java.</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen aus dem Naturhistorischen Museum in Hamburg, Hamburg</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roewer</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>)<article-title> Die Familien der Assamiiden und Phalangodiden der Opiliones-Laniatores. (= Assamiden, Dampetriden, Phalangodiden, Epedaniden, Biantiden, Zalmoxiden, Samoiden, Palpipediden anderer Autoren).</article-title> <source>Archiv für Naturgeschichte, Berlin</source> <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>242</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roewer</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1923</year>)<article-title>Die Weberknechte der Erde</article-title>. <source>Systematische Bearbeitung der bisher bekannten Opiliones</source>. <publisher-name>Gustav Fischer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Jena</publisher-loc>, <lpage>1116</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roewer</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1927</year>)<article-title> Weitere Weberknechte I. (1. Ergänzung der: “Weberknechte der Erde,” 1923).</article-title> <source>Abhandlungen der Naturwissenschaftlichen Verein zu Bremen, Bremen</source> <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>261</fpage>-<lpage>402</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roewer</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1949</year>)<article-title> Über Phalangodiden I. (Subfam. Phalangodinae, Tricommatinae, Samoinae.) Weitere Weberknechte XIII.</article-title> <source>Senckenbergiana</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwendinger</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title>A taxonomic revision of the family Oncopodidae III: Further new species of <italic>Gnomulus</italic> Thorell (Opiliones, Laniatores)</article-title>. <source>Rev. Suisse Zool.</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969a</year>)<article-title> On a collection of opilionids from Southeast Asia.</article-title> <source>Journal of Science of the Hiroshima University, Series B, Division 1 (Zoology), Hiroshima</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969b</year>)<article-title> Some phalangids from Thailand.</article-title> <source>Journal of Science of the Hiroshima University</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Opiliones of Semangkok Forest Reserve, Malaysia.</article-title> <source>Journal of Science of the Hiroshima University, Hiroshima</source> <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> A synopsis of the Opiliones of Thailand (Arachnida) I. Cyphophthalmi and Laniatores.</article-title> <source>Steenstrupia</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorell</surname><given-names>TTT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1891</year>)<article-title> Aracnidi di Pinang raccolti nel 1889 dai Sig.ri L. Loria e L. Fea.</article-title> <source>Annali del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale di Genova, Genova</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>383</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>