<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.82.775</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                Coulmannia rossensis sp. n. (Isopoda, Asellota, Paramunnidae) from the Ross Sea, Southern Ocean
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Choudhury</surname> 
                        <given-names>Madhumita</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:12D63FBA-49E8-4ED0-A444-82D367DE64E5</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Doti</surname> 
                        <given-names>Brenda L.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:50E5ACF3-803D-4CFD-9687-1594E876975D</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Brandt</surname> 
                        <given-names>Angelika</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:0FDF2B93-7FEB-42BE-B19F-C1F11F698F09</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>Zoological Institute and Museum, University of Hamburg, Martin-Luther-King-Platz 3, 20146 Hamburg, Germany</label></aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>Departamento de Biodiversidad y Biología Experimental, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Ciudad Universitaria, C1428EHA, Buenos Aires, Argentina</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Brenda L. Doti (<email xlink:type="simple">bdoti@bg.fcen.uba.ar</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Saskia Brix</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>23</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>82</issue>
            <fpage>45</fpage>
            <lpage>57</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>16</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Madhumita Choudhury, Brenda L. Doti, Angelika Brandt</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:877640DF-AC07-448C-83B1-DEFFA073A977</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new species of <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name>, is described from the Ross Sea, Antarctica. It is most similar to <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia ramosae</tp:taxon-name> Castelló, 2004, but can easily be distinguished from this species bythe males yielding a pair of granulate humps on the dorsum of the pereonites 1–6 and a single granulate hump on the pereonite 7 and the free pleonite. <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold> is sexually dimorphic. The dorsal sculpture of the female bodies yield a single granulate hump on all the pereonites and free pleonite. The species of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name> are restricted to the Southern Ocean, and <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold> is the fourth species included in it.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Isopoda</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Coulmannia</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>Ross Sea</kwd>
                <kwd>Southern Ocean</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Paramunnidae Vanhöffen, 1914 is a large family of asellote isopods; at present it includes 42 genera, many of them recently erected (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Just and Wilson 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Doti et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Just 2009a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Shimomura 2009</xref>). This family has a worldwide <!--PageBreak-->distribution, but with an overwhelming preponderance of species in temperate to cold water of the Southern Hemisphere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Wilson 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Just and Wilson 2004</xref>). In agreement with this observation, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Choudhury and Brandt (2007)</xref> found Paramunnidae to be one of the most abundant and frequent families among the Isopoda collected in the Ross Sea with RV <italic>Italica</italic> in 2004. A preliminary study of this collection showed that many of the species found in this survey were new to science (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Choudhury and Brandt 2009</xref>). Based on this material, a new paramunnid of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name> is described.</p>
            <p>To date species in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name> have been exclusively reported from the Southern Ocean. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hodgson (1910)</xref> erected the genus <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name> to include two new species from the Ross Sea, viz.: <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia australis</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910 from Coulman Island and <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia frigida</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910 from McMurdo Sound. More recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Castelló (2004a)</xref> described the third species of the genus, <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia ramosae</tp:taxon-name> Castelló, 2004 from the South Shetland Islands. In the present paper <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is described from the Ross Sea. The morphological differences of the four species belonging to this genus are discussed and presented in a table, an identification key is offered.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. were collected during the 19th Antarctic expedition to the Ross Sea on board the RV <italic>Italica</italic>, in February 2004. Samples were taken along a latitudinal transect between Cape Adare and Terra Nova Bay with a modified Rauschert dredge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Lörz et al. 1999</xref>). The material was sieved using a 500 µm mesh and fixed in pre-cooled 96% ethanol for later DNA analysis.</p>
            <p>For the taxonomic description some specimens were stained with Chlorazole Black E®, and their appendages were dissected and temporarily mounted in glycerine. Pencil drawings of the whole animal and dissected appendages were prepared using a Carl Zeiss (Axioskop 2) compound microscope equipped with a camera lucida. Digital illustrations were made with a Wacom tablet and the Adobe Illustrator program following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Coleman (2003)</xref>.</p>
            <p>The length of the head, pereonites, free pleonite, and pleotelson were all estimated along the mid-dorsal line. The width of the head was measured between the tips of the eyestalks. Body length as well as lengths of the articles of the appendages were measured according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hessler (1970)</xref>.</p>
            <p>The material examined of <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is lodged at the Zoological Museum of Hamburg (ZMH). For comparison purposes, the type material of <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia ramosae</tp:taxon-name> Castelló, 2004 (holotype male MZB 2003-1229A and paratype male MZB 2003-1229B) deposited in the Museum of Zoology, Barcelona (MZB) was also examined.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <p><bold>Family Paramunnidae Vanhöffen, 1914</bold></p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hodgson, 1910</tp:taxon-authority> 
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Composition"><title>Composition.</title>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia australis</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910; <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia frigida</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910; <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia ramosae</tp:taxon-name> Castelló, 2004 and <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to species of Coulmannia"><title>Key to species of Coulmannia</title>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral margins of all pereonites produced into 2 processes</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia australis</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral margins of at least one pereonite produced into a single process</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral margins of pereonite 1 produced into a single process, remaining pereonites produced into 2 processes</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia frigida</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral margin of pereonites 2–4 produced into a single process, remaining pereonites rounded</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male: pereonites 1–6 with a pair of granulate humps mid-dorsally, pereonite 7 and free pleonite with a single granulate hump. Female: all pereonites and free pleonite with a single granulate hump</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male: pereonites 1 and 2 with a pair of granulate humps mid-dorsally, remaining pereonites and free pleonite with a single granulate hump. Female: unknown</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia ramosae</tp:taxon-name> Castello, 2004</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">rossensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4F4A530A-2215-4B75-8CCB-6CF828F56EE9</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Ross Sea, RV <italic>Italica</italic>.</p>
                    <p><italic>Holotype:</italic> Adult male 1.7 mm (ZMH 42000-718); station H out 2, 72°17.5'S, 170°29.4'E, 353 m depth, 11 Feb 2004.</p>
                    <p><italic>Paratypes, same locality as holotype:</italic> 5 males (1.3–1.4 mm), 4 brooding females (1.6–1.7 mm), 2 females (1.2, 1.3 mm) and 2 juveniles (0.9, 1 mm); (ZMH 42000-719).</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Holotype male (ZMH–42000-718), <bold>a</bold> dorsal view <bold>b</bold> lateral view, <bold>c</bold> head in ventral view. Paratype female (ZMH–42000-719-a) <bold>d</bold> dorsal view. Paratype female (ZMH–42000-719-b) <bold>e</bold> lateral view. <italic>Scale bars</italic> 1 mm (a), 0.2 mm (c), 0.5 mm (d, e); a and b share the same scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-081-045-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <p><italic>Additional material:</italic> Station H in 3, 72°17.0'S, 170°13.1'E, 316 m depth, 16 Feb 2004: 5 males, 2 brooding females, 1 female and 2 juveniles. Station H in 4, 72°17.1'S, 170°14.0'E, 196 m depth, 16 Feb 2004: 7 males, 3 females and 2 juveniles. Station H in 2, 72°16.9'S, 170°12.2'E, 391 m depth, 10 Feb 2004: 4 males and 1 female. Station SMN, 74°43.2'S, 164°13.1'E, 366 m depth, 20 Feb 2004: 2 males and 2 juveniles. Station H out 1, 72°15.7'S, 170°24.8'E, 458 m depth, 9 Feb 2004: 2 males, 1 female <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->and 2 juveniles. Station H out 4, 72°18.5'S, 170°26.8'E, 235 m depth, 12 Feb 2004: 4 males and 2 females. Station A 4, 71°18.4'S, 170°28.9'E, 230 m depth, 14 Feb 2004: 1 female. Station C 1, 73°24.5'S, 170°23.2'E, 474 m depth, 18 Feb 2004: 1 brooding female. Station C 2, 73°22.7'S, 170°06.9'E, 410 m depth, 18 Feb 2004: 2 males, 3 brooding females, 6 females and 3 juveniles.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Males with dorsal sculpture formed by a pair of granulate humps on pereonites 1–6, and a single granulate hump on pereonite 7 and free pleonite. Females with single granulate hump on all pereonites and free pleonite; hump on pereonite 1 widest and shallowest, following humps gradually becoming narrower and higher towards distal end. Lateral margins of pereonites 1 and 5–7 rounded, those of pereonites 2–4 produced into single process. Coxae rounded, visible dorsally on pereonites 5–7 only.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description of adult male"><title>Description of adult male</title>
                    <p>(body description based on the holotype male, description of appendages based on a paratype male).Body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a, b</xref>) total length 1.7 mm; width 0.6 length, widest at pereonite 3. Cephalon width 1.9 length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>), anterior margin broadly rounded. Eyestalks prominent, width 0.6 length, with 5 ommatidia. Pereonites 1–6 with two granulate humps mid-dorsally, pereonite 7 and free pleonite with a single granulate hump each. Lateral margins of pereonites 1 and 5–7 rounded, those of pereonites 2–4 produced into a single process. Coxae rounded, visible in dorsal view on pereonites 5–7 only. Pleotelson and free pleonite together 1.7 as long as last 3 pereonites combined. Pleotelson oval, lateral margins smooth and convex, apex pointed. Uropods inserted at about 2/3 of pleotelson length in posterolateral indentations.</p>
                    <p>Antennula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>), articles 1–3 longer than wide; first article not extending beyond apex of eyestalk, with 1 penicillate and 4 simple setae; second article largest, with 4 penicillate and 5 simple setae; article 3 shorter than article 2, with 1 simple seta; article 4 shortest, with 1 penicillate seta, article 5 slightly longer than article 6, without setation; article 6 with 5 simple setae, 1 penicillate seta and 1 aesthetasc.</p>
                    <p>Antenna (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>), article 1 broken off during dissection, without setation (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>); article 2 with 1 simple seta; article 3 shorter than article 5, with 5 simple setae; article 4 shortest, with 2 simple setae; article 5 with 3 simple setae; article 6 longest, with 5 penicillate and 5 simple setae; flagellum with 7 articles, each article with numerous simple setae.</p>
                    <p>Left mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>) stout, without palp; incisor process with 5 blunt cusps; spine row with 1 serrate and 2 simple setae; lacina mobilis 4-cusped; molar process cylindrical, transversely truncated, with lower margin of apex toothed. Right mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2d</xref>) as left one, except for: spine row with 3 serrate and 1 simple setae; lacinia mobilis absent.</p>
                    <p>Maxillula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>), lateral lobe with 10 stout cuspidate setae distally and 1 simple seta near distal margin; medial lobe with 2 simple and 2 setulate setae distally.</p>
                    <p>Maxilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>), lateral and medial lobes with 2 simple and 2 pectinate setae, distomedial margin with single acute projection finely setose; inner lobe with 5 simple, 2 pectinate and 2 setulate setae on distomedial margin, 4 simple slender setae on medial margin<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                    <p>Maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2g</xref>), endite reaching half-length of palp article 3, with 2 coupling hooks, distal margin with 4 setulate setae (see detail), ventral surface with 1 setulate and 2 fan setae, dorsal with 3 setulate setae; epipod ovate, width 0.5 length, reaching dorsal margin of palp article 2. Palp, article 1 with 1 tooth on lateral margin, relative lengths of articles 1.0:1.4:1.4:1.7:1.0.</p>
                    <p>Pereopod I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>) stoutest. Basis longest article, with 4 simple setae. Ischium with 4 simple setae. Merus with 1 robust and 1 simple setae distodorsally, ventral margin with 4 simple setae. Carpus triangular, length 0.88 ischium length, ventral margin with 2 robust and 4 simple setae and 2 cuticular combs, distodorsal margin with 1 simple seta. Propodus oval, ventral and dorsal margins with 4 simple setae each, anterior surface with 1 simple seta and cuticular combs. Dactylus with 4 simple setae near distal margin and 2 simple setae between unguis and ventral claw, unguis slightly longer than dactylus, ventral claw shorter than unguis, approximately 0.5 unguis length.</p>
                    <p>Pereopods II–VII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3b–f</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4a</xref>) subequal in shape and length. Meri distodorsally with 1 robust seta on pereopods II–IV and 2 robust setae on pereopods V–VII; distoventrally with 1 robust seta on pereopods III–VI and 2 robust setae on pereopod VII. Carpi and propodi with 1 distodorsal penicillate seta each; ventral margin with 4 robust setae and 3 robust setae, respectively. Ungues 1.6–1.9 dactyli length, ventral claws 0.35 ungues length.</p>
                    <p>Pleopod I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b, c</xref>), lateral lobes at level of 2/3 of its length, each lobe with 8 simple setae; ventral surface with 8 simple setae; distal margin with 8 simple setae.</p>
                    <p>Pleopod II (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>), sympod lateral margin rounded and setose; endopod stylet-like, curved to the apex of the sympod, relative lengths endopod: sympod, 1.0:1.3; exopod distally concave, without setae.</p>
                    <p>Pleopod III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4e</xref>), endopod width 0.6 length, with 3 plumose setae distally; exopod with 2 articles, distal one with 1 simple seta apically, extending beyond tips of endopod setae.</p>
                    <p>Pleopod IV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4f</xref>), endopod width 0.54 length, exopod reaching half length of endopod.</p>
                    <p>Pleopod V (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4g</xref>) width 0.5 length.</p>
                    <p>Uropod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4h</xref>) biramous; exopod 0.4 endopod length, distally with 2 simple setae (broken in the specimen drawn); endopod with 5 penicillate and 3 simple setae.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Paratype male (ZMH–42000-719-c), <bold>a</bold> antennula <bold>b</bold> antenna <bold>c</bold> left mandible with detail of the incisor and molar processes <bold>d</bold> right mandible <bold>e</bold> maxillula <bold>f</bold> maxilla <bold>g</bold> maxilliped with detail of endite distal end (fan setae were omitted in the detail). <italic>Scale bars</italic> 0.1 mm (a–d, g), 0.05 mm (e, f); c and d share the same scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-081-045-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description of adult female"><title>Description of adult female</title>
                    <p>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1d, e</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4i</xref>). As male in body shape, except for: dorsal sculpture with a single granulate hump on all pereonites and free pleonite; hump on pereonite 1 widest and shallowest, following humps gradually becoming narrower and higher towards distal end. Operculum width 0.74 length, margins finely setose, ventral surface with 6 simple setae. Remaining appendages as those of the male.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 3.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Paratype male (ZMH–42000-719-c), <bold>a</bold> pereopod I <bold>b</bold> pereopod II <bold>c</bold> pereopod III <bold>d</bold> pereopod IV <bold>e</bold> pereopod V <bold>f</bold> pereopod VI. <italic>Scale bars</italic> 0.1 mm; b–f share the same scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-081-045-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 4.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Paratype male (ZMH–42000-719-c), <bold>a</bold> pereopod VII <bold>b</bold> pleotelson in ventral view <bold>c</bold> pleopod I <bold>d</bold> pleopod II <bold>e</bold> pleopod III <bold>f</bold> pleopod IV <bold>g</bold> pleopod V <bold>h</bold> uropod. Paratype female (ZMH–42000-719-a) <bold>i</bold> operculum. <italic>Scale bars</italic> 0.1 mm (a, c–g, i), 0.2 mm (b), 0.05 mm (h).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-081-045-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Only known from type locality (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The species name refers to the type locality, the Ross Sea.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>Because of the dorsal ornamentation and the lateral margins of the pereonites <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is most similar to <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia ramosae</tp:taxon-name> Castelló, 2004. The main differences between these two species are (characters found in <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia ramosae</tp:taxon-name> <!--PageBreak-->in parentheses): two granulate humps on pereonites 1–6, single granulate hump on pereonite 7 and free pleonite (two granulate humps on pereonites 1 and 2, single granulate humps on remaining segments); pleotelson width 0.76 length (width 0.51<!--PageBreak--> length, apex of pleotelson more produced); basis of pereopods with simple setae only (with simple and robust setae); propodi of pereopods II–IV with 3 robust setae (with 4 robust setae).</p>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 5.</label>
                        <caption><p>Geographic distribution of the <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name> species. <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (cross); <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia ramosae</tp:taxon-name> Castelló, 2004 (triangle); <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia australis</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910 (square); <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia frigida</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910 (circle). Full square and full circle stand for the type locality of the latter two species.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-081-045-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Table 1.</label> 
                        <caption><p>Character comparison of the species included in <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910. <italic>Abbreviations</italic>: <bold>Prns.</bold> = pereonites; <bold>PI</bold>= first pereopod; <bold>RS</bold> = robust setae. <bold>*</bold> This range includes the data from the specimens described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hodgson (1910)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Nordenstam (1933)</xref>.</p></caption>
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lateral margins of pereonites</italic></th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="2"><italic>Dorsal sculpture of pereonites and free pleonite</italic></th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Coxae in dorsal view</italic></th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>PI, carpus ventral margin with</italic></th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Body length (mm)</italic></th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia australis</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prns. 1–7 produced into two processes</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="2">One smooth conical hump on each segment (without sexual dimorphism; José Castelló, pers. comm.)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not visible</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–5 RS*</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5–9*</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia frigida</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prn. 1 produced into a single process, prns. 2–7 produced into two processes</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="2">One smooth conical hump on each segment(sexual dimorphism unknown)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not visible</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unknown</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia ramosae</tp:taxon-name> Castelló, 2004</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prns. 1 and 5–7 rounded, prns. 2–4 produced into a single process</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="2">Two granulate humps on prns. 1–2, single granulate hump on remaining segments(sexual dimorphism unknown)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Visible on prns. 5–7 only</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 RS</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prns. 1 and 5–7 rounded, prns. 2–4 produced into a single process</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">♂♂: two granulate humps on prns. 1–6, single granulate hump on remaining segments</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">♀♀: single granulate hump on all segments, hump on prn. 1 widest and shallowest </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Visible on prns. 5–7 only</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 RS</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9–1.7</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>At present, the genus <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910 contains four species, each one with a particular arrangement in the dorsal sculpture of the body and in the lateral margins of the pereonites (see Table 1). It is worth noticing that other genera of Paramunnidae, such as <tp:taxon-name>Heterosignum</tp:taxon-name> Gamô, 1976; <tp:taxon-name>Meridiosignum</tp:taxon-name> Just and Wilson, 2007; <tp:taxon-name>Holodentata</tp:taxon-name> Doti, Choudhury and Brandt, 2009; and <tp:taxon-name>Pentaceration</tp:taxon-name> Just, 2009 also include species with different dorsal sculptures and/or lateral margins arrays. The pereonites of <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. and <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia ramosae</tp:taxon-name> Castelló, 2004 show lateral margins similar to those present in the species of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Heterosignum</tp:taxon-name>. This genus, however, differs from <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name> in having long and slender eyestalks, antenna with an elongate third article, and pleotelson with denticulate margins, anteriorly narrow and cylindrical.<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. has a remarkable sexual dimorphism in the arrangement of the dorsal sculpture. Contrary, no sexual dimorphism was found in <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia australis</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910 (José Castelló, pers. comm.). Regarding <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia frigida</tp:taxon-name> Hodgson, 1910, both the original description and that presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Vanhöffen (1914)</xref> were based on a single specimen, and none of these authors mentioned the sex of the specimens examined. Thus, sexual dimorphism in <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia frigida</tp:taxon-name> remains unknown. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Castelló (2004a)</xref> had only two males when he described <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia ramose</tp:taxon-name>; therefore, the sexual dimorphism in this species is also unknown.</p>
            <p>The four species belonging to <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name> were found exclusively in the Southern Ocean, <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia australis</tp:taxon-name> being the most widely distributed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). This species was originally described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hodgson (1910)</xref> from a single specimen collected on Coulman Island, Ross Sea at 183–400 m depth. Afterward, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Nordenstam (1933)</xref> reported <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia australis</tp:taxon-name> from the Antarctic Peninsula at 360–400 m depth, and the South Georgia Island at 252–310 m depth, and more recently <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Castelló (2004b)</xref> recorded it from the South Shetland Islands at 89–220 m depth. Limited distributions have been reported for many asellote species (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hessler 1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Just and Wilson 2004</xref>). Besides lacking free-living larvae, paramunnid species display a reduced mobility; hence, <!--PageBreak-->limited distributions are expected. <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia australis</tp:taxon-name>, however, seems to have a circumpolar distribution. There are some minor differences between the specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia australis</tp:taxon-name> described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hodgson (1910)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Nordenstam (1933)</xref>, mainly in the body length and in the number of robust setae on the ventral margin of carpus of first pereopod. The variation in the number of setae most probably is related to the body length: the specimen described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hodgson (1910)</xref> is 5 mm long and has 2 or 3 robust setae on the carpus of pereopod I, whereas the specimen described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Nordenstam (1933)</xref> is 9 mm long and has 5 robust setae. A carefully examination of the type specimen of <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia australis</tp:taxon-name> and those reported from other areas is required to corroborate this wide distribution.</p>
            <p>Records from the remaining three species of <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia</tp:taxon-name> are scarce: <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia frigida</tp:taxon-name> was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hodgson (1910)</xref> from McMurdo Sound at 229 m depth, and later on reported from the Gauss Station, Wilkes Land at 385 m depth by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Vanhöffen (1914)</xref>; <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia ramosae</tp:taxon-name> was found only in the South Shetland Island at 89–220 m depth by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Castelló (2004a)</xref>; and <tp:taxon-name>Coulmannia rossensis</tp:taxon-name> is herein reported from the Ross Sea at 196–474 m depth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>The authors are grateful to the crew of the RV <italic>Italica</italic> for their help on board. We also would like to thank Dr Peter Rehm for providing and pre-sorting the material of the <italic>Italica</italic> expedition and Dr Francesc Uribe (Museu Ciències Naturals de Barcelona) for loan of the type material of <italic>Coulmannia ramosae</italic>. We also thank to Dr Jean Just, Dr José Castelló, Dr George (Buz) Wilson and two anonymous reviewers, whose comments helped to improve the manuscript. The second author is grateful to the DAAD–MECyT for being granted. This study was partially supported by the German Science Foundation (DFG Br 1121/20), the Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas (CONICET), and the Universidad de Buenos Aires (UBACyT X-190).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Castelló</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004a</year>)<article-title> Two new species of Paramunnidae (Crustacea, Isopoda, Asellota) from the South Shetland Islands.</article-title> <source>Antarctic Science</source> <volume>16</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>239</fpage>-<lpage>252</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Castelló</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004b</year>)<article-title> Isopods (Crustacea, Isopoda) from the Spanish “Bentart-94/95” expeditions to the South Shetland Islands (sub-Antarctic).</article-title> <source>Polar Biology</source> <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Composition and distribution of benthic isopod (Crustacea, Malacostraca) families off the Victoria-Land Coast (Ross Sea, Antarctica).</article-title> <source>Polar Biology</source> <volume>30</volume> (<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1431</fpage>-<lpage>1437</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Benthic isopods (Crustacea, Malacostraca) from the Ross Sea, Antarctica: species checklist and their zoogeography in the Southern Ocean.</article-title> <source>Polar Biology</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>599</fpage>-<lpage>610</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Digital inking: How to make perfect line drawings on computers.</article-title> <source>Organism, Diversity and Evolution</source> <volume>3</volume> (<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Doti</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> <italic>Holodentata</italic> gen. nov. (Isopoda: Asellota: Paramunnidae) with a description of two new species: <italic>H. caeca</italic> and <italic>H. triangulata</italic> from the Southern Ocean.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2096</volume>:<fpage>395</fpage>-<lpage>412</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hessler</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> The Desmosomatidae of the Gay Head-Bermuda Transect.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography</source> <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>185</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1910</year>)<article-title> Crustacea. IX. Isopoda. National Antarctic Expedition 1901–1904.</article-title> <source>Natural History, Zoology and Botany,</source> <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Just</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009a</year>)<article-title> <italic>Pentaceration</italic>, an unusual new genus of Paramunnidae from Australia (Isopoda, Asellota).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2134</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Just</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009b</year>)<article-title> <italic>Compoceration garyi</italic>, a new genus and species of Paramunnidae (Crustacea, Isopoda, Asellota), from south-eastern Australia.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of Museum Victoria</source> <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Just</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GDF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Revision of the <italic>Paramunna</italic> complex (Isopoda: Asellota: Paramunnidae).</article-title> <source>Invertebrate Systematics</source> <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>377</fpage>-<lpage>466</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Just</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GDF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Revision of Southern Hemisphere <italic>Austronanus</italic> Hodgson, 1910, with two new genera and five new species of Paramunnidae (Crustacea: Isopoda: Asellota).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1111</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Just</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GDF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Revision of <italic>Austrosignum</italic> Hodgson and <italic>Munnogonium</italic> George &amp; Strömberg (Paramunnidae) with descriptions of eight new genera and two new species (Crustacea: Isopoda: Asellota).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1515</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lörz</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>di Renzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nickel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Comparative analysis of three sampling gear types for marine macrobenthos.</article-title> <source>Berichte zur Polarforschung</source> <volume>330</volume>:<fpage>134</fpage>-<lpage>151</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordenstam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1933</year>)<article-title> Marine Isopoda of the families Serolidae, Idotheidae, Pseudidotheidae, Arcturidae, Parasellidae and Stenetriidae mainly from South Atlantic.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Further Zoological Results of the Swedish Antarctic Expedition 1901–1903.</source> <publisher-name>Norstedt &amp; Söner</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc>, <lpage>284</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimomura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Ten new species of paramunnid isopods (Peracarida: Asellota: Paramunnidae) from Kyushu, Southern Japan.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the National Museum of Nature and Science, Ser A, Suppl.</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanhöffen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1914</year>)<article-title> Die Isopoden der Deutschen Südpolar-Expedition 1901–1903.</article-title> <source>Deutsche Südpolar-Expedition 1901–1903, Zoologie</source> <volume>7</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>447</fpage>-<lpage>598</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> New insights into the colonization of the deep sea: Systematics and zoogeography of the Munnidae and the Pleurogoniidae <italic>comb. nov.</italic> (Isopoda; Janiroidea).</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>-<lpage>236</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>    
</article>