<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.133.1613</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Revision of the <italic>Paridris nephta</italic>species group (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea, Platygastridae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Talamas</surname>
                        <given-names>Elijah J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:19124B60-4D11-46AF-ADBF-E48A9988B102</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Masner</surname>
                        <given-names>Lubomír</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:F1505310-F606-4F6C-A1DF-74B9A0055B2E</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Johnson</surname>
                        <given-names>Norman F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:3508C4FF-F027-445F-8417-90AB4AB8F30D</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Entomology, The Ohio State University, 1315 Kinnear Road, Columbus, Ohio 43212, U.S.A.
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label> Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada, K.W. Neatby Building, Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0C6, Canada
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Department of Evolution, Ecology and Organismal Biology, The Ohio State University, 1315 Kinnear Road, Columbus, Ohio 43212, U.S.A.
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Elijah J. Talamas (<email xlink:type="simple">talamas.1@osu.edu</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Michael Sharkey</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>5</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>133</issue>
            <fpage>49</fpage>
            <lpage>94</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>26</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>1</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Elijah J. Talamas, Lubomír Masner, Norman F. Johnson</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:BCD3BD6E-5E29-447F-AEB6-176C19EEF3E8</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> group is revised (<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Platygastridae</tp:taxon-name>). Fifteen species are described, 14 of which are new: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris atrox</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Yunnan Province, China), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris bunun</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Taiwan), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris ferus</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Thailand), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris kagemono</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Japan), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris minator</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Laos, Thailand), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris mystax</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Laos, Thailand), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic>(Kozlov) (Japan, North Korea, South Korea, Far Eastern Russia), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nilaka</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Thailand), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris reptilis</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Taiwan), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris rugulosus</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Laos, Vietnam), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris solaris</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Laos, Thailand, Vietnam), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris teres</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Vietnam), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris toketoki</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Taiwan), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris verrucosus</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Guangdong Province, China), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris yak</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, <bold>sp. n.</bold>(Thailand).</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Egg-parasitoid</kwd>
                <kwd>Platygastroidea</kwd>
                <kwd>key</kwd>
                <kwd>species description</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomic revision</kwd>
                <!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>In 1978, M. Kozlov described a new genus of scelionine wasps based on material from the Russian Far East, with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tuora nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kozlov as its sole species. No major taxonomic changes occurred in this group until <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Kononova and Kozlov (2008)</xref> treated<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tuora</tp:taxon-name></italic> as a junior synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic>Kieffer, a huge cosmopolitan group. Examination of material from East and Southeast Asia has brought to light many new species that are morphologically close to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, constituting a rather homogenous group that may be readily separated from the remainder of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <p>The goals of this paper are to define the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> group and describe its species. This work is conducted as part of the <tp:taxon-name>Platygastroidea</tp:taxon-name> Planetary Biodiversity Inventory and represents a step toward revision of <tp:taxon-name>Scelionini</tp:taxon-name> sensu lato and resolution of the relationships between its constituent genera. The contributions of the authors are as follows: E.J. Talamas: character definition, species group concept development, species concept development, imaging, key development, manuscript preparation; N.F. Johnson: species concept development, key development, manuscript preparation; L. Masner: species group concept development, manuscript preparation.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods"><title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p><bold>Specimens:</bold> This work is based upon specimens deposited in the following collections, with abbreviations used in the text: CNCI, Canadian National Collection of Insects, Ottawa, Canada<sup>1</sup>; IEBR, Institute of Ecology and Biolgical Resources, Hanoi, Vietnam<sup>2</sup>; IZCAS, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Institute of Zoology, Beijing, China<sup>3</sup>; OSUC, C.A. Triplehorn Insect Collection, Columbus, OH<sup>4</sup>; QSBG, Queen Sirikit Botanic Garden, Chiang Mai, Thailand<sup>5</sup>; ROME, Royal Ontario Museum, Ontario, Canada<sup>6</sup>; RMNH, Leiden Nationaal Natuurhistorische Museum, Netherlands<sup>7</sup>.</p>
            <p><bold>Morphology:</bold> Abbreviations and morphological terms used in text: A1, A2, ... A12: antennomere 1, 2, ... 12; claval formula: distribution of the multiporous basiconic sensilla on the underside of apical antennomeres of the female, with the antennomere interval specified followed by the number of sensilla per segment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bin 1981</xref>); palpal formula: number of maxillary and labial palpal segments, respectively; S1, S2, ... S6: metasomal mediosternite 1, 2, ... 6; T1, T2, ... T7: metasomal mediotergite 1, 2, ... 7.; posterior vertex: area between the posterior ocelli and the occipital carina. Morphological terminology largely follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Mikó et al. 2007</xref>; the following are illustrated and labeled to facilitate their use.</p>
            <p>Axillular carina (axc: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 15–16</xref>)</p>
            <p>Epomial carina (epc; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>)</p>
            <p>Lateral ocellus (loc; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 10–11</xref>)</p>
            <p>Metapleural sulcus (mtps; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 36</xref>)</p>
            <p>Paracoxal sulcus (pcxs; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 36</xref>)<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <p>Transverse carina of T2 (trc; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 12</xref>)</p>
            <p>Transverse pronotal carina (tpc; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>)</p>
            <p>Morphological terms used in this revision were matched to the <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name> Anatomy Ontology (HAO, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Yoder et al. 2010</xref>) (Appendix I). Identifiers (URIs) in the format http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_XXXXXXX represent anatomical concepts in HAO version http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/hao/2011-05-18/hao.owl. They are provided to enable readers to confirm their understanding of the anatomical structures being referenced. To find out more about a given structure, including, images, references, and other metadata, use the identifier as a web-link, or use the HAO:XXXXXXX (note colon replaces underscore) as a search term at http://glossary.hymao.org. Notable changes in term usage from a previous taxonomic work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Talamas et al. 2011</xref>) are given in Appendix I.</p>
            <p>The description of surface sculpture is presented in two formats. Areas of the exoskeleton in which the sculptural elements are inseparable are described simply as “sculpture”. For areas in which the sculptural elements vary independently, sculpture is divided into three categories: punctation: round depressions associated with setae; macrosculpture: raised or sunken patterns of texture that are oriented linearly or radially with respect to punctation or the axes of the body; microsculpture: unoriented, very fine wrinkles or pustulations that occur on, in, or between elements of macrosculpture and punctation.</p>
            <p><bold>Information Management:</bold> The locality data reported for primary types are not literal transcriptions of the labels: some abbreviations are expanded; additional data from the collectors are also included. The holotypes should be unambiguously identifiable by means of the unique identifier or the red holotype label. The numbers prefixed with “OSUC ” and “CASENT ” are unique identifiers for the individual specimens (note the blank space after the acronyms). Details on the data associated with these specimens may be accessed at the following link, purl.oclc.org/NET/hymenoptera/hol, and entering the identifier in the form. This monograph also features simultaneous publication and distribution of taxonomic and occurrence records through the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) using DarwinCore Archives as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Talamas et al. (2011)</xref>. All new species have been prospectively registered with Zoobank (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Polaszek et al. 2005</xref>) and other taxonomic names have been retrospectively registered therein. All names are also registered in the <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name> Name Server (hns.osu.edu). Life sciences identifiers, lsids, may be resolved at the URLs specified in the footnotes or at lsid.tdwg.org.</p>
            <p><bold>Cybertools:</bold>The species descriptions are generated by a database application, vSysLab (purl.oclc.org/NET/hymenoptera/vSysLab), designed to facilitate the generation of taxon by character data matrices, to integrate these with the existing taxonomic and specimen-level database, and to export the data both as text and as input files for other applications. The output is in the format of “Character: Character state(s).”</p>
            <p><bold>Imaging:</bold> Images were produced using Combine ZP and AutoMontage extended-focus software. The individual images are archived at the image database at The Ohio <!--PageBreak-->State University (purl.oclc.org/NET/hymenoptera/specimage) and with MorphBank (www.morphbank.net). The latter also contains collections of images organized by plate.</p>
            <p><bold>Species Concept:</bold> For the purpose of this revision, species are defined as taxa diagnosable by putative autapomorphies or a unique combination of fixed character states.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Comments on ParidrisKieffer"><title>Comments on <tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name>Kieffer</title>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Idris</tp:taxon-name></italic> was described by Arnold Förster in 1856, and the name has been used as the root for a number of generic names in <tp:taxon-name>Platygastroidea</tp:taxon-name>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Wheeler (1935)</xref> proposed that it would be a useful root for names within the <tp:taxon-name>Formicidae</tp:taxon-name>, relieving the stress on roots such as –<italic>myrmex</italic> and –<italic>myrma</italic>. According to Wheeler, the name is a substantive noun, derived from classical Greek, meaning “the knowing or provident one.” As such, it may be either masculine or feminine in grammatical gender. While workers in <tp:taxon-name>Platygastroidea</tp:taxon-name> have treated the name and its derivatives as masculine, myrmecologists have used names with this root as feminine nouns. Here, we continue our tradition and use <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic> as a masculine noun.</p>
            <p>The Nearctic <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris brevipennis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fouts has one documented host association with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Gryllus pennsylvanicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burmeister (label data of a specimen in the USNM reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Masner and Muesebeck 1968</xref>). Based on this information, we speculate that the species of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> group are also parasitoids of gryllid eggs.</p>
            <p>With the exception of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Masner (1976)</xref>, previous workers treated <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic> within only a restricted geographical context (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Mani and Sharma 1982</xref>, Galloway and Austin 1984, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Kozlov and Kononova 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Kozlov and Kononova 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Kononova and Petrov 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Lê 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Mineo 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Rajmohana 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Kononova and Kozlov 2008</xref>). Perhaps unsurprisingly, the characters they used for identification of the genus are insufficient when the world fauna is considered: the length of R1 (postmarginal vein) is variable; the shape of the metascutellum is highly variable, and in females may be entirely obscured by the horn of T1; the lateral ocellus is often close to the inner orbit of the compound eye; and the horn of T1 is missing in some members of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> species group.</p>
            <p>Previous authors have mentioned that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic> may be confused with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Galloway and Austin 1984) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anteris</tp:taxon-name></italic> Förster (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Masner 1976</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Masner (1976)</xref> indicated that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anteris</tp:taxon-name></italic> and Neotropical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic> are close to each other, and indeed they are highly similar in most of the external characters typically used for identification. Based on a yet unpublished phylogeny, we consider many of the similarities between these two genera to be convergent and not indicative of close relationship.</p>
            <p>Separation of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic> from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a more complicated matter because both are polytypic. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has neither notauli (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9–10</xref>) nor an externally developed metascutellum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9–10</xref>), and always has spines, points, or dense tufts of setae on the propodeum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9–10</xref>). The epomial carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>) is present in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (always absent in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic>), with the exception of one widespread species group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>) that also has setose eyes and a strongly reduced postmarginal vein. The<!--PageBreak--> transverse carina of T2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 12</xref>) unambiguously identifies <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic> but is not present in all species (e.g. the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta species</tp:taxon-name></italic> group). In some Neotropical and Oceanic species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the lateral propodeal carinae form two points lateral to the metasomal depression, similar to the propodeal points in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kieffer. The following key separates <italic><tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anteris</tp:taxon-name></italic> from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic> with the fewest characters possible.</p>
            <sec sec-type="Key to separate Paridris, Probaryconus and Anteris"><title>Key to separate <tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Anteris</tp:taxon-name></title>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palpal formula 2-1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>); female T7+8, when extruded with ovipositor, connected to T6 by short, unsegmented conjunctiva (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anteris</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palpal formula 4-2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>); female T7+8, when extruded with ovipositor, connected to T6 by long, segmented conjunctiva (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metanotum visible medially and unaltered by horn of T1, or horn absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 10, 12</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metanotum obscured medially by horn of T1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9, 11</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metascutellum visible externally, shape variable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 12</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metascutellum not visible externally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral ocellus remote from inner orbit, separated by distance of at least one ocellar diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 11</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral ocellus contiguous with inner orbit or separated by distance less than one ocellar diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Diagnosis of nephta species group"><title>Diagnosis of nephta species group</title>
                <p>The <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> species group can be separated from the remainder of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the combination of the following characters: occipital carina reaching base of mandible; mesoscutal suprahumeral sulcus absent mesal to notaulus; scutoscutellar and posterior scutellar sulci comprised of deep cells; metascutellum bispinose, glabrous; mesepisternum below femoral groove with coarse rugose sculpture; paracoxal and metapleural sulci not fused in dorsal half of metapleuron (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 32</xref>); posterior margin of metapleuron with triangular point above metapleural sulcus; propodeum coarsely punctate rugose; plica indistinguishable or poorly distinguished from background sculpture of propodeum; anterior T2 without transverse carina; T6 evenly rounded, without dense microsculpture; felt field on S2 punctate, present throughout length of sternite.</p>
                <p>Sexual dimorphism combined with the small number of males prevented us from associating males with females for all but two species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris mystax</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Consequently, only females are treated in the key and descriptions. Males for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris mystax</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> have been entered as determined material, but not as paratypes for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris mystax</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Four other male morphotypes have been imaged and can be found online at www.specimage.osu.edu and www.morphbank.net<sup>8,9,10,11</sup>.</p>
                <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 1–6.</label>
                    <caption><p><bold><sup>62</sup></bold> <bold>1</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anteris</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., head, mouthparts, ventral view, male (OSUC 241115)<bold>2</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., head, mouthparts, anteroventral view, female (OSUC 190976)<bold>3</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anteris</tp:taxon-name></italic>sp., T5–T7, ovipositor, female (OSUC 261917)<bold>4</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nilaka</tp:taxon-name></italic>, T6–T7, ovipositor, female (OSUC 266165)<bold>5</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anteris</tp:taxon-name></italic>sp., lateral habitus, female (OSUC 261917)<bold>6</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic>sp., lateral habitus, female (OSUC 191490). Scale bar in millimeters.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figures 7–12.</label>
                    <caption><p><bold><sup>63</sup></bold> <bold>7</bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus</tp:taxon-name></italic>sp., pronotum, lateral view, female (OSUC 146809)<bold>8</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus</tp:taxon-name></italic>sp., head and pronotum, female (OSUC 58741)<bold>9</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus</tp:taxon-name></italic>sp., mesosoma and T1, dorsal view, female (OSUC 404933)<bold>10</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Probaryconus rufipes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kieffer), head and mesosoma, dorsal view, female (OSUC 396820)<bold>11</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic>sp., head, mesosoma, T1, dorsal view, female (OSUC 262120)<bold>12</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris</tp:taxon-name></italic>sp., metascutellum, propodeum, T1–T2, dorsal view, female (OSUC 265183). Scale bar in millimeters.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Key to females of the Paridris nephta species group (a Lucid key is included as a Appendix II)"><title>Key to females of the <tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name> species group (a Lucid key is included as a Appendix II).</title>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brachypterous, forewing not reaching apex of metasoma in repose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 31, 33</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">67, 69</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Macropterous, forewing extending beyond apex of metasoma in repose</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3<!--PageBreak--></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A7 with basiconic sensillum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 14</xref>); sculpture of T3 reduced medially (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 33</xref>); metapleural sulcus simple dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 36</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris ferus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A7 without basiconic sensillum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 13</xref>); sculpture of T3 not reduced medially (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 72</xref>); metapleural sulcus foveolate dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 68</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris reptilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral clypeal margin edentate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 89</xref>); T3 covered in finely reticulate microsculpture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 90</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris teres</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral clypeal margin serrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 53</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">101</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">107</xref>); sculpture of T3 variable</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral metapleural area entirely setose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 50</xref>); frons densely setose ventrolaterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 53</xref>); head and metasoma black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 49</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris mystax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral metapleural area with glabrous area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 62</xref>); frons moderately to sparsely setose ventrolaterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 107</xref>); body color variable</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Notaulus absent or indicated only at posterior margin of mesoscutum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 22</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">106</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Notaulus present through posterior half of mesoscutum, usually reaching mesoscutal suprahumeral sulcus as smooth furrow or row of punctures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 58</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">76</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1–T5, S3 with microsculpture throughout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 17</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">102</xref>); T3 evenly reticulate in medial third (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 102</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris verrucosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metasoma without microsculpture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 18</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">105</xref>); T3 longitudinally strigose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 12</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">105</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frons immediately below median ocellus smooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 23</xref>); axillular carina rounded dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>); S3 with longitudinal striae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 18</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris atrox</tp:taxon-name></italic> Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frons immediately below median ocellus rugose, with setigerous foveae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 107</xref>); axillular carina pointed dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 15</xref>); S3 without longitudinal striae</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris yak</tp:taxon-name></italic>Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A7 with basiconic sensillum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 14</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A7 without basiconic sensillum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 13</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R1 (postmarginal vein) distinctly shorter than r-rs (stigmal vein) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 109</xref>); T3 smooth with weakly impressed longitudinal striae laterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 30</xref>), microsculpture absent; punctation of head fine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 29</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris bunun</tp:taxon-name></italic> Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R1 (postmarginal vein) about as long as r-rs (stigmal vein) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 111</xref>); T3 with prominent longitudinal strigae laterally, often strigose throughout, microsculpture usually present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 48</xref>); punctation of head variable, often coarse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 47</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris minator</tp:taxon-name></italic> Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesoscutellum punctate, interspaces between punctures smooth and usually broad (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs. 58</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">82</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesoscutellum rugulose to areolate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 40</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">76</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">94</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><!--PageBreak-->11</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frons evenly striate throughout, striae directly above interantennal process sometimes effaced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 59</xref>); interstitial punctation on frons very fine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 59</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kozlov)<!--PageBreak--></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frons directly below median ocellus coarsely strigose to rugose; frons always with smooth area above interantennal process; interstitial punctation on frons coarse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 83</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris solaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frons evenly striate throughout, with microsculpture present interstitially (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 41</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris kagemono</tp:taxon-name></italic> Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Striae of frons, if present, not uniform throughout, microsculpture absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 65</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">95</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum with uniform, fine, white setae along transverse pronotal carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 66</xref>); body dark brown to black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 61</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nilaka</tp:taxon-name></italic> Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum with dark, bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 77</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">94</xref>); body color variable</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum below transverse pronotal carina mostly smooth, with sparse rugulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 77</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris rugulosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum below transverse pronotal carina densely punctate (as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 66</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris toketoki</tp:taxon-name></italic> Talamas, sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>

                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">atrox</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:BCD3BD6E-5E29-447F-AEB6-176C19EEF3E8</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:275737</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_atrox</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 16</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">19–24</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>12</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    		<p>Female body length: 2.73 mm (n=1). Color of head: reddish brown. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: smooth. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally strigose laterally. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: irregularly rugulose. Sculpture of gena: irregularly rugulose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: absent.</p>
                    		<p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: equal to r-rs. Notaulus: absent. Color of mesosoma: variably orange to brown. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: areolate rugulose. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: areolate rugulose. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: present. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: rugulose posteriorly. Sculpture of femoral groove: striate below mesopleural pit. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: rugulose. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: absent. Mesopleural carina: present. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: moderately dense. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                    		<p><!--PageBreak-->Color of metasoma: reddish brown. Horn of T1: bulge smooth, at least anteriorly. Microsculpture of T2: absent. Microsculpture on T3: absent. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: weakly longitudinally strigose. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: longitudinally strigose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: weakly rugulose. Punctation of T4: moderately dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: absent.<!--PageBreak--> Punctation of T5: moderately dense throughout. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: weakly longitudinally strigose.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 13–18.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold><sup>64</sup></bold> <bold>13</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nilaka</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n., antennal clava, ventral view, female (OSUC 334247)<bold>14</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris minator</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n., antennal clava, ventral view, female holotype (OSUC 237531)<bold>15</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris yak</tp:taxon-name></italic>,sp. n, scuto-axillar complex, lateral view, female holotype (OSUC 237530)<bold>16</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris atrox</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n., scuto-axillar complex, lateral view, female holotype (OSUC 241473)<bold>17</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris verrucosus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n., S2–S3, ventrolateral view, female holotype (OSUC 334249)<bold>18</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris atrox</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n., S3, ventrolateral view, female holotype (OSUC 241473). Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 19–24.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold><sup>65</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris atrox</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype (OSUC 241473) <bold>19</bold> Lateral habitus<bold>20</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view<bold>21</bold> Dorsal habitus<bold>22</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view<bold>23</bold> Head, anterior view<bold>24</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view. Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris atrox</tp:taxon-name></italic> may be separated from the other members of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> species group by the absence of notauli and the presence of striation on S3.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris atrox</tp:taxon-name></italic> is named for the severe appearance of its head, its mandibles in particular. The specific epithet is adjectival, and means “fearsome” in Latin.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>13</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: <bold>CHINA:</bold> Yunnan Prov., Baoshan City, 28 km (air)SE Tengyue (Teng Chong), pass over Gaoligong Mts., clearing / natural forest, Luoshuidong, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">24°57'N, 98°45'E</named-content>, 2300m, 26.X–31.X.1998, flight intercept trap, C. Griswold, D. Kavanaugh &amp; C. L. Long, OSUC 241473 (deposited in IZCAS).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">bunun</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A3CA8ADB-0B8F-47C1-A757-9CEAE44779A2</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:273886</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_bunun</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figures 25–30</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>14</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p> Female body length: 3.41 mm (n=1). Color of head: dark red, becoming darker dorsally. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: smooth. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally strigose laterally. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: finely punctate. Sculpture of gena: densely and finely punctate. Basiconic sensillum on A7: present.</p>
                        <p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: less than r-rs. Notaulus: present in posterior half of mesoscutum. Color of mesosoma: variably red to black. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: densely punctate throughout. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: densely punctate. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: absent. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: finely punctate. Sculpture of femoral groove: smooth. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: present. Mesopleural carina: present along anterior half of femoral groove. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: moderately dense. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                        <p>Color of metasoma: reddish brown. Horn of T1: bulge smooth, at least anteriorly. Microsculpture of T2: absent. Microsculpture on T3: absent. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: absent. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: weakly longitudinally strigose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: weakly longitudinally strigose. Punctation of T4: sparse in medial third, moderately dense laterally. Macrosculpture of T5: absent. Punctation of T5: absent in medial third, moderately dense laterally. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: absent.</p>
                        <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 25–30.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold><sup>66</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris bunun</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype (OSUC 262237) <bold>25</bold> Lateral habitus<bold>26</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view<bold>27</bold> Propodeum, posterodorsal view<bold>28</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view<bold>29</bold> Head, anterior view<bold>30</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view. Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris bunun</tp:taxon-name></italic> is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris minator</tp:taxon-name></italic>, though the two have widely disjunct distributions, Taiwan and Southeast Asia, respectively. The two may be separated by the medially smooth T3 and short R1 (postmarginal vein) of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris bunun</tp:taxon-name></italic> and the longer setation of the body in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris minator</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris bunun</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a much larger species than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris minator</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but it is known from a single specimen and thus we are not able to assess its size variation. Some species of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> group are known to exhibit significant size variation (e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nilaka</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and thus size should be used cautiously.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The species is named for the Bunun tribe of Taiwan that historically occupied the region where it was collected. The name is treated as a noun in apposition.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>15</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: <bold>TAIWAN:</bold> Taiwan Prov., Pingtung Co., T’eng-chih (Tengchi) Medium-Altitude Experiment Station, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">23°05.75'N, 120°47.37'E</named-content> , 1660m, 3.VI–5.VI.2008, yellow pan trap, L. Masner, OSUC 262237 (deposited in CNCI).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">ferus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6B7296C1-4E71-4A35-B937-ABB1949B7DBE</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:241281</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_ferus</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 31–36</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>16</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Female body length: 2.89 mm (n=1). Color of head: black throughout. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: smooth. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally striate throughout. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: punctate rugulose. Sculpture of gena: dorsoventrally strigose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: present.</p>
                    <p>Wings: brachypterous, apex of forewing ending before T4. Notaulus: percurrent. Color of mesosoma: variably orange to brown. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: densely punctate, with longitudinal rugae in posterior half. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: smooth along midline, otherwise punctate rugulose. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: absent. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: finely punctate. Sculpture of femoral groove: striate in ventral end. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: present. Mesopleural carina: present along anterior half of femoral groove. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: dense. Color of legs: pale brown throughout.</p>
                    <p>Color of metasoma: orange to brown. Horn of T1: bulge smooth, at least anteriorly. Microsculpture of T2: absent. Microsculpture on T3: absent. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: absent. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: longitudinally strigose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: absent. Punctation of T4: moderately dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: absent. Punctation of T5: moderately dense throughout. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: longitudinally strigose.</p>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 31–36.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold><sup>67</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris ferus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype (OSUC 192426) <bold>31</bold> Lateral habitus<bold>32</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view<bold>33</bold> Dorsal habitus<bold>34</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view<bold>35</bold> Head, anterior view<bold>36</bold> Metapleuron, lateral view. Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris ferus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris reptilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are the only brachypterous species known in the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> group. Aside from this character, these two species are not particularly similar and may be separated by the presence of a basiconic sensillum on A7, the smooth form of the metapleural sulcus and longitudinal striation of S3 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris ferus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The adjectival epithet “ferus” means “wild” or “untamed” in Latin and refers to the “savage” appearance of this species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>17</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: <bold>THAILAND:</bold> Chiang Mai Prov., summit forest, T178, Doi Inthanon National Park, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">18°35.361'N, 98°29.157'E</named-content> , 2500m, 9.VIII–16.VIII.2006, malaise trap, Y. Areeluck, OSUC 192426 (deposited in QSBG).<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">kagemono</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:59410F97-5DD7-4E7E-A7C3-2F25DD7665AE</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:273916</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_kagemono</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figures 37–42</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>18</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Female body length: 2.65 mm (n=1). Color of head: dark orange, becoming brown at vertex. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: dorsoventrally striate. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally striate throughout. Microsculpture of frons: present. Sculpture of posterior vertex: punctate rugulose. Sculpture of gena: irregularly rugulose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: absent.</p>
                    <p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: less than r-rs. Notaulus: percurrent. Color of mesosoma: orange throughout. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: densely punctate throughout. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: punctate rugulose throughout. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: absent. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: punctate rugulose. Sculpture of femoral groove: striate below mesopleural pit. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: present. Mesopleural carina: absent. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: moderately dense. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                    <p>Color of metasoma: orange throughout. Horn of T1: absent. Microsculpture of T2: present. Microsculpture on T3: present. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: reticulate rugose. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: reticulate rugose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: weakly rugulose. Punctation of T4: moderately dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: absent. Punctation of T5: moderately dense throughout. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: absent.</p>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 37–42.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold><sup>68</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris kagemono</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype (OSUC 262193) <bold>37</bold> Lateral habitus<bold>38</bold> Mesosoma, lateral view<bold>39</bold> Forewing, dorsal view<bold>40</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view<bold>41</bold> Head, anterior view<bold>42</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view. Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris kagemono</tp:taxon-name></italic> is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic>. It may be separated from it, and all other members of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> species group, by the presence of microsculpture between the striae of the frons.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The epithet “kagemono” means “supernatural creature of the night” in Japanese. It is used as a noun in apposition.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>19</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: <bold>JAPAN:</bold> Fukuoka Pref., Kyushu Isl., primary evergreen forest, Mount Tachibana, 1.VII–6.VII.1979, yellow pan trap, K. Yamagishi, OSUC 262193 (deposited in CNCI).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">minator</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6A07840D-7470-4B42-89E2-7012B99C6C8F</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:241284</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_minator</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 14</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">43–48</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>20</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Female body length: 2.27–2.53 mm (n=9). Color of head: uncertain, reddish brown. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: smooth. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally strigose throughout; rugose. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: finely punctate; punctate rugulose. Sculpture of gena: punctate rugulose; densely and finely punctate. Basiconic sensillum on A7: present.</p>
                    <p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: equal to r-rs; longer than r-rs. Notaulus: percurrent. Color of mesosoma: variably red to black. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: densely punctate throughout. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: densely punctate. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: absent. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: finely punctate. Sculpture of femoral groove: smooth. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: present. Mesopleural carina: present. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: moderately dense. Color of legs: pale brown throughout; yellow throughout.</p>
                    <p>Color of metasoma: dark brown to black throughout; reddish brown. Horn of T1: bulge smooth, at least anteriorly. Microsculpture of T2: absent. Microsculpture on T3: present. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: reticulate; longitudinally strigose; weakly longitudinally strigose. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: longitudinally strigose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: weakly rugulose; absent. Punctation of T4: moderately dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: absent. Punctation of T5: moderately dense throughout. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: absent.</p>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 43–48.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold><sup>69</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris minator</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype (OSUC 237531) <bold>43</bold> Lateral habitus<bold>44</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view<bold>45</bold> Dorsal habitus<bold>46</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view<bold>47</bold> Head, anterior view<bold>48</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view. Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris minator</tp:taxon-name></italic> is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris solaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> in size, habitus and distribution and to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris bunun</tp:taxon-name></italic> in its diagnostic characters. It is best separated from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris solaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of a basiconic sensillum on A7 and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris bunun</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the coarse punctation of the head and prominent striae of lateral T3.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The Latin epithet “minator” means “threatener” and is given to this species for its fierce appearance.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>21</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p> Holotype, female: <bold>THAILAND:</bold> Chiang Mai Prov., checkpoint 2, T73, Doi Inthanon National Park, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">18°31.559'N, 98°29.941'E</named-content> , 1700m<!--PageBreak-->, 15.VII–22.VII.2006, malaise trap, Y. Areeluck, OSUC 237531 (deposited in QSBG). <italic>Paratypes</italic>: (8 females) <bold>LAOS:</bold> 1 female, OSUC 334241 (CNCI). <bold>THAILAND:</bold> 7 females, OSUC 262239, 334245, 396845 (CNCI); OSUC 334205 (OSUC); OSUC 334005, 334215, 334246 (QSBG).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">mystax</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:67E77FD7-4ECC-494F-B7B0-497E4B82AB59</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:241282</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_mystax</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figures 49–54</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">111</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>22</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p> Female body length: 2.53-3.26 mm (n=20). Color of head: black throughout. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: smooth. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally strigose throughout. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: punctate rugulose. Sculpture of gena: irregularly rugulose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: absent.</p>
                        <p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: equal to r-rs; less than r-rs. Notaulus: percurrent. Color of mesosoma: orange to dark red anteriorly, brown posteriorly, mesoscutellum black. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: densely punctate throughout. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: punctate rugulose throughout; smooth along midline, otherwise punctate rugulose. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: absent. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: finely punctate. Sculpture of femoral groove: smooth; striate in ventral end. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: present. Mesopleural carina: present along anterior half of femoral groove. Setation of ventral metapleural area: present throughout. Setation of metapleural triangle: dense. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                        <p>Color of metasoma: orange to black. Horn of T1: bulge smooth, at least anteriorly. Microsculpture of T2: absent. Microsculpture on T3: present. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: reticulate; absent. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: reticulate rugose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: rugulose. Punctation of T4: dense throughout; moderately dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: weakly rugulose laterally; absent. Punctation of T5: dense throughout; moderately dense throughout. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: absent.</p>
                        <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 49–54.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold><sup>70</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris mystax</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>49</bold> Lateral habitus, female holotype (OSUC 237667)<bold>50</bold> Mesosoma, lateral view, female holotype (OSUC 237667)<bold>51</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view, female holotype (OSUC 237667) <bold>52</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view, female (OSUC 262229)<bold>53</bold> Head, anterior view, female (OSUC 237533)<bold>54</bold> T4<bold>–</bold>T6, dorsal view, female holotype (OSUC 237667). Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris mystax</tp:taxon-name></italic> is one of the most distinctive species and can be easily identified by the dense setation throughout the ventral metapleural area and on the ventrolateral frons.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The epithet “mystax”, meaning “hair on the upper lip” in Greek, is given to this species for the conspicuous setation of the ventral frons.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>23</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p> Holotype, female: <bold>THAILAND:</bold> Loei Prov., Pong Neep Forest Unit, dry evergreen forest, T783, Phu Kradung National Park, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">16°56.589'N, 101°42.074'E</named-content> , 273m, 14.X–21.X.2006, malaise trap, S. Glong-lasae, OSUC 237667 (deposited in QSBG). <italic>Paratypes</italic>: (19 females) <bold>LAOS:</bold> 1 female, OSUC 265072 (CNCI). <bold>THAILAND:</bold> 18 females, OSUC 396840–396841, 396846 (CNCI); OSUC<!--PageBreak--> 254570, 254594–254595, 334210, 381817, 396837 (OSUC); OSUC 237533, 254569, 265198–265199, 334209, 334224–334226, 334228 (QSBG). <italic>Other material</italic>: <bold>THAILAND:</bold> 18 males, OSUC 181202, 181292, 237529, 396844, 396847 (CNCI); OSUC 254552, 265200, 334208, 334211, 334216 (OSUC); OSUC 237666, 261871, 265201, 266164, 334202–334203, 334212, 334227 (QSBG).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">nephta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C8471114-0E15-44FB-BFA4-2FE3A0E7EAE8</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:243854</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_nephta</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>(Kozlov)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figures 55–60</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>24</sup></xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Tuora nephta</tp:taxon-name><comment> Kozlov, 1976: 98 (original description); Kozlov &amp; Kononova, 1990: 263 (description of male and female); Kononova, 1995: 86 (keyed).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Kozlov): Kononova &amp; Kozlov, 2008: 279, 281 (description, keyed, generic transfer).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Description.</bold> Female body length: 2.53–3.10 mm (n=20). Color of head: dark brown to black. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: dorsoventrally striate. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally striate throughout. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: densely punctate. Sculpture of gena: finely punctate strigose; irregularly rugulose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: absent.</p>
                    <p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: equal to r-rs; less than r-rs. Notaulus: percurrent. Color of mesosoma: variably orange to brown. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: densely punctate throughout. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: densely punctate. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: absent. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: finely punctate. Sculpture of femoral groove: striate below mesopleural pit. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: present. Mesopleural carina: present. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: sparse. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                    <p>Color of metasoma: orange to brown. Horn of T1: bulge smooth, at least anteriorly; present as a small bulge. Microsculpture of T2: present. Microsculpture on T3: present. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: reticulate rugose. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: reticulate rugose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: rugulose. Punctation of T4: dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: absent. Punctation of T5: dense throughout. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: absent; weakly longitudinally strigose.</p>
                    <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 55–60.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold><sup>71</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>55</bold> Lateral habitus, female (OSUC 265087)<bold>56</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view, female (OSUC 265087)<bold>57</bold> Dorsal habitus, female (OSUC 265150). 58, Head and mesosoma, dorsal view, female (OSUC 262229)<bold>59</bold> Head, anterolateral view, female (OSUC 143437)<bold>60</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view, female (OSUC 265195). Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> is best distinguished by the uniform striation of the frons below the median ocellus, absence of microsculpture on the head and the smooth interspaces of the mesoscutellum. Color patterns are highly variable in this species and should be avoided entirely for identification.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>25</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p> <italic>Other material</italic>: (129 females, 95 males) <bold>JAPAN</bold>: 73 females, 71 males, OSUC 181186–181189, 181191–181196, 181203–181209, 181213–181214, 181216–181218, 181221, 262145–262186, 262194–262199, 262225–262233, 262240–262247, 265063–265068, 265070–265071, 265073–265085,<!--PageBreak--> 265087–265089, 265093–265099, 265122–265132, 265134, 265139–265145, 265150–265152, 265155, 265195–265196 (CNCI). <bold>RUSSIA:</bold> 3 females, 3 males, OSUC 143437, 241513, 241655–241657, 404916 (OSUC). <bold>SOUTH KOREA:</bold> 53 females, 21 males, OSUC 181190, 181197, 181210, 181215, 181222–181225, 262187–262192, 262210–262219, 262221–262224, 262234, 262248–262258, 262260–262262, 265069, 265100–265121, 265136–265138, 265146–265149, 265197 (CNCI).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">nilaka</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:EC0F912C-9AA2-4401-9251-4906A7B2BD1A</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:273890</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_nilaka</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 13</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">61–66</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">109</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>26</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Female body length: 2.60–4.00 mm (n=7). Color of head: black throughout. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: smooth. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally strigose throughout; rugose. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: punctate rugulose. Sculpture of gena: punctate rugulose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: absent.</p>
                    <p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: less than r-rs. Notaulus: percurrent. Color of mesosoma: dark brown to black. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: densely punctate, with longitudinal rugae in posterior half; areolate rugulose. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: punctate rugulose throughout. Dark bristle-like setae along transverse pronotal carina: absent. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: finely punctate. Sculpture of femoral groove: smooth; striate in ventral end. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: present. Mesopleural carina: present along anterior half of femoral groove. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: dense. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                    <p>Color of metasoma: dark brown to black throughout. Horn of T1: bulge smooth, at least anteriorly; absent. Microsculpture of T2: absent. Microsculpture on T3: present. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: weakly longitudinally strigose. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: reticulate rugose; longitudinally strigose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: rugulose. Punctation of T4: sparse along midline, otherwise dense; dense throughout; moderately dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: absent; rugulose laterally. Punctation of T5: dense throughout; sparse medially, dense laterally. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: absent.</p>
                    <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 61–66.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold><sup>72</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nilaka</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>61</bold> Lateral habitus, female holotype (OSUC 266165)<bold>62</bold> Mesosoma, lateral view, female holotype (OSUC 266165)<bold>63</bold> Mesosoma, dorsal view, female (OSUC 254613). 64, Metasoma, dorsal view, female holotype (OSUC 266165)<bold>65</bold> Head, anterior view, female holotype (OSUC 266165)<bold>66</bold> Pronotum, anterolateral view, female (OSUC 334223). Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> The rugulose sculpture of the dorsal mesoscutum and mesoscutellum in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nilaka</tp:taxon-name></italic> is shared with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris rugulosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris toketoki</tp:taxon-name></italic>; it may be separated from both by the dense, fine setation of the pronotal shoulder. Additionally, the typically black color of the body may be useful for identification, but should be used with caution given the color plasticity seen in many species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The epithet “nilaka” means “black” in Thai, and is used as a noun in apposition.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>27</sup> <!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p> Holotype, female: <bold>THAILAND:</bold> Chiang Mai Prov., checkpoint 2, T1909, Doi Inthanon National Park, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">18°31.554'N, 98°29.940'E</named-content> , 1700m, 14.XI–15.XI.2006, pan trap, Y. Areeluck, OSUC 266165 (deposited in QSBG). <italic>Paratypes</italic>: <bold>THAILAND:</bold> 6 females, OSUC 334247 (CNCI); OSUC 254613, 381811 (OSUC); OSUC 334223, 334295, 396843 (QSBG).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">reptilis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:519CC4FD-EC66-48EA-9652-ECB6FDF14FC9</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:273878</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_reptilis</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figures 67–72</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>28</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p> Female body length: 2.35–2.40 mm (n=2). Color of head: reddish brown. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: mostly smooth with faint dorsoventral striation. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally strigose laterally. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: irregularly rugulose. Sculpture of gena: irregularly rugulose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: absent.</p>
                        <p>Wings: brachypterous, apex of forewing ending before T4. Notaulus: percurrent. Color of mesosoma: variably yellow to brown. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: areolate rugulose. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: areolate rugulose. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: absent. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: rugulose posteriorly. Sculpture of femoral groove: striate in ventral end. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: present. Mesopleural carina: present. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: moderately dense. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                        <p>Color of metasoma: reddish brown. Horn of T1: bulge smooth, at least anteriorly; absent. Microsculpture of T2: present. Microsculpture on T3: absent. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: longitudinally strigose. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: longitudinally strigose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: rugulose. Punctation of T4: sparse along midline, otherwise dense. Macrosculpture of T5: absent. Punctation of T5: moderately dense throughout. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: absent.</p>
                        <fig id="F12" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 67–72.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold><sup>73</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris reptilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype (OSUC 181211) <bold>67</bold> Lateral habitus<bold>68</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view<bold>69</bold> Dorsal habitus<bold>70</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view<bold>71</bold> Head, anterior view<bold>72</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view. Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g012.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris reptilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris ferus</tp:taxon-name></italic> are the only known brachypterous species in the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> group. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris ferus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a basiconic sensillum on A7 and lacks interstitial microsculpture on T2. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris reptilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> does not have a sensillum on A7 and T2 is densely microsculptured.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The adjectival epithet “reptilis”, meaning “crawling” in Latin, refers to the reduced wing size in this species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>29</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p> Holotype, female: <bold>TAIWAN:</bold> Taiwan Prov., Pingtung Co., Kuai-Ku Hut, T-103, Pei-ta-wu (Peitawushan) Mountain, 2125m, 26.IV–30.IV.1992, A. Smetana, OSUC 181211 (deposited in CNCI). <italic>Paratype</italic>: <bold>TAIWAN:</bold> 1 female, OSUC 265153 (CNCI).<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">rugulosus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8B3B767C-6BC7-40D8-B531-9DD8ED1B57EF</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:273914</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_rugulosus</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figures 73–78</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>30</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p> Female body length: 2.48–2.56 mm (n=2). Color of head: yellow, becoming darker dorsally; black throughout. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: smooth. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally strigose laterally; dorsoventrally strigose throughout. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: irregularly rugulose; punctate rugulose. Sculpture of gena: irregularly rugulose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: absent.</p>
                        <p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: equal to r-rs. Notaulus: percurrent. Color of mesosoma: variably yellow to brown. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: areolate rugulose. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: punctate rugulose throughout; areolate rugulose. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: present. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: smooth. Sculpture of femoral groove: smooth; striate in ventral end. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: absent. Mesopleural carina: present. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: sparse. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                        <p>Color of metasoma: reddish brown. Horn of T1: absent. Microsculpture of T2: absent. Microsculpture on T3: absent. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: weakly longitudinally strigose. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: longitudinally strigose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: weakly rugulose. Punctation of T4: moderately dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: absent. Punctation of T5: moderately dense throughout. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: absent.</p>
                        <fig id="F13" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 73–78.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold><sup>74</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris rugulosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype (OSUC 265238) <bold>73</bold> Lateral habitus<bold>74</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view<bold>75</bold> Head and mesosoma, ventral view<bold>76</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view<bold>77</bold> Head and pronotum, anterolateral view<bold>78</bold> T2–T4, dorsolateral view. Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g013.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris rugulosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris toketoki</tp:taxon-name></italic> and may be separated by the smooth surface of the lateral pronotum.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The Latin adjectival epithet “rugulosus” refers to the rugulose sculpture of the head and dorsal mesosoma in this species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>31</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p> Holotype, female: <bold>VIETNAM:</bold> Vinh Phuc Prov., Tam Dao, 1050–1175m, 14.VI–17.VI.2007, malaise trap, C. v. Achterberg &amp; R. de Vries, OSUC 265238 (deposited in RMNH). <italic>Paratype</italic>: <bold>LAOS:</bold> 1 female, OSUC 262200 (CNCI).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">solaris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B2878DA2-1E8F-4B6E-96C4-86B571C11F04</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:241280</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_solaris</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figures 79–84</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">110</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>32</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p> Female body length: 1.96–3.43 mm (n=19). Color of head: reddish brown; orange throughout; dark brown to black; yellow. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: smooth. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally strigose throughout; rugose. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: finely punctate; moderately punctate; punctate rugulose. Sculpture of gena: punctate rugulose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: absent.</p>
                        <p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: equal to r-rs; longer than r-rs. Notaulus: percurrent. Color of mesosoma: variably orange to brown; yellow throughout; orange throughout. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: densely punctate, with longitudinal rugae in posterior half; densely punctate throughout. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: smooth medially, moderately punctate laterally; densely punctate. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: absent. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: finely punctate. Sculpture of femoral groove: smooth; striate in ventral end. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: present. Mesopleural carina: present. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: dense; moderately dense; sparse. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                        <p>Color of metasoma: yellow; orange to brown. Horn of T1: bulge smooth, at least anteriorly; absent. Microsculpture of T2: absent. Microsculpture on T3: absent. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: longitudinally strigose; weakly longitudinally strigose. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: longitudinally strigose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: absent. Punctation of T4: dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: absent. Punctation of T5: dense throughout; moderately dense throughout. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: weakly longitudinally strigose.</p>
                        <fig id="F14" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 79–84.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold><sup>75</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris solaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>79</bold> Lateral habitus, female holotype (OSUC 240944)<bold>80</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view, female holotype (OSUC 240944)<bold>81</bold> Lateral habitus, female (OSUC 237532). 82, Head and mesosoma, dorsal view, female holotype (OSUC 240944)<bold>83</bold> Head, anterior view, female (OSUC 240948)<bold>84</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view, female (OSUC 240946). Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g014.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris solaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris minator</tp:taxon-name></italic>. It may be separated from it by the absence of a basiconic sensillum on A7.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The adjectival epithet “solaris” means “of the sun” in Latin and references the bright yellow-orange color present in many individuals of this species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>33</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p> Holotype, female: <bold>VIETNAM:</bold> Thua Thien-Hue Prov., ~1.5km NE along trail behind upper guesthouse, light gap / semi-tropical evergreen forest, ROM 2000512, Bach Ma National Park, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">16°11'50.3"N, 107°51'17.7"E</named-content>, 1200m, 6.VI–17.VI.2000, malaise trap/pan trap, B. Hubley, OSUC 240944 (deposited in ROME). <italic>Paratypes</italic>: (21 females) <bold>LAOS:</bold> 3 females, OSUC 334242–334243<!--PageBreak-->, 334248 (CNCI). <bold>THAILAND:</bold> 5 females, OSUC 334144, 396849 (OSUC); OSUC 237532, 265212, 334207 (QSBG). <bold>VIETNAM:</bold> 13 females, OSUC 240940 (IEBR); OSUC 240945, 404917–404918 (OSUC); OSUC 265234–265236, 277369, 281520 (RMNH); OSUC 240946, 240948, 266180, 404919 (ROME).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                        <p> The color of specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris solaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> varies significantly according to geographical location. Those from Vietnam are typically yellow throughout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 79</xref>) and those from Thailand are variably orange, red, and black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 81</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">teres</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8A24D695-8FC0-4921-8885-B8FC3493FBE3</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:273893</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_teres</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figures 85–90</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>34</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p> Female body length: 2.42 mm (n=1). Color of head: yellow. Ventral clypeal margin: smooth. Sculpture of frons medially: smooth. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally strigose throughout. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: punctate rugulose. Sculpture of gena: punctate rugulose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: absent.</p>
                        <p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: equal to r-rs. Notaulus: percurrent. Color of mesosoma: yellow throughout. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: densely punctate, with longitudinal rugae in posterior half. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: smooth along midline, otherwise punctate rugulose. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: absent. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: finely punctate. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: present. Mesopleural carina: present. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: moderately dense. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                        <p>Color of metasoma: yellow. Horn of T1: absent. Microsculpture of T2: absent. Microsculpture on T3: present. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: absent. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: absent. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: weakly rugulose. Punctation of T4: dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: rugulose laterally. Punctation of T5: moderately dense throughout. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: weakly longitudinally strigose.</p>
                        <fig id="F15" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 85–90.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold><sup>76</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris teres</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype (OSUC 265237) <bold>85</bold> Lateral habitus<bold>86</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view<bold>87</bold> Dorsal habitus<bold>88</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view<bold>89</bold> Head, anterior view<bold>90</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view. Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g015.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris teres</tp:taxon-name></italic> may be easily identified by the smooth ventral margin of the clypeus.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The epithet “teres”, meaning smooth in Latin, refers to the smooth margin of the clypeus and is used as a noun in apposition.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>35</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: <bold>VIETNAM:</bold> Vinh Phuc Prov., Tam Dao, 1050–1175m, 14.VI–17.VI.2007, malaise trap, C. v. Achterberg &amp; R. de Vries, OSUC 265237 (deposited in RMNH).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>The sole specimen of this species was damaged during examination after it was imaged. The head, propleuron and forelegs are now mounted on the point separate from the remainder of the body; A7–12 of the right antenna are lost.<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">toketoki</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:628BBEF3-C3BA-4EE4-A905-3334CBD8ED7F</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:273915</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_toketoki</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figures 91–96</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>36</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p> Female body length: 2.54 mm (n=1). Color of head: dark orange, becoming brown at vertex. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: smooth. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally strigose laterally. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: punctate rugulose. Sculpture of gena: punctate rugulose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: absent.</p>
                        <p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: less than r-rs. Notaulus: smooth furrow incomplete, reaching suprahumeral sulcus as row of punctures. Color of mesosoma: variably orange to brown. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: densely punctate throughout. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: punctate rugulose throughout. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: present. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: finely punctate. Sculpture of femoral groove: smooth. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: present. Mesopleural carina: present along anterior half of femoral groove. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: moderately dense. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                        <p>Color of metasoma: orange to brown. Horn of T1: bulge smooth, at least anteriorly. Microsculpture of T2: absent. Microsculpture on T3: uncertain, absent. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: weakly longitudinally strigose. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: longitudinally rugulose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: rugulose. Punctation of T4: dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: rugulose laterally. Punctation of T5: sparse medially, dense laterally. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: weakly longitudinally strigose.</p>
                        <fig id="F16" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 91–96.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold><sup>77</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris toketoki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype (OSUC 181200) <bold>91</bold> Lateral habitus<bold>92</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view<bold>93</bold> Dorsal habitus<bold>94</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view<bold>95</bold> Head, anterior view<bold>96</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view. Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g016.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris toketoki</tp:taxon-name></italic> is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris rugulosus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. It differs most conspicuously in having the lateral face of the pronotum densely punctate along its dorsal margin.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> This species is named for the great Paiwan chief, Toketok.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>37</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: <bold>TAIWAN:</bold> Taiwan Prov., Nantou Co., Jih-yüeh (Sun Moon) Lake, H025, Te-hua-she (Tehuache), 800m, 5.VI.1980, J. Heraty, OSUC 181200 (deposited in CNCI).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">verrucosus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:CCEB3258-CADF-4F0F-B2E2-983F94AF5372</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:275741</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_verrucosus</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 17</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">97–102</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>38</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p> Female body length: 1.97 mm (n=1). Color of head: dark brown to black. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: smooth. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: dorsoventrally strigose throughout. Microsculpture of frons: uncertain, absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: irregularly rugulose. Sculpture of gena: irregularly rugulose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: absent.</p>
                        <p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: equal to r-rs. Notaulus: absent. Color of mesosoma: variably orange to brown. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: areolate rugulose. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: areolate rugulose. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: present. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: rugulose posteriorly. Sculpture of femoral groove: striate below mesopleural pit. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: rugulose. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: absent. Mesopleural carina: present. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: moderately dense. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                        <p>Color of metasoma: reddish brown. Horn of T1: absent. Microsculpture of T2: present. Microsculpture on T3: present. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: reticulate. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: longitudinally rugulose. Microsculpture of T4: present. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: rugulose. Punctation of T4: moderately dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: rugulose laterally. Punctation of T5: moderately dense laterally and along anterior margin. Microsculpture of S3: present. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: longitudinally strigose.</p>
                        <fig id="F17" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 97–102.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold><sup>78</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris verrucosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype (OSUC 334249) <bold>97</bold> Lateral habitus<bold>98</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view<bold>99</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view<bold>100</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view<bold>101</bold> Head, anterior view<bold>102</bold> T3–T6, dorsolateral view. Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g017.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris verrucosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the only species in the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nephta</tp:taxon-name></italic> group with microsculpture on S3.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The adjectival epithet “verrucosus” means “full of warts” in Latin; it is given to this species for the dense microsculpture of the metasoma.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>39</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: <bold>CHINA:</bold> Guangdong Prov., creek, Nankunshan, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">23°37.287'N, 113°51.267'S</named-content> , 581m, 29.X–31.X.2009, yellow pan trap, L. Masner, OSUC 334249 (deposited in CNCI).<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Paridris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">yak</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:37D0E197-226E-4EB5-B367-76F0C5D46276</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:241283</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Paridris_yak</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Talamas</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 15</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">103–108</xref><xref>Morphbank<sup>40</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p> Female body length: 4.15–4.16 mm (n=3). Color of head: dark orange, becoming brown at vertex. Ventral clypeal margin: serrate. Sculpture of frons medially: smooth. Sculpture of frons immediately ventral of median ocellus: rugose. Microsculpture of frons: absent. Sculpture of posterior vertex: areolate rugulose. Sculpture of gena: punctate rugulose. Basiconic sensillum on A7: absent.</p>
                        <p>Wings: macropterous, apex of forewing extending beyond posterior margin of T3. Length of R1: equal to r-rs; less than r-rs. Notaulus: absent; indicated only at posterior margin of mesoscutum. Color of mesosoma: orange to dark red anteriorly, brown posteriorly, mesoscutellum black; variably red to black. Sculpture of mesoscutum medially: areolate rugulose. Sculpture of mesoscutellum: areolate rugulose. Dark bristlelike setae along transverse pronotal carina: absent. Sculpture ventral of transverse pronotal carina: finely punctate. Sculpture of femoral groove: smooth. Sculpture of ventral half of posterior mesepimeral area: smooth. Fine setigerous punctures on dorsal half of posterior mesepimeral area: present. Mesopleural carina: present. Setation of ventral metapleural area: absent in area immediately below metapleural sulcus. Setation of metapleural triangle: moderately dense. Color of legs: yellow throughout.</p>
                        <p>Color of metasoma: orange to black. Horn of T1: bulge smooth, at least anteriorly. Microsculpture of T2: absent. Microsculpture on T3: absent. Macrosculpture of T3 medially: longitudinally strigose; weakly longitudinally strigose. Macrosculpture of T3 laterally: longitudinally strigose. Microsculpture of T4: absent. Macrosculpture of T4 laterally: rugulose. Punctation of T4: dense throughout. Macrosculpture of T5: rugulose laterally. Punctation of T5: dense throughout. Microsculpture of S3: absent. Macrosculpture of S3 laterally: absent.</p>
                        <fig id="F18" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 103–108.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold><sup>79</sup></bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris yak</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female holotype (OSUC 237530) <bold>103</bold> Lateral habitus<bold>104</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view<bold>105</bold> Dorsal habitus<bold>106</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view<bold>107</bold> Head, anterior view<bold>108</bold> T5<bold>–</bold>T6, dorsal view. Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g018.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F19" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 109–111.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold><sup>80</sup></bold> <bold>109</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris nilaka</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., R1 (postmarginal vein) and r-rs (stigmal vein), dorsal view, female holotype (OSUC 266165)<bold>110</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris solaris</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n., R1 (postmarginal vein) and r-rs (stigmal vein), dorsal view, female holotype (OSUC 240944)<bold>111</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris mystax</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n., fore and hind wing, dorsal view, male (OSUC 265200). Scale bars in millimeters.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-133-049-g019.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paridris yak</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a large distinctive species best identified by its reduced or absent notaulus, dorsally rugose frons and dorsally pointed axillular carina.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p> The word “yak” is Thai for a mythological ogre. It is treated as a noun in apposition.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to Distribution Map"><title>Link to Distribution Map.</title>
                        <p><sup>41</sup></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined"><title>Material Examined.</title>
                        <p> Holotype, female: <bold>THAILAND:</bold> Trang Prov., forest research center, Khao Chong Mountain, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">07°33.2'N, 99°47.22'E</named-content> , 75m, XI–2005, malaise trap, D. Lohman, OSUC 237530 (deposited in QSBG). <italic>Paratypes</italic>: <bold>THAILAND:</bold> 3 females, OSUC 396848 (OSUC); OSUC 266085, 334214 (QSBG).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>Thanks to A. Bennett, D.C. Darling, W. Pulawski, K. van Achterberg and M. Sharkey (Thai specimens collected under NSF grant No. DEB-0542864) for the loans of material for this study; to I. Mikó and M. Yoder for generating the appendix of morphological terms; and to L. Musetti, J. Cora, and S. Hemly for critical assistance with specimen handling, software, and databasing. This material is based upon work supported in part by the National Science Foundation under grant No. DEB–0614764 to N.F. Johnson and A.D. Austin<!--PageBreak-->.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<article-title> Definition of female antennal clava based on its plate sensilla in Hymenoptera Scelionidae Telenominae.</article-title> <source>Redia </source> <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>-<lpage>261</lpage>.<sup>42</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Förster</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1856</year>)<source> Hymenopterologische Studien.</source> <publisher-name>II. Heft. Chalcidae und Proctotrupii. Ernst ter Meer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Aachen</publisher-loc>, <lpage>152</lpage> pp.<sup>43</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kononova</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozlov</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<source> [Scelionids of the Palearctic (Hymenoptera, Scelionidae).</source> <publisher-name>Subfamily Scelioninae.] Tovarishchestvo Nauchnykh Izdanii KMK</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Saint Petersburg</publisher-loc>, <lpage>489</lpage> pp.<sup>44</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kononova</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> [A review of the genera <italic>Triteleia</italic>, <italic>Paridris</italic> and <italic>Calotelea</italic> (Hymenoptera, Scelionidae, Scelioninae) of Palaearctic region.</article-title> <source>] Vestnik Zoologii </source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>35</lpage>.<sup>45</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozlov</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>)<article-title> [A new genus of Scelionidae (Hymenoptera, Proctotrupoidea) from the Far East.</article-title> <source>] Trudy Zoologicheskogo Instituta Akademii Nauk SSSR </source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>-<lpage>99</lpage>.<sup>46</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozlov</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kononova</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> [New Palearctic genera of scelionids (Hymenoptera, Scelionidae) of the fauna of the USSR.</article-title> <source>] Vestnik Zoologii </source> <volume>1985</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>36</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.<sup>47</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozlov</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kononova</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<source> [Scelioninae of the Fauna of the USSR (Hymenoptera, Scelionidae, Scelioninae).</source> <publisher-name>] Nauka</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Leningrad</publisher-loc>, <lpage>344</lpage> pp.<sup>48</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lê</surname><given-names>X-H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<source> Egg-parasites of family Scelionidae (Hymenoptera). Fauna of Vietnam, vol. 3.</source> <publisher-name>Science and Technics Publishing House</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Hanoi</publisher-loc>, <lpage>386</lpage> pp.<sup>49</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<article-title> Proctotrupoidea (Hymenoptera) from India. A review.</article-title> <source>Oriental Insects </source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>-<lpage>258</lpage>.<sup>50</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Masner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>)<article-title> Revisionary notes and keys to world genera of Scelionidae (Hymenoptera: Proctotrupoidea).</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the Entomological Society of Canada </source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>87</lpage>.<sup>51</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Masner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Key to genera of Scelionidae of the Holarctic region, with descriptions of new genera and species (Hymenoptera: Proctotrupoidea).</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the Entomological Society of Canada</source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>54</lpage>.<sup>52</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Masner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muesebeck</surname><given-names>CFW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> The types of Proctotrupoidea (Hymenoptera) in the United States National Museum.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the United States National Museum </source> <volume>270</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>143</lpage>.<sup>53</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>WRM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> Standard drawing conventions and definitions for venational and other features of wings of Hymenoptera.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington </source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.<sup>54</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikó</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilhelmsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pénzes</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Skeletomusculature of Scelionidae (Hymenoptera: Platygastroidea): head and mesosoma.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1571</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>.<sup>55</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mineo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> New scelionid wasps from Italy (Hymenoptera).</article-title> <source>Scelionidae (Hymenoptera) </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.<sup>56</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Polaszek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agosti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Zarazaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beccaloni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Place Bjørn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brothers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Earl of</surname><given-names>Cranbrook</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evenhuis</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godfray</surname><given-names>HCJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krell</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipscomb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyal</surname><given-names>CHC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mawatari</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>PKL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyle</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taverne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Tol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>QD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> A universal register for animal names. Nature 437:477.</source><sup>57</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajmohana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Studies on Proctotrupoidea and Platygastroidea (Hymenoptera: Insecta) of Kerala.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the Zoological Survey of India </source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>153</lpage>.<sup>58</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Talamas</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Revision of the Malagasy genus <italic>Trichoteleia</italic> Kieffer (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea, Platygastridae).</article-title> <source>ZooKeys </source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>126</lpage>.<sup>59</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1935</year>)<article-title> Two new genera of myrmicine ants from Papua and the Philippines.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the New England Zoological Club </source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.<sup>60</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikó</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seltmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertone</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deans</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source> A gross anatomy ontology for Hymenoptera. PLosONE 5(12): e15991</source><sup>61</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
        </ref-list>
        <sec sec-type="Endnotes"><title>Endnotes</title>
            <p>1	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1012" xlink:type="simple">http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1012</ext-link></p>
            <p>2	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:35284" xlink:type="simple">http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:35284</ext-link></p>
            <p>3	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:33578" xlink:type="simple">http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:33578</ext-link></p>
            <p>4	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1014" xlink:type="simple">http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1014</ext-link></p>
            <p>5	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1016" xlink:type="simple">http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1016</ext-link></p>
            <p>6	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1017" xlink:type="simple">http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1017</ext-link></p>
            <p>7	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34212" xlink:type="simple">http://biocol.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34212</ext-link></p>
            <p>8	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592382" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592382</ext-link></p>
            <p>9	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592383" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592383</ext-link></p>
            <p>10	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592384" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592384</ext-link></p>
            <p>11	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592385" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592385</ext-link></p>
            <p>12	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592369" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592369</ext-link></p>
            <p>13	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=275737" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=275737</ext-link></p>
            <p>14	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592365" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592365</ext-link></p>
            <p>15	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273886" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273886</ext-link></p>
            <p>16	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592344" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592344</ext-link></p>
            <p>17	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=241281" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=241281</ext-link></p>
            <p>18	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592366" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592366</ext-link></p>
            <p>19	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273916" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273916</ext-link></p>
            <p>20	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592362" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592362</ext-link></p>
            <p>21	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=241284" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=241284</ext-link></p>
            <p>22	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592379" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592379</ext-link></p>
            <p>23	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=241282" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=241282</ext-link></p>
            <p>24	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592377" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592377</ext-link></p>
            <p>25	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=243854" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=243854</ext-link></p>
            <p>26	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592370" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592370</ext-link></p>
            <p>27	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273890" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273890</ext-link></p>
            <p>28	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592367" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592367</ext-link></p>
            <p>29	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273878" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273878</ext-link></p>
            <p>30	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592364" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592364</ext-link></p>
            <p>31	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273914" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273914</ext-link></p>
            <p>32	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592363" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592363</ext-link></p>
            <p>33	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=241280" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=241280</ext-link></p>
            <p>34	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592343" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592343</ext-link></p>
            <p>35	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273893" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273893</ext-link></p>
            <p>36	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592374" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592374</ext-link></p>
            <p>37	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273915" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=273915</ext-link></p>
            <p>38	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592375" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592375</ext-link></p>
            <p>39	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=275741" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=275741</ext-link></p>
            <p>40	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592368" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592368</ext-link></p>
            <p>41	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=241283" xlink:type="simple">http://hol.osu.edu/map-large.html?id=241283</ext-link></p>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <p>42	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:131" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:131</ext-link></p>
            <p>43	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:330" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:330</ext-link></p>
            <p>44	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:22163" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:22163</ext-link></p>
            <p>45	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:9730" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:9730</ext-link></p>
            <p>46	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:1501" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:1501</ext-link></p>
            <p>47	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:968" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:968</ext-link></p>
            <p>48	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:340" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:340</ext-link></p>
            <p>49	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:9718" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:9718</ext-link></p>
            <p>50	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:236" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:236</ext-link></p>
            <p>51	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:311" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:311</ext-link></p>
            <p>52	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:474" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:474</ext-link></p>
            <p>53	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:312" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:312</ext-link></p>
            <p>54	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:7039" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:7039</ext-link></p>
            <p>55	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2007f/zt01571p078.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2007f/zt01571p078.pdf</ext-link></p>
            <p>56	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21224" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21224</ext-link></p>
            <p>57	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:20959" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:20959</ext-link></p>
            <p>58	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21131" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21131</ext-link></p>
            <p>59	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:23390" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:23390</ext-link></p>
            <p>60	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:3440" xlink:type="simple">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:3440</ext-link></p>
            <p>61	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0015991" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0015991</ext-link></p>
            <p>62	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592361" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592361</ext-link></p>
            <p>63	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592381" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592381</ext-link></p>
            <p>64	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592386" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592386</ext-link></p>
            <p>65	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592387" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592387</ext-link></p>
            <p>66	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592388" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592388</ext-link></p>
            <p>67	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592373" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592373</ext-link></p>
            <p>68	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592389" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592389</ext-link></p>
            <p>69	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592390" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592390</ext-link></p>
            <p>70	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592393" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592393</ext-link></p>
            <p>71	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592394" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592394</ext-link></p>
            <p>72	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592380" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592380</ext-link></p>
            <p>73	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592395" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592395</ext-link></p>
            <p>74	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592396" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592396</ext-link></p>
            <p>75	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592397" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592397</ext-link></p>
            <p>76	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592378" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592378</ext-link></p>
            <p>77	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592398" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592398</ext-link></p>
            <p>78	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592399" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592399</ext-link></p>
            <p>79	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592400" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592400</ext-link></p>
            <p>80	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://morphbank.net/?id=592401" xlink:type="simple">http://morphbank.net/?id=592401</ext-link></p>
            <!--PageBreak-->
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Appendix I"><title>Appendix I</title>
            <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <caption><p>Abbreviations Label Used in Text Unique Identyfier of HAO class Label Used in Talamas et al. 2011</p></caption>
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">axc</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">axillular carina </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000161" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000161</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">basiconic sensillum </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001729" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001729</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">body </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000182" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000182</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">compound eye </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000217" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000217</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">conjunctiva </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000221" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000221</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">epc</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">epomial carina </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000307" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000307</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">vertical epomial carina</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">felt field </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000322" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000322</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">femoral groove </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000326" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000326</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">femoral depresssion</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">frons </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001044" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001044</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gena </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000371" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000371</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">horn of T1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">inner orbit of compound eye</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000419" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000419</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">interantennal process </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000422" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000422</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">loc</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lateral ocellus </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000481" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000481</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lateral propodeal carina</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000486" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000486</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">leg</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000494" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000494</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mandible </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000506" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000506</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">median ocellus </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000526" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000526</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mesepisternum </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000541" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000541</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mesoscutal suprahumeral sulcus</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000570" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000570</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mesoscutellum </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000574" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000574</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mesoscutum </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000575" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000575</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mesosoma </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000576" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000576</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mtps</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">metapleural sulcus </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000614" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000614</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">metapleural triangle </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000615" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000615</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">metapleuron </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001869" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001869</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">metascutellum </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000625" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000625</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">metasoma </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000626" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000626</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">metasomal depression</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000627" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000627</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">notaulus </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000647" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000647</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">occipital carina </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000653" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000653</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ovipositor </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000679" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000679</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pcxs</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">paracoxal sulcus </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000685" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000685</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">plica</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000735" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000735</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">posterior mesepimeral area</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000751" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000751</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">posterior scutellar sulcus</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000757" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000757</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pronotum</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000853" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000853</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">posterior propodeal projection</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000763" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000763</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">propodeum</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001249" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001249</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000035" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000035</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">scutoscutellar sulcus </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000920" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0000920</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001147" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001147</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001151" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001151</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001468" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001468</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">trc</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">transverse carina on T2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tpc</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">transverse pronotal carina</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001031" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001031</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">dorsal epomial carina</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ventral clypeal margin</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001767" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001767</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ventral metapleural area</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001062" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001062</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">vertex</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001077" xlink:type="simple">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/HAO_0001077</ext-link></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Appendix II"><title>Appendix II</title>
            <p>Lucid key to females of the <italic>Paridris nephta</italic> species group. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.133.1613.app" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.3897/zookeys.133.1613.app</ext-link>)</p>
            <p>Copyright notice: This dataset is made available under the Open Database License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/odbl/1.0/" xlink:type="simple">http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/odbl/1.0/</ext-link>). The Open Database License (ODbL) is a license agreement intended to allow users to freely share, modify, and use this Dataset while maintaining this same freedom for others, provided that the original source and author(s) are credited.</p>
        </sec>
    </back>
</article>