<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.176.2379</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Terrestrial isopod community as indicator of succession in a peat bog</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Antonović</surname>
                        <given-names>Ivan</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Brigić</surname>
                        <given-names>Andreja</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Sedlar</surname>
                        <given-names>Zorana</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Bedek</surname>
                        <given-names>Jana</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Šoštarić</surname>
                        <given-names>Renata</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Faculty of Science, University of Zagreb, 10000 Zagreb, Croatia
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Department of Zoology, Faculty of Science, University of Zagreb, Rooseveltov trg 6, 10000 Zagreb, Croatia
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Department of Botany, Faculty of Science, University of Zagreb, Marulićev trg 20/II, 10000 Zagreb, Croatia
            </aff>
            <aff id="A4">
                <label>4</label>Croatian Biospeleological Society, Demetrova 1, 10000 Zagreb, Croatia
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Ivan Antonović (<email xlink:type="simple">ivan.antonovic89@gmail.com</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: S. Sfenthourakis</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>20</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>176</issue>
            <fpage>171</fpage>
            <lpage>188</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>16</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>27</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Ivan Antonović, Andreja Brigić, Zorana Sedlar, Jana Bedek, Renata Šoštarić</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Terrestrial isopods were studied in the Dubravica peat bog and surrounding forest in the northwestern Croatia. Sampling was conducted using pitfall traps over a two year period. Studied peat bog has a history of drastically decrease in area during the last five decades mainly due to the process of natural succession and changes in the water level. A total of 389 isopod individuals belonging to 8 species were captured. Species richness did not significantly differ between bog, edge and surrounding forest. High species richness at the bog is most likely the result of progressive vegetation succession, small size of the bog and interspecific relationships, such as predation. With spreading of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Molinia</tp:taxon-name></italic> grass on the peat bog, upper layers of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphagnum</tp:taxon-name></italic> mosses become less humid and probably more suitable for forest species that slowly colonise bog area. The highest diversity was found at the edge mainly due to the edge effect and seasonal immigration, but also possibly due to high abundance and predator pressure of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmica</tp:taxon-name></italic> ants and lycosid spiders at the bog site. The most abundant species were <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus rathkii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, in the bog area and in the forest, respectively. Bog specific species were not recorded and the majority of the species collected belong to the group of tyrphoneutral species. However, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyloniscus adonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> could be considered as a tyrphoxenous species regarding its habitat preferences. Most of collected isopod species are widespread eurytopic species that usually inhabit various habitats and therefore indicate negative successive changes or degradation processes in the peat bog.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Edge</kwd>
                <kwd>seasonal dynamics</kwd>
                <kwd>pitfall trapping</kwd>
                <kwd>predation</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Trachelipus rathkii</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Protracheoniscus politus</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Hyloniscus adonis</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>tyrphoxenous species</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <!--PageBreak-->
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Peat bogs are a type of wetlands characterized by a high water table, low levels of nutrients, low pH values, and are dominated by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphagnum</tp:taxon-name></italic> mosses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Spitzer and Danks 2006</xref>). They are widely distributed in specific climatic regions where climates are cool and precipitation is relatively high, mostly in the boreal zones of Europe, Asia and North America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Rydin and Jeglum 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Spitzer and Danks 2006</xref>). In terms of biogeography, peat bogs in Croatia represent a southern enclave of their northern continuous distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Topić and Stančić 2006</xref>). Peat bogs are highly endangered ecosystems in Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Holmes et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Dapkus and Tamutis 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Buchholz et al. 2009</xref>) and some are listed as priority habitat types in Annex I of the European Habitats Directive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Anonymous 1992</xref>). Due to their small size, isolation, drainage and abandonment of traditional human activities, and especially to the progressive vegetation succession, such habitats are among critically endangered habitats in Croatia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Topić and Stančić 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Topić and Vukelić 2009</xref>).</p>
            <p>These unique ecosystems often consist of specialized flora and fauna, largely limited only to these habitats. Although most of the peat matrix is dead, it contains a great variety of living organisms that contribute in decomposing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Rydin and Jeglum 2006</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Peus (1932)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Roubal (1934)</xref> species that inhabit peat bogs can be classified into four categories: (a) tyrphobiontic species (occur only in bogs), (b) tyrphophilous species (characteristic of bogs but not strictly confined to them), (c) tyrphoneutral species (distributed across various types of habitats) and (d) tyrphoxenous species (vagrants or immigrants that cannot live in bogs).</p>
            <p>As members of the soil macrofauna community, isopods play an important role in the processes and soil formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">Wolters and Ekschmitt 1997</xref>). As soil humidity is their essential requirement, they occur in microhabitats such as under stones and logs in leaf litter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Schmalfuss 1978</xref>). There are several papers about isopod fauna in Central European wetlands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Sallai 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Farkas 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Tajovský 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Vadkerti and Farkas 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Tuf 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Vilisics et al. 2007</xref>). However, isopod fauna on peatlands is basically unknown, especially in Europe.</p>
            <p>The objectives of this study were: (1) to determine the terrestrial isopod assemblages and their spatial distribution in the peat bog remnant and surrounding forest, (2) to determine which basic ecological groups inhabit the peat bog and adjacent forest (3) to analyze the seasonal dynamics of the dominant isopod species and (4) to asses possible influence of soil temperature and humidity on isopod abundance.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
            <title>Methods</title>
            <sec sec-type="Study area">
                <title>Study area</title>
                <p>Peat bog Dubravica is located in the Northwestern part of Croatia, in Hrvatsko zagorje Region (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">45°57.430'N, 14°44.470'E</named-content>). It is situated in sessile oak and hornbeam forest<!--PageBreak--> (ass. <italic>Epimedio-Carpinetum betuli</italic> (Ht.1938) Borh. 1963) at an altitude of l60 m asl. Since 1966 it has been protected as a Botanical Reserve and it is a potential NATURA 2000 site.</p>
                <p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Horvat (1939)</xref> there were three bogs that covered the area of 2566 m<sup>2</sup> in total, but during the last 50 years the bog area has drastically decreased in size. There is only one small peat bog remnant covering the area of 605 m<sup>2</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Hršak 1996</xref>). This is mainly due to changes of the water level and abandonment of traditional management practices, such as mowing. All that led to the process of natural vegetation succession. A great part of the bog is overgrown by purple moor grass (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Molinia caerulea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (L.) Moench) and some woody species like the alder (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Alnus glutinosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> L.) and alder buckthorn (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Frangula alnus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mill.). These changes in vegetation structure dry out and rise up the bog, enabling growth of less moisture substrate seeking plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Hršak 1996</xref>). In order to preserve biodiversity of the peat bog remnant, the bog area is nowadays mowed once a year. Also, the presence of wild animals, like wild boar, brings to halting the spread of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Molinia</tp:taxon-name></italic> grass by rooting the land.</p>
                <p>Three sites were selected in and around the bog area, situated in different vegetational associations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The site B is located in the centre of the bog and the bog vegetation belongs to the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhynchosporetum albae</tp:taxon-name></italic> W. Koch, 1926 association. The ground layer was dominated by typical bog plant species: common sundew (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Drosera rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name></italic> L.), white beak-sedge (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhynchospora alba</tp:taxon-name></italic> (L.) Vahl.) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphagnum</tp:taxon-name></italic> mosses (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphagnum subsecundum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ness.). Site E is located on the edge of the bog and sessile oak and hornbeam forest. The edge is covered with rather strong <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rubus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. plants, which are opportunistically taking the open area on the edge zones. In order to avoid edge effect, site F is located 60 m from the edge into the forest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Lindenmayer and Fischer 2006</xref>). This site belongs to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epimedio-Carpinetum betuli</tp:taxon-name></italic> association. Sessile oak (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Quercus robur</tp:taxon-name></italic> L.) and hornbeam (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Carpinus betulus</tp:taxon-name></italic> L.) are the dominant species in a tree layer.</p>
                <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 1.</label>
                    <caption><p>Sampling sites in the Dubravica bog and surrounding forest. <bold>Site B</bold> - bog <bold>Site E</bold> - edge  <bold>Site F</bold> - forest.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-176-171-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Sampling">
                <title>Sampling</title>
                <p>Isopods were collected using pitfall traps during the carbide beetle study and sampling was conducted from May to November 2008 and from May to November 2009. Five plastic traps per site were placed (volume 0.3 dm<sup>3</sup>) 5 m apart. They were half filled with a saturated solution of sodium chloride with a few drops of detergent to break the surface tension of the liquid. A styrofoam roof was placed above each trap to protect them from rain. The traps were emptied once a month. The collected specimens were kept in 75% ethyl-alcohol with glycerol. The individuals were identified to the species level, apart from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Armadillidium</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. and <tp:taxon-name>Oniscidae</tp:taxon-name> sp., due to lack of adult male individuals. All individuals were identified by authors (I. A. and J. B.), with the exception of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyloniscus adonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, which was identified by Stefano Taiti (Istituto per lo Studio degli Ecosistemi, Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Soil analysis">
                <title>Soil analysis</title>
                <p>Basic pedophysiological properties of the soil were determined using standard methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Škorić 1982</xref>). Soil temperature and humidity were measured once a month at all three sites, next to every pitfall trap and average values were calculated. Temperature was measured at depth of 7 cm using P300 Dostmann electronic thermometer and soil humidity after every field trip by taking a soil sample at approximately 10 cm. In substrate samples water content was determined by the gravimetric method. The same soil sample was used to measure pH in water with a ratio of 1:2.5 (w/v) (10 g substrate / 25 mL H<sub>2</sub>O) and in KCl with a ratio of 1:2.5 (w/v) (10 g substrate / 25 mL KCl), using WTW pH 330i meter. Phosphorus, as P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> was measured by the colorimetric method using the spectrophotometer DR/2000 HACH (1996). Total nitrogen (TN) and total carbon (TC) content in substrate were simultaneously determined using the dry combustion method (elemental analysis) with the Vario Macro CHNS analyzer, Elementar.</p>
                <p>Soil analysis showed that pH values were very low at each sampling site, while calcium carbonate concentration was lowest in the forest, but higher at the edge and at the bog site (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Soil humidity was highest (sometimes ≥80%) at the bog during most of the sampling period. In addition, comparable results were observed at the edge, where soil humidity was also high (≥70%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Soil humidity was particularly low in the forest (18–33%) in both study years. Oscillations of the soil temperature<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> were most expressed at the edge (during both study years), especially during summer. At the bog an intermediate pattern was recorded (between edge and forest). Conversely, the lowest temperatures were measured at the bog site (during autumn and winter). Differences in soil humidity were observed in autumn between two study years, most likely due to higher amount of rain in 2009.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Table 1.</label>
                    <caption><p>Vegetational and pedagogical properties of studied sites in the Dubravica peat bog.  <bold>Site B</bold> – bog; <bold>Site E</bold> – edge; <bold>Site F</bold> – forest.</p></caption>
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Environmental variable</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Site B</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Site E</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Site F</bold></th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="4">Vegetation analysis</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant association</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhynchosporetum albae</tp:taxon-name></italic> W. Koch</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epimedio-Carpinetum betuli</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Ht 38) Both. 63</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetation height/m</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2-0.5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetation density</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">high</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">low</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle, thick layer of litter</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tree layer, dominant plant species</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% <italic><tp:taxon-name>Carpinus betulus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Quercus robur</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frutescent layer, dominant plant species</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0%</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50% <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rubus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% <italic><tp:taxon-name>Carpinus betulus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herbaceous layer, dominant plant species</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphagnum subsecundum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Molinia caerulea</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10% <italic><tp:taxon-name>Molinia caerulea</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80% <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epimedium alpinum</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="4">Soil analysis</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil type</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">peat</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">stagnosol</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH (H<sub>2</sub>0)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.09</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH (KCl)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.92</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.57</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Humus (Tjurin) %</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub> mg/100 g</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CaCO<sub>3</sub> %</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.235</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.226</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C/N</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.6</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 2.</label>
                    <caption><p>Soil temperature and soil humidity at the Dubravica bog and adjacent forest during 2008 and 2009. Temperature values are presented with different symbols and humidity values with bars. <bold>Site B</bold> – bog; <bold>Site E</bold> – edge; <bold>Site F</bold> – forest.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-176-171-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Data analysis">
                <title>Data analysis</title>
                <p>Activity-density was compared between two years, using Mann-Whiney U test and Spearman correlation. To calculate the diversity of the isopod assemblages we used Simpson (1-λ’) and Shannon-Wiener indices (H’). Evenness was estimated using Pielou’s evenness (J). Similarity between sites was calculated using the Bray-Curtis similarity coefficient, calculated on square root transformed and standardized abundance data (traps total catches). Non-metric MDS (multidimensional scaling) was constructed on Bray-Curtis similarity. The analyses were carried out using the PRIMER program v.6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Clarke and Gorley 2006</xref>). Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient was used to identify relationship between isopod abundance and environmental parameters (soil temperature and humidity). Activity density data did not follow normal distribution (Shapiro-Wilk test, p&lt;0.05), so square root transformation was applied (Shapiro-Wilk test, p&gt;0.05). ANOVA was used to compare abundances of isopods (monthly data pooled for five traps) between sampling sites. Tukey HSD (Honestly Significant Difference) test was used for <italic>post-hoc</italic> comparisons. Normality of data was tested using Shapiro-Wilk W test. ANOVA was executed using Statistica 7.0 (StatSoft inc.). An independent and comparable habitat fidelity index was made for collected species for each habitat type. In the case of isopods from family <tp:taxon-name>Oniscidae</tp:taxon-name> sp. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Armadillidium</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. habitat fidelity index was not calculated due to small number of specimens caught. It was conducted according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Nyilas (1994)</xref>, based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Erdakov et al. (1979)</xref>. The formula was:</p>
                <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-176-171-i001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <p>n<sub>i</sub> = number of individuals in habitat; n: number of individuals in all habitats; N: number of habitats, Hi: habitat i, Hi’: all habitats except habitat i. The values of this index range from -1 to +1. The maximum value, +1 shows that all individuals of the given species were in the given habitat, whereas -1 indicates that no individuals of the species were recorded in the habitat, and 0 indicates that there was an average number of individuals in the habitat (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Nyilas 1994</xref>). The sum of absolute values of the indices for a species gives the habitat selection index of the species.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <sec sec-type="Species richness, activity density and diversity">
                <title>Species richness, activity density and diversity</title>
                <p>During both study years, a total of 389 isopod individuals belonging to 8 species were captured (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Species richness and activity density were both lowest at the bog (over the whole study period). Overall, the highest number of individuals was recorded in the forest. ANOVA indicated significant difference in activity density between sites (d.f. = 2.42, F = 3.604, p&lt;0.05). <italic>Post-hoc</italic> test separated activity density in the bog from values in the forest (Tukey HSD, p&lt;0.05), while other combinations were not significantly different (Tukey HSD, p&gt;0.05). Overall, activity density was positively correlated between the two years of the study. Moreover, no significant difference of the latter between 2008 and 2009 was recorded for site B (Mann-Whitney U-test, p=0.327), in contrast to sites E and F (Mann-Whitney U-test, p=0.013 and p=0.007). Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient was statistically significant for site B (R<sub>s</sub>=0.83, p=0.022), marginally significant for site E (R<sub>s</sub>=0.73, p=0.10) and not significant for site F (R<sub>s</sub>=0.55, p=0.20). Therefore, data for both years were pooled for subsequent analyses.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Table 2.</label>
                    <caption><p>Isopod species recorded at Dubravica bog and adjacent forest with indices of diversity and evenness. <bold>Site B</bold> – bog; <bold>Site E</bold> – edge; <bold>Site F</bold> – forest; <bold>Tn</bold> – tyrphoneutral species <bold>Tx</bold> – tyrphoxenous species; <bold>%</bold> – percent share of total individuals per site. </p></caption>
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Species name</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>site B</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>%</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>site E</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>%</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>site F</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>%</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ecological group</bold></th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Armadillidium carniolense</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff, 1901</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Armadillidium</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ligidium germanicum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff, 1901</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Oniscidae</tp:taxon-name> sp.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic>  C. Koch, 1841</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus rathkii</tp:taxon-name></italic> Brandt, 1883</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus ratzeburgi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Brandt, 1883</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyloniscus adonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff, 1927</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tn (possible Tx)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of isopod species (S)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of isopod individuals (N)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">146</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simpson index (1-λ’)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.697</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.750</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.218</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shannon-Wiener index (H’)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.339</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.576</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.549</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pielou’s evenness index (J’)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.748</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.810</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.283</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>Soil temperature was positively correlated with the isopod total monthly catch at all three studied sites (Spearman’s rank correlation; site B: N=14, R<sub>s</sub>=0.594, p=0.025; site E: N=13, R<sub>s</sub>=0.619, p=0.024; site F: N=14, R<sub>s</sub>= 0.558, p=0.038). On the contrary, soil humidity negatively correlated with the isopod total monthly catch in the bog and forest samples, but the correlations were not statistically significant (Spearman’s rank<!--PageBreak--> correlation; site B: N=14, R<sub>s</sub>= -0.246, p=0.397; site F: N=14, R<sub>s</sub>= -0.372, p=0.190). However, in edge samples correlations between soil humidity and the total monthly catch was positive, but also statistically not significant (Spearman’s rank correlation; site E: N=13, R<sub>s</sub>=0.077, p=0.802).</p>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> C. Koch was generally the most abundant species (61.4% of the total catch). Together with following species; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus rathkii</tp:taxon-name></italic> Brandt (13.1%), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Armadillidium carniolense</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff (10%) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus ratzeburgi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Brandt (6.7%) it constituted 91.2% of the total catch. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus rathkii</tp:taxon-name></italic> was the most abundant species at the bog (44.4% of the catch), while its abundance decreased at the edge, and was the lowest in the forest (reaching only 1.7%). Three following species; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (30.2%), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Armadillidium carniolense</tp:taxon-name></italic> (12.7%) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ligidium germanicum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff (9.5%) also accounted for a larger proportion of the catch at the bog. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (41.8%) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Armadillidium carniolense</tp:taxon-name></italic> (19.2%) were the most frequent species at the edge and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was particularly abundant in the forest (88.3%). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyloniscus adonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff,had the highest abundance at the edge, while only 1 specimen was found at the bog. Majority of isopod taxa found at the bog are tyrphoneutral. According to diversity and evenness indices, the greatest and lowest diversity was recorded at the edge and in the forest, respectively.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Seasonal activity">
                <title>Seasonal activity</title>
                <p>Activity density of dominant <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was expressed as the total number of individuals caught monthly and plotted against time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). The maximum seasonal activity was observed in July at both forest and edge sites. During August, the number of individuals decreased at all studied sites, whereas an increase was observed in September. Overall, low number of individuals was caught at the bog, and this was insufficient to observe seasonal dynamics. Seasonal activity density of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> did positively correlate with soil temperature at the edge and forest sites (Spearman’s rank correlation; site E: N=14, R<sub>s</sub>=0.093, p=0.751; site F: N=14, R<sub>s</sub>=0.427, p=0.128), and negatively at the bog (Spearman’s rank correlation; site B: N=14, R<sub>s</sub>= -0.168, p=0.565). However, the correlations were not statistically significant. Additionally, Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient was positive between soil humidity and seasonal activity density of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> at the bog and edge (site B: N=14, R<sub>s</sub>=0.025, p=0.932; site E: N=14, R<sub>s</sub>=0.033, p=0.910, respectively) and negative in the forest (site F: N=14, R<sub>s</sub>= -0.461, p=0.096). Also, correlations were not statistically significant.</p>
                <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 3.</label>
                    <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> seasonal activity at three studied sites with different vegetation. <bold>Site B</bold> – bog; <bold>Site E</bold> – edge; <bold>Site F</bold> – forest; Y-axis shows total number of monthly caught individuals.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-176-171-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Similarity and habitat fidelity">
                <title>Similarity and habitat fidelity</title>
                <p>The habitat fidelity values of collected isopod species are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>. According to these results, two dominant species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus rathkii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, preferred different habitat types. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> mostly inhabited forest (site F) with a high habitat fidelity value (+ 0.6), while positive habitat fidelity value was calculated for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus rathkii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (+ 0.4) at the <!--PageBreak-->bog site. Typical hygrophylic species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ligidium germanicum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyloniscus adonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> also showed quite different habitat preferences. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ligidium germanicum</tp:taxon-name></italic> occurred mostly at the bog area (+ 0.33), while <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyloniscus adonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> preferred the edge site (+ 0.77). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Armadillidium carniolense</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus ratzeburgi</tp:taxon-name></italic> seemed both to prefer edge site with a higher habitat fidelity values in contrast to the values calculated for the other sites.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Table 3.</label>
                    <caption><p>The habitat fidelity values of dominant isopod species in each of the three habitats.   <bold>Site B</bold> – bog; <bold>Site E</bold> – edge; <bold>Site F</bold> – forest. </p></caption>
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>∑ N</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>site B</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>site E</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>site F</bold></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Habitat selection index</bold></th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">239</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 0.7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 0.05</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ 0.6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus rathkii</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ 0.4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ 0.1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 0.8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Armadillidium carniolense</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 0.32</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ 0.67</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 0.73</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus ratzeburgi</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 0.88</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ 0.54</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 0.06</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyloniscus adonis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 0.8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ 0.77</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 0.47</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ligidium germanicum</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ 0.33</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 0.2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">- 0.2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>Non-metric MDS ordination based on Bray-Curtis similarity index, with superimposed results of cluster analysis (group-average linking), shows generally high degree of similarity between studied sites (i.e. they all cluster at 46% similarity level; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). In particular, high degree of similarity is obvious for forest and edge sites that cluster together at 71% similarity level. Forest replicate samples grouped strongly together at the same similarity level, whereas, most of the edge replicate samples clustered together<!--PageBreak--> at 80% similarity level. On the contrary, bog replicate samples did not form a distinct group and they were combined with edge samples.</p>
                <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 4.</label>
                    <caption><p>nMDS ordination of studied sites and Bray-Curtis similarities with superimposed results of cluster analysis. <bold>Site B</bold> – bog; <bold>Site E</bold> – edge; <bold>Site F</bold> – forest.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-176-171-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Current study shows that isopod species richness of the isolated bog was surprisingly high and it did not considerably differ from the species richness of the edge or adjacent forest. Contrary to this, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Peus (1932)</xref> found that isopods may be almost completely excluded from acidic bogs, mainly due to specific and rather extreme environmental conditions, particularly low acidity. The same was observed in isopod studies in the Canadian peat bogs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Judd 1963</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Blades and Marshall 1994</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Judd (1963)</xref> only two isopod species were recorded at the Byron bog, but none of them was found in the open bog area, than on the adjacent wooded slopes. However, our study shows completely different pattern. This is possibly a result of several factors including progressive vegetation succession, low water table and small size of the bog, thus enabling immigration from adjacent habitats. In contrast to northern acidic peat bogs where water level is at or near the surface of the substratum and the peat is infra aquatic, water level at the studied bog has considerably fallen under the minimum necessary level to prevent spreading of taller plants, such as purple moor grass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Hršak 1996</xref>). <!--PageBreak-->Consequently, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphagnum</tp:taxon-name></italic> hummocks became less humid and such changes might have in particular affected isopod presence at the bog. Another cause might be the latitude, since generally isopod species richness increases from north to south (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Hornung and Sólysmos 2007</xref>), and the same pattern was observed for e.g. spiders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Koponen et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Koponen 2002</xref>) and ants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Gotelli and Ellison 2002</xref>) in peat bogs. Comparing our results with recent study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Farkas and Krčmar (2004)</xref> in the Danube and Drava floodplains where 11 isopod species were recorded using more pitfall traps and covering more different habitats, it seems that isopod diversity of the isolated Dubravica bog is not negligible.</p>
            <p>The greatest diversity of isopods in the current study was found exactly in the edge mainly due to the edge effect. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Hilty et al. (2006)</xref> ecotones are sites of high productivity and enhanced biodiversity. Furthermore, species richness of carabid beetles and ants were also highest at the edge in the Dubravica bog (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Brigić et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bujan et al. 2010</xref>). According to the nMDS analysis, forest and edge sites show high degree of similarity most likely due their vicinity. Although these two sites differ considerably in soil humidity, it seems that forest isopod species can successfully disperse into or even inhabit the edge zone. Bog replicate samples do not form a firm group and cluster near edge sites most likely due to the process of immigration.</p>
            <p>In our study, isopod activity density significantly differed between the bog and surrounding habitat (forest), being the lowest at the bog. This is in accordance with data from studies on other ground dwelling arthropods in peat bogs, e.g. carabid beetles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Främbs et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Nietupski et al. 2008</xref>). Most likely, the findings are influenced by sampling method, environmental variables (such as soil humidity, pH values, vegetation structure and density) and predation pressure. Pitfall traps are most commonly used in various ecological studies of ground dwelling arthropods, such as carabid beetles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Thiele 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Spence and Niemelä 1994</xref>) or spiders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Uetz and Unzicker 1976</xref>). However, pitfall trapping depends on the activity of an organism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Thiele 1977</xref>), therefore factors influencing arthropod activity, also affect the number of caught individuals. Consequently, cryptozoic isopod species that live under the stones, tree bark or in the soil were under sampled or are missing from our list (e.g. (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscus</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Haplophthalmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp.). Furthermore, lower isopod activity might be caused by the surface structure of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphagnum</tp:taxon-name></italic> mosses creating a thick carpet and hence some isopod species may not be recorded. Furthermore, heavy and large bodied bumbling isopods would easily fall into the pitfall traps, whereas smaller ones would more likely be able to stop themselves on the edge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Sutton 1972</xref>).</p>
            <p>The harsh environmental conditions, such as daily and annual temperature differences and low pH values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) might also have affected the isopod species richness and activity at the bog (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">Zimmer et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Tuf and Jeřábková 2008</xref>). Mostly due to large calcium demands for cuticular calcification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Sutton 1972</xref>), isopods prefer to inhabit more alkaline than acid habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">Wolters and Ekschmitt 1997</xref>). Hygropositive and photo-negative behaviour is known in isopods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Gunn 1937</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Waloff 1941</xref>) enabling them to inhabit most favourable environments. Our study reveals that isopod activity (total monthly catch) was positively correlated with soil temperature.<!--PageBreak--> Soil temperature fluctuates annually and daily and it is affected mainly by variations in air temperature (Zehng et al. 1993). Positive correlation could be the result of higher isopod’s activity during colonisation of more suitable microhabitats (i.e. from hot and drier environments to the ones with higher humidity level and lower temperatures; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Edney 1953</xref>). Similar trend was observed in correlation of isopod activity with soil humidity. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Gunn (1937)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Waloff (1941)</xref> have both shown that isopod’s activity has decreased at high humidity conditions. These conditions were present at the bog area, where we collected low number of isopod individuals. However, in the forest, pitfall traps were probably positioned in microhabitats with optimum ecological conditions and therefore higher numbers of individuals were collected. A comprehensive study applying additional sampling methods, such as hand collecting or extracting from soil samples with Tullgren apparatus, should provide more precise results.</p>
            <p>Except above mentioned grounds, predation might also influence isopod activity density at the bog. High population density of lycosid spiders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Štambuk and Erben 2002</xref>) and ants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bujan et al. 2010</xref>) were found at the studied bog. Both arthropod groups are common predators on isopods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Sutton 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Sunderland and Sutton 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Deslippe et al. 1996</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bujan et al. (2010)</xref> extremely high number of the ants was caught at the studied bog, precisely 13 584 individuals (while at both edge and forest sites less than 1000 individuals). Two ant species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmica rubra</tp:taxon-name></italic> L. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmica ruginodis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Nyl., accounted for 99% of the catch. These species prefer wet habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Seifert 1988</xref>) and their great colony density is most likely caused by specific way of colony founding-colony budding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Steiner et al. 2005</xref>), wherefore there is one big anthill present at the bog (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bujan et al. 2010</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Castillo and Kight (2005)</xref> showed that ant presence can influence both isopod behaviour (defensive and aversive behaviour) and reproductive success (shortening brooding period). Concerning the spiders, lycosid spiders were dominant members of the spider fauna at the bog and they made 72.7 % of the total catch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Štambuk and Erben 2002</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Sutton (1970)</xref> they have a low food capacity for isopods, although in a combination of their high population density and small living area they could be considered as significant predators on isopods.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus rathkii</tp:taxon-name></italic> was the dominant species at the bog. Its abundance decreased towards the forest where the soil humidity was lower comparing to other two sites. Furthermore, its habitat fidelity value was highest at the bog (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). As a widely distributed and common isopod species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus rathkii</tp:taxon-name></italic> inhabits different biotopes, including extreme ones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Gruner 1966</xref>), but prefers open places, and it is usually not found within woods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Schmidt 1997</xref>), which is in accordance with our study. This species is typical for flooded ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Farkas 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">Tuf and Tufová 2005</xref>) and it is common inhabitant of wetlands and peat bogs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Potočnik 1993</xref>). Throughout the experiments, it was observed that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus rathkii</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a high ability to survive under water and can therefore colonise such habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">Tufová and Tuf 2005</xref>). It was also found in few other bogs in Croatia (Antonović, unpublished data). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Judd (1963)</xref> recorded this species on the wooded slopes with no records in the bog area. However, that bog area was completely flooded and unfavourable for any terrestrial isopod species. In contrast to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus rathkii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trachelipus ratzeburgi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a sylvan species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Farkas et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">Tuf and Tufová 2005</xref>, <!--PageBreak--><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Farkas and Vilisics 2008</xref>), found in relatively low numbers in all explored sites, with highest abundance at the edge.</p>
            <p>Although species from the family <tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>, including <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyloniscus</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. are highly hygrophylic, and usually inhabit wetlands, species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyloniscus adonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is not abundant on the bog, but surprisingly on the edge. Due to bog’s inclination towards the edge, high, but relatively even soil humidity was recorded throughout the sampling period at the edge site. Hence, availability of microhabitats with optimum ecological conditions for this species, but also lower predation pressure from ants and lycosid spiders could explain its highest abundance at the edge.</p>
            <p>Among typical central European species, rather rare and less known isopod <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ligidium germanicum</tp:taxon-name></italic> was present at all study sites. It is highly hygrophylic species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Potočnik 1993</xref>), therefore the highest abundance at the bog site is expected.</p>
            <p>At all studied sites, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was one of the most frequent and numerous species. It was dominant species in the forest where the soil humidity content was considerably lower. It is a xerophilous species that prefers dryer habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Potočnik 1993</xref>). Additionally, it is sylvan species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Karaman 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Tomescu et al. 2008</xref>) inhabiting woodlands, where it is a constant and dominant element (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Karaman 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Farkas and Krčmar 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">Tuf and Tufová 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Farkas and Vilisics 2008</xref>). Therefore, it is not surprising that its habitat fidelity value was highest in the forest (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was also found in the bog. It seems that this species can easily enter the bog area especially during the summer, most likely due to the size of the bog and progressive vegetation succession (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). The activity of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was the highest in July and September. The soil temperatures in summer were the highest, but Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient was not statistically significant, therefore soil temperature is not the key factor for activity differences. The latter is in accordance with results of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Oberfrank et al. (2011)</xref>. The population study from north western Romania showed also two peaks in population’s dynamics, the first in April-May-June and the second in September-October (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Radu and Tomescu 1972</xref>). Such seasonal activity could possibly be explained by the facultative iteroparous univoltine reproductive strategy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Protracheoniscus politus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, having the reproductive season from May to August. Temporal pattern of sex ratio has its maximum (0.98 for males) by the end of April, during males-search and copulation, but the overall yearly sex ratio was around 0.27. Similar as in our study, the second reproductive peak with postmarsupial females was in July, and total female activity was highest in September (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Oberfrank et al. 2011</xref>). The presence of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Armadillidium carniolense</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a further sylvan species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Tomescu et al. 2002</xref>), at the bog area is an additional evidence of strong impact of vegetation succession on the bog, changing it into a drier habitat. Similar was observed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Štambuk and Erben (2002)</xref> during the study of the lycosid fauna. Although the lycosid fauna of the bog was relatively bog-specific, changes in the habitat structure resulted in higher abundance of some forest species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Štambuk and Erben 2002</xref>).</p>
            <p>Within the current and previous studies (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Judd 1963</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Blades and Marshall 1994</xref>), typical tyrphobiontic and tyrphophilous species were not recorded. On the contrary, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyloniscus adonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> could be considered as a potential tyrphoxenous species, since it<!--PageBreak--> showed some habitat preferences. Isopod fauna of peatlands is generally poorly investigated, hence further comprehensive studies providing more data on ecology of isopods inhabiting peat bogs are necessary.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Conclusions">
            <title>Conclusions</title>
            <p>This study reveals that vegetation succession has a strong impact on community composition of fauna inhabiting the peat bog. With overgrowth of the peat bog by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmica caerulea</tp:taxon-name></italic> grass, water level has significantly decreased. Therefore, the bog area becomes dryer, shaded and more suitable for forest species. Although there were no previous studies on isopod fauna, the presence of forest species indicates such changes in this habitat. Peat bog size and interspecific relationships, such as predation, also affected isopod species richness, activity density and diversity. Typical tyrphobiontic and tyrphophilous species were not observed, but further studies implying additional sampling methods should provide more detailed insight into isopod faunistics and ecology. In order to preserve suitable microclimatic conditions and biodiversity of the bog, management practices, like mowing, are required.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>We are very grateful to Ivan Tuf, Martin Zimmer and Ferenc Vilisics for providing us some papers, to Stefano Taiti for identification of <italic>Hyloniscus</italic>, to Renata Matoničkin Kepčija who helped us with statistical analysis, to Ana Previšić for English corrections and to anonymous reviewers for their critical comments and suggestions.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Anonymous</surname></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<source> Official Journal of the European Communities: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:1992:206:0007:0050:EN:PDF" xlink:type="simple">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:1992:206:0007:0050:EN:PDF</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blades</surname><given-names>DCA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Terrestrial arthropods of Canadian peatlands: synopsis of pan trap collections at four southern Ontario peatlands.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the Entomological Society of Canada </source> <volume>169</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>284</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/entm126169221-1" xlink:type="simple">10.4039/entm126169221-1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brigić</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alegro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sedlar</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Šegota</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Šoštarić</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vujčić-Karlo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Carabid beetles (Coleoptera, Carabidae) in Croatian peat bogs.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hengeveld</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noordijk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Opsteeg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermuelen</surname><given-names>HJW</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Carabid beetles as bioindicators, the use of ground beetles in ecological and environmental studies.</issue-title> <source>The usefulness and threats of methods used for monitoring species and populations. Book of abstracts, Westerbork (Netherlands), September 2009. Willem Beijerinck Biological Station</source>: <fpage>30</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchholz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hannig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schirmel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Ground beetle assemblages of peat bog remnants in Northwest Germany.</article-title> <source>Entomologia generalis </source> <volume>32</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bujan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brigić</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ješovnik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source> Ant diversity in Croatian peat bogs. In: Nash DR, den Boer SPA, De Fine Licht HH, Boomsma JJ (Eds) Book of abstracts. Meeting of the International Union for the Study of Social  Insects (IUSSI), Copenhagen (Denmark), August 2010. Clausen Offset ApS, 18.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kight</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Response of terrestrial isopods, <italic>Armadillidium vulgare</italic> and <italic>Porcellio laevis</italic> (Isopoda: Oniscidea) to the ant <italic>Tetramorium caespitum</italic>: morphology, behaviour and reproductive success.</article-title> <source>Invertebrate Reproduction and Development </source> <volume>47</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>183</fpage>-<lpage>190</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/07924259.2005.9652158" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/07924259.2005.9652158</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorley</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> PRIMER v6: User Manual/Tutorial.</source> <publisher-name>PRIMER-E</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Plymouth</publisher-loc>, <lpage>190</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dapkus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamutis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Assemblages of beetles (Coleoptera) in a peatbog and surrounding pineforest.</article-title> <source>Baltic Journal of Coleopterology </source> <volume>8</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Deslippe</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jelinski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Defense by use of a proteinaceous glue: woodlice vs. ants.</article-title> <source>Zoology </source> <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>-<lpage>210</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Edney</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1953</year>)<article-title> The temperature of woodlice in the sun.</article-title> <source>The Journal of Experimental Biology </source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>331</fpage>-<lpage>349</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdakov</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Efimov</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galaktionov</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sergeev</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> Quantitative evaluation of the fidelity of habitat.</article-title> <source>The Soviet Journal of Ecology </source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>-<lpage>295</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> Population dynamics, spatial distribution, and sex ratio of Trachelipus rathkei Brandst (Isopoda: Oniscidea) in a wetland forest by the Drava river.</article-title> <source>Israel Journal of Zoology </source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>323</fpage>-<lpage>331</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morschhauser</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Composition of isopod assemblages in different habitat types.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tajovský</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pižl</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Soil Zoology in Central Europe, České Budějovice (Czech Republic), April 1999.</issue-title> <source>ISB AS CR</source>: <fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krčmar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Terrestrial isopods (Isopoda: Oniscidea) of Baranya (Croatia).</article-title> <source>Natura Croatica </source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>161</fpage>-<lpage>170</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilisics</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Results of the field surveys on terrestrial isopods (Isopoda, Oniscidea) in the Drava basin, Croatia.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Purger</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>Biodiversity studies along the Drava river.</issue-title> <source>University of Pécs, Hungary</source>: <fpage>143</fpage>-<lpage>163</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Främbs</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dormann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mossakowski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Spatial Distribution of Carabid Beetles on Zehlau bog.</article-title> <source>Baltic Journal of Coleopterology </source> <volume>2</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gotelli</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellison</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Biogeography at a regional scale: determinants of ants species density in New England bogs and forests.</article-title> <source>Ecology </source> <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>1604</fpage>-<lpage>1609</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1890/0012-9658(2002)083[1604:BAARSD]2.0.CO;2" xlink:type="simple">10.1890/0012-9658(2002)083[1604:BAARSD]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruner</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1966</year>)<article-title> Krebstiere order Crustacea. V. Isopoda.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalll</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>Die Tierwe1t Deutschlands 53.</issue-title> <source>Gustav Fischer, Iena</source>: <fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>380</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1937</year>)<article-title> The humidity reaction of the woodlouse, <italic>Porcellio scaber</italic> (Latreille).</article-title> <source>The  Journal of Experimental Biology </source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>-<lpage>186</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilty</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lidicker</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merenlender</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> Corridor Ecology: the science and practice of linking landscapes for biodiversity conservation.</source> <publisher-name>Island Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc>, <lpage>323</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> The ground beetle (Coleoptera, Carabidae) fauna of welsh peatland biotopes: factors influencing the distribution of ground beetles and conservation implications.</article-title> <source>Biological Conservation </source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0006-3207(93)90504-T" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/0006-3207(93)90504-T</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sólymos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> Macroecology and biogeography of terrestrial isopods in Europe: a preliminary report. In: Abstracts Volume of the 7 the International Symposium on the Biology of Terrestrial Isopods. Tunis (Tunisia), March 2007. Unité de Recherche  de Biologie Animale et Systématique Evolutive, Faculté de Sciences de Tunis, 24.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Horvat</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1939</year>)<article-title> Prilog poznavanja cretova u Hrvatskom zagorju.</article-title> <source>Hrvatski geografski glasnik </source> <volume>8</volume> (<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hršak</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Vegetation succession at acidic fen near Dubravica in the Hrvatsko zagorje region.</article-title> <source>Natura Croatica </source> <volume>5</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Judd</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<article-title> Studies of the Byron Bog in Southwestern Ontario. XIV. Observations on Sowbugs <italic>Cylisticus convexus</italic> (Degeer) and <italic>Tracheoniscus rathkei</italic> (Brandt) (Isopoda: Oniscidae).</article-title> <source>Ecology </source> <volume>44</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>615</fpage>-<lpage>617</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1932554" xlink:type="simple">10.2307/1932554</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Karaman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<article-title> Beitrag zur Kenntnis der Gattung <italic>Protracheoniscus</italic>, Verhoeff 1918 (Crustacea, Isopoda Terrestria).</article-title> <source>Buletin i Punimeve Shkencore </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Koponen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Relys</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dapkus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Changes in structure of ground-living spider (Araneae) communities on peatbogs along a transect from Lithuania to Lapland.</article-title> <source>NorwegianJournal ofEntomology </source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>174</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Koponen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<source> Ground-living spiders in bogs in northern Europe. Journal of Arachnology</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>262</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindenmayer</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> Habitat Fragmentation and Landscape Change, An ecological and conservation synthesis.</source> <publisher-name>Island Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc>, <lpage>352</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nietupski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciepielewska</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosewska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Assemblages of epigeic carabidae (Col.) in a peatbog nature reserve situated in an urban area.</article-title> <source>Polish Journal of Natural Sciences </source> <volume>23</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>611</fpage>-<lpage>623</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2478/v10020-008-0048-5" xlink:type="simple">10.2478/v10020-008-0048-5</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyilas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> <year>1994</year> <source>Habitat distribution of <italic>Brachinus</italic> species in alkaline and salty steppes and loess grassland (Coleoptera, Crabidae). In: Desender K, Dufrene M, Loreau M, Luff ML, Maelfait JP (Eds) Carabidae Beetles, Ecology and Evolution. 8<sup>th</sup> European Carabidologists Meeting, Louvain (Belgium), September 1992. Kluwer Academic Publishers, Dordrecht, 193–199.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberfrank</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Végh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Reproductive strategy of <italic>Protracheoniscus politus</italic> (C. Koch, 1841) (Oniscidea: Crinocheta: Agnaridae).</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zidar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Štrus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Proceedings of the 8th International Symposium of Terrestrial Isopod Biology – ISTIB 2011, Bled (Slovenia), June 2011.</issue-title> <source>University of Ljubljana, Biotechnical faculty, Department of Biology, Ljubljana</source>, <fpage>135</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Peus</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1932</year>)<article-title> Die Tierwelt der Moore unter besonderer Berücksichtigung der europäischen Hochmoore.</article-title> <source>Handbook Moorkunde (Berlin) </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>277</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Potočnik</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<source> Faunistic and ecological studies of woodlice (Isopoda Terrestria) in a part of Southeastern Europe. PhD thesis, Zagreb, Croatia: University of Zagreb.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Radu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomescu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Studiul populaţiei de <italic>Protracheoniscus politus</italic> (Crustacea, Isopoda) într-o pădure de foioase.</article-title> <source>StudiaUniversitatis Babeş-Bolyai, Biologia </source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roubal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1934</year>)<article-title> Die Coleopterenwelt (Tyrphobionte, Tyrphophile, Tyrphoxene, etc.) der Treboner (Wittingauer) Moore.</article-title> <source>Folia Zoologica et Hydrobiologica </source> <volume>7</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>56</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rydin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeglum</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> The biology of peatlands.</source> <publisher-name>Oxford University Press Inc.</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <lpage>343</lpage> pp.doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780198528722.001.0001" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/acprof:oso/9780198528722.001.0001</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sallai</surname><given-names>Á</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Ecofaunistical investigations in a boggy forest in the Protected Landscape Area at Ócsa (Kiskunság National Park, Hungary).</article-title> <source>Opuscula Zooologica (Budapest) </source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmalfuss</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>)<article-title> Morphology and function of cuticular micro-scales and corresponding structures in terrestrial isopods (Crust., Isop., Oniscidea).</article-title> <source>Zoomorphology </source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>-<lpage>274</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF00999815" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/BF00999815</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Revision of the European species of the genus <italic>Trachelipus</italic> Budde-Lund, 1908 (Crustacea: Isopoda: Oniscidea).</article-title> <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society </source> <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>129</fpage>-<lpage>244</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.1997.tb00337.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1096-3642.1997.tb00337.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> A Taxonomic Revision of the <italic>Myrmica</italic> Species of Europe, Asia Minor, and Caucasia (Hymenoptera, Formicidae).</article-title> <source>Abhandlungen und Berichte des Naturkundemuseums Görlitz </source> <volume>62</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niemelä</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Sampling carabid assemblages with pitfall traps: the madness and the method.</article-title> <source>The Canadian Entomologist </source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>881</fpage>-<lpage>894</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/Ent126881-3" xlink:type="simple">10.4039/Ent126881-3</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danks</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Insect biodiversity of boreal peat bogs.</article-title> <source>Annual Review of  Entomology </source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ento.51.110104.151036" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.ento.51.110104.151036</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B44"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlick-Steiner</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konrad</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moder</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crozier</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stauffer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buschinger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> No sympatric speciation here: multiple data sources show that the ant <italic>Myrmica microrubra</italic> is not a separate species but an alternate.</article-title> <source>European Society for Evolutionary Biology </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>-<lpage>787</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B45"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sunderland</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> A serological study of arthropod predation on woodlice in a dune grassland ecosystem.</article-title> <source>Journal of Animal Ecology </source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>987</fpage>-<lpage>1004</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/4240" xlink:type="simple">10.2307/4240</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B46"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> Predation on woodlice; an investigation using the precipitin test.</article-title> <source>Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata </source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>285</lpage>.doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1570-7458.1970.tb00111.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1570-7458.1970.tb00111.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B47"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<source> Woodlice.</source> <publisher-name>Ginn &amp; Company Limited</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>144</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B48"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Škorić</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<source> Manual for pedological investigations.</source> <publisher-name>Faculty of Agriculture</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Zagreb</publisher-loc>, <lpage>172</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B49"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Štambuk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erben</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Wolf spiders (Araneae: Lycosidae) on the overgrowing peat bog in Dubravica (north-western Croatia).</article-title> <source>Arachnologische Mitteilungen </source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B50"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tajovský</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> Diversity of terrestrial isopods (Oniscidea) in flooded and nonflooded ecosystems of southern Moravia, Czech Republic.</article-title> <source>Israel Journal of Zoology </source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>311</fpage>-<lpage>322</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B51"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>)<source> Carabid Beetles in Their Environments. Zoophysiology and Ecology 10.</source> <publisher-name>Springer Verlag</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>, <lpage>369</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B52"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomescu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mureşan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Popa</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Faunistic and ecological researches on the terrestrial isopods from the superior sector of the Arieş river basin.</article-title> <source>Studia Universitatis Babeş-Bolyai, Biologia </source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B53"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomescu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogdan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Covaciu-Marcov</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Terrestrial Isopods from the Western and North-Western Romania.</article-title> <source>Studia Universitatis Babes–Bolyai, Biologia </source> <volume>53</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B54"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Topić</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stančić</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Extinction of fen and bog plants and their habitats in Croatia.</article-title> <source>Biodiversity and Conservation </source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>3371</fpage>-<lpage>3381</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10531-005-4874-2" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10531-005-4874-2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B55"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Topić</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vukelić</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Priručnik za određivanje kopnenih staništa u Hrvatskoj prema Direktivi o staništima EU.</source> <publisher-name>Državni zavod za zaštitu prirode</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Zagreb</publisher-loc>, <lpage>376</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B56"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuf</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Development of the community structure of terrestrial isopods (Isopoda, Oniscidea) after a summer flood.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sfenthourakis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Araujo</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmalfuss</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taiti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szlavecz</surname></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <issue-title>Biology of terrestrial isopods 5.</issue-title> <source>Proceedings of the 5th international symposium on the biology of terrestrial isopods, Crete (Greece), May 2001. Brill</source>: <fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>242</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B57"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuf</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tufová</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Communities of terrestrial isopods (Crustacea: Isopoda: Oniscidea) in epigeon of oak-hornbeam forests of SW Slovakia.</article-title> <source>Ekológia (Bratislava) </source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>-<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B58"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuf</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeřábková</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Diurnal epigeic activity of terrestrial isopods (Isopoda: Oniscidea).</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charfi-Cheikhrouha</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taiti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Proceedings of the International Symposium of Terrestrial Isopod Biology – ISTIB-07.</issue-title> <source>IV. Behaviour, Tunisia (Tunis), March 2007. Shaker Verlag GmbH, Germany</source>, <fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>172</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B59"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tufová</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuf</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Survival under water – comparative study of millipedes (Diplopoda), centipedes (Chilopoda) and terrestrial isopods (Oniscidea).</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tajovský</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlaghamerský</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pižl</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Contributions to Soil Zoology in Central Europe I, České Budějovice (Czech Republic), April 2005.</issue-title> <source>ISB AS CR</source>: <fpage>195</fpage>-<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B60"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Uetz</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Unzicker</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>)<article-title> Pitfall trapping in ecological studies of wandering spiders.</article-title> <source>Journal of Arachnology </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B61"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vadkerti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> The terrestrial isopod fauna of the Rinya region IV. Szilonics-puszta.</article-title> <source>Natura Somogyiensis </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B62"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilisics</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sólymos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> A preliminary study on habitat features and associated terrestrial isopod species. In: Tajovský K, Schlaghamerský J, Pižl V (Eds) Contributions to Soil Zoology in Central Europe II: 195–199.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B63"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Waloff</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1941</year>)<article-title> The mechanism of humidity reactions of terrestrial isopods.</article-title> <source>The Journal of Experimental Biology </source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>118</fpage>-<lpage>135</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B64"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolters</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekschmitt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Gastropods, Isopods, Diplopods, and Chilopods: Neglected Groups of Decomposer Food Web.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Benckiser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>Fauna in Soil Ecosystems: recycling processes, nutrient fluxes, and agriculture production.</issue-title> <source>Marcel Dekker, Inc., New York</source>: <fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>281</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B65"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Running</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> A daily soil temperature model based on air temperature and precipitation for continental applications.</article-title> <source>Climate Research </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>-<lpage>191</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3354/cr002183" xlink:type="simple">10.3354/cr002183</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B66"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brauckmann</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Broll</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topp</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Correspondence analytical evaluation of factors that influence soil macro-arthropod distribution in abandoned grassland.</article-title> <source>Pedobiologia </source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>695</fpage>-<lpage>704</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1078/S0031-4056(04)70082-7" xlink:type="simple">10.1078/S0031-4056(04)70082-7</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>