<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.254.4043</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Two new genera and species of the termite symbiont lineage Termitohospitini (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Aleocharinae) from Bolivia and peninsular Malaysia</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Kanao</surname>
                        <given-names>Taisuke</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:38A7BB31-AD25-4C09-B8DC-47535DC5D417</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Eldredge</surname>
                        <given-names>K. Taro</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:682046BE-35EB-4228-807A-D6888BE7081C</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Maruyama</surname>
                        <given-names>Munetoshi</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:2F8BEE60-1C25-42BB-8D59-AA71D7EB7141</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Entomological Laboratory, Graduate School of Bioresource and Bioenvironmental Sciences, Kyushu University, Fukuoka, 812-8581 Japan
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, and Division of Entomology Biodiversity Institute, 1501 Crestline Dr., Suite 140, University of Kansas, Lawrence, KS 66045-2811, U. S. A.
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>The Kyushu University Museum, Fukuoka, 812-8581 Japan
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Taisuke Kanao (<email xlink:type="simple">kanatai1225@gmail.com</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: J. Klimaszewski</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>21</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>254</issue>
            <fpage>67</fpage>
            <lpage>87</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>26</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>5</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Taisuke Kanao, K. Taro Eldredge, Munetoshi Maruyama</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:0A80E5CF-3E19-4CE5-BD5F-548F659AEF91</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermocola clavicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>gen. &amp; sp. n.</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotermitosocius bolivianus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>gen. &amp; sp. n.</bold> of the termite inquilinous tribe <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> are described from peninsular Malaysia and Bolivia, respectively. The <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> are most readily diagnosable by the distally migrated anterior tentorial pits that are no longer associated with the antennal fossae, and by the enlarged vertex which obscures the antennal fossae dorsally. Additionally, the <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> are hypothesized to share a recent common ancestor with the <tp:taxon-name>Masuriini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Myllaenini</tp:taxon-name> due to shared derived morphologies of the lacinia distal teeth with lateral cuticular processes, presence of a unique maxillary palpomere III sensilla, and anterolateral angles of mentum produced. Habitus photographs and illustrations of diagnostic features are provided for the two new genera in order to facilitate future work.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><italic>Coptotermes</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>Hetairotermitina</kwd>
                <kwd>Termitohospitina</kwd>
                <kwd>limuloid</kwd>
                <kwd>Masuriini</kwd>
                <kwd>Myllaenini</kwd>
                <kwd>physogastry</kwd>
                <kwd>termitophily</kwd>
<!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Eusocial insect colonies are often accompanied by a unique faunal assembly that takes advantage of available colony resources (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Hölldobler and Wilson 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Wheeler 1928</xref>). Symbionts of termites are commonly referred to as termitophiles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Kistner 1969</xref>). A large number of termitophiles have evolved within the beetle family <tp:taxon-name>Staphylinidae</tp:taxon-name>, particularly in lineages of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Aleocharinae</tp:taxon-name>. Among the recognized 58 tribes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bouchard et al. 2011</xref>), 1,151 genera and 12,851 species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Thayer 2005</xref>) of <tp:taxon-name>Aleocharinae</tp:taxon-name>, approximately 650 species and 190 genera among 17 tribes have recorded associations with termites, of which eleven tribes are comprised exclusively of termitophilous species (Kanao unpublished data).</p>
            <p>Termitophilous <tp:taxon-name>Aleocharinae</tp:taxon-name> that exhibit relatively complex symbiosis with their host termites have repeatedly converged on physogastric and limuloid body plans (e.g. Figs 24–27). Physogastry is the result of abdominal or thoracic inflation and is hypothesized to serve a mimetic function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Kistner 1969</xref>). Physogastric species are generally well integrated into the termite social system, actively interacting with their hosts and slow moving. On the other hand, limuloid taxa are teardrop-shaped and the body plan is hypothesized to serve a defensive function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Kistner 1979</xref>). Limuloid taxa often also exhibit extremely compact appendages and cavities to receive structures more vulnerable to host aggression (e.g. distal podomeres). In contrast to physogastric species, limuloid species are faster moving and usually do not actively interact with their hosts.</p>
            <p>Among the aleocharine termitophiles, the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> Seevers, 1941 is comprised exclusively of termite symbiotic species. This tribe was originally proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Seevers (1941)</xref> to separate a handful of Neotropical termitophilous species of the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Bolitocharini</tp:taxon-name> (presently <tp:taxon-name>Homalotini</tp:taxon-name> Heer, 1839). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Seevers (1957)</xref> later expanded <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> to include termitophiles from other biogeographic regions based on the 4-4-5 tarsal formula and proposed four subtribes: <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitina</tp:taxon-name> Seevers, 1941 for Neotropical members; <tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermitina</tp:taxon-name> Seevers, 1957 for Australian and Oriental members; <tp:taxon-name>Termitospectrina</tp:taxon-name> Seevers, 1957 for Pantropical members; <tp:taxon-name>Termitusina</tp:taxon-name> Seevers, 1957 for Ethiopian members. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Kistner and Jacobson (1976)</xref> subsequently raised <tp:taxon-name>Termitusina</tp:taxon-name> to tribe with <tp:taxon-name>Termitospectrina</tp:taxon-name> as a subtribe within it, based on 4-articled maxillary and 3-articled labial palpi. Therefore, <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> is presently divided into two subtribes, <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitina</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermitina</tp:taxon-name>. <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitina</tp:taxon-name> includes 15 species distributed among five genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Mann 1923</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Silvestri 1947</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Seevers 1957</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Borgmeier 1959</xref>) and <tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermitina</tp:taxon-name> includes 21 species distributed among seven genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Lea 1910</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Cameron 1920</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">1950</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Seevers 1957</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Kistner 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">1976</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Abdel-Galil and Kistner 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Roisin and Pasteels 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Oke 1933</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Pace 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Maruyama and Iwata 2002</xref>).</p>
            <p>Most species of <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> ancestrally share a limuloid body form but a few taxa have secondarily evolved physogastric forms (Kanao et al. in preparation). Notably, the species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptoxenus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kistner, 1976 exhibits physogastry of the thorax, a peculiar condition among aleocharines. With a diversity of body forms, the tribe offers a unique opportunity to study the independent evolution of adaptive morphologies<!--PageBreak--> as it correlates with integration and behavior with host termite societies. However, as with most termitophiles, basic understanding of <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> biodiversity lags behind that of their free-living relatives. Inquilinous groups are difficult to collect and relatively few specimens are available for comprehensive understanding of their biodiversity. Here we describe two new genera and species of <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> as part of our ongoing research on the evolution of termitophily in termitohospitines. We provide habitus photographs, illustrations of diagnostic features, a new tribal diagnosis as an update to previous diagnoses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Seevers 1941</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">1957</xref>), and putative synapomorphies that support a close relationship of <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> with <tp:taxon-name>Masuriini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Myllaenini</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods">
            <title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>The first author conducted fieldwork at Ulu Gombak, which is approximately 25 km northwest of Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia in 2010, 2011 and 2012. Specimens of a new genus collected at the site for this study were initially preserved in 2.0 ml vials of 80% ethanol. The other undescribed genus was discovered in the Snow Entomological Museum Collection at the University of Kansas.</p>
            <p>The technical procedures used for this study generally follow those described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Maruyama (2006)</xref>. When a permanent mount was made, cleared specimens or parts were dehydrated by successively transferring specimens to higher ethanol (EtOH) concentrations until finally reaching 100% EtOH, and then placed into Euparal. When appropriate, dissections were made within Euparal on a glass mounting substrate. Full body dissections were made and preserved on glass microscope slides. Dissected body parts were preserved and mounted on halved glass cover slips, subsequently glued onto a halved paper glue board, and mounted under the respective specimen (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Maruyama 2004</xref>, for details).</p>
            <p>In the descriptions, macrochaetotaxy formulas depict raw numbers of setae and not the numbers of setal pairs. Additionally, the number of macrosetae on tergite IX and X refers to one side of the body and therefore the numbers of setal pairs.</p>
            <table-wrap position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Table 1.</label>
                <caption><p> Checklist of described species of <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name>. Asterisks indicate type species.</p></caption>
                <table id="T1">
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tribe <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name></bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Subtribe <tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermitina</tp:taxon-name> </bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptophysa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Roisin &amp; Pasteels, 1990</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptophysa obesa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Roisin &amp; Pasteels, 1990</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptophysella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Roisin &amp; Pasteels, 1990</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptophysella pulposa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Roisin &amp; Pasteels, 1990</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermocola</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n.</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermocola clavicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptoxenus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kistner, 1976</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptoxenus thronileyi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kistner, 1976</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cameron, 1920</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes agilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cameron, 1920</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kistner, 1970</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes bryanti</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cameron, 1950</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes capitalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kistner, 1970</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes gayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kistner, 1970</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes greavesi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kistner, 1970</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes barretti</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cameron, 1950</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes hirsutus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kistner, 1970</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes insulanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1957</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes latevricola</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Lea, 1910) *</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kistner, 1970</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes piceus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cameron, 1920</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hetairotermes punctiventris</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Lea, 1910)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Japanophilus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Maruyama &amp; Iwata, 2002</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Japanophilus hojoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Maruyama &amp; Iwata, 2002</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sinophilus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kistner, 1985</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sinophilus rougemonti</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pace, 1993</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sinophilus xiai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kistner, 1985 *</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sinophilus yukoae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Maruyama &amp; Iwata, 2002</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitobra</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1957</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitobra perinthoides</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1957</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Subtribe <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitina</tp:taxon-name></bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Blapticoxenus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mann, 1923</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Blapticoxenus brunneus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mann, 1923</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Noetermitosocius</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n.</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Noetermitosocius bolivianus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paratermitosocius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1941</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paratermitosocius vestitus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Mann, 1923)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitohospes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1941</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitohospes brasiliana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1957</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitohospes guianae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1941</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitohospes limulus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1957</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitohospes miricroniger</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1941 *</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitohospes nitens</tp:taxon-name></italic> Borgmeier, 1959</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitohospes panamensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1941</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitohospes punctulatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Borgmeier, 1959</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitohospes silvestrii</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1957</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitohospes tachyporoides</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1957</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitohospes unicolor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Silvestri, 1947)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitosodails</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1941</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitosodails barticae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1941 *</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitosodails fasciatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Silvestri, 1947)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitosocius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1941</bold></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitosocius microps</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1941</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="tribe">Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Seevers, 1941</tp:taxon-authority>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type genus">
                    <title>Type genus:</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitohospes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1941.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Members of the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> most closely resemble the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Myllaenini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Masuriini</tp:taxon-name> (<italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Ahn and Ashe 2004</xref>), and are hypothesized to be closely related based on the following combination of putative synapomorphies: 1) subapical marginal setae of maxillary lacinia with basal, paired cuticular processes (spinose scales of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Ahn and Ashe 2004</xref>); 2) presence of a unique sensory patch on lateral surface of maxillary palpomere III; 3) anterolateral angles of mentum produced.</p>
                    <p>Species of <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> are diagnosable from all other <tp:taxon-name>Aleocharinae</tp:taxon-name>, including <tp:taxon-name>Myllaenini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Masuriini</tp:taxon-name>, by the following putative synapomorphies: 1) anterior tentorial arms of the head migrated anteriorly and disassociated from antennal fossae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Seevers 1941</xref>); 2) antennal fossae dorsally obscured by enlarged vertex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Seevers 1941</xref>); 3) maxillary lacinia with basal paired cuticular processes reduced in size; 4) processes of anterolateral angles of mentum reduced in size; 5) ligula broad and reduced in length.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Neotermitosocius</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7CEBD279-F24B-4BA5-A2F6-2496848C786E</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Neotermitosocius</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Kanao, Eldredge &amp; Maruyama</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                    <title>Type species:</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotermitosocius bolivianus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This monotypic genus is distinguishable from other <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> by its slender parallel-sided body, longer legs and apically truncate pronotum, which dorsally exposes much of the head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Overall shape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) parallel-sided and somewhat dorsoventrally flattened. Posterior one-fifth of head covered by pronotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>) transverse, widest at eyes. Antennal fossae deep, partially dorsally obscured by vertex. Eyes large and produced anterolaterally. Antennae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>) with 11 articles; antennal articles compact and article pedicles scarcely visible externally; antennomeres I and XI longest; antennomere I partially obscured by enlarged antennal fossae; antennomere II approximately three times longer than wide, dilated at apex, narrower than other articles; antennomere III trapezoidal, apex twice as wide as base; antennomere IV trapezoidal, slightly shorter than antennomere III; antennomere V–X successively widening distally; antennomere XI narrowed apically. Labrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 5</xref>) transverse, with pores at middle, anterior margin of membranous area concave; epipharynx (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 5</xref>) relatively smooth, midline with pores from apex to middle. Mandibles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 6–7</xref>) almost symmetrical, apex acute, dorsally covered with numerous pores, with anterior one-fifth curved adorally, moderately developed tooth present at middle of adoral margin, base of scrobe strongly laterally developed. Right mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 7</xref>) apex slightly more acute. Maxillary (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 8</xref>) lacinia elongate, adorally with 11 strong setae; apical three setae shortest, preceding basal three setae with cuticular processes (spinose scale of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Ahn and Ashe 2004</xref>) on either side of base; galea as long as lacinia, slightly dilated apically, apex densely setulate; palpus with 4 articles; article I trapezoidal; article II oval, narrowed at base; article III approximately twice as long as article II, more than three times longer than wide, widest at middle, sparsely covered with long setae, sensory <!--PageBreak-->patch near middle of lateral surface; article IV narrow and parallel-sided, approximately one-fourth as wide as apical margin of article III; pseudosegment poorly delimited and inconspicuous. Mentum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 9</xref>) trapezoidal, sparsely covered with setae and small pseudopores; anterior margin bisinuate, with a pair of long setae at middle; anterolateral corners produced and with 2 long setae; posterior margin almost straight. Labial palpus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>) with 3 articles, first article a fusion of I + II; article I + II with a seta (probably homologous with seta h of Sawada [1972]) at outer medial margin, twin and medial pores present; article III half as long as article I, with a pore at anterolateral corner; ligula triangular with posterior half sclerotized; prementum wider than long, disc with a pair of setal pores and two pair of real pores present; apodemes broad and longer than disc, dilated posteriorly with apices recurved internally and almost touching.</p>
                    <p>Pronotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 11</xref>) transverse, widest near middle; anterior margin broadly concave; posterior margin slightly rounded. Prosternum reduced in length. Elytra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 12</xref>) subquadrate, longer than wide with lateral margin deflexed. Wings fully developed. Mesoventrite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 13</xref>) short, approximately half as long as metaventrite; mesoventral<!--PageBreak--> process developed posteriorly and carinate; mesocoxal cavity narrowly separated and marginal bead complete. Legs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 14–16</xref>) overall slender; tarsal formula 4-4-5; tarsomeres slender and parallel-sided. Fore leg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 14</xref>) with coxa subequal in length to femur; trochanter subtriangular; femur narrowed apically; tibia thin; tarsomeres I–III <!--PageBreak-->subequal in length, tarsomere IV longer. Mid leg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 15</xref>) with coxa oval; trochanter small; femur narrowed apically; tibia thin, slightly dilated subapically, one macroseta present on dorsal surface; tarsomeres subequal in length. Hind leg with coxa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 16</xref>) subtriangular; trochanter subtriangular, macroseta present on anterior surface; femur slightly narrowed apically; tibia thin, slightly dilated apically; tarsomere I longer than II + III combined, tarsomere V twice as long as IV.</p>
                    <p>Abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–2</xref>) narrowed posteriorly. Segment I represented only by tergite I fused to metanotum. Segment II represented only by tergite II. Segments III–VII with 1 tergite, 1 sternite, and 2 pairs of paratergites respectively. Tergite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 17</xref>) narrowed posteriorly, posterior margin slightly medially produced. Sternite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 18</xref>) with posterior margin rounded. Tergite IX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 19</xref>) fully subdivided dorsally by tergite X; tergite X (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 19</xref>) fully divided medially to base. Tergite X divided, only connected each other and tergite IX on anterior margin.</p>
                    <p>Median lobe of aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–21</xref>) with basal capsule bulbous, more than three times as wide as apical lobe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 20</xref>), paramerally expanded (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 21</xref>). Paramere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 22</xref>) with a structure appearing homologous to Seevers’ (1978) medial phragma produced apically; apical lobe extremely elongate and tapered apically, subequal in length to paramerite, single seta present. Spermatheca (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 23</xref>) long and coiled.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The generic name is derived from a combination of <italic>Neo</italic>, Greek for “new” and the name of a similar-looking genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Termitosocius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seevers, 1941. The gender is masculine.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Neotermitosocius</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">bolivianus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1625FEFE-B75F-4C81-A9F9-65DAA629F1E5</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Neotermitosocius_bolivianus</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Kanao, Eldredge &amp; Maruyama</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">–23</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                    <title>Type material.</title>
                    <p><italic>Holotype</italic>: ♂, “BOLIVIA: Cochabamba/117 km E Yungas/(Cochabamba-Villa Tunari Rd)/<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">17°6'32"S; 65°41'12"W</named-content>/ca. 1,040 m alt., 1–6-II-1999; R. Hanley ex. flight/intercept trap BOL1H99 028//SMO754884/KUNHM-ENT”.</p>
                    <p><italic>Paratypes</italic>: 2♂♂, ♀, same date and locality data as holotype (♂, SEMC barcode number “SMO75489”, completely disarticulated; ♂, SEMC barcode number “SMO75488”, abdominal segments VII–X dissected off; ♀, SEMC barcode number “SMO754880”, head and abdominal segments VIII–X dissected, spermatheca not recovered). ♂, ♀, ?, same locality data as the holotype, differing data reads “8–10-II-1999”, “BOL1H99 062” (♂, SEMC barcode number “SMO 754864”, abdominal segments VIII–X dissected off; ♀, SEMC barcode number “SMO754858”, completely disarticulated; ♀, SEMC barcode number “SMO754860”, right antennomeres VI–XI and abdominal segments VIII–X dissected off; ♀, SEMC barcode number “SMO754863” and additional label reading “Termitohospitini/new genus/det. K. T. Eldredge 2011”, abdominal segments VIII–X dissected off; ?, SEMC barcode number “SMO754857”, hind wings removed); ♂, “BOLIVIA: Cochabamba/117 km E.<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> Cochabamba, ai/Lagunitas, 1000m, 17°6'22"S/65°40'57"W, 6–8-II-1999/F. Genier, mountain evergreen/forest, ex. flight intercept trap/99-037// SMO754908/KUNHM-ENT”, completely disarticulated.</p>
                    <p>All type specimens are deposited in the Snow Entomological Museum Collection (SEMC).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is diagnosable based on the generic diagnosis above.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–2</xref>) approximately 2 mm in length (1.84–2.00 mm, N = 2), almost uniformly orange brown, but head slightly darker. Dorsal surface of head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>) sparsely covered with setae, a pair of long setae present at anterior margin of clypeus. Eyes with uniform cover of inter-ommatidial setae. Antennae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>) sparsely covered with setae; antennomere I with a long macroseta at middle of internal lateral surface; antennomere II with 4–5 macrosetae around apical margin, one macroseta conspicuously longer; antennomere III with 4 thick, very long macrosetae at apical margin; antennomeres IV–X with 3–4 macrosetae around apical margin; antennomere XI with several macrosetae near middle and apex. Labrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 5</xref>) dorsal surface with 2 pairs of setae at anterolateral corners, 3 pairs of longer and 3 pairs of shorter setae at mesal area of disc; epipharynx (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 5</xref>) with two pairs of lateral setulae. Mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 6–7</xref>) dorsum with 2 pairs of scrobal setae near middle of aboral margin, six setae around base of disc. Maxillary (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 8</xref>) lacinia with 2 pores at middle; galea with 3 pores apicomedially; maxillary palpal article I with a long seta at lateral margin and a medial pore, article II sparsely covered with setae, article III sparsely covered with setae and 2 stronger setae medially.</p>
                    <p>Pronotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 11</xref>) transverse (pronotum length = 0.30–0.40 mm, pronotum width = 0.54–0.72 mm, N = 7), densely covered with setae, with a pair of long macrosetae at anterolateral corners. Elytra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 12</xref>) longer than wide (elytra length = 0.42–0.44 mm, elytra width = 0.30–0.34 mm, N = 5), densely covered with setae, setae of lateral margins longer. Mesoventrite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 13</xref>) sparsely covered with minute setae at central and posterolateral areas. Metaventrite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 13</xref>) posterior one third sparsely covered with setae. Fore leg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 14</xref>) uniformly covered with setae; coxa with a macroseta near dorsomedial of anterior surface and 5–6 long setae at apical margin; femur with longer setae near anterior inner margin; tibia with apical setae stronger, 2 spurs present at apex. Mid leg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 15</xref>) uniformly covered with setae except coxa; coxa with several long setae around anterior margin; tibia with long macroseta at middle on dorsal surface, 3 spurs present at apex. Hind leg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 16</xref>) uniformly covered with setae, coxa medially nude; coxa with 3 longer setae along cavity; trochanter and femur with a macroseta near middle of anterior surface; tibia with one longer and shorter macroseta on anterior surface, 3 apical spurs present.</p>
                    <p>Tergites and paratergites III–VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">, 17</xref>) sparsely covered with setae. Macrochaetotaxy of abdominal tergites III–VIII = 0-0-2-2-0-2. Sternite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 18</xref>) sparsely covered with setae; 3 pairs of macrosetae present, 2 pairs at mediolateral margin and one near apex. Tergite IX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 19</xref>) with pores around anterior margin, several setae near middle of disc, 2 pairs of macrosetae at mediolateral margin and apex present. Tergite X (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 19</xref>) covered in setae, 4 longer setae at apex, 2 pairs of macrosetae present at mediolateral margin and apex.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak--><italic>Male</italic>. Median lobe of aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">, 21</xref>) copulatory piece flagellate, suspensoria associated with lateral base of copulatory piece. Paramere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 22</xref>) apical lobe with pores at base.</p>
                    <p><italic>Female</italic>. Spermatheca (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 23</xref>) cuticle at apex with wrinkle-like sculpture.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–2.</label>
                        <caption><p>Habitus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotermitosocius bolivianus</tp:taxon-name></italic><bold>.</bold> <bold>1</bold> dorsal view <bold>2</bold> ventral view. </p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-254-067-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 3–4.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotermitosocius bolivianus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <bold>3</bold> head capsule, left side = dorsal view, right side = ventral view <bold>4</bold> antenna.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-254-067-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 5–10.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotermitosocius bolivianus</tp:taxon-name></italic> mouthparts. <bold>5</bold> labrum, left side = labrum, right side = epipharynx <bold>6</bold> left mandible, dorsal view <bold>7</bold> right mandible, dorsal view <bold>8</bold> maxilla, ventral view <bold>9</bold> mentum, ventral view <bold>10</bold> labium in ventral view.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-254-067-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 11–16.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotermitosocius bolivianus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, thorax and legs. <bold>11</bold> pronotum, left side with setae <bold>12</bold> elytron, left <bold>13</bold> meso- and metaventrites, anatomical left side with setae <bold>14</bold> fore leg, posterior surface <bold>15</bold> mid leg, anterior surface <bold>16</bold> hind leg, anterior surface.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-254-067-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 17–23.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotermitosocius bolivianus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, abdominal sclerites and genitalia. <bold>17</bold> tergite VIII <bold>18</bold> sternite VIII <bold>19</bold> tergites IX–X <bold>20</bold> median lobe of aedeagus, aparameral view <bold>21</bold> median lobe of aedeagus, lateral view <bold>22</bold> paramere, external view <bold>23</bold> spermatheca.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-254-067-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific epithet is derived from its type locality of Bolivia Latinized. The gender is masculine.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Cochabamba, Bolivia.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Ecology">
                    <title>Ecology.</title>
                    <p>All known specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotermitosocius bolivianus</tp:taxon-name></italic> were collected with a passive sample method (flight intercept trap) and nothing is known about its biology. It is hypothesized to be a termite symbiont based on phylogenetic relationships but the host is unknown.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Coptotermocola</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:01A98C55-BA86-4064-A554-1EC1DA6DC93A</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Coptotermocola</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Kanao, Eldredge &amp; Maruyama</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                    <title>Type species:</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermocola clavicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This monotypic genus is distinguishable from all other <tp:taxon-name>Termitohospitini</tp:taxon-name> most distinctly by the strongly carinate mesocoxal process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 27</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">38</xref>), and additionally by the compact antennae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 29</xref>) and short maxillary palpi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 33</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body form (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 24–27</xref>) limuloid. Pronotum strongly convex, dorsally obscuring most of head; abdomen posteriorly tapered.</p>
                    <p>Head capsule (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 28</xref>) transverse, widest behind eyes. Antennal fossae deep, as large as eyes and dorsally obscured by vertex. Eyes large and produced anterolaterally. Antennae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 29</xref>) compact with 11 articles; antennomere I longer than II–X and partially hidden within antennal fossae; antennomere II dilated at apex to receive antennomere III; antennomeres III–X strongly transverse and more than twice as wide as long, length increasing distally; antennomere XI fusiform; pedicles of antenomeres IV–XI obscured by apex of preceding article. Labrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 30</xref>) transverse and semicircular, anterior margin broadly concave; disc basomedially sparsely covered with pores; epipharynx (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 30</xref>) glabrous. Mandibles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 31–32</xref>) asymmetrical, dorsally covered with numerous pores around middle. Right mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 32</xref>) with a small subapical tooth; anterior one fifth strongly curved adorally. Left mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 31</xref>) without a subapical tooth. Maxillary (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 33</xref>) lacinia elongate and strongly recurved adorally, adoral margin with 11 setae; apical two setae without basal cuticular processes (spinose scale of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Ahn and Ashe 2004</xref>), third apical seta with a proximal basal cuticular process, central five setae with paired basal cuticular processes, basal three setae without basal cuticular processes; galea tapered apically, apex densely furnished with long trichae; palpus with 4 articles; article I triangular; article II trapezoidal and dilated toward apex; article III oviform, more than three times longer than wide and sparsely covered with long setae; article IV slightly narrowed toward apex with inconspicuous pseudosegment, pseudopores present apicomedially. Mentum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 34</xref>) trapezoidal, disc covered with long setae and several pores near middle and lateral areas; anterolateral corners slightly produced and with a pair of long macrosetae. Labial (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 35</xref>) palpus with 3 articles, first article a fusion of I + II; article I + II with a mediobasal seta on ventral surface (probably homologous to seta c of Sawada [1972]), twin and medial pores present; article III almost half as long as article I + II with 2 pores at apex; ligula triangular with medial subtriangular area sclerotized; prementum wider than long, with 2 pairs of both <!--PageBreak-->real and pseudopores, and a pair of setal pores present; apodemes broad and longer than disc, dilated posteriorly with apices recurved internally and almost touching.</p>
                    <p>Pronotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 36</xref>) transverse, widest at posterolateral angles; anterior margin concave with anterolateral angles slightly produced anteriorly; posterior margin rounded and slightly produced medially; marginal cuticle thin and somewhat translucent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 26</xref>). Prosternum reduced in length. Elytra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 37</xref>) subquadrate, slightly wider than long. Wings fully developed. Mesoventrite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 38</xref>) slightly shorter than metaventrite;<!--PageBreak--> mesoventral process produced as an extremely large structure widest medially and tapered at ends, microsculpture composed of longitudinal wavy lines and pores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 39</xref>), structure ventrally partially obscuring basal podomeres; mesocoxal cavity marginal bead complete, narrowly separated. Legs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 40–42</xref>) stout and laterally flattened; femora subrectangular; apical tarsomeres longest, tarsal formula 4-4-5. Fore leg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 40</xref>) with coxa approximately as long as femur; trochanter subtriangular; tibia thin. Mid leg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 41</xref>) with coxa globular; trochanter very thin; tibia thin. Hind leg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 42</xref>) subrectangular and almost as long as trochanter and femur combined; trochanter globular-triangular; femur slightly dilated apically; tibia thin.</p>
                    <p>Abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 24–27</xref>) tapered posteriorly. Segment I represented by only tergite I fused to the metanotum. Segment II represented by only by tergite II. Segments III–VII with 1 tergite, 1 sternite, and 2 pairs of paratergites. Tergite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 43</xref>) with a blunt apicomedial point. Sternite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 44</xref>) with posterior margin rounded. Tergite IX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 45</xref>) fully subdivided dorsally by tergite X. Tergite X (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 45</xref>) fully divided medially to base, only connected each other and tergite IX on anterior margin.</p>
                    <p>Median lobe of aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 46–47</xref>) with basal capsule bulbous. Paramere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 48</xref>) with a structure appearing homologous to Seevers’ (1978) medial phragma produced apically. Spermatheca (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 49</xref>) apically slightly bulbous.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The generic name is derived from a combination of the generic name of the host termite, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wasmann, 1896 and the Latin noun <italic>cola</italic> meaning “dweller”. The gender is feminine.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Coptotermocola</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">clavicornis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FEF68FC3-CB00-4B41-95C8-A6DA28E8FFA7</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Coptotermocola_clavicornis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Kanao, Eldredge &amp; Maruyama</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 24</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">–49</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                    <title>Type material.</title>
                    <p><italic>Holotype</italic>:♂, “MALAYSIA: Selangor,/Ulu Gombak, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">03°19'479"N; 101°45'170"E</named-content>,/ca. 240 m alt., X July 2011,/T. Kanao leg. KT-261”. Abdominal segments VIII–X dissected off.</p>
                    <p><italic>Paratypes</italic>:6??, MALAYSIA: same data as the holotype, one specimen is preserved in 99.5% EtOH; ♀, same locality data as the holotype, differing data reads “XXI May 2010,/ T. Kanao leg. KT-33”, fully disarticulated; 3??, same locality data as the holotype, differing data reads “XXIX May 2012,/ T. Kanao leg. KT-312”, one specimen is preserved in 99.5% EtOH.</p>
                    <p>All type specimens are deposited in the Kyushu University Museum.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is diagnosable based on the generic diagnosis above.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 24–27</xref>) approximately 2 mm in length (1.71–2.16 mm, N = 4) almost uniformly reddish brown, but head slightly darker. Dorsal surface of head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 28</xref>) glabrous, sparsely covered with pores, with 3 pairs of long setae at anterior margin of clypeus; ventral surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 28</xref>) with several setae behind eyes. Antennomere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 29</xref>) I sparsely covered with pseudopores and several macrosetae; antennomere II with 6–7 long macrosetae, 2 of them stronger and several pores present; antennomeres III–X sparsely covered with setae and 3–4 macrosetae present; antennomere XI sparsely covered with setae, with several macrosetae on dorsal and ventral surface near apex, pores present centrally on lateral surface. Labral (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 30</xref>) surface with 14–16 setae, anterolateral marginal and near-middle pairs conspicuously stronger. Epipharynx (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 30</xref>) with a pair of setulae present on anterolateral corner and three pairs of lateral marginal setulae. Mandibles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 31–32</xref>) with seta present at aboral basolateral margin. Maxillary (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 33</xref>) lacinia mesally with two pores and basally with 3 setae present; galea with 2 pores apically; maxillary palpal article I with a medial pore, article II sparsely covered with setae and longer setae present on apical margin, article III sparsely covered with longer and shorter setae.</p>
                    <p>Pronotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 36</xref>) transverse (pronotum length = 0.55–0.62 mm, pronotum width = 0.91–1.02 mm, N = 6) with 11 pairs of macrosetae. Elytra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 37</xref>) subquadrate (elytra length = 0.50–0.60 mm, elytra width = 0.51–0.63, N = 6), disc laterally sparsely setose, 2 lateral and 3 discal pairs of macrosetae present. Mesoventrite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 38</xref>) with central and lateral setose areas. Metaventrite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 38</xref>) with posterolateral setose area. Fore leg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 40</xref>) with coxa sparsely setose and 5 long macrosetae present at apical margin; trochanter and femur sparsely covered with setae; tibia covered with setae, density increasing apically, 5 apical spurs present; tarsus with few setae. Mid leg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 41</xref>) with coxa sparsely setose, 2 macrosetae at apex; trochanter sparsely covered with setae; femur overall setose, macroseta present venterobasally; tibia covered with setae, density increasing apically, with 7 strong setae present dorsally and apically<!--PageBreak--> with basal three dorsal setae longest; tarsomeres with 3–4 setae at apical margin. Hind leg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 42</xref>) with coxa mostly setose and with approximately 10 macrosetae along femoral cavity margin; trochanter partially setose and with 2 macrosetae along ventrolateral margin; femur overall setose, one macroseta near base and three macrosetae <!--PageBreak-->apically present; tibia sparsely covered with setae, with 7 strong setae present dorsally and apically, basal three dorsal setae longest; tarsomeres with 3–4 micro- and 2 macrosetae present at apical margin.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p>Tergites III–VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 25</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">, 43</xref>) laterally setose and medially glabrous. Macrochaetotaxy of abdominal tergites III–VIII = 2-4-4-4-4-4; paratergites setose. Tergite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 43</xref>) with a pair of discal and two pairs of apical macroseta present. Sternite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 44</xref>) sparsely setose and with one discal and three marginal macrosetae. Tergite IX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 45</xref>) with 3 pairs of macrosetae at apex and lateral margin; tergite X (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 45</xref>) disc sparsely covered with minute setae and 4 pair of macrosetae near apex.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak--><italic>Male</italic>. Median lobe of aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 46–47</xref>) copulatory piece flagellate, suspensoria associated with lateral base of copulatory piece. Paramere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 48</xref>) condylite with pores basally; apical lobe with 4 setae present.</p>
                    <p><italic>Female</italic>. Spermatheca (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 49</xref>) apical bulb surface with transverse wrinkle-like sculpture; stalk basal to membranous area three times as long as apical bulb.</p>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 24–27.</label>
                        <caption><p>Habitus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermocola clavicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <bold>24</bold> beetle photographed <italic>in situ</italic> <bold>25</bold> dorsal view <bold>26</bold> lateral view <bold>27</bold> ventral view.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-254-067-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 28–29.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermocola clavicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <bold>28</bold> head capsule left side = dorsal view, right side = ventral view <bold>29</bold> antenna.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-254-067-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 30–35.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermocola clavicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, mouthparts. <bold>30</bold> labrum, left side = labrum, right side = epipharynx <bold>31</bold> left mandible, dorsal view <bold>32</bold> right mandible, dorsal view <bold>33</bold> maxilla, ventral view <bold>34</bold> mentum, ventral view <bold>35</bold> labium, ventral view.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-254-067-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 36–42.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermocola clavicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, thorax and legs. <bold>36</bold> pronotum, left side with and right side without setae <bold>37</bold> elytron, left <bold>38</bold> meso- and metaventrites, anatomical left side with setae <bold>39</bold> detail of mesosternal process surface sculpture <bold>40</bold> fore leg, posterior surface <bold>41</bold> mid leg, posterior surface <bold>42</bold> hind leg, posterior surface.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-254-067-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 43–49.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermocola clavicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, abdominal sclerites and genitalia. <bold>43</bold> tergite VIII <bold>44</bold> sternite VIII <bold>45</bold> tergites IX–X <bold>46</bold> median lobe of aedeagus, aparameral view <bold>47</bold> median lobe of aedeagus, lateral view <bold>48</bold> paramere, external view <bold>49</bold> spermatheca.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-254-067-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific epithet is derived from a combination of the Latin noun <italic>clava</italic> meaning “club” and Latin adjective <italic>cornis</italic> meaning “to be horned”, in reference to the diagnostic robust antennae of the species. The gender is feminine.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Known only from the type locality Ulu Gombak, Selangor, Malaysia.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Host species">
                    <title>Host species.</title>
                    <p>All specimens were collected from the nest of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptoptermes gestroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Wasmann, 1896). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Ahmad (1965)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Kirton and Brown (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Tho (1992)</xref> was consulted for host identification.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Ecology">
                    <title>Ecology.</title>
                    <p>Specimens acquired during the KT261 collecting event were collected from the galleries of the host termites within a rotting log. The galleries were large and arranged in a complex manner. Another specimen (KT33) was collected from a trail of the hosts that occupied the exterior of a large log. KT312 specimens were collected from a rotting log occupied by the host termites. All <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> colonies that yielded <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermes clavicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> were located near rivers where the habitat in general was comparatively more moist compared to its surroundings.</p>
                    <p>All <italic><tp:taxon-name>Coptotermes clavicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens moved faster than their host termites. They did not avoid contact with hosts but instead recurved their abdomens over their bodies when they came into contact. The inquilines wedged themselves under their hosts on several occasions, but the host termites regaurdless never attacked the beetles.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>T. K. and M. M. would like to express our thanks to Dr. Rosli Hashim of the University of Malaya for supporting and provisioning our fieldwork. T. K. thanks Associate Professor Satoshi Kamitani for reviewing the manuscript. K. T. E. would like to personally thank Zachary Falin and Jennifer Thomas for their sincere help with specimens deposited at the Univeristy of Kansas, and Andrew Short for support. Finally, we would all like to thank Dr. Takashi Komatsu for assistance in the field and for permission to use the photograph used in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 24</xref>. Finally, we all thank M. Gimmel for tremendously helpful comments on drafts.</p>
            <p>Contribution from the Entomological Laboratory, Faculty of Agriculture, Kyushu University, Fukuoka (Ser. 6, No. 115).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>)<article-title> Termites (Isoptera) of Thailand.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History </source> <volume>131</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>114</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashe</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of Myllaenini and related taxa (Coleoptera: Staphyinidae: Aleocharinae).</article-title> <source>Cladistics </source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>138</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-0031.2004.00012.x">10.1111/j.1096-0031.2004.00012.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Galil</surname> <given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> New species and records of Australian termitophiles associated with <italic>Coptotermes</italic> in Australia (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology </source> <volume>13</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>153</fpage>-<lpage>165</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgmeier</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>)<source> Vier neue Gattungen und einiger neue Arten termitophiler Staphyliniden aus Costa Rica und Brasilien (Col. Staphilinidae).Studia Entomologica 2 (1/4): 289–308.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchard</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bousquet</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Zarazaga</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyal</surname> <given-names>CHC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newton</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname> <given-names>CAM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ślipiński</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>ABT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Family- group names in Coleoptera (Insecta).</article-title> <source>ZooKeys </source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>972</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.88.807">10.3897/zookeys.88.807</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1920</year>)<article-title> New species of Staphylinidae from Singapore. Part III.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the Entomological Society of London</source> <volume>1920</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1950</year>)<article-title> New species of Staphylinidae from the Malay Peninsula.</article-title> <source>Annals &amp; Magazine of Natural History </source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>131</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222935008654040">10.1080/00222935008654040</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heer</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1839</year>)<source> Fauna coleopterorum Helvetica. Pars I, fasc. 2. Orelii, Fuesslini et Sociorum, Turici, Zurich, 145–360.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hölldobler</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>EO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<source> The Ants.</source> <publisher-name>Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, Cambridge</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Massachusetts</publisher-loc>, <lpage>732</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirton</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> The taxonomic status of pest species of <italic>Coptotermes</italic> in Southeast Asia: Resolving the paradox in the pest status of the termites,<italic> Coptotermes gestroi</italic>, <italic>C. havilandi</italic> and <italic>C. travians</italic> (Isoptera: Rhinotermitidae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology </source> <volume>42</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>)<article-title> The Biology of Termitophiles.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Krishna</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weesner</surname> <given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Biology of Termites 1.</issue-title> <source>Academic Press, NY</source>: <fpage>525</fpage>-<lpage>557</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> Revision of the termitophilous tribe Termitohospitini (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae). I. The genus <italic>Hetairotermes</italic> with a numerical analysis of the relationships of Australian species.</article-title> <source>Pacific Insects </source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>467</fpage>-<lpage>484</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>)<article-title> Revision of the termitophilous tribe Termitohospitini IV. A new genus with <italic>Coptotermes</italic> from Sabah (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology </source> <volume>2</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> Social and evolutionary significanc of social insect symbionts.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hermann</surname> <given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>Social Insects 1.</issue-title> <source>Chapt. 8. Academic Press, NY</source>: <fpage>339</fpage>-<lpage>413</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> A new genus and species of termitophilous Aleocharinae from mainland China associated with <italic>Coptotermes formosanus</italic> and its zoogeographic significance (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology </source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>104</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistner</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobson</surname> <given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>)<article-title> New species and new records of termitophilous species from central America and Mexico with description of behavior, related glands and ultrastructure (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology </source> <volume>2</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lea</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1910</year>)<article-title> Australian and Tasmanian Coleoptera inhabiting or resorting to the nests of ants, bees, and termites.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria </source> <volume>23</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>116</fpage>-<lpage>230</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1923</year>)<article-title> New genera and species of termitophilous Coleoptera from northern South America.</article-title> <source>Zoologica </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>323</fpage>-<lpage>366</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<source> A Permanent Slide Pinned under a Specimen. Elytra 32 (2): 276.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Revision of the Palearctic species of the myrmecophilous genus <italic>Pella</italic> (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Aleocharinae).</article-title> <source>National Science Museum Monographs</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwata</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Two new termitophiles of the tribe Termitohospiniti (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae: Aleocharinae) associated with <italic>Coptotermes formosanus</italic> (Isoptera: Rhinotermitidae).</article-title> <source>The Canadian Entomologist </source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>419</fpage>-<lpage>432</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/Ent134419-4">10.4039/Ent134419-4</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oke</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1933</year>)<article-title> Australian Staphylinidae.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria </source> <volume>45</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pace</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Nuevo Aleocharinae orientali (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Bollettino del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale di Verona </source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>180</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roisin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pasteels</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> <italic>Coptophysa</italic> and <italic>Coptophysella</italic>, two new genera of physogastric termitophilous staphylinids associated with <italic>Coptotermes</italic> in Papua New Guinea (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Entomologie </source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>184</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sawada</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Methodological research in the taxonomy of Aleocharinae.</article-title> <source>Contributions from the Biological Laboratory Kyoto University </source> <volume>24</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Seevers</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1941</year>)<article-title> Taxonomic investigations of some temitophilous Staphylinidae of the subfamilies Aleocharinae and Trichopseniinae (new subfamily).</article-title> <source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America </source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>318</fpage>-<lpage>349</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Seevers</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1957</year>)<article-title> A monograph on the termitophilous Staphylinidae (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Fieldiana: Zoology </source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>334</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Seevers</surname> <given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>)<article-title> A generic and tribal revision of the North American Aleocharinae (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Fieldiana: Zoology </source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>275</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Silvestri</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1947</year>)<article-title> Contributo alla conoscenza dei Termitodiscinae e Cephaloplectinae (Staphylinidae, Coleoptera) termitofili.</article-title> <source>Archivio Zoologico Italiano </source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thayer</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> 11. Staphylinoidea. 11.7. Staphylinidae Latreille, 1802.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristensen</surname> <given-names>NP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beutel</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <source>Beutel RG, Leschen RAB (vol. eds) Coleoptera Vol. I. Morphology and Systematics (Archostemata, Adephaga Myxophaga, Polyphaga partim). Handbook of Zoology Vol. IV, Part 2. Arthropoda: Insecta. De Gruyter, Berlin, New York</source>: <fpage>296</fpage>-<lpage>344</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tho</surname> <given-names>YP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<source> Termites of peninsular Malaysia.</source> <publisher-name>Forest Research Institute</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Malaysia</publisher-loc>, <lpage>224</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname> <given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1928</year>)<source> The Social Insects: Their Origin and Evolution.</source> <publisher-name>Kegan Paul, Trench, Trubner &amp; Co, LTD</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>663</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>