<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.76.790</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                Twenty-four new species of Polycentropus (Trichoptera, Polycentropodidae) from Brazil
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Hamilton</surname>
                        <given-names>Steven W.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:DD7EE416-9F9E-44BE-809F-F34947F1D06E</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Holzenthal</surname>
                        <given-names>Ralph W.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:C27A1C49-F372-4232-A49C-B8B5F753CC70</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>Austin Peay State University, The Center for Field Biology, P. O. Box 4718, Clarksville, Tennessee 37044, U.S.A.</label></aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>University of Minnesota, Department of Entomology, 1980 Folwell Ave., 219 Hodson Hall, St. Paul, Minnesota 55108, U.S.A</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Steven W. Hamilton (<email xlink:type="simple">hamiltonsw@apsu.ed</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Guest editor: Christy Geraci</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>19</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>76</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>53</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>17</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Steven W. Hamilton, Ralph W. Holzenthal</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:901B0D71-8D9A-41F4-8589-8C7EF9CAA458</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Twenty-four new species of the caddisfly genus <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Insecta</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropodidae</tp:taxon-name>) occurring in Brazil are diagnosed, described, and the male genitalia of each are illustrated. Eighteen of the new species are placed in the <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus jorgenseni</tp:taxon-name> species complex of the <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus gertschi</tp:taxon-name> group of New World <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name> <italic>sensu lato</italic>. Furthermore, 6 new species within the <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus gertschi</tp:taxon-name> group <bold>(</bold><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus ancistrus</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus boraceia</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carioca</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus froehlichi</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus galharada</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus graciosa</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>) are placed in an informal diagnostic cluster of species with <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus urubici</tp:taxon-name> Holzenthal and Almeida. Ten of the other <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus gertschi</tp:taxon-name> group species form a second cluster of diagnostically similar species, the <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus soniae</tp:taxon-name> cluster (<tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus caaete</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carolae</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cheliceratus</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus fluminensis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus itatiaia</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus minero</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus santateresae</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus soniae</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus tripui</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus virginiae</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>). Two of the remaining 8 new species are included in the <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus jorgenseni</tp:taxon-name> species complex (<tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cipoensis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold> and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus verruculus</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>), while the remaining 6 are unique and cannot be placed in one of the groups at this time (<tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus acinaciformis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus amphirhamphus</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cachoeira</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus inusitatus</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus paprockii</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold> and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus rosalysae</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>).</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Trichoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Polycentropodidae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Polycentropus</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>caddisfly</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>Neotropics</kwd>
                <kwd>Brazil</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Although cosmopolitan, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name> is still not well known is South America. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Flint et al. (1999)</xref> reported 64 species of <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name> for the Neotropics. Subsequently, only 14 species in the genus have been added, 1 each from Argentina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Angrisano and Sganga 2009</xref>), Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Holzenthal and Almeida 2003</xref>) and Hispaniola (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Flint and Sykora 2004</xref>), 2 each from Costa Rica (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Chamorro-Lacayo 2003</xref>), Ecuador, and Venezuela (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hamilton and Holzenthal 2005</xref>), and 5 from Mexico (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Barba-Alvarez and Bueno-Soria 2005</xref>). In their checklist of the caddisflies of Brazil, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Paprocki et al. (2004)</xref> reported 378 species as of September, 2003. More than half (26) of the 46 species of polycentropodids included, were <tp:taxon-name>Cernotina</tp:taxon-name>. To date, the only named species of <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name> from Brazil is <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus urubici</tp:taxon-name> Holzenthal &amp; Almeida (2003). No <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name> species have been added to the known Brazilian fauna since.</p>
            <p>In this paper we add 24 new species to the list of Brazilian <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name>, 9 of which were previously described and illustrated in a dissertation on the New World species of <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name> <italic>sensu stricto</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton 1986</xref>). The remaining 15 were collected as part of asurvey of the caddisflies of southeastern and southern Brazil by Dr. Ralph Holzenthal and colleagues.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods"><title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>All material described here is based on pinned specimens, except as noted. While preparation of male genitalia occurred over many years, the procedures for clearing and illustrating the specimens generally followed those presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Holzenthal and Andersen (2004)</xref>.</p>
            <p>Terminology used in describing male genitalia follows that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton (1986)</xref> and, particularly in regard to naming the parts of the preanal appendage, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Chamorro and Holzenthal (2010)</xref>. Paired appendages and the processes of these appendages (intermediate appendages, preanal appendages, and inferior appendages) are referred to in the singular in diagnoses and descriptions. Our interpretation of the shape and position of the mostly membranous tergum IX + X should not be considered absolute because the membranous nature of the segments makes their demarcation difficult to discern and their exact shapes subject to degree of inflation at the time of preservation or during the clearing process. Likewise, the membranous attachment between the intermediate and preanal appendages as well as the shape of the endothecal membranes are variable and our descriptions represent our best interpretation of their relative positions and shapes in the specimens we have studied. Because of their small size, the shapes of the endothecal and subphallic sclerites are difficult to discern, especially if deeply embedded in membranes; in particular the shape of the pedicel of the subphallic sclerite, if present, and the length of the arms that cradle the phallobase are often hard to discern. In <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carioca</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus boraceia</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus galharada</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus graciosa</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus froehlichi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus ancistrus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., the base of the mesolateral process of the preanal appendage is lightly sclerotized, so its position relative to the mesoventral process is not fixed.<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <p>Females that were collected at the same location and date as described males are included in the type series, although the certainty of these associations awaits further investigation. Types are deposited in the collections of the Museo de Zoologia, Universidade do São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil (MZUSP), United States National Museum of Natural History, Washington, DC (NMNH), the Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil (UFRJ), the Universidade Federal do Bahia, Salvador, Brazil (UFBA), and the University of Minnesota Insect Collection, St. Paul, Minnesota, U.S.A. (UMSP), as indicated in the species description. The holotypes of <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus minero</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carolae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., are on long term loan to the NMHN from MZUSP.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Phylogenetic considerations"><title>Phylogenetic considerations</title>
            <p>Eighteen of the 24 new Brazilian species are clearly members of the <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus gertschi</tp:taxon-name> group (hereafter referred to as the <italic>gertschi</italic> group). This group, as characterized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton (1986)</xref>, comprises most of the Neotropical <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name> species. The <italic>gertschi</italic> group shares 3 synapomorphies: “(1) ventral process of phallobase is apicoventral in position, (2) each intermediate appendage free to its base and articulates basomesally on its preanal appendage, and (3) there is a sclerite formed in the membrane below and around the phallus that appears to support and guide this organ” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hamilton and Holzenthal 2005</xref>). These 18 species are further placed in the <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus jorgenseni</tp:taxon-name> species complex (hereafter referred to as the <italic>jorgenseni</italic> species complex) within the <italic>gertschi</italic> group, a clade that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton (1986)</xref> characterized based on the occurrence of a dorsal sclerotized band in the endothecal membranes (often folded back into phallobase when endothecal membrane inverted). The remaining 6 new species, including Hamilton’s (1986) “<tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. 8” and “<tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. 9,” are more problematic in regard to group affinities based on characters employed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton (1986)</xref>. All 6 species appear to lack the articulated intermediate appendages so evident in members of the <italic>gertschi</italic> group, but some of the 6 have other characters that suggest affinities to the group, including the endothecal sclerotic band in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus rosalysae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus acinaciformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cachoeira</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. In lieu of a phylogenetic analysis, discussion of suggested affinities will be included in the diagnoses of the species.</p>
            <p>In the following descriptions, the first 6 species (<tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus ancistrus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus boraceia</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carioca</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus froehlichi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus galharada</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus graciosa</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.) seem to demonstrate affinities to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus urubici</tp:taxon-name> Holzenthal &amp; Almeida (2003) based in particular on the shape of the preanal appendage. The mesolateral process of the preanal appendage is digitate and its base is narrowed and lightly sclerotized. As a result, its position relative to the rigid mesoventral process is not fixed. In addition, in these 6 species and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus urubici</tp:taxon-name>, the posteroventral region of the inferior appendage is short while the dorsolateral flange is relatively high and more elongate, forming a pointed process in most species. Also, these species have a vestiture of fine, black setae on the wings and lack the patches of pale setae so common in other <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name>. Unlike <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus urubici</tp:taxon-name>, the intermediate appendage is long, often more than twice the length of the digitate <!--PageBreak-->mesolateral process of the preanal appendage. In the diagnoses below, we refer to this diagnostic cluster of 7 species as the <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus urubici</tp:taxon-name> cluster (hereafter referred to as the <italic>urubici</italic> cluster), although we do not intend to indicate that a phylogenetic analysis has occurred nor that this cluster be recognized as a formal clade.</p>
            <p>The next 10 species descriptions, also species of the <italic>jorgenseni</italic> species complex are close to the recently described <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus aguyje</tp:taxon-name> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Angrisano and Sganga (2009)</xref> (<tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus caaete</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carolae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cheliceratus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus fluminensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus itatiaia</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus minero</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus santateresae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus soniae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus tripui</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus virginiae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.). These appear similar in the compact, often quadrate, lateral aspect of the interior appendage; the elongate, typically decurved intermediate appendage; and the shape of the preanal appendage in lateral view with its mesolateral process short and very broad and the mesoventral process more digitate. As in the <italic>urubici</italic> cluster, the wings appear solid black and lack pale patches of setae. For convenience, we will designate this diagnostically similar cluster of 11 species as the <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus aguyje</tp:taxon-name> cluster (hereafter referred to as the <italic>aguyje</italic> cluster). As in the <italic>urubici</italic> cluster discussed above, the <italic>aguyje</italic> cluster should not be recognized as a formal clade.</p>
            <p>Of the remaining 8 new Brazilian species, 2 species are clearly members of the <italic>jorgenseni</italic> species complex (<tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cipoensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus verruculus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.), but are unique and not similar to members of the <italic>urubici</italic> and <italic>aguyje</italic> clusters. The final 6 species (<tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus acinaciformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus amphirhamphus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cachoeira</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus inusitatus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus paprockii</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus rosalysae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.) cannot be placed in the <italic>jorgenseni</italic> species complex based on the synapomorphies identified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton (1986)</xref>, although several show some similarities to the complex.</p>
            <p>Ongoing investigations by Brazilian researchers and others (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Chamorro and Holzenthal 2010</xref>) may add to our understanding of the phylogenetic relationships of these and other species of Neotropical <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name>. Clearly, Brazil has a poorly understood richness of species in the genus.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Species descriptions"><title>Species descriptions</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">boraceia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8B813827-03F9-4752-8D82-E0E79968F5F8</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name><comment> new species 7 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton 1986</xref>: 93–94, 210; Fig. 6.10.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Similar to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus urubici</tp:taxon-name> Holzenthal &amp; Almeida (2003) in general form, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus boraceia</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is particularly distinct in the much greater length and shape of the intermediate appendage and the general shape of the inferior appendage. Most similar to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus galharada</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., the shape of the inferior appendage in lateral and posterior views provides distinctive features that separate <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus boraceia</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. from <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus galharada</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. as well as other species of the <italic>urubici</italic> cluster. In particular, the dorsolateral flange of the<!--PageBreak--> inferior appendage is shorter and more dorsally rounded in lateral view and the mesoventral spine in posterior aspect is acute while in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus galharada</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. this spine is more angularly truncate.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 6.1–8.8 mm. Body dark brown to black; dorsum of head and thorax dark brown, clothed with long, erect dark setae; base of forewing <!--PageBreak-->with long, erect dark setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs dark brown to black.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view subtriangular, about 2/3 height of segment VIII; in ventral view quadrate, anterior corners sharply rounded, sides slightly constricted mesally, anterior margin moderately concave, posterior margin produced medially. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage slightly sinuate, very long, length greater than height of abdomen, basal region turned laterad at base; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage moderately long, digitate, apex rounded, at base narrowly joined to dorsal portion of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, digitate, about 2/3 length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, somewhat triangular; posteroventral margin acute below moderate caudal emargination; dorsolateral flange relatively high, rounded dorsally, apically tapered to rounded or sharp point, with prominent apicoventral point, exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine present, narrow, in lateral view acute, positioned medially; in ventral view inferior appendage broad basally, slender, tapering apically, caudomesal spine prominent, acute; mesoventral spine hidden. Phallobase short; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, slightly longer than apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 2 points; separated by shallow median groove; endothecal sclerotic band somewhat broad, becoming less sclerotized apically; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite narrow in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel with narrow lateral expansions; narrow in lateral view, ventrally somewhat narrowed.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus boraceia</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: São Paulo:</bold> Estação Biológica Boraceia, Riberão Coruja, 2.iv.1977, C.M. &amp; O.S. Flint, Jr. (UMSP000136631) (NMNH).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 7 males (NMNH); Res. Casa Grande, Pedreira, 13.x.1974, Froehlich, 1 male (in alcohol) (NMNH); Res. Casa Grande, Riberão Coruja, 26.i.1974, Froehlich, 1 male, 1 female (in alcohol) (NMNH); Est. Biol. Paranapiacaba, 6.viii. 1963, Froehlich, 1 male (in alcohol) (NMNH); same, except 27.viii.1963, 1 male (in alcohol) (NMNH); Estação Biológica Boraceia, Rio Guaratuba, 23°40.039'S, 45°53.759'W, 775 m, 17.iv.1998, Holzenthal, Melo, Froehlich, 1 male (UMSP); same, except 17.ix.2002, Blahnik, Prather, Melo, Froehlich, Silva, 1 male (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named for Estação Biológica Boraceia, the biological station located on the forested slopes of the Serra do Mar, where the holotype was collected.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">galharada</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BF3019BD-3B2D-44FE-B25E-27FB65FBA33E</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>As noted in the diagnosis of <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus boraceia</tp:taxon-name>, this new species and the other 5 new species of the <italic>urubici</italic> cluster are similar to, but distinct from <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus urubici</tp:taxon-name> based on<!--PageBreak--> the shape and length of the intermediate appendage as well as the shape of the inferior appendage. Separated from <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus boraceia</tp:taxon-name> as noted above, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus galharada</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. also resembles <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus froehlichi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus ancistrus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus graciosa</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. in the shape of the inferior appendage. It is distinguished from these species in details of this organ, particularly in <!--PageBreak-->the shape of the dorsolateral flange and the caudomesal spine in addition to the shapes and relative lengths of the processes of the preanal appendage.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 7.5–8 mm. Body dark brown to black; dorsum of head and thorax black, clothed with long, erect dark setae; base of forewing with long, erect black setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs dark brown to black.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view broadly subtriangular, about 3/4 height of segment VIII; in ventral view quadrate, anterior corners very broadly rounded, sides straight, anterior margin deeply concave, posterior margin slightly concave. Terga IX + X membranous, slightly sclerotized ventrally. Intermediate appendage gently curving ventromesad, very long, length much greater than height of abdomen, basal region slightly expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage moderately long, digitate, apex somewhat swollen, rounded, at base narrowly joined to dorsal portion of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed dorsocaudad, digitate, about 2/3 length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view moderately long, somewhat triangular; posteroventral margin acute below moderate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>) to deep (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2H</xref>) caudal emargination; dorsolateral flange low, somewhat straight with 2 shallow excavations of dorsal margin beyond midlength, apically tapered to sharp point, with prominent apicoventral point, exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine present, narrow, in lateral view acute, positioned medially; in ventral view inferior appendage broad basally, slender, tapering apically, caudomesal spine prominent, acute; mesoventral spine hidden; apex angularly truncate. Phallobase moderately short; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, much longer than apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 2 points; separated by shallow median groove; endothecal sclerotic band somewhat broad, becoming less sclerotized apically; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite narrow in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel with broad lateral expansions; broad in lateral view, ventrally narrowed.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus galharada</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal <bold>H</bold> inferior appendage, variant, lateral.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: São Paulo:</bold> Parque Estadual de Campos do Jordão, Rio Galharada, 22°41.662'S, 45°27.783'W, 1530 m, 22.i.1998, Holzenthal, Froehlich, Paprocki (UMSP000033083) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: São Paulo:</bold> Parque Estadual de Campos do Jordão, Cachoeira Galharada, 22°41.735'S, 45°27.725'W, 1620 m, 7.iii.1996, Holzenthal, Rochetti, Oliveira, 4 males, 1 female (UMSP); same, 15.x.1998, Paprocki &amp; Froehlich, 1 male, 2 females (UMSP); Parque Estadual de Campos do Jordão, Rio Galharada, 22°41.662'S, 45°27.783'W, 1530 m, 4–5.iii.1996, Holzenthal &amp; Guahyba, 3 males (UFRJ); same, 22.i.1998, Holzenthal, Froehlich, Paprocki, 2 males (UFBA); Parque Estadual de Campos do Jordão, Campo do Meio, 22°41.750'S, 45°29.448'W, 1500 m, 6.iii.1996, Holzenthal &amp; Guahyba, 3 males (UMSP); same, 21.i.1998, Holzenthal, Froehlich, Paprocki, 1 male, 1 female (PUCMG); Rio Casquilho, 3.4 km NE Parque Estadual Campos do Jordão, 22°40.29'S, 45°27.87'W, 1550 m, 23.i.1998, Holzenthal, Froehlich, Paprocki, 2 males (NMNH); Serra do Japi, Córrego da Ermida and small dam, 23°12'S, 47°00'W, 9–10.xii.1997, Froehlich, 1 male (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named for the type locality.<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">froehlichi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:AFA47C3D-3C4E-458E-9EDE-515F63157527</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Resembling <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus galharada</tp:taxon-name> mainly in the shape of the preanal and inferior appendages, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus froehlichi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is distinguished from that species and the other species of the <italic>urubici</italic> cluster particularly by the phallobase where the apicoventral process is relatively thick at its base and is perpendicular to the axis of phallobase, when viewed laterally. Also, the base of the mesoventral process of the preanal appendage of <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus froehlichi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is much broader than that of <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus galharada</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 7–7.5 mm. Body black; dorsum of head and thorax black, clothed with long, black setae; base of forewing with long, erect black setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs dark brown to black.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view broadly subtriangular, about 2/3 height of segment VIII; in ventral view slightly trapezoidal, anterior corners very broadly rounded, sides strongly constricted mesally, anterior margin moderately concave, posterior margin deeply and broadly concave. Terga IX + X membranous, slightly sclerotized ventrally; with several long, slender setae. Intermediate appendage slightly curved dorsad, very long, length much greater than height of abdomen, basal region slightly expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage moderately long, broadly digitate, apex rounded, at base narrowly joined to dorsal portion of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, very broad basally, narrowing to irregularly rounded apex, about 1/2 length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view moderately long, somewhat triangular; posteroventral margin protruding, rounded below shallow caudal emargination; dorsolateral flange low, slightly rounded dorsally, apically tapered to sharp inturned point, without caudomesal spine; mesoventral spine present, broad, in lateral view obtuse, positioned medially; in ventral view inferior appendage broad basally, slender, tapering apically; mesoventral spine hidden; apex acute. Phallobase short; in lateral view apicoventral projection moderately broad, slightly shorter than diameter of apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 2 points; separated by shallow median groove; endothecal sclerotic band somewhat broad, becoming less sclerotized apically; phallotremal sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms short, pedicel with narrow lateral expansions; broad in lateral view, ventrally somewhat narrowed.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 3.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus froehlichi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Santa Catarina:</bold> Morro da Igreja, Cachoeira Veu da Noiva, 28°04.595'S, 49°31.090'W, 1300 m, 5.iii.1998, Holzenthal, Froehlich, Paprocki (UMSP000033101) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Santa Catarina:</bold> Urubici, Cachoeira Avencal, 28°02.839'S, 49°36.997'W, 1260 m, 6.iii.1998, Holzenthal, Froehlich, Paprocki, 1 male, 1 female (UMSP); same data as holotype, 1 male, 1 female (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named for the great Brazilian aquatic entomologist, Dr. Claudio G. Froehlich, University of São Paulo, in recognition of his lifelong study of the aquatic insects of Brazil.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">ancistrus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:57255A7B-5BC9-4FE0-95B7-472D92952D73</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4.</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus ancistrus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. most closely resembles <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus froehlichi</tp:taxon-name>. It is distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus froehlichi</tp:taxon-name> and the other <italic>urubici</italic> cluster species by the strongly incurved and acute apices of the dorsolateral flange and caudomesal spine of the inferior appendage as well as the near equal length of both processes of the preanal appendage.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 6 mm. Body brown; dorsum of head and thorax brown; legs stramineous.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view nearly round, slightly greater than 1/2 height of segment VIII; in ventral view slightly trapezoidal, anterior corners very sharply rounded, sides slightly convex, narrowed posteriorly, anterior margin shallowly concave, posterior margin shallowly concave. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage straight, very long, length much greater than height of abdomen, basal region simple, not expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage moderately long, digitate, apex rounded, at base broadly joined to dorsal 1/2 of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, size and shape of mesolateral process, slightly shorter than length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view moderately long, somewhat triangular; posteroventral margin acute below shallow caudal emargination; dorsolateral flange low, slightly excavated medially, apically tapered to sharp inturned point, with prominent caudomesal spine, exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine absent; in ventral view inferior appendage broad basally, slender, tapering apically, caudomesal spine prominent, acute. Phallobase moderately short; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, slightly longer than apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 2 points; separated by very shallow median groove; endothecal sclerotic band forming flanges within phallobase; phallotremal sclerite difficult to discern due to specimen condition. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel narrow; narrow in lateral view, ventrally somewhat narrowed.</p>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 4.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus ancistrus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: São Paulo:</bold> Res. Casa Grande, Rib. Courja, á luz, 26.i.1974, Froehlich, (UMSP000131229) (in alcohol) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>From the Greek <italic>ankistron</italic> for fishhook, in reference to the caudomesal spines on the inferior appendage of the male genitalia.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">graciosa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:98D3E5AB-723B-48BE-8184-ED084D0D5545</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Among the 6 new species in the <italic>urubici</italic> cluster, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus graciosa</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. resembles <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus boraceia</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus galharada</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus froehlichi</tp:taxon-name>, and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus ancistrus</tp:taxon-name> in the shape of the inferior appendage with the elongate dorsolateral flange. In <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus graciosa</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.,the dorsolateral <!--PageBreak-->flange of the inferior appendage is uniformly wide in lateral view and narrows relatively abruptly to a rounded or acute apex. Likewise, the caudomesal spine of the inferior appendage is absent, forming a rounded protrusion, and the mesoventral spine in posterior aspect is bifurcate unlike any of the aforementioned species.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 7–8 mm. Body dark brown to black; dorsum of head and thorax black, clothed with long, black setae; base of forewing with long, erect black setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs dark brown to black.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view broadly subtriangular, about 3/4 height of segment VIII; in ventral view quadrate, anterior corners sharply rounded, sides slightly constricted mesally, anterior margin shallowly concave, posterior margin moderately concave with small, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage slightly curved dorsad, very long, length much greater than height of abdomen, basal region slightly expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage moderately long, digitate, apex roundly truncate, at base narrowly joined to dorsal portion of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, broadly digitate, about 2/3 length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view moderately long, somewhat triangular; posteroventral margin protruding, rounded below shallow caudal emargination; dorsolateral flange low, slightly rounded dorsally, apically tapered to rounded point, without caudomesal spine; mesoventral spine present, broad, in lateral view acute, bifurcate, positioned well caudad; in ventral view inferior appendage broad basally, slender, tapering apically; mesoventral spine prominent; apex acute, bifurcate. Phallobase moderately short; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, approximately equal to apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 2 points; separated by shallow median groove; endothecal sclerotic band somewhat broad, becoming less sclerotized apically; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite U-shaped, arms long, pedicel with narrow lateral expansions; broad in lateral view, ventrally somewhat narrowed.</p>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 5.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus graciosa</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral (inset, variant of inferior appendage apex) <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Paraná:</bold> Rio Cascata, Graciosa, road to Morretes, 25°20.214'S, 48°53.971'W, 750 m, 10.i.1998, Holzenthal, Melo, Almeida (UMSP000033088) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 2 males, 1 female (UMSP), 1 female (MZUSP); <bold>Paraná:</bold> Quatro Barras, 900 m, 31.i.1993, V.O. Becker, 3 males, 2 females (NMNH).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named for the type locality, a river flowing through the lush Atlantic forest of the Serra da Graciosa, Paraná, Brazil.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">carioca</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:DDDEDD30-FF55-4D22-9D16-0D336CC94874</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carioca</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is the most unusual of the species in the <italic>urubici</italic> cluster. In lateral view, the mesoventral process of the preanal appendage is nearly as wide as long, while in the other 6 species this process is always much narrower relative to its length. Also, in lateral view the inferior appendage in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carioca</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.is short <!--PageBreak-->with the dorsolateral flange being compacted and rounded while the mesoventral spine in posterior view is large and erect.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 7 mm. Body dark brown; dorsum of head and thorax dark brown, clothed with long, erect dark setae; base of forewing with long, erect dark setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs dark brown to black.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view nearly round, approximately 1/2 height of segment VIII; in ventral view quadrate, anterior corners very broadly rounded, sides slightly constricted posteriorly, posterior margin moderately concave with small, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X mostly membranous with light dorsal sclerotization basally; with numerous scattered minute spicules. Intermediate appendage straight, very long, length greater than height of abdomen, basal region simple, not expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage moderately long, digitate, apex rounded, at base narrowly joined to dorsal portion of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed ventrocaudad, broadly truncate, about 2/3 length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, somewhat triangular; posteroventral margin protruding, rounded below shallow caudal emargination; dorsolateral flange relatively high, rounded dorsally, without caudomesal spine; mesoventral spine large, erect, narrow, in lateral view acute, positioned more basad; in ventral view inferior appendage rhomboidal, broadest apically; mesoventral spine with apex visible. Phallobase moderately short; much longer than apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 1 point; endothecal sclerotic band narrow, becoming less sclerotized apically; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite narrow in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel with broad lateral expansions; narrow in lateral view, ventrally somewhat narrowed.</p>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 6.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carioca</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Rio de Janeiro:</bold> Parque Nacional da Serra dos Órgãos, Rio Beija-flor, 22°27.063'S, 43°00.065'W, 1125 m, 27.ii.2002, Holzenthal, Blahnik, Paprocki, Prather (UMSP000136602) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratype"><title>Paratype:</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 1 female (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p><italic>Carioca</italic> is the Portuguese demonym for the inhabitants of the city of Rio de Janeiro.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">fluminensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A16AC0C6-F467-4EA0-90BB-004170F7F224</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
	                	<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name><comment> new species 1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton 1986</xref>: 85–86, 198; Fig. 6.4.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus fluminensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., and the other 9 species of the <italic>aguyje</italic> cluster show similarities in the shape of both processes of the preanal appendage, the strongly, often decurved intermediate appendage and the general appearance of the inferior appendage. Among the 10 species of this cluster, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus fluminensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.has the shortest and most compact inferior appendage with a strongly reduced dorsolateral plane and the mesoventral process of the preanal appendage is notably broad and short, barely exceeding the mesoventral process.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 6.5–7.5 mm. Body dark brown to black; dorsum of head and thorax black, clothed with long, black setae; base of forewing with long, <!--PageBreak-->erect black setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs dark brown to black.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view broadly subtriangular, about 2/3 height of segment VIII; in ventral view slightly trapezoidal, anterior co<!--PageBreak-->rners sharply rounded, sides very slightly constricted mesally, anterior margin deeply concave, posterior margin slightly concave with broad, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage gently curving ventromesad, long, length slightly greater than height of abdomen, basal region slightly expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage short, apex rounded, with slight apicoventral extension, at base broadly joined to mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, digitate, equal in length to mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view very short, generally oval; dorsolateral flange very low, rounded dorsally, with prominent caudomesal spine, exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine present, broad, in lateral view rounded, positioned well basad; in ventral view inferior appendage approximately oval, caudomesal spine prominent, acute. Phallobase moderately short; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, slightly longer than apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 1 point; endothecal sclerotic band narrow, ending in pair of small spines resembling a claw-hammer; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel with broad lateral expansions; narrow in lateral view, ventrally somewhat broadened.</p>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 7.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus fluminensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> phallobase, caudal <bold>H</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Rio de Janeiro:</bold> km 17, 18 km S of Teresopolis, 1180 m, 18–19.iv.1977, C.M. &amp; O.S. Flint, Jr. (UMSP000136606) (NMNH).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 5 males, 2 females (NMNH); <bold>Minas Gerais:</bold> Parque Nacional do Caparaó, small trib to Rio Caparaó, Vale Verde, 20°25.029'S, 41°50.767'W, 1350 m, 12–14.iii.2002, Holzenthal, 1 male (in alcohol) (UMSP); <bold>Rio de Janeiro:</bold> Parque Nacional da Serra dos Órgãos, Rio Paquequer, 22°26.992'S, 42°59.899'W, 1000 m, 26.ii.2002, Holzenthal, Blahnik, Paprocki, Prather, 1 male (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The word <italic>fluminensis</italic> is derived from the Portuguese demonym for the inhabitants of the state of Rio de Janeiro.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">tripui</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:225395E4-9CDB-4227-9E44-7C1083734B80</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>In lateral aspect, this species most closely resembles <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus fluminensis</tp:taxon-name>, in the compactness of the inferior appendage and the breadth of the mesolateral process of the preanal appendage. In <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus tripui</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., the dorsolateral flange of inferior appendage is larger and the mesoventral process of the preanal appendage is much broader in lateral aspect. The phallic apparatus provides several unique characters that separate this species from the other species described in this paper. The phallobase is very short and there is a very large U-shaped sclerite at the apex of the sclerotized band of the phallic membrane (typically found folded back within the phallobase).</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 6–6.5 mm. Body brown to dark brown; dorsum of head and thorax dark brown, clothed with long, erect dark setae; base of forewing <!--PageBreak-->with long, erect dark setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine brown setae, lacking patches of pale setae (in alcohol); legs brown.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view subtriangular, about 2/3 height of segment VIII; in ventral view quadrate, anterior corners very broadly rounded, sides very slightly constricted mesally, anterior margin shallowly concave, posterior margin slightly concave with very broad, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X<!--PageBreak--> membranous. Intermediate appendage gently curving ventromesad, moderate elongate, length about two-thirds height of sternum IX, basal region simple, not expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage short, apex truncate, with slight apicoventral extension, at base broadly joined to mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, broad, hatch-shaped, slightly shorter than length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, generally oval; dorsolateral flange very low, rounded dorsally, with prominent caudomesal spine, slightly exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine present, narrow, in lateral view acute, positioned well basad; in ventral view inferior appendage approximately oval, caudomesal spine prominent, acute; mesoventral spine hidden. Phallobase very short; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, much shorter than diameter of apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 2 points; endothecal sclerotic band broad, very large hooked process, appearing U-shaped in dorsal view; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms short, pedicel with broad lateral expansions; broad in lateral view, ventrally somewhat broadened.</p>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 8.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus tripui</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Estação Ecológica de Tripuí, Córrego Tiririca, 20°23.009'S, 43°33.237'W, 19.ii.1999, Paprocki, Amarante, Salgado (UMSP000046917) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Two males (UMSP); same data as holotype, Estação Ecológica de Tripuí, Córrego Botafogo, 20°22.908'S, 43°33.615'W, 1100 m, 25.xi.2001, Holzenthal, Paprocki, Blahnik, Neto, 1 male (UMSP); Estação Ecológica do Tripuí, Córrego Tripuí, 20°23.364'S, 43°32.541'W, 1070 m, 1.xi.1998, Paprocki, Braga, Amarante, 1 male (UFRJ); same, except 21.xi.1998, Paprocki, Braga, Amarante, 1 male (MZUSP); Cachoeira do Abacaxi, Vale do Tropeiro, Ouro Preto, 20°12.270'S, 43°38.163'W, 1120 m, 7.xi.2001, Holzenthal, Paprocki, Blahnik, Amarante, 1 male (UFBA).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named for the small stream in the ecological station of the same name, known for harboring an endemic species of onychophoran, <tp:taxon-name>Peripatus acacioi</tp:taxon-name> Marcus and Marcus. <italic>Tripui</italic> is the indigenous Tupi-Guarani word for fast or quick water.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">soniae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:34524969-D2DC-4AD6-94A7-6523CBC47433</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus soniae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. most closely resembles <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus fluminensis</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus tripui</tp:taxon-name>, particularly in the ventral aspect of the compact inferior appendage. It can be separated from these species by the angular dorsolateral flange of the inferior appendage and the narrower and rounded mesolateral process of the preanal appendage.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 6–7 mm. Body dark brown to black; dorsum of head and thorax black, clothed with long, erect dark setae; base of forewing with long, erect black setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs dark brown to black.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view broadly subtriangular, about 3/4 height of segment VIII; in ventral view trapezoidal, anterior corners broadly rounded, sides very slightly constricted mesally, anteriorly, posterior margin slightly concave with very broad, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage slightly curved on basal 1/3 and relatively straight for remainder of length, long, length slightly greater than height of abdomen, basal region<!--PageBreak--> slightly expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage very short, apex rounded, at base broadly joined to ventral 2/3 of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, broadly digitate, slightly shorter than length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, quadrate; dorsolateral flange low, straight dorsally, with prominent caudomesal spine, exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine present, broad, in lateral view rounded, positioned more basad; in ventral view inferior appendage approximately oval, caudomesal spine prominent, acute; mesoventral spine hidden. Phallobase short; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, much shorter than diameter of apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 1 point; endothecal sclerotic band narrow, becoming rapidly less sclerotized toward apex; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel with broad lateral expansions; broad in lateral view, ventrally narrowed.</p>
                    <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 9.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus soniae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Paraná:</bold> Rio Mãe Catira, 10 km N Porto de Cima, 25°21.821'S, 48°52.473'W, 200 m, 8–9.xii.1997, Holzenthal &amp; Huisman (UMSP000033175) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Paraná:</bold> same data as holotype, 10 males, 3 females (UFBA), 10 males, 3 females (UFRJ), 10 males, 3 females (MZUSP), 10 males, 2 females (NMNH), 20 males, 6 females (UMSP); trib. to Rio Mãe Catira, 10.5 km N Porto de Cima, 25°21.778'S, 48°52.590'W, 200 m, 10.xii.1997, Holzenthal &amp; Huisman, 28 males, 2 females (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named for Dr. Sonia N. Lazzari, professor of entomology at the Universidade Federal do Paraná, Curitiba, Brazil, in appreciation of her help and friendship during the junior author’s studies in Brazil.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">cheliceratus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E09DE9A9-2B59-4D75-86B6-03A5EA4EEE81</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name><comment> new species 2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton 1986</xref>: 86–87, 199; Fig. 6.5.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Very similar to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus minero</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cheliceratus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.can be distinguished from that species as well as the other 8 species of the <italic>aguyje</italic> cluster by the shape of the inferior appendage in both lateral and ventral views as well as the lateral aspect of the preanal appendage. Compared to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus minero</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., in lateral view, the caudoventral corner and the dorsoventral flange of the inferior appendage are less angular and the mesoventral spine is absent. Also, in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cheliceratus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. the mesolateral process of the preanal appendage is smaller in dorsoventral length and its mesoventral process is more slender and longer compared to the mesolateral process.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 6.6–7.6 mm. Body dark brown to black; dorsum of head and thorax black, clothed with long, black setae; base of forewing with long, <!--PageBreak-->erect black setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs brown.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view quadrate, about 2/3 height of segment VIII; in ventral view slightly trapezoidal, anterior corners sharply rounded, sides very slightly constricted mesally, anterior margin deeply concave, posterior margin slightly concave with broad, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous, slightly sclerotized ventrally. Intermediate appendage gently curving ventromesad, moderate elongated length about equal to height of sternum IX, basal region simple, not expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage short, apex rounded, at base broadly joined to mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed ventrad to rounded point, digitate, equal in length to mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, generally round; dorsolateral flange low, rounded dorsally, with prominent caudomesal spine, partially exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine absent; in ventral view inferior appendage<!--PageBreak--> approximately oval, caudomesal spine prominent, acute. Phallobase moderately short; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, slightly longer than apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 1 point; endothecal sclerotic band very narrow, becoming less sclerotized apically; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite narrow in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel narrow in posterior and lateral views.</p>
                    <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 10.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cheliceratus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> phallobase, caudal <bold>H</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Rio de Janeiro:</bold> km 17, 18 km S of Teresopolis, 1180 m, 18–19.iv.1977, C.M. &amp; O.S. Flint, Jr. (UMSP000136614) (NMNH).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL:</bold> same data as holotype, 1 male (NMNH); <bold>Rio de Janeiro:</bold> Nova Friburgo, municipal water supply, 950 m, 24.iv.1977, C.M. &amp; O.S. Flint, Jr., 3 males, 1 female (NMNH).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>From the Latin <italic>chela</italic> (Greek <italic>chele</italic>) for claw, in reference to the claw-like form of the inferior appendage of the male genitalia, particularly when viewed in ventral aspect.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">minero</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FE9BF381-404C-4B17-B98E-0699A5F2512D</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name><comment> new species 5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton 1986</xref>: 90–91, 202; Fig. 6.8.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Similar to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cheliceratus</tp:taxon-name>, the more angular shape of the inferior appendage in lateral and ventral aspects as well as the lateral view of the preanal appendage with its larger mesolateral process and shorter, thick mesoventral process distinguishes <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus minero</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. from it and other similar species of the <italic>aguyje</italic> cluster.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 6.4–8.2 mm. Body dark brown; dorsum of head and thorax black; general vestiture of forewing with fine brown setae (in alcohol); legs brown.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view subtriangular, about 3/4 height of segment VIII; in ventral view quadrate, anterior corners broadly rounded, sides slightly constricted anteriorly, anterior margin shallowly concave, posterior margin shallowly concave. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage gently curving ventromesad, moderate elongate, length about two-thirds height of sternum IX, basal region slightly expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage short, apex rounded, with slight ventral extension, at base broadly joined to mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed ventrad to rounded point, broadly digitate, about 2/3 length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, quadrate; dorsolateral flange low, straight dorsally, with prominent caudomesal spine, slightly exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine present, narrow, in lateral view acute, positioned well basad; in ventral view inferior appendage quadrate, caudomesal spine prominent, acute; mesoventral spine hidden. Phallobase moderately short; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, slightly shorter than diameter of apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 1 point; endothecal sclerotic band narrow, becoming less scle<!--PageBreak-->rotized apically; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite narrow in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel with broad lateral expansions; narrow in lateral view, ventrally narrowed.</p>
                    <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 11.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus minero</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Serra do Cipo, Rio Capivara, 6.vii.1974, Froehlich, Shimizu, et al. (NMNH).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL:</bold> same data as holotype, 1 female (NMNH); same, except 18.xii.1973, Froehlich, 4 males (NMNH); same except 9.ii.1974, Exp. Dep. Zool., 1 male, 2 females (NMNH).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The name <italic>minero</italic> is the Portuguese demonym for the inhabitants of Minas Gerais, the Brazilian state where the type specimens were collected.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">carolae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:870EB4ED-EAD0-4CE7-B59F-183A855BE85F</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name><comment> new species 3 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton 1986</xref>: 87–88, 200; Fig. 6.6.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carolae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is most similar in many features to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus minero</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus caaete</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. In <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carolae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., the mesoventral process of the preanal appendage slightly exceeds the mesolateral process, whereas in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus minero</tp:taxon-name> it is shorter and in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus caaete</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. it is much longer. Also, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carolae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.has a shallow excavation in the posterior margin of the inferior appendage while it is absent in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus minero</tp:taxon-name> and deeper in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus caaete</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Finally, the triangular shape of the mesolateral process of the preanal appendage and the small claw-like structure at the apex of the endothecal sclerotic band are unique to this species in the 10-species <italic>aguyje</italic> cluster.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 5.4–6.7 mm. Body dark brown to black; general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs brown.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view subtriangular, about 3/4 height of segment VIII; in ventral view slightly trapezoidal, anterior corners broadly rounded, sides slightly constricted anteriorly, anterior margin moderately concave, posterior margin slightly concave with very broad, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage gently curving ventromesad, long, length slightly greater than height of sternum IX, basal region slightly expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage short, apex slightly triangular, at base broadly joined to mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, digitate, slightly exceeding length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, trapezoidal; posteroventral margin acute below shallow caudal emargination; dorsolateral flange relatively high, straight dorsally, partially exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine present, broad, in lateral view acute, positioned more caudad; in ventral view inferior appendage approximately round, caudomesal spine hidden; mesoventral spine with apex visible. Phallobase moderately short; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, approximately equal to apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 1 point; endothecal sclerotic band narrow, apex terminating in simple claw; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel with broad lateral expansions; narrow in lateral view, ventrally somewhat narrowed.</p>
                    <fig id="F12" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 12.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carolae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g012.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Rio de Janeiro:</bold> km 54, 26 km E Nova Friburgo, 410 m, 19.iv.1977, C.M. &amp; O.S. Flint, Jr. (UMSP000136621) (NMNH).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 3 males, 1 female; same, except 25.iv.1977, 1 female; Rio de Janeiro: Cachoeiras de Macacu, 800 m, 15.x.1985, Miller, 1 male (NMNH); Parque Nacional da Serra dos Órgãos, Guapimirim, Trilha das Ruínas,<!--PageBreak--> 22°29.679'S, 42°59.729'W, 940 m, 28.ii.2002, Blahnik &amp; Paprocki, 2 males (in alcohol) (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named with affection for Mrs. Carol Flint in honor of her numerous and important collections of Trichoptera made over many years across Latin America.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">caaete</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B7D82617-4287-44A9-BA7A-87539353276E</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus caaete</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. appears to be intermediate in appearance between <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carolae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus itatiaia</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. in characters of the inferior appendage. The excavation of its posterior margin is deeper in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus caaete</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., but not as deep as in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus itatiaia</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.; the position of the caudomesal spine is similar to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carolae</tp:taxon-name>, but it is near the upper apical corner in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus itatiaia</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.; and the mesoventral spine is more basad in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus caaete</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. than in the other 2 species. The relative lengths of the 2 processes of the preanal appendage will also separate <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus caaete</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. from the other species. In the thickness of the apicoventral projection of the phallobase and the exposure of the caudomesal spine of the inferior appendage this species bears some resemblance to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus aguyje</tp:taxon-name> but can be separated by other details of the inferior and preanal appendages.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 6–6.5 mm. Body dark brown to black; dorsum of head and thorax black, clothed with long, erect dark setae; base of forewing with long, erect black setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs dark brown to black.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view broadly subtriangular, about 2/3 height of segment VIII; in ventral view slightly trapezoidal, anterior corners sharply rounded, sides slightly constricted anteriorly, anterior margin shallowly concave, posterior margin slightly concave with very broad, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage long, gently curving ventromesad, length slightly greater than height of abdomen; in dorsal view basal region narrow with slightly expanded segment slightly distad, nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage very short, apex rounded, with slight ventral extension, at base broadly joined to medial portion of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, broadly digitate, nearly 2 times the length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, quadrate; posteroventral margin rounded, protruding below caudal emargination; dorsolateral flange low, straight dorsally, with prominent caudomesal spine, partially exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine present, broad, in lateral view acute, positioned more basad; in ventral view inferior appendage approximately oval, caudomesal spine hidden; mesoventral spine with apex visible. Phallobase moderately short; in lateral view apicoventral projection moderately broad, approximately equal to apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 1 point; endothecal sclerotic band narrow, becoming rapidly less sclerotized toward apex; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal <!--PageBreak-->sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms short, pedicel with broad lateral expansions; broad in lateral view, ventrally narrowed.</p>
                    <fig id="F13" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 13.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus caaete</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold>  inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g013.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Santa Catarina:</bold> Parque Ecológica Spitzkopf, Rio Caeté above 1st falls, 27°00.35'S, 49°06.70'W, 170 m, 26.xi.2003, Holzenthal, Paprocki, Calor (UMSP000120814) (MZUSP).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 2 males, 2 females (UMSP); <bold>Paraná:</bold> trib. to Rio Mãe Catira, 10.5 km. N Porto de Cima, 25°21.778'S, 48°52.590'W, 200 m, 10.xii.1997, Holzenthal &amp; Huisman, 1 male (UMSP); <bold>São Paulo:</bold> Parque Estadual Intervales, Rio do Carmo, 24°18.983'S, 48°25.250'W, 560 m, 29.ix.2002, Blahnik, Prather, Melo, Calor, 1 male (UFBA); Agua Comprida @ bridge, 24°17.591'S, 48°25.102'W, 600 m, 30.ix.2002, Blahnik, Prather, Melo, Calor, 2 males, 1 female (MZUSP); Estação Biológica de Boracéia, Rio Claro at bridge, 23°39.002'S, 45°54.889'W, 815 m, 19.ix.2002, Blahnik, Prather, Melo, Silva, 1 male (UFRJ); small stream on São Paulo route 247, 11 km SE Bananal, 22°45.684'S, 44°23.190'W, 675 m, 23.ix.2002, Blahnik, Prather, Melo, Froehlich, Silva, 5 males (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>From <italic>caá-etê</italic>, the Tupi-Guarani word for the Atlantic forest of southeastern Brazil.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">itatiaia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C0F3E691-A6B2-453A-84FE-4C2C9A9A52E5</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Most similar to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus aguyje</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus santateresae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus itatiaia</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. differs in the shape and depth of the emargination in the posterior margin of the inferior appendage as well as the median position of the relatively low mesoventral spine of this appendage. The mesolateral process of the preanal appendage in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus itatiaia</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.is triangular, as it is in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carolae</tp:taxon-name>, and the mesoventral process is shorter and directed more ventrad.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 6–6.5 mm. Body dark brown; dorsum of head and thorax black, clothed with long, erect dark setae; base of forewing with long, erect black setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs dark brown to black.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view subtriangular, about 2/3 height of segment VIII; in ventral view slightly trapezoidal, anterior corners sharply rounded, sides slightly convex, anterior margin shallowly concave, posterior margin slightly concave with very broad, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage slightly curved on basal 1/2 and relatively straight for remainder of length, very long, length greater than height of abdomen, basal region slightly expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage very short, apex slightly triangular, at base broadly joined to medial portion of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed ventrocaudad, digitate, slightly shorter than length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, quadrate; posteroventral margin rounded, protruding below deep caudal emargination; dorsolateral flange low, straight dorsally, with prominent caudomesal spine, slightly exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine present, broad, in lateral view obtuse, positioned medially; in ventral view inferior appendage approximately round, caudomesal spine partially hidden, acute; mesoventral <!--PageBreak-->spine hidden. Phallobase moderately short; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, approximately equal to apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 1 point; endothecal sclerotic band narrow, becoming less sclerotized apically; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite narrow in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel with broad lateral expansions; broad in lateral view, ventrally somewhat narrowed.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <fig id="F14" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 14.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus soniae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g014.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Rio de Janeiro:</bold> Parque Nacional do Itatiaia, trib. to Rio Taquaral, 22°26.688'S, 44°36.464'W, 1320 m, 6.iii.2002, Holzenthal, Blahnik, Prather (UMSP000136573) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 1 female (MZUSP); Parque Nacional do Itatiaia, Rio Campo Belo, trail to Véu da Noiva, 22°25.706'S, 44°37.171'W, 1310 m, 5.iii.2002, Holzenthal, Blahnik, Paprocki, Prather, 1 male, 1 female (UFRJ); Parque Nacional do Itatiaia, Rio Campo Belo, 22°27.033'S, 44°36.818'W, 1300 m, 7.iii.2002, Holzenthal, Blahnik, Paprocki, Prather, 5 males, 2 females (UMSP); <bold>Minas Gerais:</bold> Ibitipoca, sitio of Anestis Papadopolous, 21°43.227'S, 43°54.557'W, 1200 m, 23.x.2000 m, Paprocki, 2 males (UFBA).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named for Parque Nacional Itatiaia where the type specimens were collected. <italic>Itatiaia</italic> means “many-pointed rock” in Tupi-Guarani.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">santateresae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2FB21067-F8C9-443E-B40E-EBA9931300B1</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name><comment> new species 4 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton 1986</xref>: 89–90, 201; Fig. 6.7.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus santateresae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.is distinct in the shorter length of the intermediate appendage compared to other species of the <italic>aguyje</italic> cluster. The body of the mesolateral process of the preanal appendage is round and positioned on the dorsal half of its base. We have noted some variation in the lateral view of the inferior appendages of the material examined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15A and 15H</xref>), but at this time we consider this within the range of variation for <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus santateresae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. This species, particularly the variant from Rio Caparaó in Minas Gerais, is most similar to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus aguyje</tp:taxon-name> in the shape of the caudal excavation of the inferior appendage and the shape of the mesolateral process of the preanal appendage. This species can be separated from <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus aguyje</tp:taxon-name> based on the narrow shape of apicoventral projection of the phallobase and the hidden position of the caudomesal spine of the inferior appendage in lateral view.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 5.5–6.5 mm. Body dark brown; dorsum of head and thorax black, clothed with long, erect dark setae; base of forewing with long, erect dark setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs brown.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view subtriangular, about 3/4 height of segment VIII; in ventral view trapezoidal, anterior corners broadly rounded, sides very slightly constricted mesally, anterior margin shallowly concave, posterior margin slightly concave with very broad, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage gently curving ventromesad, moderate elongate, length slightly less than height of sternum IX, basal region simple, not expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage short, apex rounded, with slight ventral <!--PageBreak-->extension, at base broadly joined to dorsal 1/2 of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, digitate, equal in length to mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, quadrate; posteroventral margin acute below deep caudal emargination; dorsolateral flange relatively high, straight dorsally, hidden in lateral view;<!--PageBreak--> mesoventral spine present, broad, in lateral view obtuse, positioned more basad; in ventral view inferior appendage quadrate, caudomesal spine prominent, acute; mesoventral spine hidden. Phallobase short; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, approximately equal to apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 1 point; endothecal sclerotic band narrow, becoming less sclerotized apically; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite narrow in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel with broad lateral expansions; narrow in lateral view, ventrally somewhat narrowed.</p>
                    <fig id="F15" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 15.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus santateresae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal <bold>H</bold> inferior appendage, variant, lateral (Minas Gerais, Rio Caparaó).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g015.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Espirito Santo:</bold> 15 km SE Santa Teresa, Fazenda Santa Clara, 460 m, 22.iv.1977, C.M. &amp; O.S. Flint, Jr. (UMSP000136628) (NMNH)</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Rio Caparaó, Hotel Parque Caparaó, Alto Caparaó, 20°25.498'S, 41°51.500'W, 830 m, 11–14.iii.2002, Holzenthal, Blahnik, Paprocki, Prather, 1 male (UMSP)</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named for the central Espirito Santo town of Santa Teresa near which this species was collected.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">virginiae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E2F15EC7-EF36-4DA1-BC4D-C44947FE8607</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus virginiae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.is readily distinguished from other <italic>aguyje</italic> cluster species by the shape of the inferior and preanal appendages. Specifically, the prominently visible recurved spine on the inferior appendage as well as the deep excavation below this spine and the large triangular flange lying dorsobasad of the spine are distinct. The mesolateral process of the preanal appendage is broad, low, and round, mostly closely resembling that of only <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus caaete</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 5.5–7 mm. Body dark brown to black; dorsum of head and thorax black, clothed with long, black setae; base of forewing with long, erect black setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine black setae, lacking patches of pale setae; legs dark brown to black.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view broadly subtriangular, about 3/4 height of segment VIII; in ventral view slightly trapezoidal, anterior corners broadly rounded, sides very slightly constricted mesally, anteriorly, anterior margin moderately concave, posterior margin slightly concave with very broad, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage slightly curved on basal 1/2 and relatively straight for remainder of length, very long, length greater than height of abdomen, basal region simple, not expanded; in dorsal view nearly uniform in diameter throughout length, gradually narrowing apically. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage very short, apex rounded, at base broadly joined to mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, digitate, 2 times the length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, trapezoidal; posteroventral margin rounded,protruding below deep caudal emargination; dorsolateral flange relatively high, protruding as rounded triangle, with prominent caudomesal spine, exposed in <!--PageBreak-->lateral view; mesoventral spine present, broad, in lateral view obtuse, positioned well basad; in ventral view inferior appendage approximately round, caudomesal spine partially hidden, acute; mesoventral spine with apex visible. Phallobase moderately short; in lateral view apicoventral projection moderately broad, much shorter than diameter<!--PageBreak--> of apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 1 point; endothecal sclerotic band narrow, becoming less sclerotized apically; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel with narrow lateral expansions; narrow in lateral view, ventrally somewhat narrowed.</p>
                    <fig id="F16" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 16.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus virginiae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g016.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Córrego da Serra de Ouro Fino, Vale do Tropeiro, 20°12.371'S, 43°38.581'W, 1000 m, 8.x.2000 m, Paprocki, Salgado, Isaac (UMSP000046828) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Aldeia da Cachoeira das Pedras, 20°06.824'S, 44°01.412'W, 925 m, 28–29.ix.2000 m, Paprocki &amp; Braga, 1 male (UMSP); Cachoeira do Abacaxi, Vale do Tropeiro, Ouro Preto, 20°12.270'S, 43°38.163'W, 1120 m, 7.xi.2001, Holzenthal, Paprocki, Blahnik, Amarante, 1 male (in alcohol) (MZUSP); Rio Caparaó, Hotel Parque Caparaó, Alto Caparaó, 20°25.498'S, 41°51.500'W, 830 m, 11–14.iii.2002, Holzenthal, Blahnik, Paprocki, Prather, 9 males, 3 females (UMSP); Parque Nacional do Caparaó, Rio Caparaó at Vale Verde, 20°25.029'S, 41°50.767'W, 1350 m, 12–13.iii.2002, Holzenthal, Blahnik, Paprocki, Prather, 2 males (UFBA), 2 males (UFRJ), 1 male (NMNH).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named with affection for Virgina Braga, in recognition for her many years of friendship with the junior author and his family.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">cipoensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E08F9BE7-0F1E-4E93-97B1-C83F6CA28B7F</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name><comment> new species 6 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton 1986</xref>: 91–93, 203; Fig. 6.9.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cipoensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is clearly a member of the <italic>jorgenseni</italic> species complex, but is otherwise easily separated from the other Neotropical <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name> by the inferior appendage which has a triangular base, but extends into a long, narrowed apex and a mesobasal process that is somewhat palmate in its posterior aspect. In addition, the intermediate appendage is short as are the 2 processes of the preanal appendage. The endothecal sclerotic band ends in a pair of prominent hooks, similar to, but larger, than those in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus fluminensis</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus tripui</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus carolae</tp:taxon-name>, and <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus acinaciformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. The apicoventral process of the phallobase, while similar to that seen in other members of the <italic>jorgenseni</italic> species complex, is notably shorter and wider and the apical emargination is broadly u-shape.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 5.8–7.0 mm. Body brown to dark brown; dorsum of head and thorax dark brown, clothed with long, erect dark setae; base of forewing with long, erect dark setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine brown setae, lacking patches of pale setae (in alcohol); legs brown.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view subtriangular, slightly greater than 1/2 height of segment VIII; in ventral view trapezoidal, anterior corners sharply rounded, sides slightly constricted anteriorly, anterior margin shallowly concave, posterior margin slightly concave with broad, shallow convex medial region. Ter<!--PageBreak-->ga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage slightly curved ventrad, short, length about one-half length of inferior appendage, basal region simple, not expanded; in dorsal view narrowly spindle-like. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage very short,<!--PageBreak--> apex truncate, at base broadly joined to dorsal 1/2 of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, broadly truncate, slightly shorter than length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view long, slender; dorsolateral flange low, protruding as rounded triangle, without caudomesal spine; mesoventral spine present, narrow, in lateral view acute, positioned well basad; in ventral view inferior appendage narrowly triangular; mesoventral spine hidden. Phallobase very short; in lateral view apicoventral projection very broad, much shorter than diameter of apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 2 points; endothecal sclerotic band broad, ending in 2-prong hook; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite Y-shaped, arms long, pedicel short, broad; narrow in lateral view, ventrally somewhat broadened.</p>
                    <fig id="F17" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 17.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cipoensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> phallobase, caudal <bold>H</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g017.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male</title>
                    <p><bold>: BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Serra do Cipó, caminho da usina, 7.vii.1974, Froehlich, Shimizu, Carvalho (UMSP000131243) (in alcohol) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> same data as holotype, except, km 110, 24.iv.1975, Froehlich, Carvalho, Shimizu, 1 male (in alcohol) (NMNH); Serra do Cipó, caminho da usina, Rio Capivara, 22.ix.1976, CGF, MAJC, GYS, 1 male, 1 female (in alcohol) (NMNH); same, except 18.xii.1973, Froehlich, 2 males (in alcohol) (NMNH); same, except 18.xii.1974, Froehlich, 1 male (in alcohol) (NMNH); same, except 18.iv.1975, Froehlich, 2 males, 4 females, (in alcohol) (NMNH); same, except afluente Rio Capivara, 19.iv.1975, Froehlich, Carvalho, Shimizu, 6 males, 2 females (in alcohol) (NMNH); Serra do Cipó, Cardeal Mota, Cachoeira Veu da Noiva, 19°18.912'S, 43°36.260'W, 800 m, 12.xi.2001, Holzenthal, Amarante, Blahnik, Paprocki, 8 males (UMSP), 1 male (in alcohol) (UMSP); Serra do Cipó, trib. to Rio Capivara, 19°14.396'S, 43°34.939'W, 1000 m, 18.ii.1998, Holzenthal &amp; Paprocki, 1 male (MZUSP); Serra do Cipó, Mãe d’Agua, Chapeu do Sol, 19°18.807'S, 43°35.665'W, 1000 m, 17.ii.1998, Holzenthal &amp; Paprocki, 1 male, 1 female (UFBA), 1 male, 1 female (UFRJ); km 110, Chapeu do Sol, á luz, 21.xii.1974, 1 male (NMNH); <bold>São Paulo:</bold> Altinópolis, Fazenda São João da Mata, Rio Baguassu, 21°00.588'S, 47°28.900'W, 745 m, 19–21.xi.2003, Holzenthal, Paprocki, Calor, 1 male (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named for Serra do Cipó, the mountain range where the species was collected.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">verruculus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E3AF8858-68AA-457D-BEE3-4BFFAEA60AF2</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 18</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>A member of the <italic>jorgenseni</italic> species complex, <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus verruculus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.is separated from others of this complex by the straight, blade-like intermediate appendage, the setose lateral knob on the mesolateral process of preanal appendage, and the very compact inferior appendage with its apicomesal tooth. Like <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cipoensis</tp:taxon-name>, the apicoventral process of the phallobase is broad and apically emarginated, but in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus verruculus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. the process is much longer and the emargination v-shaped.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 5.5 mm. Body pale brown to yellow; dorsum of head and thorax brown, clothed with long, erect brown setae; base of forewing with long, erect black setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine brown setae and many patches of pale setae scattered over surface; legs stramineous.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 18</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view trapezoidal, slightly greater than 1/2 height of segment VIII; in ventral view slightly trapezoidal, anterior corners very sharply rounded, sides slightly convex, anterior margin moderately concave, posterior margin slightly concave with small, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X mostly membranous with light dorsal sclerotization basally; with numerous scattered minute spicules and several long, slender setae. Intermediate appendage straight, moderate elongate, length equal to height of sternum IX, basal region simple, not expanded; in dorsal view with basal 2/3 blade-like, apical 1/3 narrowed abruptly, apex acute. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage short, apex rounded, laterally with laterally-directed, setose, bulbous lobe. Mesoventral process of preanal appendage absent. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, quadrate; dorsolateral flange low, slightly rounded dorsally, with broad caudomesal spine, hidden in lateral view; mesoventral spine absent; in ventral view inferior appendage rhomboidal, broadest apically, caudomesal spine partially hidden, obtusely pointed. Phallobase moderately elongate; in lateral view apicoventral projection very broad, slightly longer than apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 2 points; separated by mesal v-shaped notch over apical 1/3; endothecal sclerotic band very broad, becoming less sclerotized apically; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite narrow in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite U-shaped, arms short, pedicel absent; narrow in lateral view, ventrally somewhat broadened.</p>
                    <fig id="F18" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 18.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus verruculus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> phallobase, caudal <bold>H</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g018.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Rio Guanhães, downstream from Salto Grande dam, 19°06.289'S, 42°42.635'W, 20.x.1998, Paprocki (UMSP000046608) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratype"><title>Paratype:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: São Paulo:</bold> Altinópolis, Fazenda Sáo João da Mata, Rio Baguassu, 21°00.588'S, 47°28.900'W, 745 m, 19–21.xi.2003, Holzenthal, Paprocki, Calor, 1 male (UMSP)</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Diminutive form of the Latin word for wart, in reference to the wart-like structure on the preanal appendage.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">acinaciformis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:17FF73EC-0951-40D8-AF4C-3094BAE1B8A8</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus acinaciformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.appears to belong to the <italic>jorgenseni</italic> species complex based on the presence of the apicoventral process of the phallobase and the endothecal sclerotic band, but it lacks the intermediate appendages and there is no evidence of the subphallic sclerite. The decurved, blade-like mesolateral process of the preanal appendage as well as the shape of the inferior appendage and the claw-like process in the endotheca distinguish this species from other Neotropical <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 6.5 mm. Body brown; dorsum of head and thorax brown, clothed with long, erect dark setae; base of forewing with long, erect dark setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine brown setae (in alcohol); legs brown.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view broadly subtriangular to oval, about 2/3 height of segment VIII; in ventral view slightly trapezoidal, anterior corners very sharply rounded, sides slightly constricted mesally, anterior margin moderately concave, posterior margin shallowly concave. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate<!--PageBreak--> appendage absent. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage very long, broadest at midpoint, apex acuminate, at base narrowly joined to dorsal portion of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed ventrocaudad, digitate, less than 1/4 length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, quadrate; dorsolateral flange very low, straight dorsally, with prominent caudomesal spine, exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine absent; in ventral view inferior appendage broad basally, slender, tapering apically, caudomesal spine prominent, acute. Phallobase moderately elongate; in lateral view apicoventral projection narrow, approximately equal to apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 1 point; endothecal sclerotic band broad, ending in 2 recurved hooks; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite absent.</p>
                    <fig id="F19" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 19.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus acinaciformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g019.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Serra do Cipó, Capão da Mata, 19°19.347'S, 43°32.249'W, 1170 m, 13–14.ii.1998, Holzenthal &amp; Paprocki (UMSP000033119) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratype"><title>Paratype:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Parque Estadual do Rio Preto, trib to Rio Preto, 18°06.879'S, 43°20.595'W, 700 m, 20.v.1998, Holzenthal &amp; Paprocki, 1 male (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>From the Latin words <italic>acinaces</italic> (Greek <italic>akinakes</italic>) for scimitar and <italic>forma</italic> for shape, in reference to the sword-like shape of the mesolateral process of the preanal appendage.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">rosalysae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0B5B67EF-553D-4B71-B96A-A98472BB2CBC</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Fig. 20</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus rosalysae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.is most similar to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus amphirhamphus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Both lack the intermediate appendage and have an ovoid inferior appendage with apicomesal spine, large triangular mesoventral process of the preanal appendage, and a strongly bifurcate apicomesal process of the phallobase. This species has the sclerotic endothecal band and the apicoventral process of the phallobase is broadly divided to its base. Further, the mesoventral process of the preanal appendage is broadly triangular and its mesolateral process is nearly square. These characters render it distinct from <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus amphirhamphus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. and other Neotropical <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 6.5 mm. Body brown; dorsum of head and thorax brown, clothed with long, erect brown setae; base of forewing with long, erect brown setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine brown setae and many patches of pale setae scattered over surface; legs stramineous.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Fig. 20</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view broadly subtriangular to oval, about 3/4 height of segment VIII; in ventral view trapezoidal, anterior corners very sharply rounded, sides very slightly constricted mesally, anterior margin deeply concave, posterior margin slightly concave with small, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage absent. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage short, apex broadly truncate, at base broadly joined to <!--PageBreak-->mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, broadly triangular, equal in length to mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, generally oval; dorsolateral flange low, rounded dorsally, with prominent caudomesal spine, slightly exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine present, narrow, in lateral view acute, positioned medially; in ventral view inferior appendage quadrate, caudomesal spine mostly hidden, acute; mesoventral spine hidden. Phallobase very short; with paired apicolateral, spur-like, decurved processes on each side of phallobase<!--PageBreak--> apex; endothecal sclerotic band narrow, becoming less sclerotized, broadened apically; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite absent.</p>
                    <fig id="F20" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 20.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus rosalysae</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g020.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: São Paulo:</bold> Parque Estadual de Campos do Jordão, Rio Galharada, 22°41.662'S, 45°27.783'W, 1530 m, 4–5.iii.1996, Holzenthal &amp; Guahyba (UMSP000035686) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named with great honor for the late Dr. Rosalys Guahyba, whose friendship and help were instrumental in advancing our study of the Brazilian caddisfly fauna.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">amphirhamphus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A34C4195-7E85-4C32-B6F9-D80E6FC44C5F</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">Fig. 21</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name><comment> new species 8 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton 1986</xref>: 149–150, 244; Fig. 7.1.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>This new species is similar to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus rosalysae</tp:taxon-name> in the general shape of the preanal and inferior appendages, lack of intermediate appendage, and the bifurcate apicomesal process of phallobase. The strongly bifurcate and extreme elongation of the apicomesal process of phallobase is the most distinctive feature of <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus amphirhamphus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., separating if from all other Neotropical <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name>. Additionally, the inferior appendage lacks the mesoventral spine seen in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus rosalysae</tp:taxon-name> and has a narrower mesoventral process and more ovoid mesolateral process of the preanal appendage compared to that species.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 5.7–6.6 mm. Body pale brown to yellow; dorsum of head and thorax brown; with long, erect setae, area of long, pale setae on vertex of head, darker on thorax; base of forewing with long, erect dark setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine brown setae and many patches of pale setae scattered over surface; legs brown.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">Fig. 21</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view teardrop-shaped, about 2/3 height of segment VIII; anterior corners broadly rounded, sides very slightly constricted mesally, anteriorly, anterior margin moderately concave, posterior margin slightly concave with small, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage absent. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage short, apex broadly triangular, at base broadly joined to dorsal 2/3 of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, very broad basally, narrowing rapidly to slender process, slightly exceeding length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view short, generally round; dorsolateral flange low, rounded dorsally, with prominent caudomesal spine, partially exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine absent; in ventral view inferior appendage approximately oval, caudomesal spine prominent, rounded. Phallobase moderately elongate; with paired apicolateral, blade-like, decurved processes on each side of slightly compressed phallobase apex; endothecal sclerotic band <!--PageBreak-->absent; endothecal spines absent; phallotremal sclerite narrow in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite absent.</p>
                    <fig id="F21" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 21.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus amphirhamphus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g021.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Rio de Janeiro:</bold> Nova Friburgo, municipal water supply, 950 m, 20.iv.1977, C.M. &amp; O.S. Flint, Jr. (UMSP000131231) (in alcohol). (NMNH).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL:</bold> same data as holotype, 1 male (in alcohol) (NMNH); same, except 24.iv.1977, 1 male (NMNH); <bold>Santa Catarina:</bold> Urubici, Morro da Igreja, Cachoeira Veu da Noiva, 28°04.595'S, 49°31.090'W, 1300 m, 5.iii.1998, Holzenthal, Froehlich, Paprocki, 2 males; <bold>São Paulo:</bold> Parque Estadual de Campos do Jordão, Rio Galharada, 22°41.662'S, 45°27.783'W, 1530 m, 13–15.ix.2002, Blahnik, Prather, Melo, Huamantinco, 6 males (UMSP), 1 male (in alcohol) (MZUSP); Estação Biológica Boraceia, Rio Venerando, 23°39.185'S, 45°53.414'W, 850 m, Blahnik, Prather, Melo, Froehlich, Silva, 1 male (in alcohol) (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>From the Greek <italic>amphi</italic> for double and <italic>rhamphos</italic> for a curving beak or bill, in reference to the long, paired beaklike processes on the phallobase of the male genitalia.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">cachoeira</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5A9E2969-A3D3-4001-BF8B-29AE7074D030</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 22</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cachoeira</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.has some similarity to other Brazilian <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name> of the <italic>jorgenseni</italic> species complex. Most notable is the general shape of the phallus and its sclerotic endothecal band as well as the shape of the inferior appendage which resembles that of <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus tripui</tp:taxon-name> except that it is more elongated in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cachoeira</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. This species lacks the intermediate appendage and the subphallic sclerite found in other members of the species complex. <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cachoeira</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.is very similar to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus inusitatus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. in the shape of most of the genitalic structures including a pair of large endothecal spines. The 2 species are reliably separated by details of the preanal appendage and phallus. The mesolateral and mesoventral processes of the preanal appendage are equally long in lateral view and broadly fused in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cachoeira</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., while in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus inusitatus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. the mesoventral process is markedly shorter and not so completely fused to the mesolateral process as seen in dorsal view. In <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cachoeira</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., the apicoventral process of the phallobase is undivided and there is an endothecal sclerotic band, whereas in <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus inusitatus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. the apex of the process is divided and the endothecal band is absent.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 5 mm. Body brown to dark brown; dorsum of head and thorax brown, clothed with long, erect brown setae; base of forewing with long, erect brown setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine brown setae and many patches of pale setae scattered over surface; legs stramineous.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 22</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view broadly subtriangular, about 2/3 height of segment VIII; in ventral view slightly trapezoidal, anterior corners very broadly rounded, sides slightly constricted anteriorly, anterior margin nearly straight, posterior margin slightly concave with small, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous, dorsum with several long, slender setae. Intermediate appendage absent. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage short, apex rounded, with acute caudal point, at base broadly joined to dorsal 1/2 of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, size and shape of mesolateral process, equal in length <!--PageBreak-->to mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view moderately long, rhomboidal; dorsolateral flange low, straight dorsally, with prominent caudomesal spine, exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine absent; in ventral view inferior appendage quadrate, caudomesal spine prominent, acute. Phallobase moderately elongate; in lateral view apicoventral projection broad, slightly longer than apical diameter of phallobase apex,<!--PageBreak--> with 1 point; endothecal sclerotic band very broad, becoming less sclerotized apically; with pair of large endothecal spines; phallotremal sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite absent.</p>
                    <fig id="F22" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 22.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cachoeira</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g022.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Santa Catarina:</bold> Urubici, Cachoeira Avencal, 28°02.839'S, 49°36.997'W, 1260 m, 6.iii.1998, Holzenthal, Froehlich, Paprocki (UMSP000033106) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 2 males (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p><italic>Cachoeira</italic> is Portuguese for cascade or waterfall, in reference to the habitat where the species was collected.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">inusitatus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C77C7962-C590-416E-8017-3ADA378D8011</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23">Fig. 23</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name><comment> new species 9 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hamilton 1986</xref>: 140–142, 239; Fig. 6.45.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus inusitatus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.is most similar to <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus cachoeira</tp:taxon-name>, but may be differentiated from it by the absence of the endothecal sclerotic band, the divided apicoventral process of the phallobase, and the shorter mesoventral process of the preanal appendage.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 5.5–5.8 mm. Body brown; dorsum of head and thorax dark brown; forewings nearly denuded, membrane pale brown with white areas at <italic>r-m</italic>, <italic>m</italic>, <italic>m-cu</italic> crossveins (in alcohol); legs paler apically.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23">Fig. 23</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view trapezoidal, about 2/3 height of segment VIII; in ventral view slightly trapezoidal, anterior corners nearly angular, sides constriction anteriorly, anterior margin nearly straight, posterior margin slightly concave with very broad, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage absent. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage short, apex rounded, shorter ventrally, at base broadly joined to mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, broadly truncate, about 1/2 length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view moderately long, rhomboidal; dorsolateral flange low, straight dorsally, with prominent caudomesal spine, exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine absent; in ventral view inferior appendage rhomboidal, caudomesal spine prominent, acute. Phallobase short; in lateral view apicoventral projection broad, slightly shorter than diameter of apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 2 points; separated by narrow mesal split dividing apical 1/2; endothecal sclerotic band absent; with pair of large endothecal spines; phallotremal sclerite narrow in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite U-shaped, arms long, pedicel absent; very narrow in lateral view.</p>
                    <fig id="F23" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 23.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus inusitatus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>E</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>F</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g023.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Rio de Janerio:</bold> Brejo da Lapa, Itatiaia, Coll. Museum Nacional, R. J., no date (NMNH).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratype"><title>Paratype:</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 1 male (NMNH).</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->The holotype and the paratype were sent to the senior author by Luiz S. W. Terra, Estacao Aquicola, Vila do Conde, Portugal.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Latin for rare, uncommon, or unusual, in reference to our knowledge of only 2 specimens.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycentropus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">paprockii</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E26A63F6-3CC4-4913-96CC-8956F7E65F03</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hamilton &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Fig. 24</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus paprockii</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. has several characteristics that suggest similarity to the 7 species of the <italic>urubici</italic> cluster. In particular, this similarity is suggested by the shape of the inferior appendage in all aspects, the notched apex of the apicoventral process of the phallobase, and the shape of the preanal appendage in dorsal view.<!--PageBreak--> <tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus paprockii</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.lacks the endothecal sclerotic band, but has 2 prominent endothecal spines, which are not found in these other species. The species also lacks the intermediate appendage and the mesolateral process of the preanal appendage is not digitate as in species of the <italic>urubici</italic> cluster.</p>
                    <p>Adult. Length of forewing (male) 5–5.5 mm. Body brown; dorsum of head and thorax brown, clothed with long, erect brown setae; base of forewing with long, erect brown setae, general vestiture of forewing with fine brown setae and many patches of pale setae scattered over surface; legs stramineous.</p>
                    <p>Male. Genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Fig. 24</xref>. Sternum IX in lateral view subtriangular, about 2/3 height of segment VIII; in ventral view quadrate, anterior corners broadly rounded, sides slightly constricted posteriorly, anterior margin very shallowly concave, posterior margin moderately concave with small, shallow convex medial region. Terga IX + X membranous. Intermediate appendage absent. Mesolateral process of preanal appendage moderately long, apex triangular, expanded basally, at base broadly joined to dorsal 2/3 of mesoventral process; mesoventral process directed caudad, broadly digitate, about 1/2 length of mesolateral process. Inferior appendage in lateral view moderately long, somewhat triangular; posteroventral margin acute below shallow caudal emargination; dorsolateral flange low, slightly excavated medially, apically tapered to sharp, inturned point, with broad caudomesal spine, exposed in lateral view; mesoventral spine present, broad, in lateral view obtuse, positioned medially; caudomesal spine forming broad triangular base, obtusely pointed; mesoventral spine with apex visible; apex acute. Phallobase very short; in lateral view apicoventral projection moderately broad, slightly shorter than diameter of apical diameter of phallobase apex, with 2 points; separated by shallow median groove; endothecal sclerotic band absent; with pair of large endothecal spines; phallotremal sclerite wide in dorsal aspect. Subphallic sclerite U-shaped, arms long, pedicel short, broad; very narrow in lateral view.</p>
                    <fig id="F24" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 24.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Polycentropus paprockii</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> lateral (inset, variant, inferior appendage, apex) <bold>B</bold> dorsal <bold>C</bold> ventral <bold>D</bold> inferior appendages, caudal <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral (inset, apicoventral projection of phallobase, caudal) <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal <bold>G</bold> subphallic sclerite, caudal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00001/ZooKeys-076-001-g024.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype male"><title>Holotype male:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Parque Estadual do Rio Preto, Rio Preto, 18°06.993'S, 43°20.373'W, 650 m, 19.v.1998, Holzenthal &amp; Paprocki (UMSP000033123) (MZUSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes:</title>
                    <p> <bold>BRAZIL: Minas Gerais:</bold> Same data as holotype, 1 male (UMSP); Serra do Cipó, Capão da Mata, 19°19.347'S, 43°32.249'W, 1170 m, 13–14.ii.1998, Holzenthal &amp; Paprocki, 1 male (UFBA); same, except 18°07’50"S, 43°20’15"W, 791 m, 12.x.2000 m, Paprocki, Amarante, Salgado, 1 male, 2 females (in alcohol) (MZUSP); same, except trib. to Rio Preto, 18°06.879'S, 43°20.595'W, 700 m, 14.xi.2001, Holzenthal &amp; Paprocki, 1 male, 1 female (UMSP); spring trib. to Rio Macauba, near Pandeiros, 15°28.637'S, 44°44.627'W, 525 m, Paprocki &amp; Blahnik, 1 male (in alcohol) (UFRJ); Rio São Francisco @ BR 135, 8 km S Januaria, 15°35.823'S, 44°23.396'W, 480 m, Holzenthal, Blahnik, Paprocki, Amarante, 2 males (in alcohol) (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named in honor of the collector, Dr. Henrique Paprocki, professor of biology at the Pontifícia Universidade Católica de Minas Gerais, Belo Horizonte, Brazil; in recognition of his contribution to our knowledge of Brazilian caddisflies.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>This work represents many years of work beginning with species described in the dissertation of the senior author and continuing to the present in the Neotropical<!--PageBreak--> caddisfly research at the University of Minnesota. As such, many people have contributed during the many manifestations of this project. For the species described in the senior author’s dissertation, we acknowledge the substantial assistance and hospitality of Oliver S. Flint, Jr. and his wife Carol who collected and gathered many of the specimens as well as giving openly of their home during visits to the National Museum of Natural History. Also greatly appreciated is the support and encouragement provide by John C. Morse during the development, research, and writing of the dissertation by the senior author while at Clemson University, Clemson, South Carolina.</p>
            <p>Assistance in the field and in the museum was rendered by Marcelo Amarante, Roger Blahnik, Virginia Braga, Adolfo Calor, Claudio Froehlich, Henrique Paprocki, Aysha Prather, and Adriano Sanches Melo. We particularly appreciate the efforts of Roger Blahnik who sorted and made preliminary identifications of the more recently collected material.</p>
            <p>This material is based upon work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grant Nos. DEB 9971885 and 0117772. Additional support for travel of the senior author during the development of the manuscript was provided by the Center of Excellence for Field Biology at Austin Peay State University.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Angrisano</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sganga</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Two new species of Trichoptera from Salto Encantado Provincial Park (Misiones Province, Argentina).</article-title> <source>Aquatic Insects</source> <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>271</fpage>-<lpage>278</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barba-Alvarez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bueno-Soria</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> New species of the genus <italic>Polycentropus</italic> Curtis (Trichoptera: Polycentropodidae) from Mexico.</article-title> <source> Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington</source> <volume>107</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>-<lpage>670</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamorro</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Taxonomy and phylogeny of New World <italic>Polyplectropus</italic> Ulmer, 1905 (Trichoptera: Psychomyioidea: Polycentropodidae) with the description of 39 new species.</article-title> <source>  Zootaxa</source> <volume>2582</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>252</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamorro-Lacayo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Seven new species of Polycentropodidae (Trichoptera) from Nicaragua and Costa Rica.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington</source> <volume>105</volume>:<fpage>484</fpage>-<lpage>498</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>OS Jr</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SC </given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> Catalog of the Neotropical Caddisflies (Trichoptera)</source>. Special Publication, <publisher-name>Ohio Biological Survey</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Columbus, Ohio</publisher-loc>, <lpage>239</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>OS Jr</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sykora</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Caddisflies of Hispaniola, with special reference to the Dominican Republic (Insecta: Trichoptera).</article-title> <source> Annals of Carnegie Museum</source> <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<source> Systematics and biogeography of the New World <italic>Polycentropus sensu lato</italic> (Trichoptera: Polycentropodidae)</source>. PhD dissertation, <publisher-loc>Clemson, South Carolina, United States</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Clemson University</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Five new species of Polycentropodidae (Trichoptera) from Ecuador and Venezuela</article-title>. <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>810</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Almeida</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> New species of Polycentropodidae (Trichoptera) from southeastern and southern Brazil</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> The caddisfly genus <italic>Triaenodes</italic> in the Neotropics (Trichoptera: Leptoceridae).</article-title> <source> Zootaxa</source> <volume>511</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Paprocki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blahnik</surname><given-names>RJ </given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Checklist of the Trichoptera (Insecta) of Brazil I</article-title>. <source>Biota Neotropica</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>