<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.73.837</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    A new species of Heser Tuneva, 2005 (Araneae, Gnaphosidae) from the south of India
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Bosselaers</surname>
                        <given-names>Jan</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"></xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:D6AD7414-3540-4F06-8631-8873450AA90C</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>Section of invertebrates, Royal Museum for Central Africa, B-3080 Tervuren, Belgium</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Jan Bosselaers (<email xlink:type="simple">hortipes@dochterland.org</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Yuri Marusik</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>29</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>73</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>11</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>17</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Jan Bosselaers</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:0131B174-BDBC-46EF-827C-5B0A3C6FDEF8</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new species of <tp:taxon-name>Heser</tp:taxon-name> Tuneva, 2005 (Gnaphosidae) is described from the south of India. A key is provided to the species of <tp:taxon-name>Heser</tp:taxon-name> and the importance of Gnaphosidae for the study of world spider biodiversity is briefly discussed.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Dionycha</kwd>
                <kwd>Karnataka</kwd>
                <kwd>Hampi</kwd>
                <kwd>Zelotinae</kwd>
                <kwd>key</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Aponedyopus</italic></kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Heser</tp:taxon-name> Tuneva, 2005 belongs in the gnaphosid subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Zelotinae</tp:taxon-name> by the presence of metatarsal preening combs on legs III and IV, and was delimited by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Tuneva (2005)</xref> based on the possession of a male palp with an elongated, hook-shaped median apophysis, and with a prolateral-basally inserted embolus which has a relatively narrow base and which is extending transversally across the distal end of the palpal bulb. Moreover, the genus can be distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Zelotes</tp:taxon-name> Gistel, 1848 by lacking an intercalary sclerite and terminal apophysis of the male palp, as well as by the absence of coiled median and blind paramedian vulval ducts and the presence of glands <!--PageBreak-->on the insemination ducts in females, and it differs from most other zelotine genera by its large posterior median eyes. As a consequence, <tp:taxon-name>Heser</tp:taxon-name> resembles <tp:taxon-name>Camillina</tp:taxon-name> Berland, 1919 by the shape of the posterior median eyes, wich are large, subtriangular and almost contiguous. However, it differs from that genus by the absence of a bifid, prolateral palpal terminal apophysis, by a different shape of the embolar base and by the absence of a subtriangular to hemicircular anterior median epigynal plate. From <tp:taxon-name>Drasyllus</tp:taxon-name> Chamberlin, 1922, <tp:taxon-name>Heser</tp:taxon-name> also differs by the absence of a bifid palpal terminal apophysis or a median epigynal plate, while it can be easily distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Setaphis</tp:taxon-name> Simon, 1893 by the absence of a terminal coil on the embolus and from <tp:taxon-name>Zelowan</tp:taxon-name> Murphy &amp; Russell-Smith, 2010 by its retrolateral tibial apophysis, which does not consist of two small triangular lobes. At present, <tp:taxon-name>Heser</tp:taxon-name> counts three species: the type species <tp:taxon-name>Heser malefactor</tp:taxon-name> Tuneva, 2005, as well as <tp:taxon-name>Heser aradensis</tp:taxon-name> (Levy, 1998) and <tp:taxon-name>Heser infumatus</tp:taxon-name> (O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1872) which were transferred from <tp:taxon-name>Zelotes</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Tuneva (2005)</xref>. The genus has a known distribution area in the eastern Mediterranean, tropical Africa and central Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Murphy 2007</xref>). On an archaeological mission to the south of India in 2006 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bosselaers and Valcke 2009</xref>), the author collected both sexes of a new species of <tp:taxon-name>Heser</tp:taxon-name> among the ruins of Hampi, the former capital of the Vijayanagar empire (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Filliozat 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Fritz and Michell 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Verghese 2002</xref>). The new species expands the range of the genus to southern India (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 20</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The specimens were observed, photographed and drawn under Euromex MIC 465 and Olympus SZC-X9 binocular microscopes equipped with an eyepiece grid and a Praktica DC42 digital camera.. The vulva (cleared in methyl salicylate) was observed and drawn using a Wild M12 compound microscope. All measurements are in mm, unless otherwise stated. The format for leg spination follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Platnick and Shadab (1975)</xref>, amended for ventral spine pairs according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bosselaers and Jocqué (2000)</xref>. Leg spination is also illustrated in a schematic representation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 9, 11</xref>) where pl, do, rl and ve sides of leg articles are flattened as a folding net (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Dürer 1525</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bosselaers 2009</xref>).</p>
            <p>Abbreviations:</p>
            <p><bold>AER</bold> anterior eye row; <bold>ALE</bold> anterior lateral eyes; <bold>ALS</bold> anterior lateral spinnerets; <bold>AME</bold> anterior median eyes; <bold>fe</bold> femur; <bold>MOQ</bold> median ocular quadrangle; <bold>mt</bold> metatarsus; <bold>pa</bold> patella; <bold>PER</bold> posterior eye row; <bold>PLE</bold> posterior lateral eyes; <bold>PLS</bold> posterior lateral spinnerets; <bold>PMS</bold> posterior median spinnerets; <bold>ti</bold> tibia.</p>
            <p>Abbreviation of institutional collection (curator in parentheses):</p>
            <p><bold>RBINS</bold> Royal Belgian Institute of Natural Sciences, Brussels (L. Baert)<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <p>Heser <bold>Tuneva, 2005</bold></p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Heser</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">vijayanagara</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4CD46D69-8560-49BD-B58F-825F96510C14</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–8, 10–11</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">12–19</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male:India, Karnataka, Hospet, Hampi World Heritage Site, 15°18'27.7"N 76°28'32.8"E, alt. 455 m, under stone close to archaeological office, 25 November 2006, J. Bosselaers leg. (RBINS). Allotype female, same data (RBINS).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>The species can be distinguished from the other three species of <tp:taxon-name>Heser</tp:taxon-name> by the abdominal dorsal scutum in males, the pronounced S-shaped curve of the sperm duct, the small, transversally oriented median apophysis and the hook-shaped embolus tip circling the broad membranous conductor in the male palp, as well as the narrow anterior epigynal hood, the large spermathecae and the circular insemination ducts in females.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Entymology"><title>Entymology.</title>
                    <p> The species epithet is a noun in apposition and refers to the imperial city of Vijayanagara (Hampi, Karnataka, India) among whose ruins the type specimens of the new species were found (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 9</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> Male (holotype). Total length: 5.00. Carapace length: 2.24; width: 1.63. Carapace orange brown, unicolorous, with a deep and narrow fovea in the posterior half (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Eight eyes in two rows, ringed with black, AER width 0.47, straight from above, slightly procurved from front, PER width 0.56, procurved from above, strongly procurved from front. MOQ depth 0.35, anterior width 0.29, posterior width 0.32. Eyes of AER subequal, AME grey and circular, separated by half their diameter, ALE oval, pearly white, touching AME. PME oval to subtriangular, pearly white, touching, larger than AME (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). PLE subquadratic, pearly white, slightly smaller than ALE, separated from PME by half the PLE diameter. Clypeus vertical, slightly larger than diameter of AME. Chilum small, sclerotised, subtriangular and single, orange-brown. Chelicerae brown, with a few scattered thin setae on anterior face, anterior cheliceral rim with two very small teeth close to fang base and three larger teeth further from fang base, posterior cheliceral rim with one very small tooth close to fang base end two medium-sized teeth further from fang base. Sternum smooth, orange-brown, shield-shaped with a thin border, length 1.32; width 1.08. No precoxal triangles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bosselaers and Jocqué 2002</xref>: 247, fig. 1K, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Penniman 1985</xref>: 16) or intercoxal sclerites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bosselaers and Jocqué 2002</xref>: 247), pleural bars (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bosselaers and Jocqué 2002</xref>: 247, fig. 1P; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Simon 1892</xref>: 11, fig. 29) yellow-brown, weakly sclerotised and isolated, not protruding between coxae. Labium brown, longer than wide, with a slightly thickened anterior rim. Endites longer than labium, dumbbell-shaped with oblique depression, and provided with an apical hair tuft (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>). Abdomen mottled grey dorsally, with a <!--PageBreak-->frontal row of curved hairs and a small, shiny, brown anterior do scutum covering less than 10% of abdominal do surface area. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Lateral and ventral sides of abdomen creamy white (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2</xref>). ALS and PLS large and cylindrical, PMS thin and slender, shorter than PLS. Legs yellow-brown, unicolorous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2</xref>). No trochanter notch, no retrocoxal hymen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Raven 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bosselaers and Jocqué 2002</xref>), patellar indentation<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Simon 1892</xref>: 22, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Ledoux and Canard 1991</xref>: fig. 15A-15B) long and narrow, 2/3 of pa length. Metatarsi III and IV with ventral terminal preening comb composed of stiff, black setae. Tarsi with two pectinate claws, no claw tufts. Leg formula 4123. Leg spination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 10</xref>): fe: palp do 0–1-2; I pl 0–0-1 do 1–1-0;II pl 0–0-1 do 1–1-0;III do 1–3-3; IV do 1–3-2; pa: palp pl 1–0 do 0–1; III do 0–2-0; ti: palp do 0–0-1; III pl 1–0-1 do 3–0-0 rl 1–0-1 ve 2–2-2; IV pl 1–0-1 do 1–1-0 rl 1–0-1 ve 2–2-2; mt: III pl 0–1-1 do 2–1-2 rl 0–1-1 ve 2–2-1; IV pl 0–1-1 do 2–2-2 rl 0–1-1 ve 2–2-1; ta: palp pl 1–0-0 do 1–0-0 rl 1–0-0.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–11.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Heser vijayanagara</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <bold>1</bold> Male holotype, dorsal <bold>2</bold> Male holotype, ventral <bold>3</bold> Female allotype, dorsal <bold>4</bold> Female allotype, ventral <bold>5</bold> Male palp, prolateral <bold>6</bold> Male palp, ventral <bold>7</bold> Male palp, retrolateral <bold>8</bold> Epigyne, ventral <bold>9</bold> Pattabhirama temple in close vicinity of the <italic>locus typicus</italic>, giving a good impression of the type of terrain where the type specimens were found <bold>10</bold> Male leg spination diagram, legend below right <bold>11</bold> Female leg spination diagram. Scale bars: 1–4: 1.0; 5–8: 0.25.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00000/supp/ZooKeys-073-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 12–19.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Heser vijayanagara</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <bold>12</bold> Female allotype, dorsal view of body <bold>13</bold> Male palp, ventral, with conductor (C), embolus (E), and median apophysis (MA) indicated <bold>14</bold> Male palp, retrolateral <bold>15</bold> Epigyne, ventral <bold>16</bold> Female metatarsi III (left) and IV, with ventral terminal preening comb <bold>17</bold> Female cheliceral teeth <bold>18</bold> Vulva, ventral <bold>19</bold> Vulva, dorsal. Scale bars: 12: 1.0; 13–17: 0.5; 18–19: 0.1.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00000/supp/ZooKeys-073-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Leg measurements"><title>Leg measurements:</title>
                    <p>.</p>
                    <table-wrap position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">fe</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">pa</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ti</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">mt</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ta</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.21</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.10</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.44</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->Male palp with a slender, basally-prolaterally inserted embolus circling more than half of the tegulum, having a hook-shaped tip pointing in prolateral direction, which is curling around the broad, membranous conductor. Median apophysis small and subtriangular, oriented transversally. Sperm duct with a pronounced, S-shaped curve in basal half of tegulum. Retrolateral tibial apophysis pointed, subtriangular (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 5–7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">13–14</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Female (allotype). Total length: 6.31. Carapace length: 2.37; width: 1.79. Carapace as in male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>). Eyes as in male, AER width 0.53, PER width 0.58, MOQ depth 0.39, anterior width 0.30, posterior width 0.31. PME subtriangular, somewhat smaller than in male, almost touching (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">12</xref>). Clypeus and chilum as in male. Cheliceral teeth as in male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 17</xref>). Sternum smooth, yellow-brown with a darker margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>), shield-shaped with a thin border, length 1.45; width 1.13. No precoxal triangles or intercoxal sclerites, pleural bars as in male. Labium and endites as in male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>). Abdomen pale grey dorsally, with a frontal row of curved hairs and a number of paler chevrons in posterior half, no do scutum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>). Ventral side of abdomen pale white (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>). Legs yellow-brown, unicolorous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3, 4</xref>). No trochanter notch, no retrocoxal hymen, patellar indentation as in male. Metatarsi III and IV with ventral terminal preening comb composed of stiff, black setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 16</xref>). Tarsi with two pectinate claws, no claw tufts. Leg formula 4123. Leg spination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 11</xref>): fe: palp do 0–1-2; I pl 0–0-1 do 1–1-0;II pl 0–0-1 do 1–1-0;III do 1–3-3; IV do 1–3-2; pa: palp pl 1–0 do 1–1; III do 0–2-0; ti: palp pl 0–1-2 do 0–0-1; III pl 1–0-1 do 3–0-0 rl 1–0-1 ve 2–2-2; IV pl 1–0-1 do 1–1-0 rl 1–0-1 ve 2–2-2; mt: III pl 0–1-1 do 2–1-2 rl 0–1-1 ve 2–2-1; IV pl 0–1-1 do 2–2-2 rl 0–1-1 ve 2–2-1; ta: palp pl 0–2-1 do 1–0-0 rl 0–1-0 ve 0–0-2.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Leg measurements"><title>Leg measurements:</title>
                    <p>.</p>
                    <table-wrap position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">fe</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">pa</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ti</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">mt</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ta</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.79</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.76</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.23</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.39</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->Epigyne simple and poorly sclerotised, with a narrow anterior hood and showing large, oval spermathecae, as well as the connected, stout, inward directed part of the looped anterior insemination ducts. Copulatory openings small and medially situated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 8</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">15, 18, 19</xref>). Vulva (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 18, 19</xref>) with two large, thick-walled, oval, posterior spermathecae, connected to the anterior, medially situated copulatory openings by an insemination duct looped over 360°. The first, hemicircular stretch of the looped insemination duct passes dorsally behind the anterior part of the spermathecae, while the second, straight, longitudinally directed stretch carries an accessory gland (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 19</xref>), and the third, stout, outward directed and ventrally situated stretch connects to the large spermathecae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 18</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 20.</label>
                        <caption><p>Distribution map of the four species of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Heser</tp:taxon-name>. <tp:taxon-name>Heser aradensis</tp:taxon-name>: blue square; <tp:taxon-name>Heser infumatus</tp:taxon-name>: yellow triangle; <tp:taxon-name>Heser malefactor</tp:taxon-name>: brown lozenge; <tp:taxon-name>Heser vijayanagara</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.; red circle.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00000/supp/ZooKeys-073-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Key to the species of Heser"><title>Key to the species of Heser</title>
            <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Males</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total length less than 4 mm. Cymbium blunt-tipped, male palpal ti longer than wide, retrolateral tibial apophysis short and blunt (Levy 1998, fig. 116)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Heser aradensis</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total length more than 4 mm. Cymbium pointed, male palpal ti at least as long as wide, retrolateral tibial apophysis triangular and pointed</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membranous conductor of the male palp subtriangular and more or less pointed (Levy 1998, fig. 112)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Heser infumatus</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membranous conductor broad and blunt</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embolus tip pointing towards bulbus base, median apophysis large, with a long basally oriented tip bent outwards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Tuneva 2005</xref>, fig. 10). No dorsal abdominal scutum</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Heser malefactor</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Embolus tip curled around conductor, pointing in prolateral direction. Median apophysis small, triangular, directed transversally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 13</xref>). Small anterior dorsal abdominal scutum.</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Heser vijayanagara</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total length 4 mm or less</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total length 5 mm or more</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No anterior epigynal hood present, copulatory openings relatively small, their long axis directed transversally (Levy 1998, fig. 118)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Heser aradensis</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broad anterior epigynal hood present, copulatory openings large, their long axis oriented longitudinally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Tuneva 2005</xref>, fig. 13)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Heser malefactor</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior epigynal hood broad, copulatory openings a transversal slit, spermatheca diameter smaller than half the longitudinal dimension of the epigyne (Levy 1998, fig. 114)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Heser infumatus</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior epigynal hood narrow, copulatory openings a small oval, their long axis longitudinally oriented, spermatheca diameter about half the longitudinal dimension of the epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 8</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">15, 18, 19</xref>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Heser vijayanagara</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>The family <tp:taxon-name>Gnaphosidae</tp:taxon-name> is one of the largest spider families. In <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Platnick (2010)</xref>, it is listed as the sixth largest family, with 114 genera and 2102 species. Moreover, since <tp:taxon-name>Araneidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Thomisidae</tp:taxon-name>, which presently count more known species, have already been studied rather intensely, also in tropical regions, it is quite probable that <tp:taxon-name>Gnaphosidae</tp:taxon-name> will prove to be the fourth largest spider family known when it has been more thoroughly revised. Indeed, in spite of a number of excellent revisions being available (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Platnick and Shadab 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Platnick and Murphy 1984</xref>), a large number of species is still awaiting description, even in well studied regions such as Spain (Melic 2004, pers. comm.). Many newly discovered species turn out to be endemisms with relatively small distribution areas, again suggesting that many more remain to be discovered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Melic and Barriga 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Snazell and Murphy 1997</xref>). Revisions from tropical or subtropical gnaphosid genera regularly result in a considerable number of new species, especially in the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Zelotinae</tp:taxon-name>, the gnaphosids with metatarsal preening combs listed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Murphy (2007)</xref> as the “<tp:taxon-name>Zelotes</tp:taxon-name>-group” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Murphy and Russell-Smith 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nzigidahera and Jocqué 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Platnick and Murphy 1996</xref>).</p>
            <p>The <tp:taxon-name>Gnaphosidae</tp:taxon-name> of the Indian subcontinent and its surroundings have been studied by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Simon (1897)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Reimoser (1934)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Denis (1958)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Roewer (1961)</xref>, and our knowledge about them has been compiled by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Tikader (1982)</xref>. Additional data were later published by (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Gajbe (1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">2007</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Butt and Beg (2004)</xref>. <tp:taxon-name>Heser</tp:taxon-name> has not yet been mentioned for the region, and none of the zelotine species illustrated by the aforementioned authors resembles the genus. It is possible that <tp:taxon-name>Heser</tp:taxon-name> species are rare, as three out of the four known species are only known from the type locality. Alternatively, <tp:taxon-name>Heser</tp:taxon-name> species may be frequently overlooked because of their small size and nocturnal habits (Levy 1998).</p>
            <p>The recent progress made in the taxonomic study of ground spiders demonstrates that, for a long time to come, <tp:taxon-name>Gnaphosidae</tp:taxon-name>, and <tp:taxon-name>Gnaphosoidea</tp:taxon-name> in general, will remain a prime target for biodiversity studies within Araneae.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>The author is grateful to Dr. S.V.P. Halakatti and to Dr. C.S. Seshadri (Archaeological Survey of India) for their expert guidance through the ruins of Hampi as well as for taking care of many practical aspects of the field visit, and to Mr. Jayant Nadiger (Flanders Investment and Trade, Bangalore) for skilfully organising many of the logistic aspects of the author’s stay in India. Thanks are also due to Yuri Marusik, Mykola Kovblyuk and an anonymous referee for skilled comments that helped improve the manuscript.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosselaers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Studies in Liocranidae (Araneae): redescriptions and transfers in <italic>Apostenus</italic> Westring and <italic>Brachyanillus</italic> Simon, as well as description of a new genus.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2141</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosselaers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jocqué</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Studies in Corinnidae: transfer of four genera and description of the female of <italic>Lessertina mutica</italic> Lawrence 1942.</article-title> <source>Tropical Zoology</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>305</fpage>-<lpage>325</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosselaers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jocqué</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Studies in Corinnidae: cladistic analysis of 38 corinnid and liocranid genera, and transfer of Phrurolithinae.</article-title> <source>Zoologica Scripta</source> <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>-<lpage>270</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosselaers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valcke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>From wood protection to preservation of historic monuments: the commitment of Janssen PMP to cultural heritage conservation</article-title>. In: <source>International Conference on Wooden Cultural Heritage: Evaluation of Deterioration and Management of Change (Hamburg/Germany; October 7–10, 2009)</source>. <lpage>5</lpage> pp. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.woodculther.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.woodculther.org/</ext-link> [accessed: 24 August 2010]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Butt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> New species of <italic>Zelotus</italic> [sic] spider (Araneae: Gnaphosidae) from Pakistan.</article-title> <source>Pakistan Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>307</fpage>-<lpage>312</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Denis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>)<article-title> Araignées (Araneidea) de l’Afghanistan. I.</article-title> <source>Videnskabelige Meddelelser fra Dansk naturhistorisk Forening i Kobenhavn</source> <volume>120</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>-<lpage>120</lpage>.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dürer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1525</year>) <source>Underweysung der Messung mit den Zirckel, und Richtscheyt, in linien, ebnen und gantzen Corporen</source>. <publisher-name>Hieronymus Andreas Formschneider</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Nuremberg</publisher-loc>, <lpage>178</lpage> pp. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://digital.slub-dresden.de/fileadmin/data/27778509X/27778509X_tif/jpegs/27778509X.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://digital.slub-dresden.de/fileadmin/data/27778509X/27778509X_tif/jpegs/27778509X.pdf</ext-link> [accessed: 24 August 2010]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gajbe</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> A new <italic>Drassyllus</italic> spider from India (Araneae: Gnaphosidae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the zoological Survey of India</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>289</fpage>-<lpage>290</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gajbe</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Studies on some spiders of the family Gnaphosidae (Araneae: Arachnida) from Madhya Pradesh, India.</article-title> <source>Records of the zoological Survey of India</source> <volume>105</volume> (<issue>3–4</issue>):<fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gajbe</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Araneae: Arachnida. In Fauna of Madhya Pradesh (including Chhattisgarh), State Fauna Series.</article-title> <source>Zoololgical Survey of India</source> <volume>15</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>419</fpage>-<lpage>540</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Filliozat</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Hampi Vijayanagar. Histoire et légendes</source>. <publisher-name>Editions Âgamât</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Palaiseau</publisher-loc>, <lpage>160</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>New light on Hampi. Recent research at Vijayanagara</source>. <publisher-name>Marg Publications</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Mumbai</publisher-loc>, <lpage>140</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ledoux</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>Initiation à l’étude systématique des araignees</source>. <publisher-name>J.-C. Ledoux, imprimeur &amp; éditeur</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Aramon</publisher-loc>, <lpage>66</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Melic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barriga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Arañas nuevas o interesantes de la fauna ibérica (Araneae: Gnaphosidae y Corinnidae).</article-title> <source>Revista Ibérica de aracnolgía</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>-<lpage>197</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Gnaphosid genera of the world</source>. <publisher-name>British Arachnological Society</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dorchester, Volumes 1 and 2</publisher-loc>, <lpage>605</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell-Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title><italic>Zelowan</italic>, a new genus of African zelotine ground spiders (Araneae, Gnaphosidae)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Afrotropical Zoology</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nzigidahera</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jocqué</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> An update of <italic>Zelotibia</italic> (Araneae, Gnaphosidae), a spider genus with a species swarm in the Albertine Rift.</article-title> <source>Zookeys</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Penniman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <source>Revision of the <italic>britcheri</italic> and <italic>pugnata</italic> groups of <italic>Scotinella</italic> (Araneae, Corinnidae, Phrurolithinae) with a reclassification of phrurolithine spiders</source>. <publisher-name>Columbus: The Ohio State University</publisher-name>, PhD dissertation, available through University Microfilms International (n° 8510623).</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>The World Spider Catalog, version 10.5</source>. <publisher-name>The American Museum of Natural History</publisher-name>. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://research.amnh.org/iz/spiders/catalog/" xlink:type="simple">http://research.amnh.org/iz/spiders/catalog/</ext-link> [accessed 24 August 2010].</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>A revision of the spider genera <italic>Trachyzelotes</italic> and <italic>Urozelotes</italic> (Araneae, Gnaphosidae)</article-title>. <source>American Museum Novitates</source> <volume>2792</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>A review of the zelotine ground spider genus <italic>Setaphis</italic> (Araneae, Gnaphosidae)</article-title>. <source>American Museum Novitates</source> <volume>3162</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shadab</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>)<article-title> A revision of the spider genus <italic>Gnaphosa</italic> (Araneae, Gnaphosidae) in America.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</source> <volume>155</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shadab</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> A revision of the American spiders of the genus <italic>Zelotes</italic> (Araneae, Gnaphosidae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</source> <volume>174</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>-<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Revision of the Australian genera of the Miturgidae with a preview of their relationships</article-title>. In: <source>XIVth International Congress of Arachnology, Abstracts</source>: <lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Reimoser</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1934</year>)<article-title> Araneae aus Süd-Indien.</article-title> <source>Revue suisse de zoologie</source> <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>465</fpage>-<lpage>511</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roewer</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>) <article-title>Araneae Dionycha aus Afghanistan I</article-title>. <source>Acta Universitatis Lundensis (Neue Folge) (2)</source><volume>58</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1892</year>) <source>Histoire Naturelle des Araignées. Tome 1</source>. <publisher-name>Roret</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <lpage>1084</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1897</year>)<article-title> Arachides recueillis par M. M. Maindron à Kurrachee et à Matheran (près Bombay) en 1896.</article-title> <source>Bulletin du Muséum d’histoire naturelle de Paris</source> <volume>1897</volume>:<fpage>289</fpage>-<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Snazell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> <italic>Zelominor</italic> (Araneae, Gnaphosidae), a new genus of zelotine spider from the Western Mediterranean region.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British arachnological society</source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>260</fpage>-<lpage>264</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tikader</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Family Gnaphosidae</article-title>. In: <source>The fauna of India (Vol II spiders: Araneae)</source>, <publisher-loc>Calcutta</publisher-loc>: <fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>536</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuneva</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> A contribution on the gnaphosid spider fauna (Araneae: Gnaphosidae) of east Kazakhstan.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Logunov</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penney</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>European Arachnology 2003 (Proceedings of the 21st European Colloquium of Arachnology St.-Petersburg, 4–9 August 2003)</source>. <article-title>Arthropoda Selecta, Special Issue</article-title> <volume>1</volume> :<fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>332</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Verghese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Hampi. Monumental legacy</source>. <publisher-name>Pauls Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc>, <lpage>95</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>