<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.64.454</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Description of a new species of the genus Tribasodites Jeannel (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Pselaphinae) from East China with a key to world species</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Zhao</surname>
                        <given-names>Mei-Jun</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:0ECB7F20-F2B5-4495-8FFD-3D6192E1D557</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Yin</surname>
                        <given-names>Zi-Wei</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:C515106C-5782-4471-AE11-483B49606A67</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Li</surname>
                        <given-names>Li-Zhen</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:BBACC7AE-9B70-4536-ABBE-54183D2ABD4</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1"><label>1</label> Department of Biology, College of Life and Environmental Sciences, Shanghai Normal University, Shanghai, P. R. China</aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Li-Zhen Li (<email xlink:type="simple">lizhenli@shnu.edu.cn</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Roberto Poggi</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
						
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>64</issue>
            <fpage>25</fpage>
            <lpage>31</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>27</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>29</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Mei-Jun Zhao, Zi-Wei Yin, Li-Zhen Li</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:0ECB7F20-F2B5-4495-8FFD-3D6192E1D557</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A remarkable new species of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites</tp:taxon-name>, 1960, <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites spinacaritus</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold> is described and illustrated from Zhejiang Province, East China. A key to world species of the genus is provided. Systematic position of the new taxon is discussed.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Coleoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Staphylinidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Pselaphinae</kwd>
                <kwd>Tribasodites</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>East China</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <!--PageBreak-->
    
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites</tp:taxon-name> was erected by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Jeannel (1960)</xref> to accommodate two new species, <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites antennalis</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites frontalis</tp:taxon-name>, both described from North India. Twenty-six years later, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Nomura (1986)</xref> added a third species to the genus, <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites picticornis</tp:taxon-name> collected in a colony of <tp:taxon-name>Paratrechina flavipes</tp:taxon-name> (Smith) in Japan. Afterwards, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Nomura (2000)</xref> listed eight species of <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites</tp:taxon-name> based on the materials collected from Yunnan, but without <!--PageBreak-->specific name and description. Then, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Nomura (2007a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2007b)</xref> transferred two species <tp:taxon-name>Batrisodes semipunctatus</tp:taxon-name> Raffray, 1912 (Taiwan) and <tp:taxon-name>Batrisodes coiffaiti</tp:taxon-name> Jeannel, 1958 (Japan) to <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites</tp:taxon-name>. So far, five species of the genus have been known in the world.</p>
            <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites</tp:taxon-name> can be readily distinguished from its allies by a combination of the following characters: 1) male with sexually modified head or antenna; 2) pronotum with a pair of spines or denticles on lateral sides, disc with a median longitudinal sulcus; 3) elytra each with three basal foveae; 4) male metatrochanter spinulate or simple; 5) the first visible tergite (morphologically tergite IV) weakly concave near base, paratergites reduced to a pair of triangular plates demarcated by lateral carinae; 6) aedeagus asymmetrical, usually with a dorsal apophysis well-developed to totally reduced or absent.</p>
            <p>During studies on the Chinese <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites</tp:taxon-name>, some specimens were collected during a short expedition to Tiantongshan Mountain, Zhejiang Province, East China. The examination of the material revealed a remarkable species which is unknown to science.</p>
            <p>The purpose of the present paper is to describe this new species under the name of <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites spinacaritus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., and to provide a key to all known species. The systematic position of the new species is also discussed.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Specimens were collected from decaying leaf litter of the forest floor by sifting and were killed with ethyl acetate and then dried. Dissections were made in 75% ethanol; genitalia and small parts were mounted in Euparal on plastic slides that were placed on the same pin with the specimens. Photos of habitus were taken by a Canon EOS 40D Camera mounted with an MP-E 65 mm Macro Photo Lens; photos of dissected parts were taken by a Canon G9 camera mounted on an Olympus CX21 microscope; line drawings were made by Adobe Illustrator CS2.</p>
            <p>The terminology follows Chandler, 2001. ‘/’ slash is used in the text to separate different lines of the label.</p>
            <p>Type series are deposited in the Insect Collection of Shanghai Normal University, Shanghai, China (=SHNUC)</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Tribasodites</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">spinacaritus</tp:taxon-name-part>
		                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:ECD13679-7279-4023-9CBF-6C3E353F8EB2</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Yin, Li &amp; Zhao</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"/>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">22</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality"><title>Type locality.</title>
                    <p>East China, Zhejiang Province, Tiantongshan Mountain.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                    <p>HOLOTYPE, male: ‘CHINA: ZHEJIANG Prov. / Ning’bo City / Tiantongshan Mt./alt. 350 m, 24–26.iv.2009/Ting FENG leg.’ (SHNU). PARATYPES: 4 males, 6 females, same label data as holotype (SHNU)</p>

                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    	<label>Figures 1–2.</label>
                        <caption><p> Dorsal habitus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites spinacaritus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>1</bold> male <bold>2</bold> female.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-064-025-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>

                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                   <sec sec-type="Male"><title>Male.</title>
                    <p>Length 2.2–2.4 mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Reddish brown, maxillary palpi and tarsi lighter.</p>
                    <p>Head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>) slightly wider than long, nearly triangular, covered with short hair on dorsal surface. Clypeus arcuate on anterior margin. Labrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>) longer than wide, with rows of long setae anterolaterally, anteromedian margin with four minute specialized setae. Mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 6–7</xref>) with one large apical tooth and much smaller subapical tooth and row of median teeth on cutting edge; outer margin with long seta in apical one-third. Maxillary palpus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>) with palpomere I minute, II pedunculate with anterior third broadened, III nearly triangular, IV predominately large, nearly fusiform. Labium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 9</xref>) slightly wider than long, rounded laterally, labial palpus composed of large basal segment and setae-like terminal segments; lateral lobe setose. Frons depressed between antennal tubercles. Vertex convex, with one pair of vertexal foveae connected by short U-shaped carina and with median keel. Eyes large and prominent, situated in basal two-fifths of head length, not emarginated, multifaceted, each composed of about 55 facets. Postgenae nearly rounded, with pair of lateral carinae extended to antennal <!--PageBreak-->tubercles. Gular area slightly depressed; gular foveae merged into single pit. Gular carina present. Antenna long and elongate, scape large, about 1.5 times as long as wide. Pedicle much smaller than scape, subcylindrical; antennomeres III–VIII each wider than long, transverse; club three-segmented with antennomeres IX–XI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>) modified, roughly granulated. X about twice as wide as and 1.5 times as long as VIII, nearly triangular, X slightly longer than wide, inner side strongly concaved, with several short and thick setae; XI the largest, widest in the middle, inner antebasal part strongly protuberant.</p>

                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    	<label>Figures 3–14.</label>
                        <caption><p>Details of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites spinacaritus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>3</bold> head <bold>4</bold> male antennal club <bold>5</bold> labrum <bold>6</bold> right mandible, dorsal view <bold>7</bold> left mandible, ventral view <bold>8</bold> left maxilla <bold>9</bold> labium <bold>10</bold> pronotum <bold>11</bold> left metathoracic wing <bold>12</bold> mesotibia <bold>13</bold> apical protuberance of mesotibia, enlarged <bold>14</bold> metatrochanter and metafemur. Scales: <bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>, <bold>h</bold>, <bold>i</bold>, <bold>j</bold> and <bold>l</bold> = 0.2 mm, <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold>, <bold>e</bold>, <bold>f</bold>, <bold>g</bold>, and <bold>k</bold> = 0.1 mm. Abbreviations: <bold>abs</bold> = antebasal spine; <bold>ap</bold> = apical protuberance; <bold>at</bold> = apical tooth; <bold>att</bold> = antennal tubercle; <bold>aIX–aXI</bold> = antennomere <bold>IX</bold>–antennomere XI; <bold>ca</bold> = cardo; <bold>dls</bold> = disc longitudinal sulcus; <bold>gal</bold> = galea; <bold>iblf</bold> = inner basolateral foveae; <bold>lac</bold> = lacinia; <bold>llh</bold> = lateral lobe of hypopharynx; <bold>lls</bold> = lateral longitudinal sulcus; <bold>lp</bold> = labial palpus; <bold>ls</bold> = lateral spine; <bold>lss</bold> = labral specialized setae; <bold>mdr</bold> = mandibular dorsal ridge; <bold>mls</bold> = median longitudinal sulcus; <bold>mn</bold> = mentum; <bold>mt</bold>= metatrochanter; <bold>mvr</bold> = mandibular ventral ridge; <bold>oblf</bold> = outer basolateral foveae; <bold>oms</bold> = outer marginal seta; <bold>pf</bold> = palpifer; <bold>pI–pIV</bold> = palpomere I–palpomere IV; <bold>rmt</bold> = row of median teeth; <bold>sat</bold> = subapical tooth; <bold>st</bold> = stipes.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-064-025-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>                   

                    <p>Pronotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>) wider than long, lateral sides each with one median spine; with one pair of lateral and one pair of discal longitudinal sulci, one pair of antebasal spines near basal margin of pronotum, one pair of lateral antebasal foveae and two pairs of basolateral foveae distinct.</p>
                    <p>Elytra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 17</xref>) convex, longer than wide, narrowed toward base. Each tri-foveate; discal stria extended to half of elytral length; sutural stria present. Metathoracic wings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 11</xref>) fully developed, widest at middle, gradually narrowed from middle toward<!--PageBreak--> apex and base, apex rounded. Venter with clear pairs of lateral mesoventral foveae and lateral metaventral foveae.</p>
                    <p>Legs normal in structure. Mesotibia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 12–13</xref>) with apical protuberance. Metatrochanter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 14</xref>) not spinose.</p>
                    <p>Abdomen with first visible tergite (morphologically tergite IV) largest, mediobasal foveae, basolateral foveae and basomedian cavity present; discal carinae very short; tergites V–VII successively shorter and narrower, each with pair of lateral foveae. Tergite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 15</xref>) transverse, posterior side nearly flattened. Sternites IV–VII each transverse, successively shorter and narrower, each with pair of lateral foveae. Sternite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>) transverse, with anterior margin strongly emarginated and posterior margin flattened. Sternite IX (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 18</xref>) membranous.</p>
                    <p>Aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 20–22</xref>) with dorsal apophysis totally absent; parameres reduced, forming a ventral stalk with median lobe; endophallus elongate, very weakly sclerotized, gradually expanded posteriad; basal foramen large; basal bulb round posteriorly.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Female"><title>Female</title>
                    <p>Body size similar to male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>). Antennal club not modified. Eyes smaller than in male. Metathoracic wing slightly smaller than in male. Mesotibiae not protuberant at apex. Tergite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 17</xref>) semispheric. Sternite VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 18</xref>) transverse. Sternite IX reduced.</p>

                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    	<label>Figures 15–22.</label>
                        <caption><p> Details of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites spinacaritus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>15</bold> male tergite VIII <bold>16</bold> male sternite VIII <bold>17</bold> femal tergite VIII <bold>18</bold> female sternite VIII <bold>19</bold> male sternite IX <bold>20</bold> aedeagus, lateral view <bold>21–22</bold> aedeagus in ventral view. Scales: <bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold>, <bold>f</bold>, <bold>g</bold>, and <bold>h</bold> = 0.2 mm; <bold>e</bold> = 0.1 mm. Abbreviations: <bold>bb</bold> = basal bulb; <bold>bf</bold> = basal foramen; <bold>vs</bold> = ventral stalk.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-064-025-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>              

                    </sec>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific name refers to the metatrochanter without any spine or protuberance.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Relationship"><title>Relationship.</title>
                    <p>The male genitalia of the new species is somewhat similar to that of <tp:taxon-name>Batrisodes</tp:taxon-name> or some species of <tp:taxon-name>Batrisus</tp:taxon-name> genus-group, and the male spine on the hind trochanter is absent in the new species, which makes the new species looks similar to <tp:taxon-name>Batrisodes</tp:taxon-name> in some male sexual characters. But it is still quite different from <tp:taxon-name>Batrisodes</tp:taxon-name>. The new species is placed in <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites</tp:taxon-name> because of the following reasons: 1) the prothorax of the new species has basic characters (spinulate lateral margins) of the <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodes</tp:taxon-name> genus-group, which never occurs in the <tp:taxon-name>Batrisodes</tp:taxon-name> belonging to <tp:taxon-name>Batrisus</tp:taxon-name> genus-group (both genus-groups were defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Nomura and Idris 2003</xref>), 2) its male genitalia is strictly asymmetrical, which does not match the symmetrical male genitalia of <tp:taxon-name>Batrisodes</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                    <p>The new species is most close related to <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites picticornis</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites antennalis</tp:taxon-name> by relatively large body size and sexually modified antennal club. <tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites spinacaritus</tp:taxon-name> can be readily distinguished by the absence of metatrochanteral spine on posterior margin and simple structure of aedeagus, while all the other species have spinulate metatrochanter and aedeagus with fully-developed dorsal apophysis.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to species of Tribasodites Jeannel"><title>Key to species of Tribasodites Jeannel</title>
                    <p>.</p>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
															
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sexual character presents only on head, head with large excavation on vertex in male</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
															
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sexual character present only on antenna</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
															
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body medium-sized, less than 2.0 mm in length; head with a short median keel and a pair of acinous patches above postgenae</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites semipunctatus</tp:taxon-name> (Raffray, 1912) (China: Taiwan)</td>
                                </tr>
															
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body large-sized, no less than 3.0 mm in length; head lacking median keel and pair of acinous patches above postgenae</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites frontalis</tp:taxon-name> Jeannel, 1960 (India: Himachal Pradesh, Uttar Pradesh)</td>
                                </tr>
															
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metatrochanter without spine or protuberance on posterior margin</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites spinacaritus</tp:taxon-name>Yin et al., sp. n. (China: Zhejiang)</td>
                                </tr>
															
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metatrochanter with a spine or a protuberance on posterior margin</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                </tr>
															
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body large-sized, no less than 2.5 mm in length; antennomere X nearly triangular, not modified in structure</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites antennalis</tp:taxon-name> Jeannel, 1960 (India: Himachal Pradesh, Uttar Pradesh)</td>
                                </tr>
															
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body medium-sized, less than 2.0 mm in length; antennomere X not triangular, variously modified in structure</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                </tr>
															
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eyes very small, less than 40 facets; antennomere IX clearly larger than X in male, with a conical protuberance on inner side, slightly smaller than X and symmetrical in female; pronotum without lateral process, but with a pair of small antebasal denticles; each protibia with a large denticle on inner side near the middle in male</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites coiffaiti</tp:taxon-name> (Jeannel, 1958) (Japan: Kawauchi)</td>
                                </tr>
															
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eyes developed, more than 50 facets; antennomere IX smaller than X in male, X asymmetrical in male, symmetrical and subglobose in female; pronotum with a pair of large lateral processes and with a pair of antebasal denticles; protibia slender and simple in both sexes</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Tribasodites picticornis</tp:taxon-name> Nomura, 1986 (Japan: Okinawa Island)</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We are most grateful to Dr. Shûhei Nomura (Tokyo, Japan) for his great help to the present study and continuous guidance and encouragement during our work on Chinese pselaphines. We would like to thank Roberto Poggi (Genova, Italy) and Peter Hlaváč (Slovakia) for critically reading the manuscript and providing useful comments. Comments from two anonymous reviewers also improved the paper. The study is supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 30870323) and Shanghai Normal University (No. SK200833, No. SK200834).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <label>References</label>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeannel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1960</year>)<article-title> Sur les Psélaphides (Coleoptera) de l’Inde septentrionale.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History), Entomology</source> <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>-<lpage>456</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of two new myrmecophilous species of the family Pselaphidae (Coleoptera) from Japan.</article-title> <source>Kontyû</source> <volume>54</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>498</fpage>-<lpage>503</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>A list of the pselaphine and protopselaphine species (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae) collected from Yunnan, Southwest China in 1992–1998</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imadate</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Taxonomical Studies on the Soil Fauna of Yunnan Province in Southwest China</source>. <publisher-name>Tokai University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Tokai</publisher-loc>, <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>238</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007a</year>)<article-title> Two new species of the genus <italic>Batrisodes</italic> (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Pselaphinae) from Taiwan.</article-title> <source>Elytra</source> <volume>35</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>76</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007b</year>)<article-title> Taxonomical notes on the Japanese species of the genus <italic>Batrisodes</italic> Reitter, with a description of a new species from Yonagunijima Island of the Ryukyus (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae: Pselaphinae).</article-title> <source>Entomological Review of Japan</source> <volume>62</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Idris</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Faunistic notes on the batrisine species from Malaysia and Singapore (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae: Pselaphinae).</article-title> <source>Serangga, Bangi</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>