<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.236.3930</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>The first hypothelminorheic Crustacea (Amphipoda, Dogielinotidae, 
                    <italic>Hyalella</italic>) from South America
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
                        <given-names>Stella Gomes</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:AB01855C-FBD6-426B-96AA-1321A509D4DB</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Bueno</surname>
                        <given-names>Alessandra Angélica de Pádua</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:EFFD4765-AB7C-4100-BA86-C9CCB88F3EAF</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Rodrigo Lopes Ferreira</surname>
                        <given-names></given-names>
                    </name>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:139F3313-234C-41B2-A698-F1189F4318D2</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Universidade Federal de Lavras, Departamento de Biologia, Setor de Zoologia, Programa de Pós-Graduação em Ecologia Aplicada, Campus Universitário, 37200-000, Lavras, Minas Gerais, Brazil
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Stella Gomes Rodrigues (<email xlink:type="simple">stellabioufla@gmail.com</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: C. Coleman</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>2</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>236</issue>
            <fpage>65</fpage>
            <lpage>80</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>31</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>26</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Stella Gomes Rodrigues, Alessandra Angélica de Pádua Bueno, Rodrigo Lopes Ferreira</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:3F2A5556-3BFF-43A3-9E78-1DFCA4DC1862</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Most of known troglobiotic species occur in caves and subterranean environments from great depths. However, recently more attention has been given to other subterranean environments, such as the hypothelminorheic habitats. It comprises the most superficial among all subterranean habitats. This kind of environment is characterized by the constant presence of wet spots, absence of light and very particular abiotic characteristics, comprising unique species. The first hypothelminorheic Amphipoda from South America is here described, a new species of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella</tp:taxon-name></italic> which occurs in a wetland on Southern Brazil. The new species differs from other troglobiotics of the genus by the presence of a curved seta on the inner ramus of uropod 1 and elongation of appendices, as the first pair of antennae and peraeopods 6 and 7. However, human impacts in the area where the new species occurs have changed heavily their habitat, which may have led the species to a critical level of threat or even extinction, demonstrating the fragility of this environment.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Amphipoda</kwd>
                <kwd>hypothelminorheic</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Hyalella</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>biodiversity</kwd>
                <kwd>conservation</kwd><!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>For decades cave organisms, especially those more adapted, were thought to be associated mainly to deep portions of caves. Although it was known that the subterranean environment was much wider than macro-caves, the study of cave fauna has been historically focused on them. There are many studies concerning other subterranean habitats, especially the MSS (“<italic>Milleu Souterrain Superficiel</italic>”), and many troglobiotic species (exclusively subterranean-dwellers) were found in such habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Juberthie et al. 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Racovitza 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Juberthie and Decu 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Růžička 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Juberthie 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Culver and Pipan 2009a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">2009b</xref>). However, recently more attention has been given to superficial subterranean compartments, which are generally called “shallow subterranean habitats” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Culver and Pipan 2009a</xref>).</p>
            <p>Among a great variety of such habitats, there is the hypothelminorheic habitat. This habitat comprises the most superficial subterranean habitat. It is characterized by the presence of persistent wet spots fed by subterranean water in depressions of moderately sloped areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Culver et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Culver and Pipan 2009a</xref>). There is no light in such habitats, like in caves; physical and chemical properties are unique, such as the abundance of organic matter, drainage area of less than 10.000 m<sup>2</sup>, high conductivity and lower annual variation of temperature when compared with surface waters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Culver et al. 2006</xref>). Hypothelminorheic habitats may comprise species unique to this habitat or common to other subterranean environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Culver and Pipan 2009a</xref>).</p>
            <p>Amphipods are among the species that may be found in hypothelminorheic habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Fiser et al. 2010</xref>). In Europe and North America, there are species known to be restricted to such habitats. However, there are no records of hypothelminorheic species from South America, especially due to the lack of studies concerning this kind of habitat. The Neotropics comprises about 7% of described freshwater species, and the diversity of South America in family, genus and species levels is relatively low when compared with other regions of the planet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Väinölä et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
            <p>Freshwater South American amphipods belong to the families <tp:taxon-name>Dogielinotidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Bogidiellidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Ingolfiellidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Phreatogammaridae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Pontogeneiidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Paraleptamphopidae</tp:taxon-name>. However, in South America, these families are restricted to subterranean environments, except <tp:taxon-name>Dogielinotidae</tp:taxon-name>, and most of them comprise few species. On the other hand, <tp:taxon-name>Dogielinotidae</tp:taxon-name> is widespread, the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Smith, 1874 is found in many different epigean habitats, besides some troglobitic species that occur in caves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Grosso and Peralta 1999</xref>).</p>
            <p>At present, there are 56 described species for this genus, of which 14 occur in Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bastos-Pereira and Bueno 2012</xref>). Two of them are troglobiotic and both occur in caves of the São Paulo state, Southeastern of the country (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Cardoso et al. 2011</xref>). Certainly the diversity of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella</tp:taxon-name></italic> is underrepresented, particularly with respect to species that occur in subterranean environments, what results from few studies concerning the genus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Väinölä et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
            <p>The aim of this work is to describe the first hypothelminorheic <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, which also represents the first hypothelminorheic species described for South America. We also discuss about the habitat loss of this new species, considering even the possibility of its extinction due to anthropogenic actions.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The specimens were collected in July 2002, on a wetland in the municipality of Roque Gonzales, Rio Grande do Sul state, Southern Brazil. The sampling was made with the aid of a handnet, which collected the sediment, water column and the riparian vegetation.</p>
            <p>Body and head length of the animals were measured through an optic microscope with a milimetric scale. The body measurement was made from the tip of the head to the base of telson. Ten animals (five males and five females) were dissected and the appendices were mounted on permanent slides, which were used to illustrate the new species.</p>
            <p>The description was made based on main morphological characteristics of Brazilian species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, such as the gnathopods, uropods and telson, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">González et al. (2003a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">2003b</xref>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">González et al. (2006)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Cardoso et al. (2011)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bastos-Pereira and Bueno (2012)</xref>. The terminology used for setae of the appendices follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Zimmer et al. (2009)</xref>.</p>
            <p>Type material is deposited on Coleção de Crustáceos da Universidade Federal de Lavras (UFLA) and Museu Nacional do Rio de Janeiro (MNRJ).</p>
            <p>The pictures of fixed animals were taken through a stereomicroscope Zeiss Stemi 2000-C connected to a photographic camera, using Carl Zeiss AxioVision program SE64 Rel 4.8.3. The images from the site of occurrence of new species were taken from Google Earth.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics">
            <title>Systematics</title>
            <sec sec-type="Order Amphipoda Latreille, 1816">
                <title>Order <tp:taxon-name>Amphipoda</tp:taxon-name> Latreille, 1816. Suborder <tp:taxon-name>Gammaridea</tp:taxon-name> Latreille, 1802. Family <tp:taxon-name>Dogielinotidae</tp:taxon-name> Gurjanova, 1953. Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella</tp:taxon-name></italic> S. I. Smith, 1874</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Hyalella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">imbya</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F065930A-43A1-453F-8785-CCBD576E6C73</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Hyalella_imbya</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Rodrigues &amp; Bueno</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">–5</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material. </title>
                        <p>Holotype: male, Brazil, Rio Grande do Sul state, Roque Gonzales municipality, wetland, Ijuí watershed, Uruguay hydrographic region, (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">28°13'55.6"S, 54°58'37.3"W</named-content>) (MNRJ 23384), allotype female (MNRJ 23385), July, 7, 2002, Stenert, C. coll.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes">
                        <title>Paratypes.</title>
                        <p>MNRJ 23386 (5 males; 5 females; 5 juveniles), UFLA 0187 (10 males; 10 females; 10 juveniles) with the same data as the holotype.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality">
                        <title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p>Brazil, Rio Grande do Sul state: Roque Gonzales municipality, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">28°13'55.6"S, 54°58'37.3"W</named-content>, wetland, Ijuí watershed, Uruguay hydrographic region, ca 200 m high, July 7 2002, Stenert, C. coll.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Body surface smooth. Eyes absent. Antenna 1 longer than antenna 2, flagellum with 18–23 articles. Antenna 2 less than half body length, flagellum with 14-16 articles. Maxilliped with distal nail longer than dactylus. Gnathopod 1 propodus length less than twice maximum width, hammer shape, inner face with 7 pappose setae,<!--PageBreak--> without comb-scales. Gnathopod 2 carpus wider than long, posterior lobe elongated without comb-scales or denticles in the border; propodus ovate, without comb-scales, palm sub-equal to posterior margin, slope oblique, palm with two rows of several cuspidate setae with an accessory setae and simple setae. Peraeopod 5 smaller than others; peraeopod 6 and 7 much more longer than others. Uropod 1 inner ramus of male with a short curved seta, four cuspidate setae with an accessory seta apically, with one of <!--PageBreak-->them almost half length of the outer ramus. Uropod 3 shorter than telson, peduncle wider than ramus, with one cuspidate seta with an accessory seta distally. Telson wider than long, with two long simple apical setae. Sternal gills present on segments 3 to 7.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description of male.</title>
                        <p>Mean body length: 5.03 ± 0.85 mm, mean head length: 0.46 ± 0.07 mm (n=10). Body surface smooth; epimeral plates not acuminate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>).</p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 1.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Rodrigues and Bueno (male paratype, UFLA 0187). <bold>A</bold> habitus from holotype <bold>B</bold> antenna 1 <bold>C</bold> antenna 1 article showing two aesthetascs <bold>D</bold> antenna 2 <bold>E</bold> left mandible <bold>F</bold> upper lip <bold>G</bold> lower lip <bold>H</bold> maxilla 1 <bold>I</bold> maxilla 2. Scale bar equal 1 mm for <bold>A</bold>; 500 µm for <bold>B</bold>; 100 µm for <bold>C–I</bold>.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-065-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <p>Head smaller than 2 thoracic segments, rostrum absent. Eyes absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Antenna 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>) longer than antenna 2, more than half body length; peduncle surpassing head length; flagellum with 18 to 23 articles; aesthetascs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>) ocurring in pairs distally on flagellum after article 5.</p>
                        <p>Antenna 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>) peduncle not surpassing the second pereionite, less than half body length, peduncle slender, longer than head; flagellum with 14 to 16 articles, longer than peduncle.</p>
                        <p>Mandible basic amphipodan (in the sense of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Watling 1993</xref>), but without palp; incisor toothed; left lacinia mobilis with six teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>); seta row on left mandible with five main pappose setae plus accessory setae, right mandible with three main pappose setae plus accesory setae; molar large, cylindrical and triturative with setules around its circumference.</p>
                        <p>Upper lip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref>) margin rounded; distal border covered by setules on dorsal and ventral faces.</p>
                        <p>Lower lip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1G</xref>) outer lobes rounded, with setules on dorsal and ventral faces.</p>
                        <p>Maxilla 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1H</xref>) palp uniarticulate, short, longer than wide, covered by several simple setae and reaching less than half length the distance between the base of palp and tip of setae on outer plate. Inner plate slender, shorter than outer plate, with two long papposerrate apical setae, several simple setae on inner margin; outer plate with 8–9 long serrate setae.</p>
                        <p>Maxilla 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1I</xref>) inner plate shorter than outer plate, with two long papposerrate, eight serrulate and several simple apical setae; outer plate with abundant long simple setae; outer and inner plates with several setules.</p>
                        <p>Maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>) inner plate with three strong cuspidate setae apically, several pappose setae on apical and inner borders, inner plate recovered by abundant short setule; outer plate larger than inner plate, recovered by setule and with three pappose setae and several simple setae; palp longer than outer plate, four articles; article 1 wider than long, outer and inner faces with short simple setae; article 2 wider than long, inner face with several long simple setae; article 3 wider than long, outer and inner faces with several long simple setae and outer face with four pappose setae; dactylus unguiform recovered by short simple setae, shorter than third article, inner border with several simple setae; distal nail longer than dactylus.</p>
                        <p>Gnathopod 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>) subchelate; coxal plate wider than long, with simple setae on the border; basis, ischium and merus with serrate setae dorsally; carpus longer than wide, shorter than propodus, with lateral distal lobe produced and forming a scoop-like structure, border pectinate with several serrate setae, without denticles and comb-scales in their basis; border propodus width 3/4 of maximum length, hammer-shaped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>), without setae on anterior border, without comb-scales, inner face with 7 serrate setae, with simple setae on the disto-posterior border; palm slope transverse, margin slightly concave, posterior distal corner with two cuspidate setae with an accessory seta; dactylus claw-like without comb-scales, one plumose seta dorsally and few setae ventrally.</p>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 2.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Rodrigues and Bueno (male paratype, UFLA 0187). <bold>A</bold> gnathopod 1 <bold>B</bold> gnathopod 1 propodus and dactylus <bold>C</bold> gnathopod 2 <bold>D</bold> gnathopod 2 propodus and dactylus. Scale bars equals 100 µm for <bold>A–D</bold>.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-065-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Gnathopod 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>) subchelate; basis hind margin with five groups of simple setae; merus with few setae on posterior margin; carpus wider than long, posterior lobe slim produced between merus and propodus, border pectinate with several short<!--PageBreak--> serrate setae, without denticles or comb-scales; propodus ovate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>), length 1.4 maximum width, without comb-scales; palm sub-equal than posterior margin of propodus, slope oblique, palm with two rows of several cuspidate setae with an accessory setae and simple setae, posterior distal corner with few simple setae and with a cup for dactylus; dactylus claw-like, congruent with palm, with few endal setae and a plumose seta dorsally, few setae ventrally, without comb-scales.</p>
                        <p>Peraeopods 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>) and 4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>) merus and carpus posterior margin with clusters of simple setae; propodus posterior margin with six to seven groups of simple <!--PageBreak-->setae; dactylus less than half-length of propodus. Peraeopods 5 to 7 dactylus less than half-length of propodus; merus, carpus and propodus posterior margin with 4-5 marginal clusters of 2-9 cuspidate setae with an accessory setae. Peraeopod 3 sub-equal to peraeopod 4; peraeopod 5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>) smaller than others; peraeopods 6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>) and 7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref>) much longer than others. Coxal plates - peraeopod 3: longer than wide, width about half its length; peraeopod 4: wider than long; peraeopod 5: wider than long, with two lobes; peraeopod 6: ovate; peraeopod 7: wider than long. All coxal plates with simple setae on the border.</p>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 3. </label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Rodrigues and Bueno (male paratype, UFLA 0187). <bold>A</bold> peraeopod 3 <bold>B</bold> peraeopod 4 <bold>C</bold> peraeopod 5 <bold>D</bold> peraeopod 6 <bold>E</bold> peraeopod 7. Scale bars equals 200 µm for <bold>A–E</bold>.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-065-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <p>Pleopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>) peduncle smaller than flagellum, without coupling spines; rami with several plumose setae; plumose setae of the last article longer 1.4 times than peduncle.</p>
                        <p>Uropod 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>) peduncle 1.7 times longer than rami; outer ramus longer than inner ramus; outer ramus with six cuspidate setae with an accessory seta, four cuspidate setae with an accessory seta apically, one smaller and three more longer, one of them with almost half length of the outer ramus; inner ramus with two dorsal cuspidate setae with an accessory seta on inner margin, male with a short curved seta apically on the ramus, five cuspidate setae with an accessory seta apically, three smaller and two more longer, one of them more than half of the length of the inner ramus; peduncle setation present.</p>
                        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 4.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Rodrigues and Bueno (male paratype, UFLA 0187). <bold>A</bold> pleopods <bold>B</bold> maxillipod <bold>C</bold> uropod 1 <bold>D</bold> uropod 2 <bold>E</bold> uropod 3 <bold>F</bold> telson. Scale bars equals 200 µm for <bold>A</bold>; 100 µm for <bold>B–F</bold>.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-065-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <p>Uropod 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>) shorter than uropod 1; ramus and peduncle of the same length; inner ramus with three dorsal setae and four distal setae, one more than half the length of the inner ramus; outer ramus with four dorsal setae and four distal setae,<!--PageBreak--> one more than half the length of the outer ramus; peduncle wider than ramus with four cuspidate setae with an accessory setae.</p>
                        <p>Uropod 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4E</xref>) shorter than telson, shorter than peduncle of uropod 1 and uropod 2; inner ramus absent; outer ramus uniarticulate; peduncle longer than wide with one cuspidate seta with an accessory seta distally; ramus shorter than peduncle; basal width 1.8 times the width of ramus apex, with five cuspidate setae with an accesory seta and one long simple seta, longer than peduncle.</p>
                        <p>Telson (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4F</xref>) entire, apically rounded, more than 1.2 times wider than long, with two long simple apical setae; sometimes with plumose setae laterally.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Coxal gills sac-like present on pereonites 2 to 6. Sternal gills tubular present on pereonites 3 to 7.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Female">
                        <title>Female.</title>
                        <p>Mean body length: 4.8 ± 0.43 mm, mean head length: 0.48 ± 0.03 mm (n=10) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>). Antenna 1 flagellum with 19 to 20 articles; antenna 2 similar in shape to male; flagellum with 15 to 16 articles.</p>
                        <p>Gnathopod 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>) similar in size and shape to gnathopod 2; without comb-scales; propodus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>) longer than wide; similar to male gnathopod 1 except that propodus is less narrow and shorter. Gnathopod 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>) different from male gnathopod 2 in shape and smaller; propodus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5D</xref>) length 1.1 times maximum width, subchelate, inner face with five serrate setae, palm transverse, without comb-scales.</p>
                        <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 5.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Rodrigues and Bueno (female allotype, UFLA 0187). <bold>A</bold> gnathopod 1 <bold>B </bold>gnathopod 1 propodus and dactylus <bold>C</bold> gnathopod 2 <bold>D</bold> gnathopod 2 propodus and dactylus. Scale bars equals 100 µm for <bold>A–D</bold>.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-065-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific name, <italic>imbya</italic>, honors the indigenous tribe Mbyá-Guarani that inhabited the local before the colonization of european immigrants.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Habitat">
                        <title>Habitat.</title>
                        <p>Freshwater, hypothelminorheic.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>The area where specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> were collected was severely altered in the last recent years (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). The area suffered during decades with agriculture, but the recent impacts were even more harmful. Such area is drained to a tributary stream which flows to Ijuí river (its margin was about 3.5 km far from the sampled area). In 2011 the riparian vegetation of this tributary was removed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>) and a reservoir was filled, flooding the deforested area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7C</xref>). The phreatic level was altered since the distance between the sampled area and the nearest reservoir´s margin was reduced to about 2 km. In a visit maid on March 30, 2012 by two of the authors (S. G. Rodrigues and A. A. P. Bueno) to the same area no specimen was found. The area was completely dry and no spring was observed. It seems that changes in the hydrological parameters due to the building of São José reservoir altered the species habitat. Further considerations regarding such impacts will be discussed later.</p>
                        <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 6.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Rodrigues and Bueno (male holotype, UFLA 0187). <bold>A</bold> male specimen fixed (body length = 4.8 mm, head length = 0.47 mm) <bold>B</bold> detail of the head showing the absence of eyes in the male specimen fixed <bold>C</bold> female specimen fixed (body length = 4.5 mm, head length = 0.45 mm). Scale bar equal 1 mm for <bold>A</bold>; 0.5 mm for <bold>B</bold>; 1 mm for <bold>C</bold>.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-065-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 7.</label>
                            <caption><p>Habitat of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Rodrigues and Bueno. <bold>A</bold> The area bounded by a dotted line represents the region where specimens were found <bold>B</bold> the riparian vegetation was removed from a tributary stream (white arrows) from Ijuí river <bold>C</bold> the São José reservoir already filled.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-065-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <sec sec-type="Affinities">
                <title>Affinities</title>
                <p>There are four troglobiotic species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella</tp:taxon-name></italic> described: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella anophthalma</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ruffo, 1957; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella caeca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pereira, 1989, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella muerta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Baldinger, Shepard and Threloff, 2000, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella spelaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bueno and Cardoso, 2011. Two of these, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella caeca</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella spelaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, occur in Brazil, both in caves of São Paulo, Southeastern Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Cardoso et al. 2011</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella anophtalma</tp:taxon-name></italic> occurs in a cave at Venezuela (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Ruffo 1957</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella muerta</tp:taxon-name></italic> also occurs in subterranean environment in Death Valley National Park, California, USA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Baldinger et al. 2000</xref>).</p>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> has the first pair of antennae elongated, which is longer than the second pair, a characteristic previously observed only for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella muerta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). However, the largest size of the antenna is more pronounced for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic>, which presents many more articles than other troglobiotic species. The two species have sternal gills from pereonite 3 to 7, while others present such gills on pereonites 2 to 7.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
								<label>Table 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Characters of troglobiotic species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella</tp:taxon-name></italic> (A1: Antenna 1; A2: Antenna 2; G1: Gnathopod 1; G2: Gnathopod 2; U1: Uropod 1).</p></caption>
                <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characters</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella anophthalma</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ruffo, 1957</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella caeca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pereira, 1989</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella muerta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Baldinger, Shepard &amp; Threloff, 2000</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella spelaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bueno &amp; Cardoso, 2011</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> Rodrigues &amp; Bueno, 2012</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A1: No. of articles of flagellum</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18-23</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A2: No. of articles of flagellum</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14-16</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of A1 and A2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A1&lt;A2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A1&lt;A2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A1&gt;A2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A1&lt;A2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A1&gt;A2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length (mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.35</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.03</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G1: Comb-scales in propodus</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G1: No. of setae in the inner face</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G2: Lobiform process of propodus on the palmar corner</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U1: Curved seta in the inner ramus</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sternal gills tubular</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2–7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3–7</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Telson</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absence of setae</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two short simple apical setae</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Four long simple apical setae</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two short simple apical setae</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Two long simple apical setae</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> does not present comb-scales on propodus of gnathopod 1 and 2, even as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella caeca</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella muerta</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Similarly to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella muerta</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella spelaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the new species does not have a lobiform process on the propodus of gnathopod 2. When compared to <italic><tp:taxon-name>H anophthalma</tp:taxon-name></italic>, it is possible to note that the two species do not exhibit characteristic in common, only the absence of eyes.</p>
                <p>Moreover, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> also has particular characteristics that make it differ from other troglobiotic species: the presence of curved seta in the inner ramus of uropod 1; reduction in size of uropod 3 and posterior lobe in carpus of gnathopod 2; elongation of appendices, as the first pair of antennas and the pereopods 6 and 7.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                <title>Conservation status</title>
                <p>Problems concerning the hypothelminorheic habitat conservation were already discussed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Boulton 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Fiser et al. 2010</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Fiser et al. (2010)</xref>, the main threats to this habitat are land drainage and agricultural improvement. The superficial nature of the hypothelminorheic habitat allied to the restricted distribution of the species makes them especially vulnerable to impacts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Culver et al. 2006</xref>). In South America, such habitats have been completely neglected and consequently not studied.</p>
                <p>The region where the new species was found represents a very threatened type of ecosystem, the wetlands. This ecosystem presents a high diversity, with high levels of endemism, and is among the most productive environments of the world. Such traits make the wetlands priority ecosystem for conservation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Barbier et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Mitsch and Gosselink 2000</xref>).</p>
                <p>About half of South America wetlands are located in Brazil, and the state of Rio Grande do Sul has the greatest record for these ecosystems: 3.441 areas covering 10.7% of the total area of the state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Maltchik et al. 2003</xref>). Despite their great environmental importance, these ecosystems are among the most threatened habitats in the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Mitsch and Gosselink 2000</xref>).</p>
                <p>It is estimated that 90% of these areas in Rio Grande do Sul have already disappeared due to urban development, construction of dams and reservoirs, as well as expansion of areas of agriculture, especially rice and soybean, causing fragmentation and deterioration of these ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Maltchik and Rolon 2010</xref>).</p>
                <p>The agricultural expansion is one of the main factors that affect and hinder the conservation of wetlands. The soil of these ecosystems can produce up to 50 times more vegetal organic matter area then a similar natural field, and eight times more than a cultivated field, which makes them targets for growing crops of economic importance, such as rice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Barbier et al. 1997</xref>). The state of Rio Grande do Sul is the leading producer of rice in Brazil. This type of plant has a dynamic water regime, with variations between terrestrial and aquatic stages. Since the remaining surface of the culture can stay up to two years without water, this can cause a great impact to the community of plants and animals, as well as throughout the landscape as a whole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Maltchik and Rolon 2010</xref>).</p>
                <p>The severe impacts caused by the bulding of São José reservoir apparently altered the hypothelminorheic habitat of the area, furthermore nowadays the site of occurrence of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalella imbya</tp:taxon-name></italic> is inserted in a large area of soybean farming. Since only a single visit was made to the area after such impacts, it is impossible to assess the real status of the species and its habitat. Hypothelminorheic habitats are characterized by persistent wet spots, but this condition is no longer observed in the area. The species may eventually be associated from subterranean habitats at the present moment, but one cannot discard the possibility of its extinction. We can assume minimally that it is critically threatened at the moment.</p>
                <p>The Brazilian laws concerning cave fauna has been recently altered. Although it is somewhat restrictive in some cases (assuring the protection of rare troglobiotic species), it obviously lacks a broader conception of subterranean habitats. Accordingly, it is important to incorporate in such laws the protection of shallow subterranean habitats, especially those strongly threatened, as the hypothelminorheic.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>This research was funded by Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior, Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (Pr<!--PageBreak-->ocess N° 477554/2011-3), and Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de Minas Gerais. RLF thanks CNPq for the research grant (301061/2011-4). We also thank Dr. Cristina Stenert for sampling the animals and Rafaela Bastos-Pereira for helping with the laboratory work.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldinger</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shepard</surname> <given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Threloff</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Two new species of <italic>Hyalella</italic> (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Hyalellidae) from Death Valley National Park, California, U.S.A.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Biological Society of Washington </source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>-<lpage>457</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbier</surname> <given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acreman</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knowler</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<source> Economic valuation of wetlands – A guide for policy makers and planners.</source> <publisher-name>University of York</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Ramsar Convention Bureau</publisher-loc>, <lpage>143</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bastos-Pereira</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bueno</surname> <given-names>AAP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> New species and new report of <italic>Hyalella</italic> S. I. Smith, 1874 (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Dogielinotidae) from Minas Gerais state, Southeastern Brazil.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>3350</volume>: <fpage>58</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Boulton</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Chances and challenges in the conservation of groundwaters and their dependent ecosystems.</article-title> <source>Aquatic Conservation: Marine And Freshwater Ecosystems </source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>323</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/aqc.712">10.1002/aqc.712</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Boulton</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Recent progress in the conservation of groundwaters and their dependent ecosystems.</article-title> <source>Aquatic Conservation: Marine and Freshwater Ecosystems </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>731</fpage>-<lpage>735</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/aqc.1073">10.1002/aqc.1073</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardoso</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bueno</surname> <given-names>AAP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> A new troglobiotic species of <italic>Hyalella</italic> (Crustacea, Amphipoda, Dogielinotidae) from Southeastern Brazil.</article-title> <source>Nauplius </source> <volume>19</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Culver</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pipan</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gottstein</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Hypothelminorheic - a unique freshwater habitat.</article-title> <source>Subterranean Biology </source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Culver</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pipan</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009a</year>)<source> Superficial subterranean habitats - gateway to the subterranean realm? Cave and Karst Science 35: 5–12.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Culver</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pipan</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009b</year>)<source> The Biology of Caves and Other Subterranean Habitats.</source> <publisher-name>Oxford University Press, Oxford</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <lpage>256</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiser</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konec</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobe</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osanic</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruden</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Potocnik</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Conservation problems with hypothelminorheic <italic>Niphargus</italic> species (Amphipoda: Niphargidae).</article-title> <source>Aquatic Conservation: Marine and Freshwater Ecosystems </source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>602</fpage>-<lpage>604</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/aqc.1119">10.1002/aqc.1119</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>González</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watling</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003a</year>)<article-title> A new species of <italic>Hyalella</italic> from Brazil (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Hyalellidae), with redescriptions of three other species in the genus.</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History </source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>2045</fpage>-<lpage>2076</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222930210133237">10.1080/00222930210133237</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>González</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watling</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003b</year>)<article-title> A new species of <italic>Hyalella</italic> from Colombia, and the redescription of <italic>H. meinerti</italic> Stebbing, 1899 from Venezuela (Crustacea: Amphipoda).</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History </source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>2095</fpage>-<lpage>2111</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222930210133255">10.1080/00222930210133255</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>González</surname> <given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond-Buckup</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Araujo</surname> <given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Two new species of <italic>Hyalella</italic> from Southern Brazil (Amphipoda: Hyalellidae) with a taxonomic key.</article-title> <source>Journal of Crustacean Biology </source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>365</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1651/C-2599.1">10.1651/C-2599.1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grosso</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peralta</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Anfípodos de agua dulce sudamericanos. Revisión del género <italic>Hyalella</italic> Smith. I.</article-title> <source>Acta Zoológica Lilloana </source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Juberthie</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delay</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouillon</surname> <given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Sur l’existence du milieu souterrain superficiel en zone non calcaire.</article-title> <source>Comptes Rendus de l’Académie des Sciences de la France D, </source> <volume>290</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Juberthie</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Decu</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<source> Structure et diversité du domain souterrain; particularités des habitats et adaptations des espèces. In: Juberthie C., Decu V. (Eds) Encyclopaedia Biospeologica, Tome 1, Moulis and Bucharest, Société de Biospéologie, 5–22.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Juberthie</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<source> The diversity of the karstic and pseudokarstic hypogean habitats in the world. In: Wilkens H, Culver DC, Humphreys WF (Eds) Subterranean Ecosystems, Amsterdam, Elsevier, 17–39.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maltchik</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rolon</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source> Does flooding of rice fields after cultivation contribute to wetland plant conservation in southern Brazil? Applied Vegetation Science 13: 26–35. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1654-109X.2009.01046.x">10.1111/j.1654-109X.2009.01046.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maltchik</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname> <given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira,</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Inventory of wetlands of Rio Grande do Sul (Brazil).</article-title> <source>Pesquisas, Botânica </source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>100</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsch</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gosselink</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> The value of wetlands: importance of scale and landscape setting.</article-title> <source>Ecological Economics </source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0921-8009(00)00165-8">10.1016/S0921-8009(00)00165-8</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname> <given-names>VFG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Uma nova espécie de anfípode cavernícola do Brasil – <italic>Hyalella caeca</italic> sp.n. (Amphipoda, Hyalellidae).</article-title> <source>Revista Brasileira de Zoologia </source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S0101-81751989000100007">10.1590/S0101-81751989000100007</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Racovitza</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> Sur les relations dynamiques entre le milieu souterrain superficiel et milieu cavernicole.</article-title> <source>Mémoires de Biospéologie </source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruffo</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1957</year>)<article-title> Una nuova specie troglobia di <italic>Hyalella</italic> del Venezuela.</article-title> <source>Estrato Dauli Annali del Museo Civico Di Storia Naturale Di Genova </source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>-<lpage>369</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Růžička</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> The first steps in subterranean evolution of spiders (Araneae) in Central Europe.</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History, </source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>265</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/002229399300407">10.1080/002229399300407</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1874</year>)<article-title> The Crustacea of the fresh waters of the United States - Synopsis of the higher fresh-water Crustacea of the Northern United States.</article-title> <source>Report of the Comissioner of Fish and Fisheries </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>637</fpage>-<lpage>665</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Väinölä</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witt</surname> <given-names>JDS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grabowski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradbury</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jazdzewski</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sket</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Global diversity of amphipods (Amphipoda; Crustacea) in freshwater.</article-title> <source>Hydrobiologia </source> <volume>595</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>-<lpage>255</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10750-007-9020-6">10.1007/s10750-007-9020-6</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Watling</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Functional morphology of the amphipod mandible.</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History </source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>837</fpage>-<lpage>849</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222939300770511">10.1080/00222939300770511</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmer</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Araujo</surname> <given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond-Buckup</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Diversity and arrangement of the cuticular structures of <italic>Hyalella</italic> (Crustacea: Amphipoda: Dogielinotidae) and their use in taxonomy.</article-title> <source>Zoologia </source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>