<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.93.1167</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                The millipede family Polydesmidae in Taiwan, with descriptions of five new species (Polydesmida, Diplopoda)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western"> 
                        <surname>Golovatch</surname> 
                        <given-names>Sergei I.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:71532F45-BDD5-415D-BC54-86256E5D5D4A</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western"> 
                        <surname>Mikhaljova</surname>
                        <given-names>Elena V.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:C7962B1F-80FD-4330-AF41-C17B7EA0214C</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Chang</surname>
                        <given-names>Hsueh-Wen</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:B0F05141-340F-4B6C-8F43-6F64DAB5EBC2</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Institute for Problems of Ecology and Evolution, Russian Academy of Sciences, Leninsky pr. 33, Moscow 119071, Russia</aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Institute of Biology and Soil Science, Far Eastern Branch, Russian Academy of Sciences, Prospekt Stoletiya Vladivostoka 159, Vladivostok 690022, Russia</aff>
                    <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Biological Sciences, National Sun Yat-Sen University, 70 Lien-Hai Rd., Kaohsiung 804, Taiwan, ROC</aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Sergei I. Golovatch (<email xlink:type="simple">sgolovatch@yandex.ru</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Robert Mesibov</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
            	    <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>29</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>93</issue>
            <fpage>9</fpage>
            <lpage>42</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>24</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>28</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Sergei I. Golovatch, Elena V. Mikhaljova, Hsueh-Wen Chang</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:8C454563-BF19-4315-AF04-353A3B4E99BC</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Polydesmidae</tp:taxon-name> are represented in Taiwan by seven species in two genera. Neither of the genera is endemic to Taiwan, but six of the species are, including five new: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus minor</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus bispinosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus curtigonopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus flagellifer</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus pinguis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> In addition, the diagnosis of the hitherto enigmatic genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chamberlin &amp; Wang, 1953 is refined vis-à-vis the especially similar, Central Asian, Siberian and Eastern European genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizoturanius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff, 1931, chiefly based on new material of the type-species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chamberlin &amp; Wang, 1953; this species is adequately redescribed and represents still another Taiwanese endemic. A key to all three currently known species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chamberlin &amp; Wang, 1953 is given. The highly speciose Central to East Asian genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Attems, 1901 is represented in Taiwan by five species, all keyed, including <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Attems, 1901, which is long known to be highly variable in Japan and found particularly polymorphous and apparently allochthonous in Taiwan. The following synonymy is formalized: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Attems, 1901 = <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis takakuwai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff, 1913, <bold>syn. n.</bold> The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Usbekodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lohmander, 1932 is formally synonymized with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Attems, 1901, <bold>syn. n.</bold>, resulting in the following new formal transfers: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus redikorzevi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Lohmander, 1932), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus swatensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1991), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus varius</tp:taxon-name></italic> <!--PageBreak-->(Geoffroy &amp; Golovatch, 2004), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus anachoretus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1986), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus buddhis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1986), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus occultus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1986), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus sacer</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1987), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus theocraticus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1990) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus theosophicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1986), all <bold>comb. n.</bold> ex <italic><tp:taxon-name>Usbekodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The distributions of all seven species of <tp:taxon-name>Polydesmidae</tp:taxon-name> occurring in Taiwan are mapped and discussed.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>millipede</kwd>
                <kwd>Polydesmidae</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>new synonymy</kwd>
                <kwd>key</kwd>
                <kwd>Taiwan</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The millipede fauna of Taiwan is still quite poorly explored (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Korsós 2004</xref>), with fewer than 70 species currently reported from this large, subtropical to tropical island. Many more species may be expected to occur there, to judge from the recent increase in the list of Taiwanese Glomerida from one species to five (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Golovatch et al. 2010</xref>). This statement is easy to reconfirm with the large family <tp:taxon-name>Polydesmidae</tp:taxon-name>, order Polydesmida, taken as another example. Taiwan has hitherto been known to support only two polydesmid species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Attems, 1901 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chamberlin &amp; Wang, 1953, both from a few localities only (see review: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Korsós 2004</xref>).</p>
            <p>Prompted by the abundant new material collected during the last couple of decades all over the island, below we offer a revision of the Taiwanese <tp:taxon-name>Polydesmidae</tp:taxon-name>. Already seven species appear to be involved, representing two genera. These new samples also allow for the diagnosis of one genus to be refined, and the synonymy of another one formalized.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="material|methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Material serving as the basis for the present contribution was preserved in 75% alcohol and is currently shared between the collections of the National Museum of Natural Science, Taichung, Taiwan (NMNS), Taiwan Forest Research Institute, Taipei, Taiwan (TFRI), Department of Biological Sciences,National Sun Yat-Sen University, Kaohsiung, Taiwan (NSYSU), Zoological Museum, State University of Moscow, Russia (ZMUM), Natural History Museum of Denmark, University of Copenhagen, Denmark (ZMUC), Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle, Paris, France (MNHN), and Institute of Biology and Soil Science, Far Eastern Branch, Russian Academy of Sciences, Vladivostok, Russia (IBSS), as indicated hereafter. Specimens were studied and illustrated using standard stereomicroscopic, photographic and drawing equipment.</p>
            <p>In the catalogue sections, which mostly refer to the fauna of Taiwan alone, D stands for the original description, N for additional descriptive notes, and R for a mere mention or record.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics"><title>Systematics</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Nipponesmus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">shirinensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Nipponesmus_shirinensis</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Chamberlin &amp; Wang, 1953</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"/>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">13</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name><comment> Chamberlin &amp; Wang, 1953: 4 (D).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name><comment> – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Golovatch 1991</xref>: 157 (N); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Korsós 2004</xref>: 26 (R)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined:</title>
                    <p>2 juv. (NSYSU), Taiwan, Taipei City, Wenshan Distr., Chih-Nan Temple, 03.2002, leg. C.C. Chen et al.; 2 ♂, 2 ♀ (NMNS-6555-001), 1 ♂ (MNHN JC 331), Nantou County, Re-nai Township, Mei-Feng, 22.10.2001; 1 ♂ (ZMUC), 1 ♂ (NMNS-6555-002), same locality, 15.10.2001; 1 ♂ (TFRI), same locality, 19.02.2002; 1 ♂ (NMNS-6555-003), same locality, 15.10.2001; 1 ♂ (ZMUM), Nantou County, Huisun timber land, 20.09.1997; 1 ♂ (NMNS-6555-004), same locality, 10.1997; all leg. S.H. Wu; 3 ♂, 5 ♀ (TFRI), Nantou County, Lugu Township, Sitou, 15.11.2005, leg. J.D. Lee; 8 juv. (NSYSU), same locality, 6.07.2010, leg. H.W. Chang; 1 ♂, 1 ♀ (TFRI), Taitung County, Taimali Township, I-Ma forest road, 06.12.2004, leg. S.Y. Wu; 4 ♂, 1 ♀, 5 juv. (NSYSU), Chiayi County, Alishan Township, Nansi Forest road, ca 2,000 m a.s.l., 29.10.2010, leg. H.W. Chang; 1 ♂ (ZMUM), Hsinchu County, Wufeng Township, Sakaru (Shilu) trail, 30.09.2005; 1 ♂ (NMNS-6555-005), same locality, 22.09.2005, all leg. H.D. Zhu; 1 ♂ (NSYSU), Kaohsiung County, Liouguei, Shanping Workstation, 04.2004, leg. M.J. Hung; 1 ♂ (NMNS-6555-006), Kaohsiung County, Taoyuan Township, Tengjhih, 1,550 m a.s.l., 17.11.2010, leg. S. Golovatch; 2 ♀ (NMNS-6555-007), Kaohsiung County, Taoyuan Township, Chungchihkuan, 15.03.2005, leg. Y.C. Chang; 1 juv. (NSYSU), same locality, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Taiwania cryptomeroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> plantation, 15.10.2005, leg. M.H. Hsu; 1 ♂, 1 ♀ (IBSS), Pingtung County, Chunri Township, Mt Dahan, 1,200 m a.s.l., 15.12.2009; 2 ♀ (NMNS-6555-008), same locality, ca 1,850 m a.s.l., 15.12.2009, all leg. M.H. Hsu.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis:</title>
                    <p>Differs from the other <tp:taxon-name>Polydesmidae</tp:taxon-name> in Taiwan by the larger body and often a dark coloration, from the only sympatric congener <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus minor</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. also in the collum being broader than the head and in the gonopod showing a strongly elongate, slender and falcate telopodite (see also Key below).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Redescription"><title>Redescription:</title>
                    <p>Length of both sexes ca 18–25 mm, usually about 20–23 mm; width of pro- and metazona varying between specimens from 1.5–2.2 to 2.9–4.8 mm, respectively, usually 1.8–2.0 and 3.0–4.3 mm, respectively. Usually ♂♂ somewhat smaller than ♀♀. Coloration in alcohol from uniformly pallid (faded?) to dark chocolate-brown; in the latter case, sides, venter and legs (light) grey-brown to dark brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">6</xref>). Body with 20 segments. Tegument mainly dull, at most slightly shining, texture very delicately alveolate. Frons and labrum densely pilose, vertex bare; epicranial suture distinct but thin; a paramedian pair of evident, oblique ridges above antennal sockets; isthmus between antennae considerably broader than diameter of <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->antennal socket (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>). Antennae rather long and only slightly clavate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>), either slightly overreaching segment 3 dorsally (♂) or slightly shorter (♀); antennomere 3 longest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3–5</xref>); antennomeres 5 and 6 each with a small, compact, distodorsal group of bacilliform sensilla; antennomere 7 with a minute dorsoparabasal cone and a distodorsal group of microscopic sensilla.</p>
                    <p>In width, head &lt; collum &lt; segment 2 &lt; 3 &lt; 4 &lt; 5=15(16), thereafter body gradually tapering towards telson. Paraterga strongly developed, starting from collum, subhorizontal, set high but always lying slightly below a faintly convex dorsum, drawn clearly forward only on metatergum 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 3</xref>). Starting from segment 8 or 9 (♂) or 16 (♀), paraterga extending increasingly beyond rear tergal contour, caudal corners invariably evidently rounded, only on paraterga 17–19 subspiniform, usually slightly more narrowly rounded in ♂ compared to ♀ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">6–9</xref>). Paraterga more (♀) or less (♂) evidently rounded laterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">6–9</xref>); starting from segment 2, all poreless segments with three, all pore-bearing ones with four, minute, sometimes even obliterate incisions at lateral margin. Front edges of metaterga slightly bordered and upturned, straight, usually forming a distinct shoulder. Pore formula normal, ozopores evident, dorsal, located in front of posteriormost marginal indentation. Metatergal sculpture typical, well-developed, with three transverse rows of setiferous, polygonal bosses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">6–9</xref>). Tergal setae very short, mostly obliterate, partly retained only on collum and/or <!--PageBreak-->metatergum 19. Stricture between pro- and metazona wide, shallow and smooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3, 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">6–9</xref>). Limbus very thin, microdenticulate. Pleurosternal carinae absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>). Epiproct rather short, conical, preapical papillae very evident (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7, 9</xref>). Hypoproct semi-circular; caudal, paramedian, setiferous papillae small and well-separated.</p>
                    <p>Sterna without modifications, very densely (♂) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>) or poorly (♀) setose, ♀ ones often shining. Epigynal ridge very low. Legs rather long and slender (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">10</xref>), ca 1.5–1.6 (♂) or 1.1–1.2 (♀) times as long as midbody height; ♂ legs evidently enlarged, prefemora only slightly swollen dorsally and, like femora and, partly, postfemora, ventrally beset with shorter bifid setae turning into short sphaerotrichomes on postfemora, tibiae and tarsi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Gonopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 4, 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">11–13</xref>) with large, subquadrate, medially fused coxae carrying a few long setae ventrally. Telopodite elongated, slender, falcate, prefemoral (densely setose) portion almost half as long as entire telopodite; seminal groove running mesally over most of its extent, only distally moving frontally to recurve first laterad and then a little basad at base of both a somewhat shorter, more complex endomere (<bold>en</bold>) and a longer, simpler exomere (<bold>ex</bold>); <bold>en</bold> beset with long, bacilliform setae distally and supplied with an evident spine (<bold>s</bold>) mesally, as well as a prominent pulvillus near base, this pulvillus being likewise beset with bacilliform setae and marking the end of seminal groove devoid of any accessory seminal chamber; <bold>ex</bold> strongly unciform apically, with an additional lateral tooth distally to subapically.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–5.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chamberlin &amp; Wang, 1953, ♀ (<bold>1</bold>) and ♂ (<bold>2</bold>) from Mei-Feng, ♂ (<bold>3–5</bold>) from Tengjhih. <bold>1, 2</bold> habitus, lateral view <bold>3–5</bold> anterior portion of body, dorsal, lateral and ventral views, respectively. Photographed not to scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_1.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 6–9.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chamberlin &amp; Wang, 1953, ♂ (<bold>6, 7</bold>) from Tengjhih and ♀ (<bold>8, 9</bold>) from Mei-Feng. <bold>6</bold> middle portion of body, dorsal view <bold>7, 9</bold> posterior portion of body, dorsal view <bold>8</bold> anterior portion of body, dorsal view. Photographed not to scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_2.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 10–13.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chamberlin &amp; Wang, 1953, ♂ from Sitou. <bold>10</bold> leg 9 <bold>11, 12</bold> right gonopod, lateral and mesal views, respectively <bold>13</bold> distal part of gonopod telopodite, enlarged, mesal view. Scale bar: 0.5 mm (<bold>10–12</bold>) and 0.25 mm (<bold>13</bold>). See text for explanation of labels.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_3.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <p><bold>Remarks.</bold> This species is the largest, as well as one of the most conspicuous and common among the polydesmids in Taiwan. It inhabits a wide range of habitats, mainly montane woodlands above 1,200 m a.s.l. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Map 1</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Nipponesmus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">minor</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:225E19E9-CF6B-46A1-A16F-7EFAD3A91A58</object-id>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Nipponesmus_minor</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 14</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">23</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material:</title>
                    <p>Holotype ♂ (TFRI), Taiwan, Ilan County, Tatong Township, near Lakes Jialuohu, ca 2,250 m, 27.04.2003, leg. Y.M. Chen. Paratypes: 3 ♂, 1 ♀ (TFRI), same locality, 14.03.2003; 12 ♂, 8 ♀, 1 fragm. (TFRI), same locality, 28.04.2003; 1 ♂ (TFRI), same locality, 27.04.2003; 2 ♂ (ZMUM), 1 ♂ (IBSS), 2 ♂ (NSYSU), same locality, 25.12.2002; 1 ♂ (ZMUC), 1 ♂, 1 ♀ (TFRI), same locality, 7.11.2001; 1 ♂, 1 ♂ fragm. (TFRI), same locality, 4.06.2003, all leg. Y.M. Chen; 1 ♂ (ZMUM), same locality, 24.10.2002, leg. J.T. Chao; 1 ♂ (TFRI), Taichung County, Shengguang, 24.09.2002; 1 ♂ (TFRI), same locality, 24.01.2003; 1 ♀ (TFRI), same locality, 26.03.2003; 1 ♂ (MNHN JC 332), same locality, 24.01.2003; 1 ♂ (TFRI), same locality, 24.09.2002, all leg. W.C. Yeh; 1 ♂ (NMNS-6556-001), Nantou County, Ren-ai Township, Mei-Feng, 19.02.2002; 1 ♂ (NMNS-6556-002), same locality, 11.07.2002; 4 ♂ (NMNS-6556-003), same locality, 15.04.2002, all leg. S.H. Wu.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Name"><title>Name:</title>
                    <p>To emphasize the smaller body size and the shorter gonopod telopodite.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis:</title>
                    <p>Differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the only other congener known from Taiwan, in the smaller size, as well as in the collum being narrower than the head and in the gonopod telopodite being stouter and shorter (see also Key below).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description:</title>
                    <p>Length of both sexes ca 12–16 mm; width of pro- and metazona varying between specimens from 0.8–1.3 to 1.5–2.0 mm, respectively. Holotype ca 12 mm long, and 0.8 and 1.5 mm wide on pro- and metazona, respectively. Usually ♂♂<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> somewhat smaller than ♀♀. Coloration in alcohol from uniformly pallid (faded?) to yellowish to reddish-brown; in the latter case, sides, venter and legs light grey-brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 14–19</xref>).</p>
                    <p>All characters as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, except as follows.</p>
                    <p>Antennae a little shorter, usually reaching midway of segment 3. In width, collum &lt; head &lt; segment 2 &lt; 3 &lt; 4 &lt; 5=15(16), thereafter body gradually tapering towards telson. Starting from segment 16 (♂, ♀), paraterga extending increasingly beyond rear tergal contour, caudal corners invariably evidently rounded, but even on paraterga 17–19 not spiniform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 15, 18</xref>). Paraterga less evidently rounded laterally even in ♀, lateral edges mostly subparallel in ♂ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 15, 18</xref>), incisions being visible. Metatergal sculpture typical, rather superficial, with three transverse rows of setiferous, polygonal bosses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 15, 18</xref>). Tergal setae very short, usually retained at least on collum and/or metatergum 19 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 15, 16, 18</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Gonopod telopodite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–23</xref>) much stouter; endomere (<bold>en</bold>) slightly longer than exomere (<bold>ex</bold>), beset with long, bacilliform setae nearly throughout, usually supplied with an evident spine (<bold>s</bold>) or tooth mesally, as well as a usually somewhat less prominent pulvillus near base; <bold>ex</bold> often not so strongly unciform apically, often with an additional lateral tooth in distal part.</p>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 14–19.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus minor</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, ♂ paratype from Jialuohu. <bold>14</bold> habitus, lateral view <bold>15–17</bold> anterior portion of body, dorsal, lateral and ventral views, respectively <bold>18, 19</bold> posterior portion of body, dorsal and ventral views, respectively. Photographed not to scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_4.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 20–23.</label>
                        <caption><p>Left gonopods of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus minor</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., ♂ paratypes from Mei-Feng (<bold>20, 21</bold>) and Jialuohu (<bold>22, 23</bold>), mesal, lateral, mesal and lateral views, respectively. Scale bar: 0.2 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_5.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>This species is not so widely distributed in Taiwan. Allopatry is prevailing, as it is only at Mei-Feng that both the congeners co-occur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Map 1</xref>). However, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus minor</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. quite often lives even syntopically together with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see below).</p>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Map 1.</label>
                        <caption><p>Distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species in Taiwan. Borderlines show borders between the counties. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus minor</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.: filled red triangles; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>: filled black circles.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_6.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <p>A study of the ample material representing not only the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but also the above new congener from Taiwan allows for the identity of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chamberlin &amp; Wang, 1953 to finally become clarified.</p>
                    <p>This genus has hitherto remained enigmatic, originally described too poorly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Chamberlin and Wang 1953</xref>) to shed any significant light on its affinities. It was only based on the gonopod conformation of the beautifully described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus tangonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Murakami, 1973), a species from Honshu, Japan definitely most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Golovatch (1991)</xref> suggested the relationships of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> as a genus possibly somewhat intermediate between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizoturanius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff, 1931 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Attems, 1901.</p>
                    <p>In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the gonopod telopodite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 11–13</xref>) is indeed biramous only distally, being divided into subequally prominent endo- and exomere. Furthermore, the endomere (<bold>en</bold>) is beset with a characteristically bacilliform trichome, whereas the exomere (<bold>ex</bold>) is simple. The seminal groove runs mostly mesally to recurve neatly between <bold>ex</bold> and <bold>en</bold> and then to debauch somewhat basally into a prominent hairy pulvillus which is also beset with the same peculiar trichome, and is devoid of an accessory seminal chamber. The same general pattern is observed both in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus tangonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus minor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–23</xref>). What we term here as endomere is the branch which <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Murakami (1973)</xref> erroneously referred to as solenomere in his <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus tangonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Yet it can hardly be called such, because the seminal groove ends somewhat basally of it and thus fails to support it at all. This is where one of the basic distinctions between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <!--PageBreak-->and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizoturanius</tp:taxon-name></italic> seems to lie, because in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizoturanius</tp:taxon-name></italic> the recurvature point of the seminal groove between both distal branches <bold>ex</bold> and <bold>en</bold> is about level to the pulvillus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Golovatch 1979</xref>). So we can speak in this case about a true solenomere. In addition, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizoturanius</tp:taxon-name></italic> an accessory seminal chamber, however small, is present. Another characteristic feature of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> vis-à-vis not only <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizoturanius</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but also all other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Polydesmidae</tp:taxon-name> is an abundant bacilliform trichome on the endomere. Although a similar trichome is known to occur in some European <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polydesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species as well, it is always located either on the exomere or on a solenomere. These three apomorphies distinguish <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the obviously most similar <italic><tp:taxon-name>Schizoturanius</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a genus encompassing several species in Central Asia, Siberia and the southern part of the Eastern European Plain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Golovatch 1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">1991</xref>).</p>
                    <p>As regards Golovatch’s (1991) placement of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> also near <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Hoffman (1980)</xref> who had synonymized these genera, this idea is false, as they appear to show too many profound differences in gonopod structure. Thus, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic> the endomere is mostly absent, rarely present as only a rudimentary structure, while the seminal groove after the recurvature point still makes a long way basad to debauch into a prominent, simple-haired, accessory seminal chamber placed at the bottom of a profound parabasal cavity in the telopodite (see also below). Based on the gonopod conformation of one of the new Taiwanese species (see below), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Usbekodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lohmander, 1932, differing from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodu</tp:taxon-name></italic>s only in a somewhat better developed exomere, albeit also simple and more or less spiniform, is to be regarded as another junior synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, syn. n. Arguments for synonymizing both these genera have long been put forth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Geoffroy and Golovatch 2004</xref>), but until now no formal synonymy has been advanced.</p>
                    <p>This results in the following new formal transfers: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus redikorzevi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Lohmander, 1932), from Uzbekistan, Tajikistan and Afghanistan, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus swatensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1991), from Swat Province, northern Pakistan, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus varius</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Geoffroy &amp; Golovatch, 2004), from Hubei Province, southern China, as well as the Nepalese <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus anachoretus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1986), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus buddhis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1986), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus occultus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1986), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus sacer</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1987), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus theocraticus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1990) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus theosophicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Golovatch, 1986), all comb. n. ex <italic><tp:taxon-name>Usbekodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    <p>The following key can serve to separate all three currently known species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <sec sec-type="Key to Nipponesmus species"><title>Key to Nipponesmus species</title>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult body smaller, ≤ 10 mm long and ≤ 1.4 mm wide. Collum as wide as head. Endomere strongly enlarged, lobe-shaped, fringed by a very dense bacilliform trichome; exomere slender, much longer than endomere. Honshu, Japan</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus tangonis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult body larger, at least 12 mm long and ≥ 1.5 mm wide. Collum either broader or narrower than head. Endomere at most slightly enlarged, digitiform<!--PageBreak-->, beset with a dense bacilliform trichome nearly all over; exomere rather short and stout, at most only slightly longer than endomere. Taiwan</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult body 18–25 mm long and 1.55–2.0 mm wide. Collum broader than head. Gonopod telopodite considerably longer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 11–13</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult body 12–16 mm long and 2.9–4.8 mm wide. Collum narrower than head. Gonopod telopodite considerably stouter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–23</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus minor</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">orientalis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Epanerchodus_orientalis</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Attems, 1901</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 24</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8"/>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">36</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis orientalis</tp:taxon-name><comment> – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Wang 1956</xref>: 155 (R); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Wang 1963</xref>: 91 (R)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis takakuwai</tp:taxon-name><comment> – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Wang 1958</xref>: 341 (R)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="NB"><title>NB:</title>
                    <p>Complete catalogue information referring to this species can be found in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Murakami (1969)</xref></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined:</title>
                    <p>10 ♂ (TFRI), 1 ♂ (NMNS-6557-001), 1 ♀ (NSYSU), 2 ♂ (MNHN JC 333), Taiwan, Taichung County, Shengguang, 25.04.2003; 2 ♀ (TFRI), same locality, 26.03.2003; 1 ♀ (TFRI), same locality, 24.09.2002; 4 ♂ (TFRI), 1 ♂ (NMNS-6557-002), same locality, 24.07.2003, all leg. W.C. Yeh; 2 ♂, 1 ♀ (TFRI), 2 ♂, 1 ♀ (IBSS), Ilan County, Fushan, 23.03.2003; 2 ♀ (NMNS-6557-003), same locality, 18.05.2001; 5 ♂, 1 ♀ (TFRI), same locality, 19.06.2001; 1 ♂ (TFRI), same locality, without date, all leg. J.T. Chao; 1 ♂ (ZMUM), same locality, 20.11.2001, leg. S.S. Lu; 52 ♂, 17 ♀, 4 fragm. (TFRI), 2 ♂ (ZMUC), 2 ♂ (NSYSU), Ilan County, Tatong Township, near Lakes Jialuohu, ca 2,250 m, 4.06.2003; 1 ♀ fragm. (TFRI), same locality, 28.04.2003; 8 ♂, 6 ♀ (TFRI), same locality, 20.06.2002; 1 ♂ (ZMUM), same locality, 25.04.2003; 1 ♂ (TFRI), same locality, 23.07.2002, all leg. Y.M. Chen; 1 ♀ (NSYSU), Taitung County, Yanping Township, Yanping Forest road, ca. 1,250 m, 3.06.2003, leg. M.H. Hsu; 2 ♂ (NSYSU), Hualien County, Fongbin Township, Guangfong Highway, ca 300 m, 6.05.2009; 1 ♀ (NSYSU), same County, Shoufang Township, ca. 230 m a.s.l., 5.05.2009, all leg. M.H. Shu; 2 ♀ (NMNS-6557-004), Pingtung County, Chaozhou Township, Si-Lin, 1.06.1999, leg. ?; 1 ♀ (NMNS-6557-005), Kaohsiung County, Taoyuan, Provincial Road No. 20, near 142.5 km road-sign, 3.09.2009, leg. C.Y. Huang.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis:</title>
                    <p>Differs from the other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species known from Taiwan in the variable, mostly medium size, coupled with the caudal corner of most of the paraterga being pointed, and in the gonopod telopodite being relatively slender, complex, highly variable in shape and armature (see also Key below).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Redescription"><title>Redescription:</title>
                    <p>Length of both sexes ca 11–19 mm; width of pro- and metazona varying between specimens from 0.8–1.8 to 1.2–3.0 mm, respectively. Usually ♂♂ somewhat smaller than ♀♀. Coloration in alcohol from uniformly pallid (faded?) to light (reddish- to grey-) brown; in the latter case, venter and legs light grey to yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 24</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">31</xref>). Body with 20 segments. Tegument mainly dull, at most slightly shining, <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->texture very delicately alveolate. Labrum, frons and vertex densely pilose; epicranial suture clear but thin; no ridges above antennal sockets; isthmus between antennae considerably broader than diameter of antennal socket (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 29</xref>). Antennae long and only slightly clavate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 24, 25</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">28</xref>), reaching behind end (♂) or midway (♀) of segment 4 dorsally; antennomere 3 longest, 5th highest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 25</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">28</xref>); antennomeres 5 and 6 each with a small, compact, distodorsal group of bacilliform sensilla; antennomere 7 with a minute dorsoparabasal cone and a distodorsal group of microscopic sensilla.</p>
                    <p>In width, either collum ≤ segment 2 = 3 &lt; 4 &lt; head = 5(6)-15(16), or segment 2 = 3 &lt; collum &lt; head = 4 &lt; 5–15(16) (both sexes), thereafter body gradually tapering towards telson. Paraterga strongly developed, starting from collum, subhorizontal, set high but always lying slightly below a faintly convex dorsum; front shoulders and caudal edge nearly straight on several postcollum metaterga, caudal corner always pointed. Collum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 28</xref>) nearly regularly elliptical, with an incision near caudal corner and three transverse rows of setae (6+6, 4+4 and 3+3). Starting from segment 5, paraterga extending increasingly beyond rear tergal contour, mostly subspiniform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 25</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">28</xref>). Starting from segment 2, all poreless segments with three, all pore-bearing ones with four, small but evident incisions, each usually bearing a small seta on top at lateral margin. Pore formula normal, ozopores evident, dorsal, located in front of 4th indentation. Metatergal sculpture typical, rather well developed, with three transverse rows of setiferous, polygonal bosses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 25</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">28</xref>). Tergal setae short, mostly retained, a little longer only on collum and in rear row on metatergum 19 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 25, 27</xref>). Stricture between pro- and metazona rather obscure, wide, smooth and polished. Limbus very thin, microdenticulate. Pleurosternal carinae absent. Epiproct rather short, conical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 31</xref>), preapical papillae evident. Hypoproct semi-circular; caudal, paramedian, setiferous papillae evident and well-separated.</p>
                    <p>Sterna without modifications (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 29, 31</xref>), densely setose. Epigynal ridge very low, regularly rounded. Legs long and slender (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 28, 29</xref>), ca 1.8–1.9 (♂) or 1.2–1.3 (♀) times as long as midbody height; ♂ legs evidently enlarged, prefemora only slightly swollen dorsally, femora ventro-parabasally with shorter bifid setae replaced by sphaerotrichomes in remaining parts of femora, as well as on entire postfemora, tibiae and tarsi.</p>
                    <p>Gonopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 32–36</xref>) with large, subquadrate, medially fused coxae carrying a few long setae ventrally. Telopodite stout to rather slender, subfalcate, prefemoral (densely setose) portion one-third to half as long as entire telopodite; seminal groove running mesally over much of its extent, only distally moving frontally to recurve first laterad and then mesad, squeezing neatly between a simple, more or less rudimentary to completely reduced exomere (<bold>ex</bold>) and a more complex, branching and always well-developed endomere (<bold>en</bold>), then groove continuing to a considerable extent basad to end into a large accessory seminal chamber lying near base of a prominent excavation, the latter carrying an evident hairy pulvillus; <bold>en</bold> often but not alwayswith a strong mesal process (<bold>s</bold>), either slenderer and simple or larger and more complex in shape, as well as usually with a distinct, often again branching, laterobasal outgrowth (<bold>p</bold>); distal remainder of <bold>en</bold> elongate, often branching and enlarged, sometimes fringed with short setae or spines<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 24–27.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Attems, 1901, ♂ from Fushan. <bold>24</bold> habitus, lateral view <bold>25</bold> anterior portion of body, subdorsal view <bold>26</bold> middle portion of body, dorsal view <bold>27</bold> posterior portion of body, dorsal view. Photographed not to scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_7.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 28–31.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Attems, 1901, ♂ from Jialuohu. <bold>28, 29</bold> anterior portion of body, dorsal and ventral views, respectively <bold>30</bold> middle portion of body, lateral view <bold>31</bold> posterior portion of body, ventral view. Photographed not to scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_8.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 32–36.</label>
                        <caption><p>Right gonopods of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Attems, 1901, ♂♂ from Shengguang (<bold>32</bold>), Jialuohu (<bold>33–35</bold>) and Guangfong Highway (<bold>36</bold>), mesal, lateral, mesal, sublateral and submesal views, respectively. Scale bar: 0.1 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_9.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>This species seems to be the most widespread and variable among congeners. It has heretofore been accepted as being split into two nominal subspecies: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis takakuwai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff, 1913, but, given a similarly profound variation range in body size and shape, and, especially, in gonopod structure as observed in Japan alone, the subspecific status of <italic>takakuwai</italic> has long been questioned (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Miyosi 1959</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Murakami 1969</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Nishikawa and Murakami 1993</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Murakami (1993)</xref>, in the latest checklist of the Japanese Diplopoda, treats <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> without subspecies. Moreover, numerous samples from Hokkaido, Honshu and Shikoku, Japan, reveal that variation in gonopod conformation appears to be purely individual, failing to demonstrate any meaningful geographical patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Nishikawa and Murakami 1993</xref>). The same concerns the available samples from Taiwan. So we formalize here the long suspected synonymy: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Attems, 1901 = <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis takakuwai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff, 1913, syn. n.</p>
                    <p>It is noteworthy that, formally, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> fails to occur in southernmost Japan, i.e. on Kyushu Island and in the Ryukyus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Nishikawa and Murakami 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Nakamura and Korsós 2010</xref>), to reappear further south only in Taiwan. In northern Honshu, Japan, it is known to reach 26 mm in length and 3.4 mm in width, with the collum being slightly broader than the head (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Murakami 1969</xref>). In Taiwan, as proven by our study of several abundant syntopic samples, the animals tend to be smaller, the collum is invariably narrower than the head, while rather often the gonopods are totally devoid of both an exomere remnant and process <bold>s</bold>, frequently with the distal, longest part of their endomere being slender, not expanded.</p>
                    <p>Looking at such a profound variation as observed in a number of peripheral and gonopod characters in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, one cannot ignore several further nominal congeners described from Japan, including Kyushu, in which the gonopods look especially similar to those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus inferus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff, 1941, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus lobatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff, 1941, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus satoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Takakuwa, 1954, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus tenuis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Takakuwa, 1954, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus aculeatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Miyosi, 1954, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus etoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Miyosi, 1955, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus chichibensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Haga, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Takashima and Haga 1956</xref>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus yoshidai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Haga, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Takashima and Haga 1956</xref>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus lacteus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Shinohara, 1958, etc. (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Takashima and Haga 1956</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Shinohara 1958</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Miyosi 1959</xref>). We suspect that some of them might well prove to represent junior synonyms of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Only future in-depth biological observations and such genetic investigations as bar-coding of such particularly similar forms can shed light on their true identities and statuses, because polymorphic variation has long been known in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Thus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus polymorphus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mikhaljova &amp; Golovatch, 1981, widespread in the southern part of the Russian Far East and in northern Korea, shows two morphologically distinct morphs both in gonopod and peripheral structure in males, but a complete, overlapping range of the same somatic characters in females. Both male morphs invariably co-occur syntopically and either mates with any female variety (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Mikhaljova and Golovatch 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Mikhaljova 2004</xref>). A similar situation is found in the nominate species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus acuticlivus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Murakami, 1970 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus aster</tp:taxon-name></italic> Murakami, 1970, both described from the same cave in Shikoku, Japan. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Murakami (1970)</xref> explicitly admitted that they were very close, with their females being indistinguishable, while the males showed small but stable differences in gonopod telopodite armature.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->Based on the great variation observed in the populations of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Japan and, especially, Taiwan, the statuses of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus polymorphus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus acuticlivus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus aster</tp:taxon-name></italic> as further congeners highly similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are likewise to be questioned, as at least some of them might also prove to be the latter’s junior synonyms. Yet no formal synonymies are advanced here as obviously being too premature at this purely descriptive taxonomic stage.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p>That not all of the congeners similar in gonopod structure to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are synonyms of the latter is proven at least by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus koreanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verhoeff, 1937, a species common throughout Korea, in Kyushu, Japan and in the southern Russian Far East. At least in Russia, it often occurs syntopically together with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus polymorphus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Yet <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus koreanus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, despite its minor variations in gonopod conformation, is easily recognizable even superficially through its much wider paraterga (3.3–3.8 versus 2.6–3.0 mm); in addition, these species never mate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Mikhaljova 2004</xref>). As another proof to the above statement may also serve <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus pinguis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., described below and representing still one more congener quite similar in gonopod structure to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. In Taiwan, both are at least partly sympatric, but <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus pinguis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. differs markedly enough in a number of peripheral and gonopod characters to warrant recognition of a distinct species (see below).</p>
                    <p>In other words, several, but definitely not all, of the nominate species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic> that show their gonopods particularly similar in structure to those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are jeopardized as potential junior synonyms of the latter species.</p>
                    <p>In Taiwan, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> occurs in various habitats ranging from lowlands to the mid-montane belt (up to 1,250 m a.s.l.) all over the island (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Map 2</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pinguis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B0E8A6F1-335A-4961-9876-0328480D6D47</object-id>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Epanerchodus_pinguis</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 37</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">44</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material:</title>
                    <p>Holotype ♂ (head missing) (NMNS-6558-001), Taiwan, Nantou County, Huisun timber land, 15.04.2002, leg. S.H. Wu. Paratype ♂ (NMNS-6558-002), same locality, 24.03.1998, leg. S.H. Wu.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Name"><title>Name:</title>
                    <p>To emphasize the stout gonopod telopodite.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis:</title>
                    <p>Differs from the other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species, in particular from the apparently especially similar <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, in the mostly square, broader and slightly upturned paraterga, coupled with the gonopod showing an unusually densely setose coxa and a remarkably stout telopodite (see also Key below).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description:</title>
                    <p>Length ca 16 (paratype) or 20 mm (holotype); width of midbody pro- and metazona 1.5 and 2.9 mm (paratype) or 1.5 and 3.0 mm (holotype), respectively. Coloration in alcohol uniformly light red-brown to red-brown; venter and legs yellowish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 37–39</xref>).</p>
                    <p>All characters as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> except as follows.</p>
                    <p>Antennae rather long, slender, only slightly clavate, reaching behind segment 3 dorsally; antennomere 3 longest, clearly longer than highest 5th; antennomeres 5 and 6 each with an evident, compact, distodorsal group of bacilliform sensilla; antennomere 7 with a minute dorsoparabasal cone and a distodorsal group of microscopic sensilla.</p>
                    <p>In width, collum &lt; head ≤ segment 2 ≤ 3 &lt; 4 &lt; = 5–16, thereafter body gradually tapering towards telson (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 39</xref>). Paraterga strongly developed, starting from collum, slightly upturned, set high, mostly level to a very faintly convex dorsum, slightly below <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->dorsum only on collum and segment 2; paraterga on collum small, subtriangular, a small lateral incision in front of a narrowly rounded caudal corner; front shoulders drawn forward only paraterga 2 and 3, straight and subrectangular on paraterga 4, onward straight but directed increasingly caudolaterad; caudal edge nearly straight on paraterga 2–7, thereafter caudal corner increasingly acutangular, nearly always narrowly rounded, only on segment 19 spiniform and nearly pointed, mostly lying nearly level to rear tergal contour until segment 15, onward extending increasingly beyond it (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 37–39</xref>). Paraterga<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> 2 with 3–4 small lateral incisions, all following poreless segments with three, all pore-bearing ones with four, small but evident incisions, each usually bearing a small seta on top at lateral margin. Metatergal sculpture typical, rather obliterate, with three indistinct transverse rows of setiferous, polygonal bosses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 37–39</xref>). Tergal setae very short, mostly retained, a little longer only on collum and in rear row on metatergum 19 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 37, 39</xref>). Stricture between pro- and metazona wide and smooth. Limbus very thin, microdenticulate. Epiproct rather short, conical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 39</xref>), preapical papillae prominent. Hypoproct semi-circular; caudal, paramedian, setiferous papillae evident and well-separated.</p>
                    <p>Sterna without modifications, very densely setose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 40, 41</xref>). Legs long and slender, evidently enlarged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 42</xref>), ca 1.6–1.7 times as long as midbody height, prefemora not swollen dorsally, acropodite (femur+postfemur+tibia+tarsus) with sphaerotrichomes ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 42</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Gonopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 40</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">43, 44</xref>) with large, subquadrate, medially fused coxae carrying numerous long setae ventromedially. Telopodite mostly hidden inside gonocoel, unusually stout, subfalcate, prefemoral (densely setose) portion about half as long as entire telopodite; endomere (<bold>en</bold>) short, simple, with a subapical knob laterally and a rounded tip, as well as with two subunciform processes (<bold>s</bold> and <bold>p</bold>); hairy pulvillus very evident, exomere totally suppressed.</p>
                    <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 37–41.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus pinguis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., ♂ paratype. <bold>37, 40</bold> anterior portion of body, dorsal and ventral views, respectively; <bold>38</bold>, middle portion of body, dorsal view <bold>39, 41</bold> posterior portion of body, dorsal and ventral views, respectively. Photographed not to scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_10.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 42–44.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus pinguis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype. <bold>42</bold> leg 9 <bold>43, 44</bold> right gonopod, mesal and lateral views, respectively. Scale bar: 0.2 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_11.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F12" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Map 2.</label>
                      <caption><p>Distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species in Taiwan. Borderlines show borders between the counties. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus bispinosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.: empty black circle; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus curtigonopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.: blue cross; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus flagellifer</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.: filled green triangles; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>: filled grey squares; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus pinguis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.: filled red circle.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_12.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>This species is apparently very local in distribution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Map 2</xref>) and seems to be allopatric with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">bispinosus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5944975E-495B-4578-8145-779D40B9C80A</object-id>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Epanerchodus_bispinosus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 45</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">53</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material:</title>
                    <p>Holotype ♂ (NMNS-6559-001), Taiwan, Nantou County, Ren-ai Township, Mei-Feng, 15.04.2002, leg. S.H. Wu. Paratypes: 3 ♂, 1 ♂ fragm., 4 ♀, 1 ♀ juv. (NMNS-6559-002), 1 ♂, 1 ♀ (ZMUM), 1 ♂ (without head), 1 ♀ (ZMUC), 1 ♂ fragm., 1 ♀ (MNHN JC 334), 1 ♂ (TFRI), 1 ♂ (NSYSU), same locality, together with holotype.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Name"><title>Name:</title>
                    <p>To emphasize the distal half of the gonopod telopodite being like two long spines.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis:</title>
                    <p>Due to the presence of a strong and spiniform exomere, this new species joins the few congeners hitherto referred to the erstwhile genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Usbekodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see above the synonymy with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic>), but differs in the distal half of the gonopod telopodite being represented by only two spiniform branches showing no additional outgrowths (see also Key below).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description:</title>
                    <p>Length of both sexes ca 8–11 mm; width of pro- and metazona varying between specimens from 0.8–1.3 to 1.1–1.7 mm, respectively. Holotype ca 9 mm long, and 0.8 and 1.1 mm wide on pro- and metazona, respectively. Coloration in alcohol from pallid to uniformly light grey, yellow or very light red-brown, sometimes head faintly marbled light red-brown; venter and legs yellowish to greyish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 45–49</xref>).</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->All characters as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> except as follows.</p>
                    <p>Antennae rather long and evidently clavate, reaching behind end (♂) or midway (♀) of segment 3 dorsally; antennomere 3 longest, considerably longer than a relatively stout, yet highest, 5th (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 45</xref>); antennomeres 5 and 6 each with a small, compact, distodorsal group of bacilliform sensilla; antennomere 7 with a minute dorsoparabasal cone and a distodorsal group of microscopic sensilla.</p>
                    <p>In width, collum &lt; segment 2 = 3 &lt; 4 &lt; head = 5–15 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 46</xref>), thereafter body gradually tapering towards telson (♂, ♀) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 48</xref>). Paraterga moderately developed, starting from collum, set high but invariably lying slightly below a faintly convex dorsum; paraterga on collum small, subtriangular, with a small lateral incision in front of a rounded caudal corner; front shoulders drawn forward and slightly convex only paraterga 2–4, thereafter straight, increasingly well rounded and directed increasingly caudolaterad; caudal corner on pataterga 2–5 subrectangular and narrowly rounded, starting from 6th increasingly acutangular and beak-shaped, starting from segment 9 first faintly and then extending increasingly beyond rear tergal contour (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 45–48</xref>). All poreless segments with three, all pore-bearing ones with four, small but evident incisions, each usually bearing a small seta on top at lateral margin. Metatergal sculpture typical, moderately developed, with three indistinct transverse rows of setiferous, polygonal bosses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 46–48</xref>). Tergal setae very short, mostly retained, a little longer only on collum and in rear row on metatergum 19. Stricture<!--PageBreak--> between pro- and metazona wide and smooth. Limbus very thin, microdenticulate. Epiproct rather short, conical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 48</xref>), only slightly bent ventrad, preapical papillae evident. Hypoproct semi-circular; caudal, paramedian, setiferous papillae evident and well-separated.</p>
                    <p>Sterna without modifications, very densely setose. Legs rather short, slender, in ♂ evidently enlarged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 45</xref>), ca 1.5–1.6 (♂) or 1.1–1.2 times (♀) as long as midbody height, ♂ prefemora not swollen dorsally, together with femora beset with bifid setae ventrally, acropodite (postfemur+tibia+tarsus) with sphaerotrichomes ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 51</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Gonopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 50</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">52, 53</xref>) with large, subquadrate, medially fused coxae carrying only a few long setae ventrally. Telopodite slender and simple, prefemoral portion relatively short, exomere (<bold>ex</bold>) spiniform, endomere (<bold>en</bold>) only a little longer than <bold>ex</bold>, apex bent unciform mesally, devoid of any outgrowths near base; hairy pulvillus evident.</p>
                    <fig id="F13" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 45–50.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus bispinosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., ♂ paratype. <bold>45</bold> habitus, lateral view <bold>46</bold> anterior portion of body, dorsal view <bold>47</bold> middle portion of body, dorsal view <bold>48, 49</bold> posterior portion of body, dorsal and ventral views, respectively <bold>50</bold> gonopods, lateral view. Photographed not to scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_13.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F14" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 51–53.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus bispinosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., ♂ paratype. <bold>51</bold> leg 9 <bold>52, 53</bold> left gonopod, submesal and sublateral views, respectively. Scale bar: 0.4 mm (<bold>51</bold>) and 0.2 mm (<bold>52, 53</bold>).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_14.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>This species is remarkable in showing an exomere, albeit usual and spiniform, almost as long as a particularly simple endomere. This condition nicely bridges the weak distinction which has hitherto remained to formally keep <italic><tp:taxon-name>Usbekodesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic> as independent genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Geoffroy and Golovatch 2004</xref>), with the gonopod structure in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus bispinosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. providing the final evidence to formally synonymize these genera (see also above).</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus bispinosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in Taiwan is apparently very local in distribution, having been encountered only at a single locality (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Map 2</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">curtigonopus</tp:taxon-name-part>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:CBDF0100-0AEF-4D12-B88A-3A59119AD5C0</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Epanerchodus_curtigonopus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 54</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">60</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material:</title>
                    <p>Holotype ♂ (NMNS-6560-001), Taiwan, Nantou County, Ren-ai Township, Mei-Feng, 15.10.2001, leg. S.H. Wu.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Name"><title>Name:</title>
                    <p>To emphasize the remarkably short gonopod telopodite.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis:</title>
                    <p>Differs from other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species in the distal half of the gonopod telopodite being particularly stout, with the endomere represented only by a short spine supplied with a similarly short spine at its base (see also Key below). This new species seems to be particularly similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus pinguis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in sharing the gonopod which shows a densely setose coxa and a very stout telopodite (apparently, both being synapomorphies), but differs in the entire leg telopodites (prefemur+femur+postfemur+tibia+tarsus) being supplied with sphaerotrichomes ventrally, and the endomere and its basal process rudimentary and spiniform.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description:</title>
                    <p>Length ca 15 mm; width of pro- and metazona 1.3 and 2.5 mm, respectively. Coloration in alcohol pallid.</p>
                    <p>Superficially, also very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus pinguis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., except as follows.</p>
                    <p>In width, collum &lt; head &lt; segment 2 = 3 &lt; 4 &lt; 5 &lt; 6–15 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 54</xref>), thereafter body gradually tapering towards telson (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 55</xref>). Paraterga strongly developed, starting <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->from collum, set high, subhorizontal to very faintly upturned, lying slightly below dorsum only on collum and segment 2; mid-dorsum invariably extremely faintly convex, nearly flat; front shoulders mostly straight, drawn forward only on paraterga 2 and 3, thereafter directed increasingly caudolaterad and increasingly well rounded anterolaterally; caudal corner on paraterga 3–12 subrectangular and narrowly rounded, starting from 13th increasingly acutangular and evidently extending increasingly beyond rear tergal contour, but nearly pointed and beak-shaped only on segment 19 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 54, 55</xref>). Paraterga 2–5 and all following pore-bearing segments with four, following poreless ones with three, small but evident incisions, each usually bearing a small seta on top at lateral margin. Metatergal sculpture typical, moderately developed, with three indistinct transverse rows of setiferous, polygonal bosses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 54, 55</xref>). Tergal setae very short, mostly retained, a little longer only on collum and in rear row on metatergum 19. Stricture between pro- and metazona wide and smooth. Limbus very thin, microdenticulate. Epiproct rather short, conical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 55, 56</xref>), only slightly bent ventrad, preapical papillae evident. Hypoproct semi-circular; caudal, paramedian, setiferous papillae distinct and well-separated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 56</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Sterna without modifications, densely setose. Legs long and rather slender, only slightly enlarged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 56, 57</xref>), ca 1.7–1.8 times as long as midbody height, prefemora not swollen dorsally, entire telopodite (prefemur+femur+postfemur+tibia+tarsus) with sphaerotrichomes ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 58</xref>)<!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                    <p>Gonopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 57</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">59, 60</xref>) with large, subquadrate, medially fused coxae carrying numerous setae ventrally. Telopodite especially stout, prefemoral portion relatively prominent, taking up about one-third of telopodite length, endomere (<bold>en</bold>) like a short spine supplied with another, somewhat shorter spine (<bold>p</bold>) near base; both accessory seminal chamber and hairy pulvillus evident.</p>
                    <fig id="F15" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 54–57.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus curtigonopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype. <bold>54</bold> anterior portion of body, dorsal view <bold>55, 56</bold> posterior portion of body, dorsal and ventral views, respectively <bold>57</bold> middle portion of body (with gonopods), ventral view. Photographed not to scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_15.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F16" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 58–60.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus curtigonopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype. <bold>58</bold> leg 9 <bold>59, 60</bold> left gonopod, dorsomesal and ventrolateral views, respectively. Scale bar: 0.2 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_16.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>This species is remarkable in showing an extremely short, simple, spiniform endomere (<bold>en</bold>), coupled with a single, even more rudimentary process (<bold>p</bold>) at <bold>en</bold> base.</p>
                    <p>In Taiwan, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus curtigonopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. occurs very locally, having been found only at a single locality (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Map 2</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">flagellifer</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:35EAB5D4-7E11-496E-8292-4ED5C0676C83</object-id>
										<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Epanerchodus_flagellifer</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 61</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">68</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material:</title>
                    <p>Holotype ♂ (NMNS-6561-001), Taiwan, Nantou County, Huisun timber land, 24.04.1998, leg. S.H. Wu. Paratypes: 1 ♂ (NMNS-6561-002), same locality, together with holotype; 1 ♂ (NMNS-6561-003), same locality, 04.1998; 1 ♂ (ZMUM), same locality, 25.04.1999; 1 ♂ (TFRI), same locality, 24.04.1999, all leg. S.H. Wu.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Name"><title>Name:</title>
                    <p>To emphasize the remarkably long, flagelliform distal part of the gonopod telopodite.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis:</title>
                    <p>Differs from other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species in the distal half of the gonopod telopodite being particularly long, flagelliform, coupled with the presence of two rounded teeth at the base of the endomere (see also Key below). From the other congeners known from Taiwan, this new species differs also in the absence of sphaerotrichomes on ♂ legs.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description:</title>
                    <p>Length of both sexes ca 8–11 mm; width of pro- and metazona varying between specimens from 0.8–1.0 to 1.4–1.5 mm, respectively. Holotype ca 9 mm long, and 0.9 and 1.4 mm wide on pro- and metazona, respectively. Coloration in alcohol pallid to light grey- to red-brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 61–65</xref>).</p>
                    <p>All characters as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> except as follows.</p>
                    <p>Antennae rather long and evidently clavate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 61, 64</xref>), reaching behind segment 3 dorsally.</p>
                    <p>In width, collum &lt; segment 2 &lt; head = 3 = 4 &lt; 5–15(16) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 62</xref>), thereafter body gradually tapering towards telson (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 63</xref>). Paraterga well-developed, starting from collum, set high, subhorizontal to very faintly upturned, mostly nearly level to a very faintly convex dorsum, only on collum and segment 2 lying clearly below dorsum; paraterga on collum small, subtriangular, a small lateral incision in front of a rounded caudal corner; front shoulders drawn forward and slightly convex only paraterga 2 and 3, straight on paraterga 4, thereafter increasingly well rounded and directed increasingly caudolaterad; caudal edge straight on segments 2–4, thereafter increasingly bisinuate and acutangular caudolaterally; starting from segment 10, caudal corners extending <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->increasingly beyond rear tergal contour, spiniform on segments 17–19 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 61–65</xref>). All poreless segments with three, all pore-bearing ones with four, small but evident incisions, each usually bearing a small seta on top at lateral margin. Metatergal sculpture typical, moderately developed, with three indistinct transverse rows of setiferous, polygonal bosses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 62, 63</xref>). Tergal setae very short, mostly retained, a little longer only on collum and in rear row on metatergum 19. Stricture between pro- and metazona wide and smooth. Limbus very thin, microdenticulate. Epiproct rather short, conical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 65</xref>), only slightly bent ventrad, preapical papillae evident. Hypoproct semi-circular (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 65</xref>); caudal, paramedian, setiferous papillae evident and well-separated.</p>
                    <p>Sterna without modifications, very densely setose. Legs rather long, slender, only slightly incrassate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 61, 64</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">66</xref>), ca 1.7–1.8 times (♀) as long as midbody height, prefemora not swollen dorsally, sphaerotrichomes missing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 66</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Gonopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 67, 68</xref>) with large, subquadrate, medially fused coxae carrying only a few long setae ventrally. Telopodite simple and especially slender, prefemoral portion relatively short, endomere (<bold>en</bold>) flagelliform, with two small dentiform outgrowths at base; hairy pulvillus evident.</p>
                    <fig id="F17" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 61–65.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus flagellifer</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., ♂ paratype. <bold>61</bold> habitus, lateral view <bold>62, 64</bold> anterior portion of body, dorsal and ventral views, respectively <bold>63, 65</bold> posterior portion of body, dorsal and ventral views, respectively. Photographed not to scale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_17.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F18" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 66–68.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus flagellifer</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., ♂ paratype. <bold>66</bold> leg 9 <bold>67, 68</bold> left gonopod, mesal and lateral views, respectively. Scale bar: 0.2 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__93_9_18.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>This small species is remarkable in showing a particularly long, flagelliform endomere, coupled with only two short outgrowths at its base.</p>
                    <p>In Taiwan, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus flagellifer</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. occurs very locally, having been encountered only at a single locality (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Map 2</xref>)<!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <sec sec-type="Key to Epanerchodus species known from Taiwan (valid mostly for adult males)"><title>Key to Epanerchodus species known from Taiwan (valid mostly for adult males)</title>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gonopod coxae unusually densely setose, while telopodite particularly stout: prefemoral, setose part at least half as long as entire telopodite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 43, 44</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">59, 60</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gonopod coxae usual, with only a few strong setae, while telopodite elongate: prefemoral, setose part less than half as long as entire telopodite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 32</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">52, 53</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">67, 68</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">♂ legs devoid of sphaerotrichomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 66</xref>). Gonopod endomere (en) like a short spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 67, 68</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus curtigonopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all ♂ telopoditomeres with sphaerotrichomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 42</xref>). Gonopod endomere (en) like a strong tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 40</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">43, 44</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus pinguis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body usually larger, 11–19 mm long. Gonopod telopodite highly variable, complex: exomere (ex), if present, rudimentary, while endomere (en) branching (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 29, 30</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">32–36</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body usually smaller, 8–11 mm long. Gonopod telopodite simple: exomere (ex), if present, strong and spiniform, while endomere (en) like a strong spine or a long flagellum</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gonopod telopodite biramous, exomere (ex) strong and spiniform, while endomere (en) like a strong spine ending in a strong uncus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figs 52, 53</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus bispinosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gonopod telopodite uniramous, exomere absent, endomere (en) flagelliform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 67, 68</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus flagellifer</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title>
            <p>At present we can state that Taiwan supports a reasonably rich and quite peculiar polydesmid fauna represented by seven species in two genera. Of these, six species seem to be endemic, being largely restricted to the mountains in the central and northern parts of the island. Considering the distributions demonstrated by the Taiwanese <tp:taxon-name>Polydesmidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Maps 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">2</xref>), allopatry is prevailing while sympatry, probably even syntopy, has only been observed in two places. Thus, the normally much larger <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the slightly smaller <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus pinguis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and the smallest <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus flagellifer</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. co-occur at Huisun. Similarly, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus shirinensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nipponesmus minor</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus bispinosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., which also form a comparable succession of size decrease, are sympatric if not syntopic at Mei-Feng. Such examples seem to be best explained in terms of local niche segregation long documented elsewhere for a number of insular groups of Diplopoda (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Enghoff 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Enghoff and Báez 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Golovatch and Enghoff 2003</xref>), including those of Taiwan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Golovatch et al. 2010</xref>).</p>
            <p>The only polydesmid that is remarkably widespread and polymorphous in Taiwan, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Epanerchodus orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, appears to be confined to lowland to foothill habitats (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Map 2</xref>). For this reason alone, this species, which is also known to be extremely widely distributed, <!--PageBreak-->variable and lowland-dwelling across at least most of Japan, seems to be the only allochthonous element in the fauna of <tp:taxon-name>Polydesmidae</tp:taxon-name> of Taiwan, likely a later colonizer from Japan.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We are most grateful to the National Science Council, Taiwan, Republic of China and to the Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscow, Russian Federation for the support rendered to the Taiwanese and Russian teams, headed by H. W. Chang and S.I. Golovatch, respectively, to actively collaborate in our joint ecofaunistic studies on the Myriapoda of Taiwan.</p>
            <p>Special thanks go to K. S. Lee (NMNS) and J. T. Chao (TFRI) for kindly loaning material under their care. K. Makarov (Moscow, Russia) very skillfully took the pictures, N. Likhitrakarn (Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand) kindly helped in preparing the plates with colour photographs, while H.Y. Hsu (NSYSU) executed the maps. We are greatly obliged to C. C. Chen, S. Y. Wu, M. H. Hsu, J. D. Lee, H. D. Zhu, M. J. Hung, Y. M. Chen, W. C. Yeh, C. Y. Huang and S. H. Wu for their help in collecting material. We also thank the administration of the National Parks of Taiwan, and all departments of the county and city governments of Taiwan for permitting the collection of millipedes.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamberlin</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1953</year>)<article-title> Records of millipeds (Diplopoda) from Japan and other oriental areas, with descriptions of new genera and species.</article-title> <source>American Museum Novitates</source> <volume>1621</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Enghoff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> Adaptive radiation of the millipede genus <italic>Cylindroiulus</italic> on Madeira: habitat, body size, and morphology (Diplopoda, Julida: Julidae).</article-title> <source>Revue d’Écologie et de Biologie du Sol</source> <volume>20</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>403</fpage>-<lpage>415</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Enghoff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Báez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title/> <source>Biological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>277</fpage>-<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Geoffroy</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golovatch</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Some polydesmidan millipedes from caves in southern China (Diplopoda: Polydesmida), with descriptions of four new species</article-title>. <source>Arthropoda Selecta</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1/2</issue>): <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Golovatch</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> The composition and zoogeographical connections of the fauna of Diplopoda of Middle Asia. Communication 1</article-title>. <source>Zoologicheskiy Zhurnal</source> <volume>58</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>987</fpage>–<lpage>1001</lpage>. [in Russian, English summary]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Golovatch</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> The millipede family Polydesmidae in Southeast Asia, with notes on phylogeny.</article-title> <source>Steenstrupia</source> <volume>17</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>141</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Golovatch</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enghoff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Pill-millipedes of the Canary Islands: the <italic>Glomeris alluaudi</italic>-group (Diplopoda, Glomeridae).</article-title> <source>Vieraea</source> <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Golovatch</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikhaljova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Pill-millipedes (Glomerida, Diplopoda) in Taiwan</article-title>. <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2447</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<source> Classification of the Diplopoda</source>. <publisher-name>Muséum d’histoire naturelle</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Genève</publisher-loc>, <lpage>237</lpage> pp. [for 1979]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Korsós</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Checklist and bibliography of millipedes (Diplopoda) of Taiwan.</article-title> <source>Collection and Research</source> <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikhaljova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<source> The millipedes of the Asian part of Russia</source>. <publisher-name>Pensoft</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Sofia–Moscow</publisher-loc>, <lpage>292</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikhaljova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Golovatch</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<article-title> Polymorphism in a new species of <italic>Epanerchodus</italic> (Diplopoda, Polydesmidae) from the USSR Far East</article-title>. <source>Zoologicheskiy Zhurnal</source> <volume>60</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1183</fpage>–<lpage>1189</lpage>. [in Russian, English summary]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyosi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>)<source> Über japanische Diplopoden</source>. <publisher-name>Arachnological Society of East Asia</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Osaka</publisher-loc>, Special Number, <lpage>244</lpage> pp. [in Japanese]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>)<article-title> Myriapods found in limestone caves of northern Honshu, Japan.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the National Science Museum</source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>557</fpage>-<lpage>582</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> More new species of <italic>Epanerchodus</italic> (Diplopoda, Polydesmidae) found in limestone caves in eastern Shikoku, Japan.</article-title> <source>Annotationes Zoologicae Japonenses</source> <volume>43</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>157</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>)<article-title> Two new species of polydesmid millipeds from western Honshu, Japan.</article-title> <source>Annotationes Zoologicae Japonenses</source> <volume>44</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>253</fpage>-<lpage>258</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<source> Diplopoda, Pauropoda, Symphyla. A list of Japanese species. Invertebrates 1</source>. <publisher-name>Shizen-Kankyô-Kenkyû Center. Environmental Agency Japan</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc>: <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>. [in Japanese]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korsós</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Distribution and diversity of millipedes of the Ryukyu Archipelago, with the Senkaku and Daito island groups: A literature review (Arthropoda: Diplopoda).</article-title> <source>Acta Arachnologica</source> <volume>59</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>73</fpage>-<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Distributional records on Japanese millipeds (II)</article-title>. <source>Faculty of Letters Review of Otemon Gakuin University</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>. [in Japanese]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>)<article-title> Polydesmoidea millipeds from Chichibu</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of the Chichibu Museum of Natural History</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. [in Japanese, with English abstract]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Takashima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1956</year>)<article-title> A contribution towards the Japanese cave-dwelling species of the class Diplopoda</article-title>. <source>Miscellaneous Reports of Yamashina’s Institute of Ornithology and Zoology</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>. [in Japanese]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y-HM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1956</year>)<article-title> Serica 1e: Records of myriapods on Formosa with description of new species (2).</article-title> <source>Quarterly Journal of the Taiwan Museum</source> <volume>9</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>155</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y-HM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>)<article-title> Serica 1i: On Diplopoda from Taiwan with a new strongylosomids.</article-title> <source>Quarterly Journal of the Taiwan Museum</source> <volume>11</volume> (<issue>3–4</issue>):<fpage>340</fpage>-<lpage>344</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y-HM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<article-title> Serica 1q: Millipedes and centipedes of Quemoy, Fukien Province and Taiwan Island, Botel Tobago (Lan Yu), Taiwan Province and of Singapore.</article-title> <source>Quarterly Journal of the Taiwan Museum</source> <volume>16</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>96</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>