<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.100.1542</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                How unique is the tiger beetle fauna (Coleoptera, Cicindelidae) of the Balkan Peninsula?
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Jaskuła</surname>
                        <given-names>Radomir</given-names>
                    </name>
										
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"/>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label/>Department of Invertebrate Zoology and Hydrobiology, University of Łódź, Banacha 12/16, 90-237 Łódź, Poland
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Radomir Jaskuła (<email xlink:type="simple">radekj@biol.uni.lodz.pl</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Th. Assmann</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
            	    
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>20</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>100</issue>
            <fpage>487</fpage>
            <lpage>502</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>30</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2009</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>31</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Radomir Jaskuła</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The tiger beetle fauna of the Balkan Peninsula is one of the richest in Europe and includes 19 species or 41% of the European tiger beetle fauna. Assembled by their biogeographical origins, the Balkan tiger beetle species fall into 14 different groups that include, Mediterranean, Middle Oriental, Central Asiatic, Euro-Siberian, South and East European, Pannonian-Sarmatian, West Palaearctic, Turano-European and Afrotropico Indo-Mediterranean species. The Mediterranean Sclerophyl and the Pontian Steppe are the Balkan biogeographical provinces with the highest species richness, while the Balkan Highlands has the lowest <tp:taxon-name>Cicindelidae</tp:taxon-name> diversity. Most species are restricted to single habitat types in lowland areas of the Balkan Peninsula and only <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera aulica aulica</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera littoralis nemoralis</tp:taxon-name></italic> occur in respectively 3 and 4 different types of habitat. About 60% of all Balkan <tp:taxon-name>Cicindelidae</tp:taxon-name> species are found in habitats potentially endangered by human activity.</p>    
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Balkan Peninsula</kwd>
				
                <kwd>biodiversity</kwd>
				
                <kwd>distribution</kwd>
				
                <kwd>Europe</kwd>
				
                <kwd>zoogeography</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Tiger beetles occur world-wide, with the exception of the polar regions and some oceanic islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Cassola and Pearson 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Pearson and Vogler 2001</xref>). Detailed studies from different regions show that many species have narrow habitat specialization and occur only in one or at most in few very similar types of habitat. As a result, tiger <!--PageBreak-->beetles have become a significant global flagship group for beetle conservation used as biological indicators for determining global and regional patterns of biodiversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Knisley and Hill 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Pearson and Cassola 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Carroll and Pearson 1998a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Andriamampianina et al 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Pearson and Vogler 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Arndt et al. 2005</xref>). In most species, adult beetles are diurnal and highly mobile, while larvae are sedentary and live in burrows constructed in the substrate where the eggs are oviposited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Pearson 1988</xref>). Both imagines and larvae are predators that prey on small invertebrates, a characteristic that makes them potentially natural biological controls of pests with an economic value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">Rodriguez et al. 1998</xref>).</p>
            <p>The Balkan Peninsula is part of the Mediterranean basin. It is one of the 25 most important world hotspot areas of biodiversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Myers et al. 2000</xref>). Together with two other South European peninsulas, the Iberian and the Italian, the Balkans were the most important terrestrial Pleistocene glacial refugia in Europe. Phylogeographical studies on many different groups of animals and plants show that these areas are regions from which the re-colonisation of northern Europe started after the last glaciation period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Hewitt 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Blonden and Aronson 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Thompson 2005</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">Weiss and Ferrand (2007)</xref> suggest that high biodiversity of the South European Peninsulas, including the Balkan Peninsula, can be explained by relatively high climatic stabilization of this region as well as heterogeneous landscapes occurring in this area. Moreover, the Balkans have served as an important natural bridge for historical dispersal between Asia Minor and northern, western and central Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Crnobrnja-Isailovic 2007</xref>).</p>
            <p>The first data on the tiger beetle fauna of the Balkan Peninsula were published at the end of the 19th and beginning of the 20th century (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Reitter 1881</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Horn and Roeschke 1891</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Apfelbeck 1904</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">1907</xref>). Since then, more than 40 papers have been published on this topic, many of which however only describe information on a single species or present incomplete faunistic and taxonomic data. Recently more complete information on the fauna of some regions have been summarized for Bulgaria (Guéorguievand Guéorguiev1995), Montenegro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Jaskuła et al. 2005</xref>), Albania (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Guéorguiev 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Jaskuła 2007a</xref>), Romania (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Cassola and Jaskuła 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Jaskuła 2007b</xref>), Greece (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Franzen 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Jaskuła et al. – in preparation</xref>) and the European part of Turkey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Cassola 1999</xref>; Avgın and Özdikmen 2007).</p>
            <p>The aim of this paper is to summarize knowledge on the diversity of tiger beetles in the Balkan Peninsula with particular emphasis on total group diversity, zoogeographical composition, distribution, and ecological preferences of the species.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Study area"><title>Study area</title>
            <p>We can define the Balkan Peninsula as a part of southeastern Europe with its northern boundary at the Danube, Sava and Kupa rivers. The rest of its margins are made up of the Black Sea in the east, the Adriatic Sea in the west, and the Mediterranean Sea (including the Aegean and Ionian seas) in the south (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The region has a combined<!--PageBreak--> area of ca. 550,000 km2, which is nearly 5% of the entire European continent. The peninsula includes twelve countries, seven of which are completely confined to the Balkan Peninsula (Albania, Bulgaria, Greece, Macedonia FYR, Montenegro, Kosovo, and Bosnia-Herzegovina), and five (Romania, Serbia, Croatia, Slovenia, and Turkey) have only a part of their territories on the peninsula.</p>
            <p>The largest surface of the Balkan Peninsula is mountainous. Lowlands extend along the lower reaches of rivers that are grouped into three catchments draining into the Adriatic, Aegean, and Black Sea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">Reed et al. 2004</xref>). Geographically this area is divided into the following main regions: Dinaric, Pindus, Tracian-Macedonic, Balkanic, Danubian plain, and North-Dobroudzha (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Geographical and administrative divisions of the Balkan Peninsula: <bold>I</bold> Dinaric region <bold>II</bold> Pindus region <bold>III</bold> Tracian-Macedonian region <bold>IV</bold> Balkanid region <bold>V</bold> Danubian plain region <bold>VI</bold> North-Dobroudzha region <bold>AL</bold> Albania <bold>BG</bold> Bulgaria <bold>BH</bold> Bosnia and Herzegovina <bold>CR</bold> Croatia <bold>GR</bold> Greece <bold>KO</bold> Kosovo <bold>MA</bold> Macedonia FYR<bold>, MO</bold> Montenegro <bold>RO</bold> Romania <bold>SB</bold> Serbia <bold>SL</bold> Slovenia <bold>TR</bold> Turkey.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-100-487-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p><!--PageBreak-->According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Udvardy (1975)</xref> the Balkan Peninsula belongs to three main biogeographical provinces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>): Mediterranean Sclerophyl – which includes European parts of Turkey, the Adriatic coast of Albania, Montenegro, Bosnia-Herzegovina, Croatia and Slovenia, and the sea coast of continental Greece; Balkan Highlands – with mountain areas of Bulgaria, Albania, Montenegro, Kosovo, Bosnia-Herzegovina, Serbia (except Voivodina), and partly also the mountains of Greece, Croatia and Slovenia, as well as the southern part of the Bulgarian Black Sea Coast; Pontian Steppe – the smallest area of the Balkans with only a small part of the northeastern Bulgarian Black Sea Coast and southeastern Romania, with its northern border at the Danube Delta.</p>
            <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                <label>Figure 2.</label>
                <caption><p>Tiger beetle faunas in the biogeographical provinces of the Balkan Peninsula (division after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Udvardy 1975</xref>): light grey – Mediterranean Sclerophyl, dark grey – Pontian Steppe, black – Balkan Highlands. Numbers in the circles indicate the number of cicindelid taxa for the separate regions and the squares give the number of taxa common to the provinces shared.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-100-487-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="material|methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The basis for this analysis of Balkan tiger beetles comes from published literature data; such as museum collections of the Museum and the Institute of Zoology, Polish Academy of Sciences (Warsaw, Poland), Royal Belgian Institute of Natural Sciences (Brussels, Belgium), Zoological Museum (Copenhagen, Denmark), Finnish Museum of Natural History (Helsinki, Finland), University of Montenegro (Podgorica, Montenegro); and original collections made by the author in the years 2005–2009 during five scientific expeditions covering almost all Balkan countries (“I-III Amphi-Balkan expeditions” and “Ist and IIIrd TB-Quest expeditions”).</p>
            <p>Tiger beetle species richness and distribution of taxa were analysed based on squares of 1o latitude and longitude. In each square the number of all species recorded was summarized. Similarities among tiger beetle fauna between geographical units were measured using the Bray-Curtis index for presence<italic>/</italic>absence data (Primer v.2.0). Jaccard’s (1902) index was used to present the degree of dissimilarity between zoogeographic regions distinguished by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Udvardy (1975)</xref>:</p>
            <p>R= 100c/a+b-c</p>
            <p>where: a = number of species in the richest fauna; b = number of species in the poorest fauna, c = number of species comon to both faunas.</p>
            <p>Chorotypes follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">Vigna Taglianti et al. (1999)</xref>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results"><title>Results</title>
            <sec sec-type="Diversity of tiger beetles in the Balkan Peninsula"><title>Diversity of tiger beetles in the Balkan Peninsula</title>
                <p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Putchkov and Matalin (2003)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">López et al. (2006)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Fauna Europea Web Service (2004)</xref> 49 tiger beetle species occur in Europe. Of these, 19 species have been found in the area of the Balkan Peninsula (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), or 39% of all European tiger<!--PageBreak--> beetle species. This number increases to 41% if three species known only from Mediterranean islands of Europe are excluded (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota tibialis</tp:taxon-name></italic> – Cyprus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera lunulata</tp:taxon-name></italic> – Sicily, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Habrodera nilotica</tp:taxon-name></italic> – Canary Islands). The Balkan species belong to five genera (55.5% of European fauna) including: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myriochila</tp:taxon-name></italic> (1 species, 50% of European species), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota</tp:taxon-name></italic> (4 species, 33%), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera</tp:taxon-name></italic> (4 species, 57%), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera</tp:taxon-name></italic> (4 species, 57%), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela</tp:taxon-name></italic> (7 species, 41%). Only four European genera – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Megacephala</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lophyra</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cassolaia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Habrodera</tp:taxon-name></italic> do not occur in this area. Two taxa (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela campestris oliviera</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela monticola albanica</tp:taxon-name></italic>) are endemic to this area. Additionally, for eleven species the Balkan Peninsula is the only place in Europe where they occur (having also distributions outside Europe).</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Table 1.</label>
                    <caption><p>Comparison of area and tiger beetle species richness of some European regions [based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Putchkov and Matalin (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Fauna Europea Web Service (2004)</xref>].</p></caption>
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Region</italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Area(km2)</italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Number of species</italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Species density(species number/1000 km2)</italic></th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Balkan Peninsula</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">550 000</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iberian Peninsula</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">580 000</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italian Peninsula</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 000</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scandinavian Peninsula</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">800 000</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France (mainland)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">675 000</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ukraine</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">603 700</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia (European part)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 268 850</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>The number of Balkan tiger beetle species is high compared with the number noted from other European regions with similar sized areas, especially north of the Balkan Peninsula (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Moreover, the diversity of the tiger beetle fauna in the studied area is similar to the fauna known from the entire territory of the European part of Russia. Among European regions with a similar area, only the Iberian Peninsula and the Ukraine exhibit similar numbers of tiger beetle species.</p>
                <p>Balkan <tp:taxon-name>Cicindelidae</tp:taxon-name> belong to 14 different groups according to their geographical origin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">Vigna Taglianti et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Except Balkan endemics and Mediterranean species, representatives of Middle Oriental, Central Asiatic, Euro-Siberian, South and East European, Pannonian-Sarmatian, West Palaearctic, Turano-European, or even Afrotropico Indo-Mediterranean taxa can be found in this area.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Table 2.</label>
                    <caption><p>Chorotypes of Balkan tiger beetles (after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">Vigna Taglianti et al. 1999</xref>).</p></caption>
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Balkan endemics</italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela campestris oliviera</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela monticola albanica</tp:taxon-name></italic></th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mediterranean</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera littoralis nemoralis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota circumdata circumdata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera aulica aulica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Mediterranean</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera concolor concolor</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Mediterranean</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera trisignata trisignata</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Middle Oriental</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera fischeri fischeri</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Asiatic</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota chiloleuca</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera contorta contorta</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Northeast Mediterranean (Aegean)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota turcica</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera trisignata hellenica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">East European</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota elegans stigmatohora</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Palaearctic</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela campestris campestris</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera germanica germanica</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela hybrida</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turano-European </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela monticola rumelica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">South European</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela sylvicola</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera germanica muelleri</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pannonian-Sarmatian</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela soluta pannonica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Euro-Siberian</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela sylvatica</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera arenaria viennensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Afrotropico Indo-Mediterranean</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myriochila melancholica melancholica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Distribution of tiger beetles in the Balkans"><title>Distribution of tiger beetles in the Balkans</title>
                <p>Within the Balkan Peninsula, species richness of particular regions differs both in number of taxa and species composition. Records from the literature and my own observations within single squares of 1o latitude and longitude show that the highest numbers of tiger beetle species are along sea coasts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Moreover, within biogeographic provinces as definied by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Udvardy (1975)</xref> the greatest tiger beetle species richness in the Balkan Peninsula is found in the Mediterranean Sclerophyl region (13 species, 68% of the Balkan fauna), and somewhat lower in the Pontian Steppe (10 species, 52%), and the Balkan Highlands (12 species, 63%). This, despite the fact that the Balkan Highlands cover a part of the peninsula that is larger than both previous biogeographical provinces combined. Moreover, the Balkan part of the Pontian Steppe <!--PageBreak-->is almost 17 times smaller than the Balkan Highlands and about ten times smaller than the Mediterranean Sclerophyl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Figure 3.</label>
                    <caption><p>Species richness of tiger beetles within the Balkan Peninsula. The colour gradient indicates an enhanced diversity from one species (white square) to eight (black square).</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-100-487-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Bray<italic>-</italic>Curtis analysis of similarities among tiger beetle faunas from different Balkan geographical regions shows the presence of three main clades (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). The Dinaric, Tracio-Macedonian and Balkanic regions group mainly mountain areas, with lowlands only as very small parts, and covers a great part of Udvardy’s (1975) Balkan Highlands. The Danubian plain and North-Dobroudzha regions compose the second group, mentioned in biogeographic studies as the Pontian Steppe and north-eastern part of the Balkan Highlands. Clearly different is the Pindus area, which covers a large area of the Mediterranean Sclerophyl province. The Jaccard’s similarity index for Mediterranean Sclerophyl – Pontian Steppe was 53%, for Mediterranean Sclerophyl – Balkan Highland was 47%, and for Pontian Steppe – Balkan Highland was 38% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Figure 4.</label>
                    <caption><p>Similarities among tiger beetle faunas inhabiting regions of the Balkan Peninsula (Bray<italic>-</italic>Curtis similarity index for presence<italic>/</italic>absence data).</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-100-487-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Ecotypes of Balkan Cicindelidae"><title>Ecotypes of Balkan <tp:taxon-name>Cicindelidae</tp:taxon-name></title>
                <p>The most eurytopic species are <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera littoralis nemoralis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera aulica aulica</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>), occupying four and three habitats respectively. Ten species have been found occurring in only one type of habitat, including three <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota</tp:taxon-name></italic> species in saltmarshes,<!--PageBreak--> three species restricted to sandy sea coasts (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera concolor</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera contorta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera trisignata</tp:taxon-name></italic>), four to river banks (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera fischeri</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela sahlbergii albanica</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera soluta pannonica</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera arenaria viennensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>), and one – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela sylvatica</tp:taxon-name></italic>, to forested sandy areas. Another five species were noted as occurring only in two types of habitat. Among all these tiger beetles, fifteen species (79% of the fauna) can be classified as coastal and riverine taxa, occurring in habitats adjacent to water, such as sea coasts, salt marshes (including lagoons and estuaries), and banks of rivers and freshwater lakes.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Table 3.</label>
                    <caption><p>Tiger beetles of the Balkan Peninsula and their ecological distribution: <bold>1</bold> salt marshes <bold>2</bold> sandy sea beaches <bold>3</bold> banks of rivers <bold>4</bold> banks of lakes <bold>5</bold> forest roads <bold>6</bold> mountain and highland pastures <bold>7</bold> flat coastal rocks (based on literature data and personal observations).</p></caption>
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>No.</italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Species</italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>1</italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>2</italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>3</italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>4</italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>5</italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>6</italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>7</italic></th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera aulica aulica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera concolor concolor</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera fischeri fischeri</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera littoralis nemoralis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota (Cephalota) turcica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota (Taenidia) chiloleuca</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota (Taenidia) circumdata circumdata</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota (Taenidia) elegans stigmatophora</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela (Cicindela) campestris</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela (Cicindela) hybrida</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela (Cicindela) monticola albanica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela (Cicindela) soluta pannonica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela (Cicindela) sylvatica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela (Cicindela) sylvicola</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera (Cylindera) germanica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera (Eugrapha) arenaria viennensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera (Eugrapha) contorta contorta</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera (Eugrapha) trisignata</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myriochila (Myriochila) melancholica melancholica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="2">Total</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion and conclusions"><title>Discussion and conclusions</title>
            <sec sec-type="Diversity and distribution of tiger beetles in the Balkan Peninsula"><title>Diversity and distribution of tiger beetles in the Balkan Peninsula</title>
                <p>Compared to the area size of other regions of Europe, the diversity of tiger beetles of the Balkan Peninsula is high and constitutes about 41% of all European tiger beetle species. This result confirms an important role of the Balkans as a biodiversity hotspot noted earlier for many other groups of organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Blonden and Aronson 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Kryštufek and Reed 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Thompson 2005</xref>). The high diversity of tiger beetles in the Balkans can be explained by two characteristics. The first is the topographic position <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->of this area within the European continent – the Peninsula was (and still is) a natural dispersal bridge for faunas from the Middle East and West, North and East Europe. The second is the high diversity of open habitats prefered by these beetles, including salt marshes, salty lagoons, sandy beaches, river banks, steppes, or mountain areas.</p>
                <p>The Balkan Peninsula is inhabited by a mixed tiger beetle fauna with representatives of 19 species belonging to 14 different groups according to their geographical origin (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Such a mosaic of faunal elements clearly suggests an important role of the Balkan Peninsula as a natural geographic „bridge” between Europe and Asia Minor for this group in the past. Similar patterns have been noted also among other groups of insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Kenyeres et al. 2009</xref>), spiders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Deltshev 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">2004</xref>), amphibians and reptiles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Crnobrnja-Isailovic 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Džukić and Kalezić 2004</xref>), mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Kryštufek 2004</xref>) and plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Thompson 2005</xref>).</p>
                <p>A high level of landscape heterogeneity also helps in explaining the general distribution pattern of tiger beetle species within the Balkan Peninsula and their higher species richness in the lowlands. Sandy habitats preferred both by larvae and adult are more diverse at sea coasts than those found in mountain areas. This patterns for Balkan tiger beetles is similar to that reported from other regions of the Mediterranean area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Cassola 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1973</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Lisa 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Jaskuła – unpublished</xref>). Moreover, a higher diversity of tiger beetles along sea coasts over that found in mountain areas has been found on the Indian subcontinent and in western and northern Australia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Pearson and Cassola 1992</xref>). It is most likely attributed to high habitat diversity occurring in lower altitudes (sandy beaches, salt marshes, lagoons, dunes, ect).</p>
                <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Plate 1.</label>
                  <caption><p>Balkan tiger beetle species: <bold>A</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera littoralis nemoralis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>B</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera fischeri fischeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>C</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota chiloleuca</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>D</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota chiloleuca circumdata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>E</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela sylvicola</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>F</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela campestris oliviera</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>G</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera trisignata hellenica</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>H</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myriochila melancholica melancholica</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-100-487-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Ecological preferences in Balkan Cicindelidae"><title>Ecological preferences in Balkan <tp:taxon-name>Cicindelidae</tp:taxon-name></title>
                <p>The narrow specialization to habitat type recorded for most of the Balkan tiger beetle species is similar to that in tiger beetles occurring in other regions of the world, both for adults and larvae. For example, of the 151 species noted on the Indian subcontinent by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Acciavatti and Pearson (1989)</xref> only one – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calochroa flavomaculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hope – was recorded from several different habitat types. In Australia among 29 species only two – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myriochila mastersi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Castelnau and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myriochila semicincta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Brulle – occur found as occurring in several habitat types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Freitag 1979</xref>). In the Tambopata Reserve Zone (Madre de Dios, Peru) only one of 29 species – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Odontocheila annulicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Brulle – occurred in more than one forest habitat type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Pearson 1984</xref>), and of the 20 species noted in the Sulphur Springs Valley (Arizona, USA) only <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindelidia nigrocoerulea</tp:taxon-name></italic> Leconte was recorded as inhabiting more than one habitat type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Knisley and Pearson 1984</xref>). Moreover, the specialization can be so narrow that species occurrence can be restricted to only a small part of a particular habitat. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Schultz and Hadley (1987)</xref> showed during their studies of two riparian species in the USA that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela oregona</tp:taxon-name></italic> Leconte occurred mainly at stream edges while <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cicindela tranquebarica</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Herbst) preferred dry areas. Also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Ganeshaiah and Belavadi (1986)</xref> noted that four tiger beetle species segregated distinctly along river beds into separate microhabitats in India. In the Balkans, I observed similarly <!--PageBreak-->narrow microhabitat specialization in the Evros river delta (eastern Greece) for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera littoralis nemoralis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (wet sand), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota circumdata circumdata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cylindera trisignata hellenica</tp:taxon-name></italic> (dry parts of river bed), and in the Danube river delta (eastern Romania) for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cephalota chiloleuca</tp:taxon-name></italic> (drier salt marsh substrate), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera littoralis nemoralis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (edge of reservoirs).</p>
                <p>Such narrow specialization to habitat/microhabitat types among tiger beetle species is explained by physiological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Schultz and Hadley 1987</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Hadley et al. 1990</xref>), morphological (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Pearson and Mury 1979</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Schultz and Hadley 1987</xref>), and behavioural (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Knisley and Pearson 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Pearson and Lederhouse 1987</xref>) adaptations of adults and larvae.</p>
                <p>Most Balkan tiger beetles occupy sandy habitats localized in lowlands, mainly on the sea coasts and in river deltas (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). More than 90% of south-east European salt marshes are found in the Balkan Peninsula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Dijkema 1984</xref>). As a result of human activity some of these areas have been significantly altered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Saveljić 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Davy et al. 2009</xref>) and are threatened. Therefore, this habitat is included among important biodiversity sites in the European Union’s Habitats Directiveand Water Framework Directive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Directive 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">2000</xref>). Given the ecological distribution of Balkan tiger beetles (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>), at least 42% of the recorded species occur in these threatened environments. Moreover, studies of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calomera</tp:taxon-name></italic> species show that some tiger beetles characteristic of coastal sandy beaches are negatively influenced by tourist activity and rapid development of tourist infrastructure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Arndt et al. 2005</xref>). If valid for the Balkan Peninsula, this adds an additional two or three species to the list of potentially threatened tiger beetles, and a total of almost 60% of all Balkan tiger beetle fauna. What more, the Balkan Peninsula is a biogeographical melting pot, and a transition zone where faunal elements of various origins meet. Thus, such a biogeographical structure, unique both at a scale of the southeastern Mediterranean region and the entire European continent, is particularly vulnerable to deterioration.</p>
                <p>Hopefully the plight of these tiger beetles will help focus the attention of biologists, ecologists, and nature conservationists on the Balkan Peninsula as an important European hotspot area for conserving biodiversity of the European fauna.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>I would like to express my thanks to Michał Grabowski who first focused my attention on the Balkan tiger beetle fauna. Piotr Jóźwiak prepared maps used in this paper (both from the University of Łódź, Łódź, Poland). Finally thanks are due to two anonymous reviewers for their valuable remarks and language corrections. The research was partly financially supported by SYNTHESYS Project AT-TAF-418.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Acciavatti</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> The tiger beetle genus <italic>Cicindela</italic> (Coleoptera, Insecta) from the Indian subcontinent.</article-title> <source>Annals of Carnegie Museum</source> <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>353</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Andriamampianina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kremen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vane-Wright</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Razafimahatratra</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Taxic richness patterns and conservation of Madagascar tiger beetles (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of Insect Conservation</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>-<lpage>128</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1009667712512" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1023/A:1009667712512</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Apfelbeck</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1904</year>)<source> Die Käferfauna der Balkanhalbinsel, mit Berücksichtigung Klei-Asien und der Insel Kreta. Erstes Band: Familienreihe Caraboidea. I. Familie Cicindelidae</source>. <publisher-name>R.Friedländer und Sohn</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>, <lpage>422</lpage>pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Apfelbeck</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1907</year>)<article-title> koleopterologische Ergebnisse der mit Subvention der Kaiserlichen Akademie der Wissenschaften in Wien im Frühjahr 1905 ausgeführten Forschungsreise nach Albanien und Montenegro.</article-title> <source>Sitzungsberichte der Kaiserlichen Akademie der Wissenschaften in Wien, Mathematisch-naturwissenschaftliche Klass (AbtI)</source> <volume>116</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>-<lpage>506</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Tourism impairs tiger beetle (Cicindelidae) populations – a case study in a Mediterranean beach habitat.</article-title> <source>Journal of Insect Conservation</source> <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>-<lpage>206</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10841-005-6609-9" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1007/s10841-005-6609-9</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Avgin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Özdikmen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Check-list of tiger beetles of Turkey with review of distribution and biogeography (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Munis Entomology and Zoology</source> <volume>2</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blonden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aronson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> The Mediterranean Region: Biological Diversity through Space and Time</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>, <lpage>328</lpage>pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998a</year>)<article-title> Spatial modelling of butterfly species richness using tiger beetles (Cicindelidae) as bioindicator taxon.</article-title> <source>Ecological Applications</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>531</fpage>-<lpage>543</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1890/1051-0761(1998)008[0531:SMOBSR]2.0.CO;2" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1890/1051-0761(1998)008[0531:SMOBSR]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998b</year>)<article-title> The effectc of scale and sample size on the accuracy of spatial predictions of tiger beetle (Cicindelidae) species richness.</article-title> <source>Ecography</source> <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>401</fpage>-<lpage>414</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-0587.1998.tb00405.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.1600-0587.1998.tb00405.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassola</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> The Cicindelidae of Italy.</article-title> <source>Cicindela</source> <volume>2</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassola</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>)<article-title> Etudes sur les Cicindelides. VI. Contribution a la connaissance des Cicindelides du Maroc (Coleoptera Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Société de Sciences Naturelles et Physiques du Maroc</source> <volume>53</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>253</fpage>-<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassola</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Studies on tiger beetles. CVII. The cicindelid fauna of Anatolia: faunistics and biogeography (Coleoptera, Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Biogeographia</source> <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>276</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassola</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaskuła</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Material to the knowledge of the tiger beetles of Romania (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Polskie Pismo Entomologiczne</source> <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>214</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassola</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Global patterns of tiger beetle species richness (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae): their use in conservation planning.</article-title> <source>Biological Conservation</source> <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>-<lpage>208</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0006-3207(00)00034-3" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/S0006-3207(00)00034-3</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Crnobrnja-Isailovic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Cross-section of a refugium: genetic diversity of amphibian and reptile populations in the Balkans</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Phylogeography of Southern European Refugia</source>. <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Davy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Human modification of European salt marshes</source>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Silliman</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertness</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grosholz</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Human impact on salt marshes – a global perspective</source>. <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Berkeley-Los Angeles-London</publisher-loc>, <fpage>311</fpage>–<lpage>336</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Deltshev</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> A faunistic and zoogeographical review of the spiders (Araneae) of the Balkan Peninsula.</article-title> <source>Journal of Arachnology</source> <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>261</lpage>.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Deltshev</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> The endemic spiders (Araneae) of the Balkan Peninsula</article-title>. <source>Ekológia</source> <volume>19</volume>, Supl. 3: <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Deltshew</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> A zoogeographical review of spiders of the Balkan Peninsula</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kryštufek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Balkan biodiversity: pattern and process in the European hotspot</source>. <publisher-name>Kluwer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>, <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkema</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Saltmarshes in Europe</article-title>. <source>Nature and Environment Series</source> <volume>30</volume>. <publisher-name>Council of Europe</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Strasbourg</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Directive 1992/43/EEC on the Conservation of natural habitats and of wild fauna and flora.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Directive 2000/60/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 October 2000 establishing a framework for Community action in the field of water policy.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Džukić</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalezić</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> The biodiversity of amphibians and reptiles in the Balkan Peninsula</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kryštufek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Balkan biodiversity: pattern and process in the European hotspot</source>. <publisher-name>Kluwer</publisher-name>, <source>Dordrecht</source>, <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fauna Europaea Web</surname><given-names>Service</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<source> Fauna Europaea version 1.1</source>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.faunaeur.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.faunaeur.org</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Franzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Verbreitung und Lebensräume der Sandlaufkäfer der Peloponnes-Halbinsel, Griechenland (Coleoptera, Cicindelidae)</article-title>. <source>Nachrichtenblatt der Byerischen Entomologen</source> <volume>55</volume> (<issue>3/4</issue>): <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Freitag</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> Reclassification, phylogeny and zoogeography of the Australian species of <italic>Cicindela</italic> (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Zoology (Supplementary Series)</source> <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganeshaiah</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belavadi</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> Habitat segregation in four species of adult tiger beetles (Coleoptera; Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Ecological Entomology</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2311.1986.tb00289.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.1365-2311.1986.tb00289.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guéorguiev</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> Annotated catalogue of the carabid beetles of Albania (Coleoptera: Carabidae)</source>. <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Sofia-Moscow</publisher-loc>, <fpage>243</fpage>pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guéorguiev VB</surname><given-names>Guéorguiev BV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<source> Catalogue of the ground beetles of Bulgaria (Coleoptera: Carabidae)</source>. <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>, <source>Sofia-Moscow</source>, <fpage>279</fpage>pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadley</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knisley</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> Water relations of tiger beetle larvae (<italic>Cicindela marutha</italic>): correlations with habitat microclimate and burrowing activity.</article-title> <source>Journal of Arid Environments</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>-<lpage>197</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Some genetic consequences of ice ages, and their role in divergence and speciation.</article-title> <source>Biological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>-<lpage>276</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Post-glacial re-colonization of European biota.</article-title> <source>Biological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>112</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.1111/j.1095-8312.1999.tb01160.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:doi:10.1111/j.1095-8312.1999.tb01160.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roeschke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1891</year>)<article-title> Bestimmungs-Tabelen der europäischen Coleopteren. XXIII. Heft. Enthaltend die Familie der Cicindelidae</article-title>. <source>Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift</source>, Biheft i-ix, <lpage>199</lpage>pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaccard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1902</year>)<article-title> Lois de distribution florale dans la zone alpine</article-title>. <source>Bull. Soc. Vaudoise Sci. Nat.</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>130</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaskuła</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007a</year>)<article-title> Remarks on distribution and diversity of the tiger beetle fauna (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae) of Albania.</article-title> <source>Fragmenta Faunistica</source> <volume>50</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaskuła</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007b</year>)<article-title> Furthern records of tiger beetles from Romania (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Cicindela</source> <volume>39</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaskuła</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>in prep.</year>)<source> Catalogue of tiger beetles of the Balkan Peninsula.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaskuła</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peśić</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavicević</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Remarks on distribution and diversity of the tiger beetle fauna of Montenegro (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Fragmenta Funistica</source> <volume>4</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaskuła</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rewicz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janusz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>in prep.</year>)<source> Notes on tiger beetles of Greece (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae).</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenyeres</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Racz</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varga</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Endemism hot spots, core areas and disjunctions in European Orthoptera</article-title>. <source>Acta zoologica cracoviensia</source> <volume>52B</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>): <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Knisley</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Effects of habitat change from ecological succession and human impact on tiger beetles.</article-title> <source>Virginia Journal of Science</source> <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>134</fpage>-<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Knisley</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<article-title> The function of turret building behaviour in the larval tiger beetle, <italic>Cicindela willistoni</italic> (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Ecological Entomology</source> <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>401</fpage>-<lpage>410</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2311.1981.tb00631.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.1365-2311.1981.tb00631.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Knisley</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Biosystematics of larval tiger beetles of the Sulphur Springs Valley, Arizona.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the American Entomological Society</source> <volume>110</volume>:<fpage>465</fpage>-<lpage>551</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B44"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kryštufek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> A quantitative assessment of Balkan mammal diversity</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kryštufek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Balkan biodiversity: pattern and process in the European hotspot</source>. <publisher-name>Kluwer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>, <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B45"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kryštufek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Patterns and Process in Balkan Biodiversity – an overview</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kryctufek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Balkan Biodiversity: Pattern and Process in the European Hotspot</source>. <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>, <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>217</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B46"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lisa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Le <italic>Cicindela</italic> d’Italia</article-title>. <source>Revue de l’Association Roussillonnaise d’Entomologie</source>, Supl. 1: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B47"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>López</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Rosa</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Descripción de <italic>Cephalota</italic> (<italic>Taenidia</italic>) <italic>dulcynea</italic> sp. n. de la Península Ibérica (Coleoptera, Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Boletin Sociedad Entomólogica Aragonesa</source> <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>-<lpage>170</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B48"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittermeier</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittermeier</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Fonseca</surname><given-names>GAB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennifer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Biodiversity hotspots for conservation priorities.</article-title> <source>Nature</source> <volume>403</volume>:<fpage>853</fpage>-<lpage>858</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/35002501" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1038/35002501</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B49"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> The tiger beetles (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae) of the Tambopata Reserved Zone, Madre e Dios, Perú.</article-title> <source>Revista Peruana de Entomologia</source> <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B50"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> Biology of tiger beetles.</article-title> <source>Annual Review of Entomology</source> <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>147</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.en.33.010188.001011" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1146/annurev.en.33.010188.001011</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B51"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassola</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> World-wide species richness patterns of tiger beetles (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae): indicator taxon for biodiversity and conservation studies.</article-title> <source>Conservation Biology</source> <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>376</fpage>-<lpage>391</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1523-1739.1992.06030376.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1046/j.1523-1739.1992.06030376.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B52"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassola</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Are we doomed to repeat history? A model of the past using tiger beetles (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae) and conservation biology to anticipate the future.</article-title> <source>Journal of Insect Conservation</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.1007/s10841-006-9018-9" xlink:type="simple">doi:doi:10.1007/s10841-006-9018-9</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B53"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lederhouse</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Thermal ecology and the structure of an assemblage of adult tiger beetles (Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Oikos</source> <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>-<lpage>255</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/3566008" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.2307/3566008</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B54"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mury</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> Character divergence and convergence among tiger beetles (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Ecology</source> <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>557</fpage>-<lpage>566</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1936076" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.2307/1936076</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B55"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<source> Tiger beetles : the evolution, ecology and diversity of the cicindelids</source>. <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca and London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>333</lpage>pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B56"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Putchkov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matalin</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Subfamily Cicindelinae Latreille, 1802</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Löbl</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smetana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Catalogue of Palaearctic Coleoptera. V.1. Archeostemata – Myxophaga – Adephaga</source>. <publisher-name>Apollo Books</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Strenstrup</publisher-loc>, <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>118</lpage>.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B57"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kryštufek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastwood</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> The physical geography of the Balkans and nomenclature of place names</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kryštufek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Balkan biodiversity: pattern and process in the European hotspot</source>. <publisher-name>Kluwer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>, <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B58"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Reitter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1881</year>)<article-title> Neue und seltere Coleopteren, im Jahre 1880 in Süddalmatien und Montenegro gesammelt und beschrieben.</article-title> <source>Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift</source> <volume>25</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>181</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B59"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrera</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> A test for adequacy of bioindicator taxa: are tiger beetles (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae) appropriate indicators for monitoring the degradation of tropical forests in Venezuela?</article-title> <source>Biological Conservation</source> <volume>83</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0006-3207(97)00017-7" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/S0006-3207(97)00017-7</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B60"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Saveljić</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Eco-guide to lagoon ecosystems of Montenegro.</article-title> <source>Tra Terra e Mare</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>119</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B61"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadley</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Microhabitat segregation and physiological differences in co-occurring tiger beetle species, <italic>Cicindela oregona</italic> and <italic>Cicindela tranquebarica</italic>.</article-title> <source>Oecologia</source> <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>-<lpage>370</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF00385252" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1007/BF00385252</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B62"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Plan evolution in the Mediterranean</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <lpage>293</lpage>pp. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780198515340.001.0001" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1093/acprof:oso/9780198515340.001.0001</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B63"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Udvardy</surname><given-names>MDF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>)<source> A classification of the biogeographical provinces of the world.</source> <publisher-name>IUCN Occasional Paper No.18 International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources.</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>4</publisher-loc> <lpage>9</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B64"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigna Taglianti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Audisio</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biondi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bologna</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpaneto</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Biase</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fattorini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piattella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sindaco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zapparoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> A proposal for a chorotype classification of the Near East fauna, in the framework of the Western Plearctic region.</article-title> <source>Biogeographia</source> <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B65"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Current perspective in phylogeography and the significance of South European refugia in the creation and maintenance of European biodiversity</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Phylogeography of Southern European Refugia</source>. <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>357</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>