<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.130.1487</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new, enigmatic family for new genus and species of Polyneoptera from the Upper Permian of Russia</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Gorochov</surname>
                        <given-names>Andrej V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"></xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:420774EA-BF2B-4562-A3B1-2A621B3383EC</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">Zoological Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences, St Petersburg 199034, Russia</aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Andrej V. Gorochov (<email xlink:type="simple">orthopt@zin.ru</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: D. Shcherbakov</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>130</issue>
            <fpage>131</fpage>
            <lpage>136</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>6</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>1</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Andrej V. Gorochov</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:415731F9-B7B5-4A2A-889D-2D2453A4B697</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Alexarasniidae</tp:taxon-name> <bold>fam. n.</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alexarasnia rossica</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>gen. et sp. n.</bold> are described from the Upper Permian of European Russia. Systematic position of this enigmatic family within the infraclass <tp:taxon-name>Polyneoptera</tp:taxon-name> is unclear.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>new taxa</kwd>
                <kwd>possible Polyneoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Alexarasnia</kwd>
                <kwd>Alexarasniidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Russia</kwd>
                <kwd>Upper Permian</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Among numerous fossil insects collected from the Upper Permian locality Isady (European Russia), there are two wings with an unusual venation which does not allow me to include these fossils in any known order of the subclass Pterygota. One of these wings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2</xref>) is not deformed and has the partly parallel longitudinal venation. Wings with such venation are aerodynamically unfit for flight, therefore parallel venation may be developed only in forewings which are used as tegmina or elytra for the protection of hind wings during rest. The main organs of flight in insects with such forewings are the hind wings, and all these insects belong to <!--PageBreak-->the order <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name> or to the infraclass <tp:taxon-name>Polyneoptera</tp:taxon-name> (= orthopteroid insects). The above-mentioned Upper Permian wings are with the well-developed venation including crossveins, i. e., they were clearly not as sclerotized or leathery as elytra in <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>. So, it is most probable that these wings are tegmina belonging to <tp:taxon-name>Polyneoptera</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematic Paleontology">
            <title>Systematic Paleontology</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Family</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Alexarasniidae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D6A2D4C4-6E69-4450-B12F-2488A6D9B6B7</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Alexarasniidae</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Gorochov</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">fam. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type genus">
                    <title>Type genus.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alexarasnia</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Composition">
                    <title>Composition.</title>
                    <p>Only the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alexarasnia</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Tegmen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">4</xref>) differs from that of <tp:taxon-name>Titanoptera</tp:taxon-name>, majority representatives of <tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name>, and Paleozoic and Triassic <tp:taxon-name>Phasmatoptera</tp:taxon-name> in the absence of precostal area (presence of this area is a synapomorphy of all these orders). From the other representatives of two latter orders, this family differs in the reduction of Sc branches in the tegmen and/or clearly more numerous longitudinal tegminal veins (CuA has six or more branches in <tp:taxon-name>Alexarasniidae</tp:taxon-name> and four or less branches in all the other representatives of <tp:taxon-name>Phasmatoptera</tp:taxon-name>). Tegminal venation of the new family is distinguished from that of all the other orders of <tp:taxon-name>Polyneoptera</tp:taxon-name> by the partly parallel longitudinal veins in combination with the following characters: straight CuP, very narrow radial and interradial areas, and reduction of branches of RA and RS (from <tp:taxon-name>Dictyoptera</tp:taxon-name>); reduction of branches of Sc and/or RS, partial fusion of distal parts of some longitudinal veins with formation of long loop-like cells along anal edge of tegmen, and presence of intercalary veins between majority of longitudinal veins (from Grylloblattida as well as from the families <tp:taxon-name>Lemmatophoridae</tp:taxon-name> Sellards, 1909 and <tp:taxon-name>Atactophlebiidae</tp:taxon-name> Martynov, 1930 possibly belonging to the extinct order Eoblattida; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Gorochov 2004</xref>); the latter characters as well as distal part of Sc not fused with RA (from <tp:taxon-name>Plecoptera</tp:taxon-name> and the other taxa of Eoblattida); tegmen not leathery with well-developed venation (from <tp:taxon-name>Dermaptera</tp:taxon-name>), and distinctly more numerous longitudinal veins (from <tp:taxon-name>Embioptera</tp:taxon-name>). Parallel venation of the tegmen is also present in the enigmatic family <tp:taxon-name>Chresmodidae</tp:taxon-name> Handlirsch, 1906 belonging to an unknown order of <tp:taxon-name>Polyneoptera</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Delclòs et al 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Zhang et al 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">b</xref>); <tp:taxon-name>Alexarasniidae</tp:taxon-name> is distinguished from it by the distal half of tegminal CuP situated not parallel to the anal tegminal edge and more numerous branches of CuA in tegmen (6–9 instead of 3–4).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–2.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alexarasnia rossica</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. et sp. n., tegmen, holotype PIN 3840/63 (part) <bold>1</bold> scheme of venation <bold>2</bold> photograph of fossil. Scale bar 5 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-130-131-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Alexarasnia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E0774B66-F8F3-4BB8-AEF6-648EE189F4A6</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Alexarasnia</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Gorochov</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                    <title>Type species.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Alexarasnia rossica</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Tegmen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2</xref>) moderately narrow, with parallel Sc, RA, RS, branches of MA and MP+CuA1, and short distal part of CuA2; all areas between longitudinal veins more or less narrow; majority of them with intercalary veins; Sc slightly concave, without branches and with apex situated near middle part of costal edge; R+RA slightly convex, but all longitudinal veins between this vein and CuP neutral; R and MA with proximal bifurcation situated in proximal part of tegmen; RA and RS probably simple (single); MA with only two branches in proximal and middle parts of tegmen; proximal part of MP before anastomosis with CuA1 indistinct; MP+CuA1 with four branches as minimum; CuA2 with two branches forming cell-like structure looking as a result of fusion of their distal parts; CuP concave (area near this vein with distinctly concave fold shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref> by dotted line), oblique and straight, but with small distal part probably looking as a result of its fusion with CuA2; 1A hardly <!--PageBreak-->convex, similar to CuP in shape; 2A neutral, looking as a single, oblique, and straight vein (its branches somewhat similar to crossveins); true crossveins simple and sparse.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 3–4.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Alexarasniidae</tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. indet., tegmen, specimen PIN 3840/1232 (part) <bold>3</bold> scheme of venation, <bold>4</bold> photograph of fossil. Scale bar 5 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-130-131-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Included species">
                    <title>Included species.</title>
                    <p>Only the type species.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The genus is named in honor of the famous Russian paleoentomologist Prof. Alexandr P. Rasnitsyn.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Alexarasnia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">rossica</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5938A644-1656-4685-80B9-27278B946A4C</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Alexarasnia_rossica</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Gorochov</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype">
                    <title>Holotype.</title>
                    <p>PIN (Paleontological Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscow) 3840/63, part and counterpart of imprint of tegmen (sex unknown) with indistinctly preserved distal area; Russia, Vologda Region, Velikij Ustyug District, left bank of Sukhona River near Isady Village (locality “Isady”); Upper Permian (Tatarian), Severodvinian Stage.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Tegmen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2</xref>) with all veins more or less dark; membranes between them slightly darkened, but with somewhat lighter subcostal area; proximal bifurcation of MP+CuA1 and that of CuA2 situated rather far distad from proximal bifurcation of R. Length of tegmen 12 mm.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific epithet is adapted from “Rossia” (Latin for Russia).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Another tegmen from the same locality (PIN 3840/1232; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 3, 4</xref>) has the similar size, coloration of veins, and type of venation. However this fossil is deformed (with the middle part contracted in costal-anal direction), and as a possible result of this deformation, its venation looks less parallel than it might be prior to deformation. Moreover, its MP+CuA1 has six branches (probably more numerous than in holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alexarasnia rossica</tp:taxon-name></italic>), proximal bifurcation of MP+CuA1 situated near proximal bifurcation of R (compare with the description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alexarasnia rossica</tp:taxon-name></italic>, above), CuA2 shorter, and area between 1A and 2A remarkably wider (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">3</xref>). These differences do not allow me to determine this wing more exactly, because it may belong to another sex of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alexarasnia rossica</tp:taxon-name></italic>, to another species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alexarasnia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, or to another genus of <tp:taxon-name>Alexarasniidae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p>Position of the new family within <tp:taxon-name>Polyneoptera</tp:taxon-name> is unclear. However, its tegminal venation looks more or less intermediate between the enigmatic Jurassic-Cretaceous water-striding family <tp:taxon-name>Chresmodidae</tp:taxon-name> [its very parallel tegminal venation was clearly figured by Delclòs et al (2008: Fig. 6); but in the same paper in figure 8, these authors figured the tegmen of <tp:taxon-name>Phasmatoptera</tp:taxon-name> from the superfamily <tp:taxon-name>Susumanioidea</tp:taxon-name> which was included mistakenly by them in <tp:taxon-name>Chresmodidae</tp:taxon-name>] and the Early and Middle Permian families <tp:taxon-name>Lemmatophoridae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Atactophlebiidae</tp:taxon-name> (possibly belonging to Eoblattida; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Gorochov 2004</xref>). The mode of life of these Permian families was probably also connected with water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Carpenter 1935</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Storozhenko 1998</xref>). In the latter publications, it was suggested that <tp:taxon-name>Lemmatophoridae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Carpenter 1935</xref>) and <tp:taxon-name>Atactophlebiidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Storozhenko 1998</xref>) had a primitive postembryonal development, with an increase in the number of tarsal segments. This ancient type of development is absent now in all polyneopterans, but such instability of tarsal composition might be one of the prerequisites for the additional increase in the number of tarsal segments in <tp:taxon-name>Chresmodidae</tp:taxon-name>. <tp:taxon-name>Alexarasniidae</tp:taxon-name> (especially unknown body fossils) may prove to be useful in understanding this adaptive process.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>The author thanks the colleagues from the Paleontological Institute in Moscow for collecting and loaning of these interesting fossils, Prof A.P. Rasnitsyn, Dr D.E. Shcherbakov and Dr D.S. Aristov from the same institute as well as Dr Peter Vršanský from the Geological Institute (Slovak Academy of Sciences) in Bratislava for the useful consultations. The present study is supported by the Presidium of the Russian Academy of Sciences (Program “Biosphere origin and evolution of geo-biological systems”).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Delclòs</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nel</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azar</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechly</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlop</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heads</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> The enigmatic Mesozoic insect taxon Chresmodidae (Polyneoptera): new palaeobiological and phylogenetic data, with the description of a new species from the Lower Cretaceous of Brazil.</article-title> <source>Neues Jahrbuch für Geologie und Paläontologie - Abhandlungen </source> <volume>247</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>353</fpage>-<lpage>381</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname> <given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1935</year>)<article-title> The Lower Permian insects of Kansas. Pt. 7. The order Protoperlaria.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Science </source> <volume>70</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>103</fpage>-<lpage>146</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/20023126">10.2307/20023126</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorochov</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Primitive Titanoptera and early evolution of Polyneoptera. Meetings in memory of N. A.</article-title> <source>Cholodkovsky </source> <volume>57</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>54</lpage>. [in Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Storozhenko</surname> <given-names>SYu</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<source> Systematics, phylogeny and evolution of the grylloblattids (Insecta: Grylloblattida). Vladivostok, Dal’nauka. 207 pp.</source> [in Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>X-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname> <given-names>Ch-K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008a</year>)<article-title> A new genus and species of Chresmodidae (Insecta: Gryllones) from Upper Jurassic-Lower Cretaceous of Yixian Formation, Inner Mongolia, China.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1702</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>X-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname> <given-names>Ch-K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008b</year>)<article-title> A water-skiing chresmodid from the Middle Jurassic in Daohugou, Inner Mongolia, China (Polyneoptera: Orthopterida).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1762</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>