<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.294.4846</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Description and scanning electron microscopic observation of a new species of the genus 
                    <italic>Polycopetta</italic> (Crustacea, Ostracoda, Cladocopina) from an interstitial habitat in Japan</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Tanaka</surname>
                        <given-names>Hayato</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:85DF11C9-6ECA-42E5-B55D-FACE65C5D1D3</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Tsukagoshi</surname>
                        <given-names>Akira</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:60EA2167-A731-407D-9295-B6A8CA0C701B</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Institute of Geoscience, Faculty of Science, Shizuoka University, Oya 836, Suruga-ku, Shizuoka City, Shizuoka Prefecture, 422-8529, Japan
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Hayato Tanaka (<email xlink:type="simple">Cladocopina@gmail.com</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: R. F. Maddocks</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>294</issue>
            <fpage>75</fpage>
            <lpage>91</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>10</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>13</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2013</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Hayato Tanaka, Akira Tsukagoshi</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:56902C37-22F2-4B8B-A96B-7FCE840582E0</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new species of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chavtur, 1981, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> is described from the interstitial environment of Mihomasaki Beach in Japan. These observations showed some morphological peculiarities of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. compared with its congeners; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta monneroni</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chavtur, 1979, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta curva</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chavtur, 1979, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta bransfieldensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Hartmann, 1987), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta pax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kornicker and Harrison-Nelson, 2005. Three characteristics are described for the first time: (1) a seta with serrated tip on the male antennula, (2) the endopodite of the fifth limb consisting of two podomeres, (3) the long spermatozoa in the male posterior body. More detailed observations of the type species are needed in order to update the generic diagnosis.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Endopodite of fifth limb</kwd>
                <kwd>long spermatozoa</kwd>
                <kwd>male antennula</kwd>
                <kwd>pore systems</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Polycopetta</italic>
<!--PageBreak--></kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, belonging to the Suborder <tp:taxon-name>Cladocopina</tp:taxon-name>, was originally proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Chavtur (1979)</xref>, but the name of this genus could not be used because the type species had not been designated. Subsequently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Chavtur (1981)</xref> assigned the type species and gave a diagnosis for the genus, after which <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chavtur, 1981 was accepted as a valid name. The generic diagnosis of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta</tp:taxon-name></italic> based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Chavtur (1981)</xref> is as follows: Carapace oval and concave anteriorly; frontal organ consists of one seta split at distal half; third podomere of male antennula with two ventral setae; male antennal endopodite bearing dorsal outgrowth and hook-like protrusion, and terminal podomere in both sexes with ventral protuberance; basis of fifth limb with one internal and three external setae, and exopodite with four terminal setae; outgrowth between the furcal lamellae rounded and armed with spines; male left furcal lamella with six claws.</p>
            <p>Thus far four species have been described in this genus: the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta monneroni</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chavtur, 1979, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta curva</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chavtur, 1979, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta bransfieldensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Hartmann, 1987) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta pax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kornicker &amp; Harrison-Nelson, 2005. Three species are found in the sediment of the seafloor at depths of 60 to 265m, except for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta pax</tp:taxon-name></italic>. This species has been reported from a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Riftia pachyptila</tp:taxon-name></italic> (giant tube worm) aggregation at a depth of 2500m.</p>
            <p>During the faunal survey along the Pacific coast in Japan, a species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta</tp:taxon-name></italic> was found in interstitial habitats for the first time. In the present paper, the authors describe this new species, including observations of the detailed structure of the carapace and appendages, obtained by using a scanning electron microscope (SEM).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods">
            <title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>Sand material was collected from the Mihomasaki beach, Shizuoka City, Shizuoka Prefecture, Japan (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) at 40 cm below the shoreline sand surface, at low tide. The samples were washed five times in a bucket with fresh water, and the top layer of water was strained through nets of 40 μm mesh size. The living specimens were picked out from the remaining deposits under a stereo-binocular microscope (SZH 10, OLYMPUS). The observed specimens were fixed in 8% formalin with neutral buffer (hexamethylenetetramine), and preserved in 80% ethanol at room temperature. The soft parts and valves were dissected with fine needles and mounted in Neo-Shigaral (Shiga Konchu Fukyusha, Tokyo, Japan), or glycerine, on glass slides under a stereo-binocular microscope, and then observed and sketched using a transmitted-light binocular microscope (BX 50, OLYMPUS) with a differential interference contrast system and a camera Lucida. The valves and soft parts, treated with the t-butyl alcohol freeze-drying method, were also coated with osmium and observed by SEM (JSM-5600LV, JEOL).</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Sampling site. <bold>A</bold> map of Japan <bold>B</bold> type locality of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <p>The type series was deposited in the collection of the Shizuoka University Museum, identified by registration numbers with prefix SUM-CO.</p>
            <!--PageBreak-->
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <sec sec-type="Order Halocyprida Dana, 1853">
                <title>Order <tp:taxon-name>Halocyprida</tp:taxon-name> Dana, 1853
                Suborder <tp:taxon-name>Cladocopina</tp:taxon-name> Sars, 1866
                Family <tp:taxon-name>Polycopidae</tp:taxon-name> Sars, 1866
                Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chavtur, 1981</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Polycopetta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2247D429-CEB0-4BA8-BD51-D9FF89F995FD</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Polycopetta_quadrispinata</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type series">
                        <title>Type series.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: adult male (SUM-CO-2093), right valve length 357 μm, height 301 μm, left valve length 358 μm, height 288 μm, soft parts mounted on a slide and valves preserved in a cardboard cell slide, Paratypes: 10 adult males (SUM-CO-2094–2103) and 11 adult females (SUM-CO-2104–2114). All specimens were collected on 24 June 2009.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality">
                        <title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p>The holotype specimen was collected from Mihomasaki beach, Shizuoka City, Shizuoka Prefecture, along the Pacific coast of central Japan, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">35°01'13&quot;N, 138°31'20&quot;E</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>); in an interstitial environment at 40 cm below the shoreline sand surface. The substrate consisted mainly of clastic very coarse sand (median grain size is about 1.5 mm).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Carapace oval and anteriorly concave in lateral view. Carapace peripheral surface covered with shallow pits, except on posterodorsal area, and with scale-like sculptures in anterior area. Anterior end of both valves with one conspicuous spine. Posteroventral margin of right valve with four conspicuous spines in both sexes. In each valve, 73 simple pores, 23 pore systems involving a circular depression and two <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->contiguous pore systems. Male second podomere of the antennula with one ventral seta, third podomere with one ventral seta with serrated tip. Spermatozoa length approximately 750 μm.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description of adult male.</title>
                        <p>Carapace (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A–E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Carapace oval and anteriorly concave in lateral view. Yellowish white colour in living individuals. Carapace periphery surface covered with shallow pits except on posterodorsal area, and with scale-like sculptures on anterior area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A, B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Anterior end of both valves with one conspicuous spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A, B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). Mid-anterior to posteroventral margin covered with serration and fringe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A, B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Posteroventral margin of right valve with four conspicuous spines and fringe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A, B</xref>) and of left valve with fine serrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). In each valve, 73 simple pores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C, D</xref>), 23 pore systems <!--PageBreak-->involving a circular depression with bifurcated seta (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>) and two contiguous double pore systems with bifurcated seta (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>). Adductor muscle scar consisting of three closely spaced scars (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5E</xref>). Marginal infold of each valve developed along anterior to posteroventral margins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2C, D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B, C, J–L</xref>). Along hinge margin of right valve: anterodorsal bar and groove (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>), anterior socket (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6E</xref>), median bar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6F</xref>), posterior socket (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6G</xref>), and posteroventral groove (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6D, H</xref>). Along hinge margin of left valve: anterodorsal bar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6I</xref>), anterior knob (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6M</xref>), median bar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6N</xref>), posterior knob (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6O</xref>), and posterior bar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6P</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Frontal organ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8B</xref>). Spinous seta divided at mid-length. Distal half with long and proximal half with short setae, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8B</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Antennula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8C</xref>). Uniramous, four articulated podomeres. First podomere rectangular in shape and tapering distally, with setulae on dorsal margin, lateral surface and at ventrodistal end, respectively. Second podomere about four-fifths as long as first podomere, with one annulated setulous seta at dorsoproximal end, one simple seta on ventrodistal end (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8C</xref>), and setulae on dorsal margin, lateral surface, ventral middle margin and at ventrodistal end, respectively. Third podomere about one-fifth as long as first podomere, with one short simple seta at dorsodistal end and one seta <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->with serrations at ventrodistal end (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8C</xref>). Fourth podomere small, with four long setulous annulated setae.</p>
                        <p>Antenna (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7D, D'</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8D</xref>). Typically biramous, with exopodite and endopodite consisting of nine and three podomeres, respectively. Basis triangular and tapering distally. Exopodite: first podomere about one–third as long as basis; podomere lengths decreasing in size from second to eighth, each podomere with one long plumose annulated seta, respectively; ninth (distal-most) podomere very small, with one long annulated, one medium annulated and one short bare setae at distal end. Endopodite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7D, D'</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8D</xref>): first podomere about two-thirds as long as first podomere of exopodite; second podomere half as long as first podomere, with one setulous seta along dorsal <!--PageBreak-->margin, one clavate process at proximal middle end (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7D'</xref>) and five setae at distal end consisting of three long annulated, one medium annulated and one short annulated setulous. Third podomere one-fifth as long as first podomere, with one dorsal outgrowth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7D'</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8D</xref>), and two long spinous annulated, one long annulated and one short setulous annulated setae at distal end.</p>
                        <p>Upper lip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10A</xref>). Semicircular in lateral view, with fine setae on surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13A</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Mandibula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10B</xref>). Coxal endite with four teeth. Basis with four plumose annulated setae on ventral margin, and one plumose annulated seta at mid-lateral surface. Exopodite pear-shaped, distal end jagged, with thin setae, and one simple seta. Endopodite consisting of two podomeres. First podomere with three annulated plumose setae on ventral margin and two annulated long setulous setae at dorsodistal end. Second podomere very small, bearing two plumose setae at distal end.</p>
                        <p>Maxillula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10C, C', C&quot;</xref>). Precoxa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10C'</xref>) with seven annulated plumose setae and one stout setulous seta on ventral side. Coxa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10C&quot;</xref>) with two short and two medium plumose setae on lateral surface near ventroproximal margin, two short and two medium plumose setae on lateral surface of ventral middle margin. Basis rectangular, dorsally-convex in lateral view, with one medium and one long <!--PageBreak-->plumose setae on ventral margin, and setulae along ventral margin. First podomere of endopodite with one long plumose seta at ventrodistal end. Second podomere three-fourths as long as first podomere, with two long and one medium annulated setulous setae on ventrodistal area, one short annulated and one medium setulous annulated seta at dorsodistal end. Third podomere small, with 4 long annulated setulous setae. Exopodite with four tufts along dorsal margin, and nine annulated setae at distal end.</p>
                        <p>Fifth limb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>). Coxa bearing branchial plate (epipodite) with 15 long plumose setae, and four short setulous setae on dorsolateral area. Basis with three setulous and three plumose setae on dorsal and ventral margin, respectively. Endopodite consisting of two podomeres (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11</xref>). First podomere with one plumose seta. Second podomere rectangle, with one plumose seta. Exopodite with four setulous setae.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Furca (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 12A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13B</xref>). Furcal claws six and seven on left and right lamella, respectively, with row of setae on dorsal side.</p>
                        <p>Male copulatory organ and posterior body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 12A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13B–D</xref>). Arising from outer surface of body on left side of terminal trunk segment as long curved copulatory duct. <!--PageBreak-->Tuft of stout setae at ventral right side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13C</xref>). Posterior body including a lot of very long spermatozoa, approximately 750 μm long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13D</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description of adult female.</title>
                        <p>Mandibula, maxillula, fifth limbs, and upper lip similar to those of adult male.</p>
                        <p>Carapace (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2F–J</xref>). Carapace length and height larger than adult males.</p>
                        <p>Antennula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7C</xref>). Uniramus, four articulated podomeres. First podomere similar to that of adult male. Second podomere about four-fifths as long as first podomere, with one annulated setulous seta at dorsoproximal end, and setulae on dorsal margin, lateral surface, ventral middle margin and at ventrodistal end, respectively. Third podomere about one-fifth as long as first podomere, with one short simple seta at dorsodistal end. Fourth podomere small, with five long setulous annulated setae.</p>
                        <p>Antenna (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7E</xref>). Only second and third podomeres of endopodite different from those of adult male. Endopodite consisting of three podomeres. Second podomere half as long as first podomere, with one setulous seta along dorsal margin and five annulated setae at distal end. Third podomere one-fifth as long as first podomere with four annulated setae at distal end.</p>
                        <p>Furca (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12B</xref>). Each lamella with seven claws.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Dimensions">
                        <title>Dimensions.</title>
                        <p>See <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
                        <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
								<label>Table 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Dimensions of valves of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. from type locality.&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="2" colspan="2"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Length (μm)</bold></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Height (μm)</bold></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mean</bold></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Observed range</bold></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mean</bold></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Observed range</bold></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold></td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right valve</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">357</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">353–361</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">296</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">292–301</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left valve</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">356</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">353–364</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">290</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">288–294</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right valve</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">380</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">372–388</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">312</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">306–322</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left valve</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">381</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">373–389</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">308</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">302–316</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 2.</label>
                            <caption><p>SEM images of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. valves. <bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold> male paratype (SUM-CO-2095) <bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold> male, paratype (SUM-CO-2096) <bold>E</bold> male, paratype (SUM-CO-2097) <bold>F</bold> female, paratype (SUM-CO-2105) <bold>G</bold> female paratype (SUM-CO-2106) <bold>H</bold> and <bold>I</bold> female, paratype (SUM-CO-2107) <bold>J</bold> female, paratype (SUM-CO-2108). <bold>A</bold> right external lateral view <bold>B</bold> left external lateral view <bold>C</bold> right internal lateral view <bold>D</bold> left internal lateral view <bold>E</bold> dorsal view <bold>F</bold> right external lateral view <bold>G</bold> left external lateral view <bold>H</bold> right internal lateral view <bold>I</bold> left internal lateral <bold>J</bold> dorsal view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 3.</label>
                            <caption><p>Valves of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Male, holotype (SUM-CO-2093). <bold>A</bold> right internal view <bold>B</bold> left internal view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 4.</label>
                            <caption><p>Distribution of pore systems and surface ornamentation of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. drawn from an SEM image. Male, paratype (SUM-CO-2095). <bold>A</bold> right external view <bold>B</bold> left external view. Solid circle, open circle and double circle indicate the positions of simple pores, pore systems involving a circular depression and contiguous pore systems, respectively.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 5.</label>
                            <caption><p>SEM images of the detailed structure of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. valves. <bold>A</bold> male, paratype (SUM-CO-2095) <bold>B–D</bold> male, paratype (SUM-CO-2098) <bold>E</bold> male, paratype (SUM-CO-2094). <bold>A</bold> four spines at posteroventral margin of right valve <bold>B</bold> spines and fringe at posteroventral margin of right valve <bold>C</bold> pore system with circular depression <bold>D</bold> contiguous pore system <bold>E</bold> internal lateral view of adductor muscle scars of right valve. Arrowheads indicate simple pores.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 6.</label>
                            <caption><p>SEM images of internal view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. valves. Male, paratype (SUM-CO-2096). <bold>A–H</bold> right valve <bold>I–P</bold> left valve <bold>A</bold> anterodorsal bar and groove <bold>B</bold> anterior area of marginal infold <bold>C</bold> anteroventral area of marginal infold <bold>D</bold> posteroventral area of marginal infold <bold>E</bold> anterior socket of hinge structure <bold>F</bold> median bar of hinge structure <bold>G</bold> posterior socket of hinge structure <bold>H</bold> posteroventral groove <bold>I</bold> anterodorsal bar <bold>J</bold> anterior area of marginal infold <bold>K</bold> anteroventral area of marginal infold <bold>L</bold> posteroventral area of marginal infold <bold>M</bold> anterior knob of hinge structure <bold>N</bold> median bar of hinge structure <bold>O</bold> posterior knob of hinge structure <bold>P</bold> posterior bar. Scale bars indicate 20 μm.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 7.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold> and <bold>D</bold> male, holotype (SUM-CO-2093) <bold>C</bold> and <bold>E</bold> female, paratype (SUM-CO-2104). <bold>A</bold> frontal organ <bold>B</bold> male antennula <bold>C</bold> female antennula <bold>D</bold> male antenna <bold>D</bold>′ endopodite of male antenna without all setae <bold>E</bold> female antenna except the exopodite. Abbreviations: <bold>ba</bold> basis <bold>en</bold> endopodite <bold>ex</bold> exopodite.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 8.</label>
                            <caption><p>SEM images of male soft parts of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A</bold> left lateral view of whole body with left valve removed <bold>B</bold> left lateral view of frontal organ <bold>C</bold> right lateral view of distal area of antennula <bold>D</bold> left lateral view of antennal endopodite. Arrow indicates a seta with serrations at ventrodistal end. Arrowhead indicates a dorsal outgrowth of male antennal endopodite. Abbreviations: <bold>1an</bold> antennula <bold>2an</bold> antenna <bold>en</bold> endopodite <bold>fif</bold> fifth limb <bold>fo</bold> frontal organ <bold>lf</bold> left furcal lamella <bold>md</bold> mandibula <bold>mx</bold> maxillula.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 9.</label>
                            <caption><p>Light micrograph of male antennula of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Arrow indicates seta with serrations at ventrodistal end.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 10.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A</bold> and <bold>D</bold> male, paratype (SUM-CO-2094) <bold>B</bold> and <bold>C</bold> male, holotype (SUM-CO-2093). <bold>A</bold> right lateral view of upper lip <bold>B</bold> mandibula <bold>C</bold> maxillula <bold>C</bold>′precoxa of maxillula except setulae on setae <bold>C</bold>&quot; coxa of maxillula except setulae on setae <bold>D</bold> fifth limb. Arrowheads indicate tip of precoxal setae of maxillula. Abbreviations: <bold>ba</bold> basis <bold>cx</bold> coxa <bold>en</bold> endopodite <bold>ex</bold> exopodite <bold>pcx</bold> precoxa.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 11.</label>
                            <caption><p>SEM images of male fifth limb of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A</bold> left lateral view <bold>B</bold> enlarged view of figure <bold>11A</bold>. Abbreviations: <bold>ba</bold> basis <bold>cx</bold> coxa <bold>en</bold> endopodite <bold>ex</bold> exopodite <bold>epi</bold> epipodite.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F12" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 12.</label>
                            <caption><p>Posterior body of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A</bold> male, holotype (SUM-CO-2093) <bold>B</bold> female, paratype (SUM-CO-2106). Arrowhead indicates the tuft of stout setae. Abbreviations: <bold>cd</bold> copulatory duct <bold>spe</bold> spermatozoa.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g012.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F13" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 13.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. SEM images of male soft parts of. <bold>A</bold> right lateral view of upper lip <bold>B</bold> left lateral view of posterior body, furcal lamellae and copulatory organ <bold>C</bold> right lateral view of the tuft of stout setae <bold>D</bold> fascicle of spermatozoa. Arrowhead indicates the tuft of stout setae. Abbreviations: <bold>cd</bold> copulatory duct <bold>lf</bold> left furcal lamella <bold>spe</bold> spermatozoa <bold>ul</bold> upper lip.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-294-075-g013.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Occurrence">
                        <title>Occurrence.</title>
                        <p>So far known only from type locality.</p>
                        <p><bold>Etymology.</bold> Specific name <italic>quadrispinata</italic>, an adjective derived from the Latin prefix <italic>quadri</italic>- (four) and Latin adjective <italic>spinatus</italic> (spiny), referring to the four spines on the posteroventral margin of the right valve in both sexes.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Existing species of Polycopetta are known from only a few specimens in seafloor sediment and deep sea tube worm aggregations. This study is the first report of a species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the interstitial environment. Because 21 specimens were obtained, the authors could observe the details of their morphologies.</p>
            <p>Four species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta</tp:taxon-name></italic> have been described: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta monneroni</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta curva</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta bransfieldensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta pax</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta curva</tp:taxon-name></italic> are similar to each other; i.e. both species have scale-like sculpture on the anterior carapace surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A, B</xref>), one clavate process at proximal middle end of second podomere of male antennal endo<!--PageBreak-->podite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8D</xref>), and four teeth as coxal endites of mandibula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10B</xref>). They are distinguished by the number of spines at posteroventral margin of right valve, four for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>) and one for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta curva</tp:taxon-name></italic>, respectively. This new species is distinguishable from each of the other three species by the number of coxal teeth (endites) of the mandibula (two in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta monneroni</tp:taxon-name></italic> vs four (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10B</xref>) in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> the carapace surface ornamentation (absent in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta bransfieldensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> vs scale-like sculpture and pits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A, B</xref>) in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> and the number of adductor muscle scars (six in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta pax</tp:taxon-name></italic> vs three (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5E</xref>) in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> This new species also differs from all previously described species by details of the chaetotaxy of the antennula, antenna, maxillula and fifth limb (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
            <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
								<label>Table 2.</label>
                <caption><p>Interspecific morphological comparison of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The dashes indicate no information from original descriptions.&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Character</bold></th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta monneroni</tp:taxon-name></italic></bold></th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta curva</tp:taxon-name></italic></bold></th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta bransfieldensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></bold></th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta pax</tp:taxon-name></italic></bold></th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic></bold></th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Carapace</tp:taxon-name></italic>, length (μm)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">325–350</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">450</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">480–490</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">540</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">372–389</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height (μm)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">350</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">470</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">302–322</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height/Length (%)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79–84</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">number of spines at posteroventral margin of right valve</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6?</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mandible</tp:taxon-name></italic>, coxal endite</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 teeth</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 teeth</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 bifurcate teeth</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 teeth</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">shape of exopodite tip</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">flat</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">flat</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">jagged</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">flat</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">jagged</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Maxillula</tp:taxon-name></italic>, seta number on precoxa</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fifth limb</tp:taxon-name></italic>, podomere number of endopodite</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">seta number of epipodite</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Furca</tp:taxon-name></italic>, claw number (left-right)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7-7)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6?-7?)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7-7)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6?-6?)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7-7)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Carapace</tp:taxon-name></italic>, length (μm)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">450</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">490</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">353–364</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height (μm)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">350</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">288–301</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height/Length (%)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80–85</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Antennula</tp:taxon-name></italic>, seta with serrations at ventrodistal end</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">absent</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">absent</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">present</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Antenna</tp:taxon-name></italic>, shape of process on 2nd podomere of endopodite</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> distally tapered hook-like </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">distally expanded and rounded hook-like</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">clavate</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Furca</tp:taxon-name></italic>, claw number (left-right)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6-7)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6-7)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6-7)</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>Our observation shows some morphological peculiarities of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta quadrispinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. when compared with its congeners. First, the third podomere of male antennula bears one seta with serrations at the ventrodistal end (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8C</xref>). This seta <!--PageBreak-->has not been identified in the other species. Since this seta is only found in the male, itmust be related to sexual activity; however the function of this seta is unknown at the present time. Second, the endopodite of the fifth limb consists of two podomeres (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11B</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Kornicker and Harrison-Nelson (2005)</xref> stated that the podomere number is only one in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta pax</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Third, the long spermatozoa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 12A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13D</xref>) are described in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta</tp:taxon-name></italic> for the first time. The males have been known for three species (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta monneroni</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta curva</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycopetta bransfieldensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>), but there is no information about their spermatozoa. In the family <tp:taxon-name>Polycopidae</tp:taxon-name> the sperm length of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eupolycope dispar</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Müller, 1894) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polycope cancellea</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hartmann, 1954 have been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Hartmann 1955</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">1968</xref>). The length of the former species is 45 μm (carapace length is 300 μm), the latter is 15 μm (carapace length is 500 μm). The sperm length (750 μm) of the new species is extreme for this family. These characters are likely to be present in other incompletely described species. In future, more detailed observation of all of these species may be needed, in order to update the generic diagnosis.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>The authors are grateful to Vladimir Chavtur and Rosalie Maddocks for their help in significantly improving this manuscript. The authors also wish to thank the members of the Ostracod Laboratory, Shizuoka University, for their valuable suggestions and continuous encouragement. This study was partly funded by a Research Fellowship for Young Scientists (No. 236212) and a Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research (No. 19370034) from the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chavtur</surname> <given-names>VG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> New data on ostracodes of the Polycopidae Family (Ostracoda, Cladocopa) from the Far-Eastern Sea. Transactions of the Institute of Oceanology, Academy of Science of the USSR.</article-title> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>105</lpage>. [in Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chavtur</surname> <given-names>VG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<article-title> On the systematic position of the modern Ostracoda in the family Polycopidae (Ostracoda, Cladocopina). Transactions of the Institute of Oceanology, Academy of Science of the USSR.</article-title> <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>. [in Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1954</year>)<article-title> Neue Polycopidae (Ostracoda: Cladocopa) von europäischen Küsten.</article-title> <source>Kieler Meeresforschungen </source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>-<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1955</year>)<article-title> Zur Morphologie der Polycopiden.</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift für Wissenschaftliche Zoologie </source> <volume>158</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>248</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<source> Ostracoda (3. Lieferung). In: Gruner H-E, ed. Klassen und Ordnungen des Tierreichs. Band 5 (Arthropoda), Abteilung I (Crustacea), Buch 2, Teil IV (Ostracoda). Leipzig: Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft, 409–568.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Antarktische benthische Ostracoden 2. Auswertung der Fahrten der ‘Polarstern’ Ant. 3/2 und der Reisen der ‘Walther Herwig’ 68/1 und 2.2. Teil: Elephant Island und Bransfield Strasse.</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen aus dem Hamburgischen Zoologischen Museum und Institut </source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>-<lpage>156</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kornicker</surname> <given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison-Nelson</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Two new species of Ostracoda from hydrothermal vents of <italic>Riftia pachyptila</italic> aggregations on the East Pacific Rise (Halocypridina; Cladocopina). Zootaxa 1071: 19–38. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2005f/z01071p038f.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2005f/z01071p038f.pdf</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1894</year>)<article-title> Die Ostracoden des Golfes von Neapel und der angrenzenden Meeres-Abschnitte.</article-title> <source>Fauna und Flora des Golfes von Neapel und der angrenzenden Meeres-Abschnitte </source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>404</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>