<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.222.3618</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    <italic>Aphaereta ceratitivora</italic> sp. n. (Hymenoptera, Braconidae), a new parasitoid of 
                    <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic> (Wiedemann) (Diptera, Tephritidae) from the Azores
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Achterberg</surname>
                        <given-names>Kees van</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:D6374CF4-8F07-4FA8-8C55-9335FD19CECD</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Teixeira</surname>
                        <given-names>Tânia</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:8BB770EA-29BC-4449-8046-53B8A120C32A</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Oliveira</surname>
                        <given-names>Luísa</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:4B1D0C91-7B7D-4AE6-A164-C711810529C4</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Dept. Terrestrial Zoology, NCB Naturalis, Postbus 9517, 2300 RA Leiden, The Netherlands
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Departamento de Biologia, Universidade dos Açores, Rua da Mãe de Deus, 9501-801 Ponta Delgada, S. Miguel, Açores, Portugal
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>IBB-CBA, CIRN Departamento de Biologia, Universidade dos Açores, Rua da Mãe de Deus, 9501-801 Ponta Delgada, S. Miguel, Açores, Portugal
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Luísa Oliveira (<email xlink:type="simple">ziza@uac.pt</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Gavin Broad</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>18</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>222</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>9</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>7</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>30</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Kees van Achterberg, Tânia Teixeira, Luísa Oliveira</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:27FB9E17-9D93-4C07-93A3-B98BBD5BB7FB</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new gregarious larval-pupal endoparasitoid of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceratitis capitata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Wiedemann) (<tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Tephritidae</tp:taxon-name>) is described and illustrated: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta ceratitivora</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> (<tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Alysiinae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Alysiini</tp:taxon-name>).</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><italic>Aphaereta ceratitivora</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>Azores</kwd>
                <kwd>gregarious parasitoid</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>In recent years interest in the parasitoid <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name> has grown as a result of the increasing demand for biological methods for pest control and their possible use as natural enemies. The <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name> are the second largest family of this order, the major<!--PageBreak-->ity of species are primary parasitoids of immature stages of <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Sharkey 1993</xref>).</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceratitis capitata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Wiedemann, 1824) (<tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Tephritidae</tp:taxon-name>) or Mediterranean fruit fly (Medfly) is a pest that causes substantial economic losses in the Mediterranean fruit production due to their high dispersal ability and ecological plasticity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Liquido et al. 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Gillani et al. 2002</xref>). In Azores (Portugal) a survey was done to see if there were possible candidates for the control of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceratitis capitata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, before considering the introduction of exotic species, that can cause adverse effects on the native parasitoids and non-target species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Oliveira et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
            <p>From two parasitized pupae of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceratitis capitata</tp:taxon-name></italic> collected in São Miguel Island (Azores, Portugal) emerged in total 12 adult parasitoids, belonging to a new species of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Foerster, 1862 (<tp:taxon-name>Alysiinae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Alysiini</tp:taxon-name>). Six adult parasitoids emerged per pupa; rearing in the lab resulted in four parasitoids per host pupa at 20°C (the optimum temperature for development). The subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Alysiinae</tp:taxon-name>, with 2321 catalogued species worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Yu et al. 2012</xref>) has a prominent position within the <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name> family (van <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Achterberg 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Dolphin and Quicke 2001</xref>) and consists of the tribes <tp:taxon-name>Alysiini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Dacnusini</tp:taxon-name>. The species of this subfamily are endoparasitoids of dipterous larvae, with oviposition into the egg or the larva of the host and emergence from the host puparium. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Wharton (2002)</xref> used this character, along with the possession of exodont mandibles, to define the subfamily. Almost all <tp:taxon-name>Dacnusini</tp:taxon-name> are parasitoids of leaf- and stem-mining dipterans, usually <tp:taxon-name>Agromyzidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Wharton 2002</xref>), but <tp:taxon-name>Alysiini</tp:taxon-name> attacks a wide range of dipterous hosts from at least 20 different families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Wharton 1980</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Description">
            <title>Description</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Aphaereta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        (<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Aphaereta</tp:taxon-name-part>)
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">ceratitivora</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6AA4B4C3-1AD2-4453-B9F3-E63425D9302A</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Aphaereta_ceratitivora</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>van Achterberg &amp; Oliveira</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                    <title>Type material.</title>
                    <p>Holotype, ♀ (RMNH), “Portugal: Azores, Ponta Delgada, reared in lab., summer 2010, L. Oliviera, RMNH’11”, “ex <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceratitis capitata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Wied.)”. Paratypes: 19 ♀ + 20 ♂ (RMNH), with same label data; 10 ♀ + 3 ♂ (RMNH), “Portugal: Azores, S. Miguel Isl., Vila Franca, 15.x.2008, [reared] in lab. ex pupae of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceratitis capitata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Tephrit.) coll. from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Capsicum annuum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, L. Oliviera, RMNH’09”.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Antenna of ♀ with 18–20 segments and 1.1–1.2 times as long as fore wing; pedicellus yellowish-brown, not contrasting with scapus; third antennal segment of ♀ dark brown or brown basally and comparatively slender (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>); outer side of fourth antennal segment of ♀ straight or nearly so (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>); fourth-seventh antennal segments of ♀ moderately shiny and dark brown; ventral convex area of side of pronotum moderately narrow and yellowish-brown; medio-posterior depression of mesoscutum absent; wing membrane slightly infuscate; axillar depression narrow to medium-sized and smooth; tegulae brown or dark brown, darker than fore femur;<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> ventrally hind basitarsus narrowly acutely protruding postero-ventrally; hind tibia distinctly setose baso-dorsally; hind basitarsus moderately slender and often more or less infuscate; tarsal claws narrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 7</xref>); median carina of propodeum in lateral view hardly protruding and narrowly lamelliform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 12</xref>); first metasomal tergite strongly widened posteriorly, medially densely and finely rugulose and dark or pale brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 11</xref>); setose part of ovipositor sheath 0.6 times as long as metasoma and 0.7–0.8 times as long as hind tibia; length of fore wing 1.6–2.4 mm and of body 1.6-2.2 mm.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–13.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta ceratitivora</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., holotype, ♀. <bold>1</bold> wings <bold>2</bold> mandible full view of third tooth <bold>3</bold> hind leg <bold>4</bold> apical segments of antenna <bold>5</bold> head anterior <bold>6</bold> basal segments of antenna <bold>7</bold> hind tarsus <bold>8</bold> head dorsal <bold>9</bold> mesosoma dorsal <bold>10</bold> mandible full view of first tooth <bold>11</bold> first metasomal tergite dorsal <bold>12</bold> habitus lateral <bold>13</bold> axillar depression.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-222-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Holotype, ♀, length of body 1.7 mm, of fore wing 1.8 mm.</p>
                    <p><italic>Head</italic>. Antenna 1.2 times length of fore wing and 1.6 times body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 12</xref>), with 19 segments, setae erect and about 1.3 times as long as width of segment, length of third segment 0.8 times fourth segment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>), length of third, fourth and penultimate segments 4.0, 5.0 and 2.6 times their width, respectively; apex of scapus oblique and pedicellus medium-sized (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>); maxillary and labial palp with 6 and 4 segments, respectively; length of maxillary palp equal to height of head; Ocular Ocellar Line : diameter of posterior ocellus : Posterior Ocellar Line = 8:3:4; frons glabrous and smooth, nearly flat; length of eye in dorsal view 1.7 times the temple (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 8</xref>); eyes glabrous except for a few setae; temples parallel-sided behind eyes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 8</xref>); median groove of vertex shallow; face smooth, but medio-ventrally punctulate and somewhat rugulose, with long erect setae; clypeus largely smooth (but somewhat punctate laterally), flattened medially, long, setose, not tuberculate laterally and ventral rim truncate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>); epistomal groove rather wide, laterally smooth and distinct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 10, 12</xref>); anterior tentorial pits medium-sized (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>); length of malar space 0.2 times basal width of mandible; mandible largely smooth, hardly widened subapically, its medial length 1.75 times maximum width, second tooth much longer than both other lobe-shaped teeth, without incision between first and second tooth, third tooth with curved carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2, 10</xref>); head 1.6 times as wide as mesoscutum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 5, 9</xref>).</p>
                    <p><italic>Mesosoma</italic>. Length of mesosoma 1.3 times its height; pronope absent, but with a transverse crenulate groove and no antescutal depression; side of pronotum smooth, antero-medially and ventro-posteriorly finely crenulate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 12</xref>), ventral area slightly convex, medium-sized and yellowish-brown; precoxal sulcus only anteriorly and medially moderately crenulate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 12</xref>); mesosternal sulcus wide and coarsely crenulate; metapleuron smooth dorsally and medially, crenulate-rugose ventrally; notauli absent, only anteriorly with horizontal carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 9</xref>); medio-posterior depression of mesoscutum absent; mesoscutum glabrous (except for a few setae), smooth and with complete lateral carina; scutellar sulcus wide, semi-circular and deep, with one short crenula; axillar depression narrow and rectangular, smooth and rather shallow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 13</xref>); scutellum slightly convex; anteriorly metanotum without median carina and not protruding dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 12</xref>); surface of propodeum mainly smooth dorsally and remainder rather sparsely rugulose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 9</xref>), without lateral protuberance, its median carina moderately protuberant and with narrow triangular medial area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 9</xref>).</p>
                    <p><italic>Wings</italic>. Fore wing: 1-SR normal; 2-SR oblique; r:3-SR:SR1 = 3:16:51; r somewhat widened (about 3 times as long as its own width), 0.7 times width of pterostigma and issued just before middle of pterostigma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>); pterostigma narrow, elliptical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>)<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->; SR1 straight and ending at apex of wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>); 1-CU1:2-CU1 = 1:6; 2-SR:3-SR: r-m = 19:32:8; first subdiscal cell open ventrally and apically; CU1a just below level of 2-CU1; m-cu converging to 1-M. Hind wing: no trace of cu-a and m-cu (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), others veins completely sclerotized.</p>
                    <p><italic>Legs</italic>. Hind coxa smooth; tarsal claws very slender (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 7</xref>), no distinct protuberance but widened basally; length of femur, tibia and basitarsus of hind leg 5.0, 11.0, and 4.3 times their width, respectively; hind femur largely smooth and parallel-sided; hind tibia somewhat widened apically and subbasally setose; hind tarsal segments with a short and sparsely setose ventro-apical protuberance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 7</xref>); hind basitarsus comparatively robust and slightly narrowed basally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 7</xref>); length of hind tibial spurs 0.4 and 0.5 times hind basitarsus.</p>
                    <p><italic>Metasoma</italic>. Length of first tergite equal to its apical width, its surface distinctly convex and finely rugose medially, remainder largely smooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 11</xref>), its dorsal carinae distinct in basal 0.8 and tergite widened behind spiracles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 11</xref>); dorsope rather large; second tergite smooth; ovipositor straight; length of setose part of ovipositor sheath 0.27 times fore wing, 0.6 times metasoma and 0.7 times hind tibia, with long setae, ribbon-shaped (except apically) and with a short apical spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 12</xref>); hypopygium medium-sized and apically subtruncate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 12</xref>).</p>
                    <p><italic>Colour</italic>. Black or dark brown; scapus and pedicellus of antenna, mandible (but margins darkened), metasoma largely ventrally and legs (but telotarsi, apex of hind tibia and hind basitarsus slightly infuscate) yellowish-brown; palpi pale yellowish; propleuron, pronotal side ventrally, tegulae, first tergite and veins brown; pterostigma (but pale apically), parastigma and remainder of metasoma rather dark brown; wing membrane slightly infuscate.</p>
                    <p><italic>Variation</italic>. Antenna of ♀ with 18 (4), 19 (17) or 20 (7) segments (but one female with 20 segments in left antenna has 21 segments in right antenna) and 1.1–1.2 times as long as fore wing, of ♂ with 19 (1), 20 (3), 21 (8), 22 (5) or 23 (3) segments and 1.2–1.5 times as long as fore wing; length of fore wing 1.6–2.4 mm, and of body 1.6–2.2 mm; first metasomal tergite 1.0–1.2 times longer than its apical width; length of setose part of ovipositor sheath 0.27–0.32 times fore wing and 0.7–0.8 times hind tibia; axillar depression narrow to medium-sized, rectangular to narrow triangular; tegulae brown or dark brown, darker than fore femur; third antennal segment dark brown or largely brown and rest dark brown; hind tarsus often entirely dark brown or infuscate; second submarginal cell of fore wing parallel-sided or widened basally.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology">
                    <title>Biology.</title>
                    <p>Gregarious parasitoid of the Mediterranean fruit fly, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceratitis capitata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Wiedemann, 1824) (<tp:taxon-name>Tephritidae</tp:taxon-name>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Portugal (Azores); most likely also France, but no material available for study (see below).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>From the generic name of its host (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceratites</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and “voro” (Latin for “devour”), because it is devouring this host.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes">
                    <title>Notes.</title>
                    <p>Similar to the gregarious Nearctic <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta pallipes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Say, 1829), but this species is a parasitoid of other families and has the setose part of the ovipositor sheath about as long as the metasoma and longer than the hind tibia. The Mediterranean fruit fl<!--PageBreak-->y has been reported as host of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta minuta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Nees, 1911) from South France (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Ghesquière 1950</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Martin 1952</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Narayanan and Chawla 1962</xref>), but this is most likely a misidentification. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta minuta</tp:taxon-name></italic> is very similar, but differs in having the hind basitarsus slenderer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 21</xref>) (less so in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta ceratitivora</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 7</xref>), the antennal segments of ♀ up to 22 (up to 20 segments), the axillar depression wide and finely crenulate (comparatively narrow and smooth), clypeus low basally (steeply elevated), the first tergite less widened posteriorly (more widened posteriorly; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 11</xref>)), the tegulae and fore femur similarly coloured (tegulae darker than fore femur) and gregarious parasitoid of dipterous larvae in dung and rotting organic matter; e.g., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Scatophaga</tp:taxon-name></italic> species in rotting seaweed, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sarcophaga</tp:taxon-name></italic> species in human excrements and rotting <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sepia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species (gregarious parasitoid of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ceratitis capitata</tp:taxon-name></italic> in fruits).</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 14–25.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. <bold>14, 16</bold> head and mesosoma lateral <bold>15, 17</bold> ovipositor sheath <bold>18, 19</bold> hind tarsal claw <bold>20, 21</bold> hind tarsus <bold>22, 23</bold> scutellum, metanotum and propodeum lateral <bold>24</bold> convex ventral part of pronotal side <bold>25</bold> mesothorax dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-222-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <sec sec-type="Key to main groups of the genus Aphaereta Foerster in Europe">
                <title>Key to main groups of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Foerster in Europe</title>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral carina of mesoscutum absent in front of tegulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 14a</xref>); ovipositor sheath very aberrantly shaped, widened submedially and up curved apically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 15</xref>); labial palp with 2 segments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 14b</xref>) and maxillary palp with 4–5 segments</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta falciger</tp:taxon-name></italic> Graham, 1960</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lateral carina of mesoscutum present in front of tegulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 16a</xref>); shape of ovipositor sheaths normal, parallel-sided and straight (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 17</xref>); labial palp with 3–4 segments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 16b</xref>) and maxillary palp with 5–6 segments</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tarsal claws comparatively robust, gradually widened submedially (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 18, 19</xref>) and third antennal segment of female about 3 times as long as wide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta stigmaticalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> group</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tarsal claws very slender, hardly widened submedially (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 20, 21</xref>); third antennal segment of female usually 4–7 times as long as wide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medio-posterior depression of mesoscutum absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 9</xref>); setose part of ovipositor sheath 0.8–1.1 times as long as hind tibia; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta minuta</tp:taxon-name></italic> group</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medio-posterior depression of mesoscutum present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 25</xref>), but sometimes minute; setose part of ovipositor sheath 0.3–1.5 times as long as hind tibia</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta tenuicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> group</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scutellum distinctly convex medially (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 22</xref>; hind femur erect bristly setose and comparatively widened apically in lateral view</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta difficilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Nixon, 1939</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scutellum slightly convex medially (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 23</xref>); hind femur less bristly setose and more slender in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tegulae brown or dark brown, darker than fore femur; hind basitarsus less slender (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 7</xref>; about 4.5 times as long as its maximal width); axillar depression narrow to medium-sized and smooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 13</xref>); ventral convex area of side of pronotum comparatively narrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 12</xref>); antenna of ♀ with 18–20 segments; gregarious parasitoid of <tp:taxon-name>Tephritidae</tp:taxon-name>; Azores, and probably southern France</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta ceratitivora</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Note. Similar to the Nearctic <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta pallipes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Say, 1829), but this species is a gregarious parasitoid of other <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name> families and has setose part of ovipositor sheath about as long as metasoma and longer than hind tibia.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tegulae yellowish-brown, similar to colour of fore femur; hind basitarsus comparatively slender (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 20, 21</xref>; about 5 times as long as its maximum width); axillar depression large triangular; ventral convex area of side of pronotum comparatively wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 24</xref>); antenna of ♀ with 19–22 segments; parasitoid of <tp:taxon-name>Scatophagidae</tp:taxon-name> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Scatophaga</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. in rotting seaweed), and <tp:taxon-name>Sarcophagidae</tp:taxon-name> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sarcophaga</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. in human excrements and rotting <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sepia</tp:taxon-name></italic>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphaereta minuta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Nees, 1811)</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>The research work was supported by funds from Regional Secretariat for Science, Technology and Equipment (SRCTE) research grant M316/F/041/2009.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Achterberg</surname> <given-names>C van</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Illustrated key to the subfamilies of the Braconidae (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonoidea).</article-title> <source>Zoologische Verhandelingen Leiden </source> <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>189</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolphin</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quicke</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Estimating the global species richness of an incompletely described taxon: an example using parasitoid wasps (Hymenoptera: Braconidae).</article-title> <source>Biological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>286</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1095-8312.2001.tb01363.x">10.1111/j.1095-8312.2001.tb01363.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghesquière</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1950</year>)<article-title> Un parasite de la <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic> Wied. en France.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Société Entomologique de France </source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>66</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillani</surname> <given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bashir</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ilyas</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Studies on population dynamics of fruit flies (Diptera: Tephritidae) in guava and nectrin orchards in Islamabad.</article-title> <source>Pakistan Journal of Biological Sciences </source> <volume>5</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>452</fpage>-<lpage>454</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Liquido</surname> <given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinoda</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> Host plants of mediterranean fruit fly (Diptera: Tephritidae): An Annotated World Review.</article-title> <source>Miscellaneous publications of the Entomological Society of America </source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1952</year>)<article-title> Observations et essais de lutte contre <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic> Wied. en Provence, 1951.</article-title> <source>Revue de Pathologie Vegetale et d’Entomologie Agricole de France </source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>52</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Narayanan</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chawla</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962</year>)<source> Parasites of fruit fly pests of the world. Beiträge zur Entomologie 12(3/4): 437–476.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medeiros</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falcó</surname> <given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beitia</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verdú</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Parasitoids from Azores (Hymenoptera: Encyrtidae, Pteromalidae, Braconidae): potential use in integrated pest management against <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae).</article-title> <source>Biocontrol Science and Technology </source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>741</fpage>-<lpage>744</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/09583150802271238">10.1080/09583150802271238</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharkey</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Family Braconidae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Goulet</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group>. <issue-title></issue-title> <source>Agriculture Canada</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>362</fpage>-<lpage>395</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wharton</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Review of the Nearctic Alysiini (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) with discussion of generic relationships within the tribe.</article-title> <source>University of California Publication in Entomology </source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>112</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wharton</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Revision of the Australian Alysiini (Hymenoptera: Braconidae).</article-title> <source>Invertebrate Systematics </source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>105</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/IT01012">10.1071/IT01012</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Achterberg</surname> <given-names>K van</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horstmann</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> Biological and taxonomical information: Ichneumonoidea 2011. Taxapad Interactive Catalogue, Ottawa.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>