    <!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
        <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.275.3782</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Redescription and anatomy of 
                    <italic>Diplodonta portesiana</italic> (d’Orbigny, 1846) (Bivalvia, Ungulinidae) from Brazil
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Romera</surname>
                        <given-names>Bárbara L. V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Simone</surname>
                        <given-names>Luiz R. L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Cunha</surname>
                        <given-names>Carlo M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de São Paulo. Laboratório de Malacologia. Avenida Nazaré, 481. CEP: 04263-000, Brazil
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Bárbara L. V. Romera (<email xlink:type="simple">barbarella.lou@gmail.com</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: B.A. Marshall</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>4</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>275</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>15</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>7</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>29</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2013</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Bárbara L. V. Romera, Luiz R. L. Simone, Carlo M. Cunha</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The present redescription of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (d’Orbigny, 1846) is the first part of the revision of this genus in the East Atlantic. This species, despite being common in the Atlantic coast, remains poorly known. A detailed shell and anatomical study was conducted based not only on specimens from the type locality’s vicinities but also on samples from other regions. Diagnostic characters for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> includes: rounded shell with a small ligament; triangular, short and deep nymph; external micro ornamentation composed of small concavities in a concentric pattern; small adductor muscles; reduced pedal gape; pair of long hemipalps with a large area covered by folds; stomach with four ducts leading to digestive diverticula; and long intestine length. Our study suggests at least two new diagnostic characters to the genus: the two pair of muscles that controls the incurrent and excurrent openings and a residual ring-like tissue surrounding the anterior half of the posterior foot retractor muscle.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><italic>Diplodonta portesiana</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>Ungulinidae</kwd>
                <kwd>anatomy</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>Atlantic Ocean</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The ungulinid genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bronn, 1831 [type: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Venus lupinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Broochi, 1814; Italy, Piemonte, Andona Valey; subsequent designation by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Bronn 1831</xref>] shows a nearly worldwide distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Olsson 1961</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Abbott 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Coan et al. 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Redfern 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Mikkelsen and Bieler 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Coan and Valentich-Scott 2012</xref>). Despite being especially <!--PageBreak-->common in the South East Atlantic coast, and as was already noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Dall (1901)</xref>, the genus’ taxonomy remains problematic, with high oscillation of number of species. Recent shell catalogues frequently show, in our concept, incomplete character lists and descriptions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Rios 2009</xref>). The last revision is half a century old and dealt only with the genus’ diagnostic characters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Chavan 1962</xref>). Moreover, the last detailed revision of the West Atlantic species complex was conducted almost one century ago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Lamy 1920</xref>), and it barely elucidates the species identification, only grouping names that were created in previous revisions, apparently lacking any discernment. The single detailed anatomical study including the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Allen 1958</xref>) is a comparison among members of the superfamily <tp:taxon-name>Lucinoidea</tp:taxon-name>, the superfamily used to include the <tp:taxon-name>Ungulinidae</tp:taxon-name> before recent revision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Williams et al. 2004</xref>).</p>
            <p>The present paper is the first of a series concerned with the systematic revision of the West Atlantic <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta</tp:taxon-name></italic>. It focuses on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (d’Orbigny, 1846), a common but usually misidentified regional species. The present redescription is based on type specimens and topotypes with a wide bulk of samples, and also extends the species’ definition to include its anatomy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>A complete list of examined material is presented after the description. The holotype was examined and the other ~40 samples contain individuals from several localities. Shell measures were taken with a digital caliper: length corresponds to the greatest distance between anterior and posterior margin; height is the longest distance between the dorsal umbo’s end and the ventral margin; width is the greatest straight line reaching from the right to the left valve. The dissected specimens were fixed in 70% ethanol and studied under a stereomicroscope by standard techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Simone 2009</xref>). All drawings were made with the aid of a camera lucida. The Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM) was provided by the Laboratório de Microscopia Eletrônica do Instituto de Biociências from the Universidade de São Paulo.</p>
            <p>The following abbreviations are used in the anatomical descriptions and figures: <bold>aa:</bold> anterior adductor muscle; <bold>an:</bold> anus; <bold>cc:</bold> cerebral connective; <bold>cg:</bold> cerebral ganglia; <bold>cn:</bold> ctenidial nerve; <bold>cp:</bold> cerebro-pedal connective; <bold>cv:</bold> cerebro-visceral connective; <bold>dd:</bold> digestive diverticula; <bold>dg:</bold> digestive gland; <bold>dh:</bold> dorsal hood; <bold>em:</bold> excurrent muscular wall; <bold>er:</bold> esophageal rim; <bold>es:</bold> esophagus; <bold>fp:</bold> posterior foot retractor muscle; <bold>fr:</bold> anterior foot retractor muscle; <bold>ft:</bold> foot; <bold>gi:</bold> gill; <bold>go:</bold> gonad; <bold>gs:</bold> gastric shield; <bold>gt:</bold> gill tissue; <bold>he:</bold> heart; <bold>id:</bold> inner demibranch; <bold>im:</bold> pair of incurrent channel muscle; <bold>in:</bold> intestine; <bold>ip:</bold> inner palp; <bold>ki:</bold> kidney; <bold>lp:</bold> labial palp; <bold>ld:</bold> left diverticula; <bold>lp</bold>: left pouch; <bold>mt:</bold> major typhlosole; <bold>na:</bold> anterior adductor muscle nerve; <bold>np:</bold> nephropore; <bold>nt:</bold> minor typhlosole; <bold>od:</bold> outer demibranch; <bold>op:</bold> outer palp; <bold>pa:</bold> posterior adductor muscle; <bold>pg:</bold> pedal ganglia; <bold>pm:</bold> pallial muscle; <bold>pn:</bold> pallial nerve; <bold>rd:</bold> right diverticula; <bold>rn:</bold> renal nerve; <bold>sm:</bold> pair of excurrent channel muscle; <bold>ss:</bold> style sac; <bold>st:</bold> stomach; <bold>vg:</bold> visceral ganglia; <bold>vm:</bold> visceral mass.</p>
            <p><!--PageBreak-->Institutional abbreviations: <bold>CENEMAR</bold>, Centro de Estudos Marinhos do Atlântico Sul, Porto Alegre, Brazil; <bold>CMAC</bold>, Museo Argentino Del Caracol, Argentina; <bold>MZSP</bold>, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de São Paulo, Brazil; <bold>MZUCR</bold>, Museu de Zoologia da Costa Rica, Costa Rica; <bold>NHMUK</bold>, Natural History Museum of United Kingdom.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics">
            <title>Systematics</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Diplodonta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">portesiana</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Diplodonta_portesiana</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>(d’Orbigny, 1846)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">–29</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Lucina portesiana</tp:taxon-name><comment> d’Orbigny, 1846: 586 (pl. 81, Figs 12–13); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Gray 1857</xref>: 72; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Baril 1862</xref>: 137; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Tryon 1872</xref>: 84; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Aguirre 1994</xref>: 357 (pl. 2, Figs 17a, b).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name><comment>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Dall 1901</xref>: 794; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Amaral et al. 1999</xref>: 44; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">2010</xref>: 238.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta nucleiformis</tp:taxon-name><comment>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Morris 1947</xref>: 44 (pl. 20, fig. 22); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Warmke and Abbott 1962</xref>: 175 (pl. 35, fig. j); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Rios 1970</xref>: 174; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">1975</xref>: 218 (fig. 1049); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">1985</xref>: 233 (fig. 1165); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">1994</xref>: 255 (fig. 1247); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">2009</xref>: 518 (fig. 1440) (non Wagner 1838).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type">
                    <title>Type.</title>
                    <p>Holotype NHMUK 1854.12.4.770 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–6</xref>) (examined).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality">
                    <title>Type locality.</title>
                    <p>São Cristóvão Bay, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Redescription">
                    <title>Redescription.</title>
                    <p><italic>Shell</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">–14</xref>): Rounded, centrally pointed, equivalve and inequilateral. Laterally inflated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 11</xref>), maximum inflation ~60% of total length. Externally covered by shallow concentric ribs. Pattern of horizontal aligned, small, rounded pits, slight parallel to concentric growth lines, only visible under SEM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 14</xref>). Color white, periostracum thin, translucent, rarely cream to dark brown close to edges. Valves fragile; internally opaque (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9–10</xref>). Anterior adductor muscle scar reniform, ventral portion 2.5 times wider than dorsal portion; located between mid and dorsal thirds of shell height. Posterior adductor muscle scar elliptical, same distance from shell border as anterior adductor, located in median third of valve height. Pallial line entire and thin, away from shell border ~10% of valve height. Umbos low, ~5% of total shell height. Ligament parvincular, opisthodetic, ~20% of total shell length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 11–13</xref>). Hinge heterodont, with two cardinal teeth, anterior tooth of left valve and posterior tooth of right valve bifid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 12, 13</xref>). Dental shelf long, length equivalent to half of total dorsal margin length, close to cardinal teeth. Dorsal margin concave, forming groove at fusion with dental shelf. Lateral teeth absent. Nymph short, ~20% of total shell length, ~5 times wider than long, triangular. Lunule and escutcheon absent.</p>
                    <p><italic>Main muscles</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 15, 16, 20</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">23</xref>): Anterior adductor muscle reniform in section, ~2.6 times higher than wider, ventral half ~2.5 wider than dorsal half (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 15, 16</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">23</xref>); occupying ~1/15 of internal shell volume, located between middle and dorsal third of shell height (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 15, 16, 20</xref>). Posterior adductor muscle ~40% smaller than anterior muscle, located at opposite end and parallel to anterior muscle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 15, 16</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">23</xref>). Pair of anterior foot retractor muscles oval in section and thin, originating dorso-posterior<!--PageBreak-->ly to anterior adductor muscle, insertion area ~1/20 of adductor insertion, length ~1/4 of total shell length, fusion of both branches occurring in its half-length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 16</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">23</xref>). Foot retractor muscles oval in section, slightly laterally compressed, thin, ~45% longer than anterior foot retractor muscles, inserting dorsally to anterior adductor muscle, in <!--PageBreak-->area equivalent to ~1/40 of anterior adductor insertion, both branches fusing in ventral quarter of shell length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 16</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">23</xref>). Incurrent and excurrent openings surrounded by two pairs of muscles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 20</xref>); pair of incurrent channel muscles bordering incurrent opening, inserting at dorsal ending of opening; long, straight and thin, equivalent to twice opening length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 20</xref>: im); pair of excurrent channel muscles narrow and thin, inserting below ventral ending of opening; bordering ~60% of excurrent opening length, ~30% shorter than pair of incurrent channel muscles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 20</xref>: sm).</p>
                    <p><italic>Foot and byssus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 15, 16</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">23</xref>): Foot long, length ~70% of shell high; terminal bulb cylindrical, expanding ~30% beyond foot width, color orange to light brown; byssal groove and byssus absent.</p>
                    <p><italic>Mantle</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 15–17</xref>): Mantle lobes symmetrical, thin, translucent, colorless. Pallial muscles strong and short, distributed evenly in ventral side of mantle lobe, length ~1/10 animal height (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 15</xref>). Mantle border with three folds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 17</xref>): outer fold long and thin, ~1/3 of shell thickness, ~15 times higher than wide; middle fold short, twice wider and ~7.5 times shorter than outer fold; inner fold short, with twice as wide and ~5 times shorter than outer fold. Periostracum produced between outer and middle fold. Middle fold with 60 pairs of papillae, bordering all ventral border (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>); papilla twice taller than wide, tip rounded, separated by area equivalent to 5 times each papilla width. Mantle lobes partially free, fused in ~35% of total mantle lobes length, by inner fold; from incurrent opening to middle portion of animal’s length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>: mf); free portion extending until ventral surface of ventral half of anterior adductor muscle, forming pedal gape, corresponding to ~55% of total shell length. Incurrent and excurrent openings formed of fusion of third mantle fold; flanked by ~30 pairs of papillae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 19</xref>: eo); excurrent opening ~1/4 of total shell length; incurrent opening ~60% of total excurrent opening length. No well-developed siphons; except for thick muscular wall internally at excurrent opening, acting like socket to demibranchs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 20</xref>: em). Small striped “ring like” tissue surrounding middle portion of posterior foot retractor muscle, below gill insertion at visceral mass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>: gt).</p>
                    <p><italic>Pallial cavity</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 15–16, 18, 22</xref>): Occupying half of inner shell volume (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>). Labial palps small, ~1/30 of inner shell area, triangular; external surface smooth; outer and inner hemipalps similar in size, ~7% longer and ~60% wider than anterior adductor muscle insertion area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 16, 22</xref>); outer hemipalp connected to mantle lobe by dorsal border, in ~2/5 of total length; inner hemipalp connected to visceral mass by dorsal border, in ~1/4 of this total length; internal surface of both hemipalps covered by 30 transversal folds; outer hemipalp folds high and rounded in section, covering ~95% of surface, thin smooth area in dorsal margin, corresponding to 1/25 of total surface of hemipalp; folds of inner hemipalp flattened in section and centrally grooved in length; covering ~80% of internal surface of hemipalp, forming two thin smooth areas at ventral and dorsal borders, corresponding 1/8 of total surface of hemipalp; near mouth folds decreasing until forming small grooves converging at middle region of palps, towards to mouth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 22</xref>). Gills large, area ~16 times wider than outer hemipalp area, ~1/3 of total valve area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 16, 18</xref>); with two demibranchs; outer demibranch fusiform, twice longer than wide; folded upon <!--PageBreak-->~1/3 of own total area; covering pericardium and kidney; connected to mantle lobe by ~15% of length of postero-dorsal border; inner demibranch triangular, ~3 times longer than wide; folded upon half of total demibranch area; ~45% of external surface covered by outer demibranch; connection to visceral sac by cilia; gill filaments with rounded tips. Suprabranchial chamber volume ~3/5 of infrabranchial chamber volume (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>).</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak--><italic>Visceral mass</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 16</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">23</xref>): Visceral sac occupying half of inner shell volume; triangular, inflated, located dorsally between pair of anterior foot retractors and pair of posterior foot retractor, ~3 times larger than muscular base; ~35% of antero-dorsal region filled with greenish brown digestive gland, remainder areas filled with cream colored gonads. Stomach and style sac located vertically at central portion of visceral sac (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 23</xref>).</p>
                    <p><italic>Circulatory and excretory systems</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 16, 21</xref>): Pericardium located dorso-posteriorly of visceral sac, between umbonal cavity and dorsal kidney surface, occupying ~1/4 of visceral mass volume (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>). Pair of auricles antero-posteriorly elongated, connected to central axis of gills in 1/5 of gills total length; walls thick and translucent. Ventricle elongated, with thick walls; located at central portion of pericardium; surrounding ~1/3 of intestinal length crossing pericardium; connected to auricles at central portion of lateral walls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 21</xref>). Kidney located postero-ventrally in visceral mass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>: ki), below posterior end of pericardium and dorsal surface of posterior foot retractor muscles, color light brown; shape triangular , occupying ~1/4 of visceral mass volume. Nephropore rounded, located at posterior portion of visceral mass, at ~10% of visceral mass height, opening in suprabranchial chamber (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>: np).</p>
                    <p><italic>Digestive system</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 22</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">–25</xref>): Palps and digestive glands described above. Mouth small, located centrally at palps intersection, with small lips (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 22</xref>). Esophagus short and narrow, ~1/5 of total length of visceral sac and ~1/10 of high (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 23</xref>), cylindrical; not touching anterior adductor muscle, crossing anterior third of anterior foot retractor muscles, parallel to anterior foot retractors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 23</xref>); inner surface covered by longitudinal folds until stomach entry, forming esophageal rim (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 25</xref>); connected to anterior surface of stomach. Stomach of medium size, occupying ~1/5 of visceral sac volume, elliptical, located anteriorly at umbo; ~60% of visceral sac length and ~1/3 of high (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 23</xref>: st); anterior portion ~30% wider than anterior portion. Pair of ducts to digestive diverticula located ventrally at anterior half of stomach, turned ventrally; digestive diverticula ducts connected to lateral walls of anterior half of stomach; one digestive diverticula duct connected at right wall, dorsally at esophagus line; one digestive diverticula duct connected at left wall, anteriorly to left pouch. Dorsal hood elongated and narrow, ~1/4 of stomach total length, ~4 times longer than wide, pointed anteriorly. Left pouch located below anterior ending of dorsal hood, anteriorly to digestive diverticula ducts; shallow and small, occupying area ~1/10 of surface of stomach (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 24</xref>); internally anterior half of gastric chamber partially divided in ventral and dorsal portion by septum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 25</xref>); originating at anterior portion of right wall until dorsal hood entrance, septum length ~1/5 of total stomach length; dorsal surface covered by two sorting areas. Inner surface of stomach mostly smooth, with three distinct sorting areas; first sorting area starting at dorsal region of anterior portion, jointly to dorsal region of esophageal rim; heading dorsally until dorsal hood entrance and folding itself, covering posterior half of dorsal surface of gastric septum, narrow and long, composed of short and transverse folds with equivalent length and width; second sorting area starting on anterior half of dorsal surface of septum; heading from right side to dorsal hood, short and wide, composed of transverse folds twice longer than wide if compared with folds of first sorting area; third sorting area starting inside dorsal hood, running <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->on latero-dorsally posterior right portion of stomach, entering style sac and attenuating. Gastric shield in central region of dorsal wall of stomach, occupying ~25% of total gastric area, translucent and iridescent, with two lateral projections, anterior projection penetrate left pouch and posterior projection penetrate dorsal hood; two gastric ridges narrow and tall running towards style sac, on ventral gastric surface, typhlosoles originating from each ridge. Long ridge originating in internal right wall of left digestive diverticula, leaving posteriorly and entering anteriorly in right side of left diverticula, forming semi-circle, touching left internal wall of diverticula and leaving anteriorly from ventral side of diverticula, on surface of anterior gastric portion, entering in anterior portion of right diverticula; bordering right lateral wall and leaving posteriorly, running on ventral wall of stomach until style sac opening, forming minor typhlosole (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 25</xref>: nt) at ventral surface of sac. Small ridge running on ventro-posterior region of stomach, circular shape, flanking style sac entrance, running on ventral surface of sac forming major typhlosole (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 25</xref>: mt). Style sac (ss) connecting ventrally to dorsal portion of stomach; conic; narrowing towards dorsal region of visceral sac, ~3.5 longer than wide; occupying ~1/6 of visceral sac total volume, height half and width ~1/10 of visceral sac high (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 23</xref>). Intestine narrow and long, originating in level where typhlosoles decreasing in shape at internal surface of style sac (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 23</xref>); running towards ventral portion of visceral sac, below central portion of stomach; with three overlapping loops, last one covering dorsally other two; following to posterior portion of visceral sac, parallel to style sac; forming loop on dorso-posterior surface of stomach, leaving visceral sac, crossing pericardium and posterior surface of kidney, crossing between pair posterior foot retractor muscles; touching entire posterior surface of posterior adductor muscle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 23</xref>); intestine total length ~10 times longer than style sac. Anus simple, sessile, opening at ventral region of posterior adductor muscle.</p>
                    <p><italic>Genital system</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>): Gonads cream- colored, in granular aspect. Pair of gonoducts connected to gonad acini along posterior portion of visceral sac. Genital pore simple, located at posterior region of visceral sac, opening inside renal chamber.</p>
                    <p><italic>Central nervous system</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 26–29</xref>): Pair of cerebral ganglia (cg) surrounding dorsal surface of anterior portion of esophagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 29</xref>); dorsally at external surface of outer labial palp; triangular shaped, longer than wide; length half of esophagus length; each ganglion with ~1/3 of a transverse section of esophagus; cerebral commissure ~1/7 longer than ganglia total length; from anterior portion connecting anterior adductor muscle nerve (na), touching posterior surface of anterior adductor muscle, bifurcating in two branches; internal branch penetrating dorso posterior third of muscle and leaving at ventral surface of muscle; outer branch bordering posterior surface of anterior muscle, both branches fusing at ventral region of anterior muscle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 26</xref>); two connectives originating dorsally in ganglia, anteriorly to cerebro-visceral connective (cv) crossing visceral mass, touching gonopore dorsally, bordering anterior portion of kidney and connecting dorsally at visceral ganglia, connecting posteriorly cerebro-pedal connective (cp) running immersed in pedal muscles, connecting to anterior region of pedal ganglia. Pair of visceral ganglia (vg) fusiform, small, length same than height, ~1/2 of cerebral ganglia length, partially fused at median portion, with slightly central groove (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 27</xref>); located <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->ventrally to kidney, parallel to posterior adductor muscle, in dorsal tip connecting cerebra-visceral connective (described above) and renal nerve (rn), penetrating into kidney area; laterally originating ctenidial nerves (cn) running thought central axis of posterior portion of gills; dorsally originating posterior adductor muscle nerve, penetrating middle region of anterior surface of posterior muscle; at ventral tip originating pallial nerve (pn), touching anterior surface of ventral portion of posterior adductor muscle, running parallel to incurrent and excurrent apertures and mantle border, diffusing at mantle lobe board (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 26</xref>). Pair of pedal ganglia (pg) oval, longer than wide, totally fused with each other, similar length and height of cerebral ganglia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 28</xref>); located internally to posterior retractor pedal muscles, above foot insertion, in anterior tip connecting cerebro-pedal connectives from cerebral ganglia; in posterior tip connecting two pairs of nerves, dorsal pair running towards posterior region, inside posterior foot retractor muscles; postero-ventral nerves curved to ventral region, running internally foot.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–6.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Holotype (NHMUK 1854.12.4.770; L: 20 mm; H: 17 mm). <bold>1</bold> Left valve, external view <bold>2</bold> Right valve, external view <bold>3</bold> Left valve, internal view <bold>4</bold> Right valve, internal view <bold>5</bold> Left hinge detail <bold>6</bold> Right hinge detail. Scale: 2 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-275-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 7–14.</label>
                        <caption><p>Specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (MZSP 22747, L: 13.4 mm, H: 13.1 mm, width: 7.7 mm). <bold>7</bold> Left valve, external view <bold>8</bold> Right valve, external view <bold>9</bold> Left valve, internal view <bold>10</bold> Right valve, internal view <bold>11</bold> Dorsal view <bold>12</bold> Left hinge detail <bold>13</bold> Right hinge detail <bold>14</bold> External surface of shell under SEM; Scale: 2 mm, except <bold>14</bold>: 200 µm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-275-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 15–22.</label>
                        <caption><p>Anatomy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <bold>15</bold> Right view, right mantle lobe removed <bold>16</bold> Same view, gill removed <bold>17</bold> Mantle border, transverse section in median portion <bold>18</bold> Gill, transverse section in middle portion <bold>19</bold> Incurrent and excurrent openings, posterior view <bold>20</bold> Same, anterior-slightly right view <bold>21</bold> Pericardium region, dorsal view <bold>22</bold> Labial palps, ventral view, hemipalps deflected; Scale: 2 mm, except <bold>17</bold>, <bold>18</bold>: 1mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-275-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 23–29.</label>
                        <caption><p>Anatomy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <bold>23</bold> Digestive system as in situ, right view, foot and main muscles also shown <bold>24</bold> Stomach, left view <bold>25</bold> Internal stomach surface, right view, dorsal gastric wall sectioned longitudinally and deflected <bold>26</bold> Nervous system and topology of other main structures, right view <bold>27</bold> Visceral ganglia, ventral view <bold>28</bold> Pedal ganglia, superior figure in right view, inferior figure in ventral view <bold>29</bold> Cerebral ganglia, anterior view; Scale: <bold>23, 26</bold>: 2 mm; <bold>24, 25</bold>: 1 mm; <bold>27–29</bold>: 0,5 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-275-001-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Habitat">
                    <title>Habitat.</title>
                    <p>Infaunal, in muddy sands; from 0 to 68 m depth.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Measurements">
                    <title>Measurements</title>
                    <p>(<italic>length, height and width in mm</italic>). MZSP 22747 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–14</xref>): 13.4 by 7.1 by 7.7; MZSP 105725 #1: 16.4 by 16.1 by 10.1; CENEMAR: 17.6 by 17.3 by 11.7.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Geographic range">
                    <title>Geographic range.</title>
                    <p>From Limón, Cahuita, Costa Rica, to, Bombinhas, Santa Catarina, Brazil.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined">
                    <title>Material Examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype HMUK 1854.12.4.770 (d’Orbigny col. 1842); COSTA RICA. <bold>Limón</bold>; Refugio Nacional de Vida Silvestre, Gandoca- Manzanillo, between Gandoca and Rio Sixaola river mouth, 12 m depth, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">09°34'37.8966"N, 82°34'33.0309"W</named-content>, MZUCR- INB0003816046, 3 valves (T: 181-S. Avilla/Lote: 73904, A. Berrocal id., S. Ávila col. 12/vi/2003); Cahuíta, National Park, 1 km to east of Puerto Vargas. 12 m depth, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">9°43'33.3681"N, 82°48'31.5178"W</named-content>, MZUCR- INB0003414093, 2 valves (S. Ávila id, S. Ávila col. 09/vi/20010); 3 km to North east of Cahuita, reef out, 12 m depth. <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">9°45'50.3530"N, 82°49'29.9092"W</named-content>, MZUCR- INB0003411964, 2 valves, (S. Ávila id., J. Magaña col. 11/vi/2001); Punta Cahuita, 8 m depth, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">9°44'58.2370"N, 82°49'10.5220"W</named-content>, MZUCR- INB0001494593, 1 valve (J. Espinosa id., Y. Camacho col. 24/v/1998). BRAZIL. <bold>Bahia;</bold> Salvador, Todos os Santos bay, MZSP 105725, 1 specimen (CETESB col. ii/2000). <bold>Rio de Janeiro;</bold> Angra dos Reis, Ilha Grande bay, 7.5 m depth, MZSP 22747, 9 specimens (Emília sta. 61, Ilha Grande Project, 10/xii/1965); 9.6m depth, MZSP 22780, 4 specimens, (Ilha Grande Project, Penna- Neme col. 25/vii/1966); Sepetiba bay, Itacuruça Island, MNRJ 12458, 8 specimens. <bold>Santa Catarina;</bold> Bombinhas, 3–5 m depth, CENEMAR, 2 specimens, (in shrimp net, J. Tarasconi col., 03/iv/ 1994); 5-10 m depth, CMAC, 3 valves (J. Tarasconi col, 1995); 8–10 m depth, CMAC, 2 valves (trawled by shrimpers, J. Tarasconi col. x/1994).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Below, characters described on this study are compared between classical anatomical studies on genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Lastly, general aspects concerning the species are analyzed, improving current data aboutthe genus.</p>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <p><bold>Shell:</bold> The original description by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">d’Orbigny (1846)</xref> lacks data on the shell variation, despite its noteworthy emphasis on the rounded form. Beyond the overall shape, a typical shell of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> has other new discovered exclusive features, such as: ligament length ~1/5 of total animal length, with its anterior limit below the umbo; a short and deep nymph. Besides, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> shell shows a concentric pattern of microscopically concavities.  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Mikkelsen and Bieler (2007)</xref> already demonstrated this character on ungulind shells, showing different patterns between species, being radial or concentric patterns.</p>
            <p><bold>Muscular system:</bold> A first description on the species’ adductor muscles was offered by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Mittré (1850)</xref>, who noticed a slight discrepancy in shape and size of both adductors in a specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta punctata</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Allen (1958)</xref> justified the presence of an elongated anterior adductor by relating it with the ability to form an anterior inhalant tube. This was the first time that pairs of anterior and posterior foot retractor muscles were described for the genus, including the absence of a pair of protractor muscles in such an active burrowing genus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Domaneschi 1979</xref>). A new pair of muscles is described in this paper: the inhalant and exhalant channel muscles. It is possible that this pair of muscles has a role in controlling the contractions of the inhalant and exhalant apertures, as well as in sustaining the muscular wall to compensate the lack of an exhalant siphon.</p>
            <p><bold>Foot:</bold> The foot shape is one of the most outstanding characters in <tp:taxon-name>Ungulinidae</tp:taxon-name>. It was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Duvernoy (1842)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Mittré (1850)</xref> as being long and cylindrical, with a terminal expansion. In histological studies, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Allen (1958)</xref> showed differences between muscular fibers of the tip and proximal portions of the foot’s terminal expansion, as well as a large concentration of mucous cells. Other biological considerations further improved this knowledge, especially regarding the production of mucous tubes: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Haas (1942)</xref> discussed the production of mucous-sediment tubes in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta orbella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Gould, 1852 to accommodate the siphons; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Domaneschi (1979)</xref> described the production of mucus by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta punctata</tp:taxon-name></italic>. As no specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been seen alive, we can only infer this habit by some mucous-sand structures surrounding the anterior portion of some shells.</p>
            <p><bold>Mantle:</bold> The current translucent mantle and the pedal gape, common to the genus (Mittré, 1850), was found in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic>. A concentration of glandular cells below the main rejection tract, i.e., between the outer and middle folds of the mantle, and no differences between the papillae of the middle and inner folds have been found in histological studies of ungulinids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Allen 1958</xref>).</p>
            <p><bold>Pallial cavity:</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Duvernoy (1842)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Mittré (1850)</xref> described two demibranchs for each gill, a feature confirmed in this study. The palps are thin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Mittré 1850</xref>) and show a moderate size, with a variable folded area. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Allen (1958)</xref> described the rejection tracts of palps as very narrow and located at their ventral margin, a feature also found. A new character is, moreover, described here: a “ring-like” tissue fused with the muscular and visceral sac surfaces located below the connection of the gill to the visceral sac. It was postulated that this could be analogous to the flower-like organ described for the <tp:taxon-name>Galeommatidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Mikkelsen and Bieler 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Simone 2001</xref>). But these structures only occur at the anterior portion of the foot, differing from the structure of the ungulinids, which occurs at the posterior half of foot. The gills of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta</tp:taxon-name></italic> are free from each other, while other ungulinid <!--PageBreak-->genera have their gills fused in their posterior portion by a tissue originated in same location as the “ring-like” tissue described here. We offer here a first hypothesis regarding this “ring-like” tissue: considering the existence of ungulinids with fused and free gills, this “ring-like” structure could be a residual tissue from a complete connection between the gills.</p>
            <p><bold>Circulatory system:</bold> A ventricle and intestine crossing was noticed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Duvernoy (1842)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Allen (1958)</xref> described the circulatory system as not significantly different from other Eulamellibranchia. Greater attention should be called to the thin and delicate pericardial tissue. The pair of auricles has thin walls and is connected to the central axis of demibranch.</p>
            <p><bold>Digestive system:</bold> The digestive structures are delicate and mostly covered by the gonads and the digestive gland. The most striking character in the digestive system is the stomach, complex, possessing several sorting areas and folds. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Allen (1958)</xref> described a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta</tp:taxon-name></italic> stomach as morphologically and functionally similar to other Eulamellibranchia. Compared to Allen’s results, the number of ducts attached to the gastric wall can be variable between species. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Purchon (1960)</xref>, based on Allen’s description, classified the ungulinids’ stomach as “type V” mainly due to: conjoined style-sac and intestine; major typhlosole penetrating both diverticula; gastric shield penetrating dorsal hood and left pouch openings; ducts to digestive diverticula opening on right wall of stomach; presence of a sorting area on roof of anterior side of dorsal hood; a sorting area inside left pouch and presence of a sorting area below esophagus orifice. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> stomach shows all characters described above, and is strongly characterized by two main gastric characters: firstly, the constancy in number of lateral ducts of digestive diverticula, each one attached at each side of stomach; second, the number of sorting areas covering gastric chamber, with one starting below esophagus’s rim and a second covering dorsal hood surface, as described to a characteristic ungulinid stomach.</p>
            <p><bold>Central nervous system:</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Duvernoy (1842)</xref> noticed three ungulinid pairs of ganglia, which were later described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Allen (1958)</xref> as having no great modifications when compared to other Eulamellibranchia. This general feature was found in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic>, except for a connection described between the pallial nerve and the anterior adductor nerve, also found in other <tp:taxon-name>Lucinoidea</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p>As stated above, a revision of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta</tp:taxon-name></italic> is still in progress, and several diagnostic morphological and shell characters have already been found. This paper, with a more complete description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic>, is only the first step of this effort. The other species already are under study in order to improve the taxonomy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the near future. The further publications will allow more comparisons and discussion of the taxonomical features, from species to family levels.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>The authors wish to thank Kathie Way, John Taylor, Phil Hurst and Andreia Salvador, NHMUK, by pictures of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diplodonta portesiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> type material; José C. Tarasconi, CENEMAR, for lent material from the South Brazil locality; Ênio Mattos and Phillip <!--PageBreak-->Lenktaitis  from Laboratório de Miscroscopia Eletrônica da Universidade de São Paulo, by the help in SEM pictures; Yolanda Camacho, MZUCR, by lent material from the central coast of East Atlantic; Daniel Forcelli, who lent samples from the South Atlantic of Argentina coast; Rodrigo B. Salvador (Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde Stuttgart) for the revision of English and precious tips to improve the text. The present study was partly supported by FAPESP (<italic>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo</italic>), proc. #2010/11401-8 (Bárbara L.V. Romera) and proc. #2010/11253-9 (Carlo M. Cunha).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbott</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<source> American seashells. 2<sup>°</sup> ed. New York: Van Nostrand Reinhold Co. 663 p.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguirre</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Type specimens of quaternary marine bivalves from Argentina.</article-title> <source>Ameghiniana </source> <volume>31</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>347</fpage>-<lpage>374</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>)<article-title> On the basic form and adaptations to habitat in the Lucinacea (Eulamellibranchia).</article-title> <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society(Serie B) </source> <volume>241</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>-<lpage>484</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rstb.1958.0010">10.1098/rstb.1958.0010</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Amaral</surname> <given-names>ACZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amaral</surname> <given-names>EHM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leite</surname> <given-names>FPP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gianuca</surname> <given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source>. Diagnóstico sobre praias arenosas: avaliação e ações prioritárias para a conservação da biodiversidade da zona costeira e marinha. In: Fundação Tropical de Pesquisa e Tecnologia André Tosello. Base de Dados Tropical, Campinas, São Paulo, Brasil. Available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.anp.gov.br/brnd/round6/guias/PERFURACAO/PERFURACAO_R6/refere/Praias%20arenosas.pdf">http://www.anp.gov.br/brnd/round6/guias/PERFURACAO/PERFURACAO_R6/refere/Praias%20arenosas.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Amaral</surname> <given-names>ACZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Migotto</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turra</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaeffer-Novelli</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Araçá: biodiversidade, impactos e ameaças. Biota Neotropica.</article-title>  <volume>10</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>264</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Baril</surname> <given-names>VL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1862</year>)<source> LʼEmpire Du Brésil, Monographie Complète de LʼEmpire Sud-Américain. Paris, Ferdinand Sartorius, 576 p.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Broochi</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1814</year>)<source> Conchiologia Fossile Subapennina com Osservazioni Geologiche Sugli Apennini e Suolo Adjacente. Vol. 2. Dalla Stamperia Reale: Milão. 242–712 p, 17 pl.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronn</surname> <given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1831</year>)<source> Italiens Tertiär-Gebilde und deren organische Einschlüsse: vier Abhandlungen. Heilderberg: Groos. 174 pg.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chavan</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962</year>)<article-title> Essai Critique de Classification des Ungulinidae. Institut Royal des Sciences Naturelles de Belgique.</article-title>  <volume>38</volume> (<issue>23</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coan</surname> <given-names>EV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valentich-Scott</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> Bivalve Seashells of Tropical West America. Marine Bivalve Mollusks from Baja California to Northern Peru. Sanra Barbara Museum of Natural History Monographs 6, Studies in Biodiversity 4. 1259 p + XV.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coan</surname> <given-names>EV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valentich-Scott</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<source>Bivalve Seashells of Western North America: Marine Bivalve Mollusks from Artic Alaska to Baja California. Santa Barbara: Santa Barbara Museum of Natural History. 764 p.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dall</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1901</year>)<source> Synopsis of the Lucinacea and of the American species. Proceedings of the United States National Museum 23: 779–833, pl. 39–42.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Domaneschi</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<source> Aspectos da biologia de <italic>Diplodonta punctata</italic> (Say, 1822) (Bivalvia:Lucinacea: Ungulinidae). Revista Nordestina de Biologia. 1/2(2): 21–25.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>d’Orbigny</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1834-1847</year>)<source> Voyage de las Amérique Méridionale. Vol. 5 Mollusques. Paris Pitois- Levraut. 758 p.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Duvernoy</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1842</year>)<source> Mémoire sur l’animal de l’onguline couleur de laque (<italic>Ungulina rubra</italic> Daud.) et de sur les rapports de ce mollusque acéphale. Annales Des Sciences Naturelles (Zoologie). 18 (2):110–122, pl. 5B.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1857</year>)<source> Figured Mollusks Animals. London: Longman, Brown, Green and Longmans vol 5, 49 p.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1942</year>)<article-title> The habits of life of some West Coast bivalves. The Nautilus.</article-title>  <volume>55</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>109</fpage>-<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamy</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1920</year>)<article-title> Révision des Lucinacea vivants du Museum Naturelle de Paris. Journal de conchyliologie.</article-title>  <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>-<lpage>388</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikkelsen</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bieler</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<source> Biology and comparative anatomy of three new species of commensal Galeommatidae, with a possible case of mating behavior in bivalves.Malacologia 34(1–2): 1–24, 33.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikkelsen</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bieler</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> Seashells of Southern Florida - Living Marine Mollusks of the Florida Keys and Adjacent Regions: Bivalves.Princeton University Press, Princeton, New Jersey 503 p.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittré</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1850</year>)<source> Notice sur les genres <italic>Diplodonta</italic> et <italic>Scacchia</italic>. Journal de Conchyliologie. 1 (3): 238–246, pl. 12</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1947</year>)<source> A field Guide to Shells of the Atlantic and Gulf Coasts and the Weste Indies. 3. ed. Boston: Hougton Mifflin.330 pg, 76 pl.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsson</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>)<source> Panamic-Pacific Pelecypoda. Mollusk of the Tropical Eastern Pacific. Particulary from the Southern Half of the Panamic-Pacific Faunal Province (Panama to Peru). Paleontological Reseach Institution, Ithaca. 666 p. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.6853">10.5962/bhl.title.6853</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Purchon</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1960</year>)<article-title> The Stomach in the Eulamellibranchia; Stomach types IV and V.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London, </source> <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>-<lpage>489</lpage></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Redfern</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<source> Bahamians Seashells: A thousand Species from Abaco, Bahamas. BahamianSeashell.com: Boca Raton, Flórida 180 pps, 124 pls.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rios</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<source>. Coastal Brazilian Seahells. Editora da FURG. 255 pg.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rios</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>)<source> Brazilian Marine Mollusks Iconography. 2 ed. Editora da FURG. 331p, 91 pl.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rios</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<source> Seashells of Brasil. 3 ed. Editora da FURG. 328 p, 101pl.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rios</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<source> Seashells of Brazil. Fundação Universidade do Rio Grande Press. Rio Grande, 368 p. 113 pls.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rios</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Compendium of Brazilian Sea Shells. Rio Grande, RS. 668 p.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simone</surname> <given-names>LRL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Revision of the genus <italic>Parabornia</italic> (Bivalvia: Galeommatoidea: Galeommatidae) from the Western Atlantic, with description of a new species from Brazil.</article-title> <source>Journal of Conchology, Londres </source> <volume>37</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>159</fpage>-<lpage>169</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simone</surname> <given-names>LRL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Comparative morphology among representatives of main taxa of Scaphopoda and basal protobranch Bivalvia (Mollusca).</article-title> <source>Papéis Avulsos de Zoologia </source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>405</fpage>-<lpage>457</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tryon</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1872</year>)<article-title> Catalogue and Synonymy of the Recent Species of the Family Lucinidae.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia </source> <volume>24</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>82</fpage>-<lpage>96</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Warmke</surname> <given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbott</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962</year>)<source> Caribbean Seashells: A guide to the marine mollusks of Puerto Rico and other West Indian Islands, Bermuda and the Lower Flórida keys. Dover Publications: New York. 348 pg + 44 pg.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glover</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Molecular Phylogeny of the Lucinoidea (Bivalvia): Non-Monophyly and separate acquisition of bacterial chemosymbiosis. Journal of Molluscan Studies.</article-title>  <volume>70</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>202</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/mollus/70.2.187">10.1093/mollus/70.2.187</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>