<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.89.921</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title><italic>Nesticus baeticus</italic> sp. n., a new troglobitic spider species from south-west Europe (Araneae, Nesticidae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>López-Pancorbo</surname>
                        <given-names>Alberto</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"></xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:0C57C1D9-E542-4EEC-87F0-D70BB4EF2CB8</uri></contrib>           
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Ribera</surname> 
                        <given-names>Carles</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"></xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:509826D6-1E4D-4201-B08C-07D0F0044CC7</uri></contrib>           
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label></label><italic>Institut de Recerca de la Biodiversitat &amp; Departament de Biologia Animal. Universitat de Barcelona, Av. Diagonal, 645, Barcelona - 08028, Spaina</italic></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Carles Ribera (<email xlink:type="simple">cribera@ub.edu</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Dmitry Logunov</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
            	    <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>11</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>89</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>13</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>19</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>14</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Alberto López-Pancorbo, Carles Ribera</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:CAE9A191-479D-46A5-B4A8-125FD4E5A0B8</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new troglobitic species, <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold> (♂♀), inhabiting the karst landscapes of the high part of the Cazorla, Segura and Las Villas Natural Park (NE Jaén, Spain) where it has been found in 8 caves is diagnosed and described, its distribution and habitat are also analyzed.The new species belongs to the Iberian species group that includes <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus luquei</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus lusitanicus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus murgis</tp:taxon-name>. Evolutionary relationships of the Iberian <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus</tp:taxon-name> species are discussed on the basis of morphological and molecular data (<italic>cox1</italic> and <italic>rrnL</italic>).</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Arachnida</kwd>
                <kwd>Araneae</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>description</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>caves</kwd>
                <kwd>Iberian Peninsula</kwd>
                <kwd>Mediterranean basin</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus</tp:taxon-name> Thorell, 1869 is distributed worldwide except for south-eastern Asia and Australia and comprises 125 species and 8 subspecies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Platnick 2011</xref>). In Europe <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus</tp:taxon-name> is represented by 23 species, of which five are known from Iberia. Unlike <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus cellulanus</tp:taxon-name> (Clerck, 1757), a species with a holarctic distribution, the four others are <!--PageBreak-->endemic to Iberia, being cavernicolous species with more or less evident troglomorphic features.</p>
            <p>The first species described from Iberia was <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus obcaecatus</tp:taxon-name> Simon, 1907, found only from a single locality: Cueva del Molino de Aso (Huesca), on the southern slopes of the Central Pyrenees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Simon 1907</xref>). The species description was originally based on a single female specimen. The male was described several decades later (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Ribera 1979</xref>), from a series of both sexes collected from the same cave. The second Iberian endemic is <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus lusitanicus</tp:taxon-name> Fage, 1931, a native species of the karst landscape in central Portugal. This species was described on the basis of females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Fage 1931</xref>), its male was found half of a century later (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Ribera 1988</xref>). The third species, which was found in several caves in Asturias and Cantabria (north-western Iberian Peninsula) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Ribera and Guerao, 1995</xref>), is <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus luquei</tp:taxon-name> Ribera &amp; Guerao, 1995. Finally, <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus murgis</tp:taxon-name> Ribera &amp; De Mas, 2003 was described from a cave in the province of Almeria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Ribera and De Mas 2003</xref>). Overall, ranges of these species are rather small, in two species (<tp:taxon-name>Nesticus obcaecatus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus murgis</tp:taxon-name>) being restricted to a single cave.</p>
            <p>This work describes a new cavernicolous species whose distribution includes several karst landscapes of the different mountain formations that make up the Sistema Bético, the ridge in southern Iberian Peninsula.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods"><title>Materials and methods</title>
            <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
                <p>Abbreviations used in the text are as follows: PL = prosoma length (from posterior edge of carapace to front edge of clypeus, measured at midline); PW = maximum prosoma width; OL = opisthosoma length (excluding the pedicel); OW = maximum opisthosoma width; MA = median apophysis; Mt = metatarsus; Tb = tibia; TTA = theridioid tegular apophysis; TTA p1 = process 1 of TTA; TTA p2 = process 2 of TTA; TL = total length (excluding the pedicel). Eyes: AM = anterior median; AL = anterior lateral; PM = posterior median; PL = posterior lateral; i = immature; sub = subadult; GEV = Grupo de Espeleología de Villacarrillo.</p>
                <p>Female vulva was removed and treated with 30% KOH. After observation and drawing, the vulva was washed in distilled water and stored in 70% ethanol. Left male palps were illustrated in all cases. We follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Coyle and McGarity (1992)</xref> for describing the paracymbium, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Huber (1993)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Agnarsson et al. (2007)</xref> for other parts of male and female copulatory organs. Holotype and paratypes have been deposited in the Arachnida Collection of the CRBA (Centre de Recursos de Biodiversitat Animal) at the University of Barcelona. Catalogue numbers are given in brackets.</p>
                <p>A Nikon Coolpix 4500 digital camera attached to a stereomicroscope was used to capture images. Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Coleman (2003)</xref> and with the aid of a Trust Scroll Tablet TB-4200 the samples were drawn with repeated reference to the specimen under the microscope. The specimens used for SEM studies were dehydrated with alcohol gradient<!--PageBreak--> dehydration and ultrasonically cleaned. They were then critical-point dried and were mounted and covered with gold and examined using a HITACHI S-2300 Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM) (SCT, Universitat de Barcelona, Spain).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Phylogeny"><title>Phylogeny</title>
                <p><bold>Taxonomic sampling</bold>. Taxa analyzed in the present study are listed in Appendix 1. All the Iberian species are included except <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus murgis</tp:taxon-name> due to impossibility to obtain fresh material for DNA analysis. <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus eremita</tp:taxon-name> Simon, 1879 from Croatia and <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus ionescui</tp:taxon-name> Dumitrescu, 1979 from Romania are also included to test the monophyly of Iberian species. Sequence from <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus</tp:taxon-name> sp. from China (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Arnedo et al. 2004</xref>) was also included in the analysis as a more distantly related <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus</tp:taxon-name> species that was used to root the tree.</p>
                <p><bold>Sample Storage and DNA Extraction</bold>. Specimens were preserved in 95% or absolute ethanol and stored at 4°C. Total genomic DNA was extracted from legs of a single specimen using the QIamp® DNA Mini Kit (QIAGEN) following the manufacturer’s protocols. The approximate concentration and purity of the DNA obtained were verified using 1% agarose/TBE gel electrophoresis.</p>
                <p><bold>PCR Amplification and Sequencing</bold>. Two regions of the mitochondrial DNA corresponding to a fragment of the cytochrome oxidase I gene (<italic>cox1</italic>) and 16S rRNA (<italic>rrnL</italic>) were selectively amplified using PCR with the following primer pairs: for <italic>cox1</italic> C1-J-1718 (5' GGAGGATTTGGAAATTGATTAGTTCC 3') with C1-N-2191 (5' CCCGGTAAAATTAAAATATAAACTTC 3') (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Simon et al. 1994</xref>); for <italic>rrnL</italic> LR-N-13398 (5' CGCCTGTTTATCAAAAACAT 3') (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Simon et al. 1994</xref>) with LR-J-12864 (5' CTCCGGTTTGAACTCAGATCA 3') (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Arnedo and Gillespie 2006</xref>). The PCR reaction mixture contained a final concentration of 0.2 μM of each primer, 0.2 mM of each dNTPs, 0.5 U Taq polymerase (Promega), with the supplied buffer, and 1.5–2.5 mM Mg Cl2 in a final volume of 25 μL.</p>
                <p>A Perkin-ElmerCetus Moldel 480 thermocycler was used to perform 35 iterations of the following cycle: 30s at 95°C, 45s at 45°C, and 1 min at 72°C, beginning with an additional step of 3 min at 95°C, and ending with another step of 10 min at 72°C. PCR results were visualized by means of a 1% agarose/TBE gel. Amplified products were purified using Microcon PCR columns following the manufacturer’s specifications. Purified products were directly cycle-sequenced from both strands using ABI BigDye (Applied Biosystems) chemistry, precipitated in DyeEx Spin kit (Qiagen, Chatsworth, CA) columns, and run out on ABI Prism 377 (Applied Biosystems) automated sequencers. Sequencing reactions were performed in our lab with the forward and reverse PCR primers. Resulting product were run and analyzed at the Serveis Científico-Tècnics of the Universitat de Barcelona.</p>
                <p><bold>Alignment</bold>. Raw sequences were compared against chromatograms and complementary contigs built and edited using the Geneious Pro 3.6.2 software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genious.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.genious.com</ext-link>). Sequences were manipulated and preliminary manual alignments constructed using BioEdit V.7.0.5.3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Hall 1999</xref>). Alignment of the <italic>cox1</italic> gene fragments <!--PageBreak-->was trivial due to the absence of length polymorphism. However, there were some length differences among the <italic>rrnL</italic> fragments, suggesting the occurrence of insertion/deletion events during the evolution of these sequences. Automatic alignment algorithms have been considered as superior to manual protocols due to their objectivity and repeatability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Giribet et al. 2002</xref>). Automatic alignments for the <italic>rrnL</italic> data set were constructed with the program MAFFT v 6.240 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Katoh and Toh 2007</xref>) The alignment was constructed using the manual strategy option set Q-INS-I, the most accurate multiple sequence alignment, whit default options. All analyses were performed by coding gaps as absence/presence character following Simmons and Ochoterena’s simple coding method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Simmons and Ochoterena 2000</xref>), as implemented in the software GAPCODER (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Young and Healy 2002</xref>). This method allows the inclusion of gap information in phylogenetic inference, minimizing the effect of increasing the weight of overlapping multiple non-homologous gaps that results from scoring gaps as 5th state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Pons and Vogler 2006</xref>).</p>
                <p><bold>Phylogenetic analyses</bold>. Parsimony analyses of the combined data matrices were conducted with the program Winclada v.1.00.08 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nixon 2002</xref>) using the following heuristic tree search strategy: 1000 iterations of 10 Wagner trees constructed with random addition taxa and subsequent TBR branch swapping, holding a total maximum of 10000 trees. This program facilitated combination of the different gene fragments in a single data set for simultaneous analyses and also provided additional statistics for those trees (CI and RI values). Clade support was assessed via Bootstrap (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Felsenstein 1985</xref>) as implemented in Winclada, based on 1000 bootstrap replicates with 20 iterations and 10 starting trees per replica. Uncorrected genetic distances between taxa of <italic>cox 1</italic> gene from terminal taxa were assessed with the program MEGA v.3.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Kumar et al. 2004</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Nesticus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">baeticus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:51EE521C-466B-47F7-81F6-244EF9FA8547</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"/>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"/>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">17</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p> <bold>Holotype:</bold> ♂ (1619-A25) Cueva de la Murcielaguina, Hornos, Jaén, Spain, 5.11.2006, GEV leg. <bold>Paratypes:</bold> 2♀♀ (1619-A25) same locality and data; 1♀ (1720-A29) same locality, 30.12.2007, GEV leg.; 1♀ (1530-A22) Sima HO-55, Hornos, Jaén, 14.8.2006, GEV leg. (drawings and description of the female are based on this specimen); 1♂ (1524-A21), 1♂sub., 1♀, 7i (1525-A22) same locality and data, GEV Leg.; 1♀ (3811–150) Sima de los Alhaurinos, Hornos, Jaén, 12.05.2002, GEV leg.; 1♀ (3812–150) same locality and data; 2i (3860-151) Sima del Campamento, Hornos, Jaén, 02.03.2003, GEV leg.; 2i, (5023-189) same locality, 27.08.2004, GEV leg.; 2♂sub., 1f, 5i (1157-A07) Sima del Laberinto, Hornos, Jaén, 04.02.2006 López, A. &amp; Pérez, A. leg.; 1♀, 1♀sub. (1343-A14) Cueva SE-20, Santiago de la Espada<!--PageBreak--> - Pontones, Jaén, 30.04.2006, GEV leg.; 1i (1539-A22) Sima del Órgano (HO-25), Hornos, Jaén, 14.08.2006, GEV leg.; 1i (5014-189) Sima Irene, Hornos, Jaén, 15.02.2004, GEV leg.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p>Single most parsimonious tree (L = 3454, CI = 0.447, RI = 0.769) found by MP analysis of the combined data set(<italic>cox1</italic>=472 bp, <italic>rrnL</italic>=456 bp and 22 gap characters) of Iberian <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus</tp:taxon-name> species (except <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus murgis</tp:taxon-name>), <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus ionescui</tp:taxon-name> from Romania and <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus eremita</tp:taxon-name> from Croatia. Numbers on nodes represent bootstrap support values. The outgroup <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus</tp:taxon-name> X130 is from China. Numbers on terminals refers to different localities (see material examined)</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The Latin name ‘<italic>baeticus’</italic> means ‘from <tp:taxon-name>Baetica</tp:taxon-name>’ (the south of Spain) and refers to the ‘Sistema Bético’, the ridge containing the karst landscapes from where the new species was collected.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> Males clearly differ from those of other <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus</tp:taxon-name> species in the shape of paracymbium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 4–5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">8–10</xref>) and in the TTA structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 3–5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">11–12</xref>). In females, the development of the median septum of the vulva (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 14–16</xref>), the shape of the spermathecae and adjoining structures are also diagnostic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 17</xref>). The degree of ocular reduction of the AM eyes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) is also characteristic compared to other Iberian species.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 2–7.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.: <bold>2</bold> female (1525) frontal view <bold>3–6</bold> male palp (Holotype). <bold>3</bold> retrolateral view <bold>4</bold> prolateral view <bold>5</bold> ventral view <bold>6</bold> frontal view <bold>7</bold> dorsal view. Abbreviations: <bold>E</bold> embolus <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis <bold>P</bold> paracymbium <bold>ST</bold> subtegulum <bold>T</bold> tegulum <bold>TTA</bold> theridioid tegular apophysis. Scale bar in μm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                    <p>On the basis of morphology, <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. lies within the group including <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus murgis</tp:taxon-name> (known from Almería) and <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus luquei</tp:taxon-name> (an endemic to northwestern Spain). The shape and arrangement of the median apophysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">11–12</xref>), the embolus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 3–7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">11–12</xref>) and the paracymbial processes of male palp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 8–10</xref>), plus the location and structure of the spermathecae and vulval glands of the female (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 17</xref>) are similar in all three species. <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.differs more significantly from <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus lusitanicus</tp:taxon-name>, both in the morphology of the copulatory organs of both sexes.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 8–13.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., male (holotype). <bold>8–10</bold> paracymbium <bold>8</bold> lateral view <bold>9</bold> frontal view <bold>10</bold> ventral view <bold>11</bold> median apophysis and theridioid tegular apophysis, ventral view <bold>12</bold> ditto, retrolateral view <bold>13</bold> apical protuberance of TTA p2. Abbreviations: <bold>di</bold> distal process <bold>dm</bold> dorsomedial apophysis <bold>do</bold> dorsal process <bold>E</bold> embolus <bold>P</bold> paracymbium <bold>pd</bold> paradistal apophysis <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis <bold>TTA</bold> theridioid tegular apophysis <bold>TTA p1</bold> process 1 of TTA <bold>TTA p2</bold> process 2 of TTA <bold>v</bold> ventral process. Sacale bar in μm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <p>The new species cannot be assigned to <tp:taxon-name>Carpathonesticus</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Typhlonesticus</tp:taxon-name> or <tp:taxon-name>Canarionesticus</tp:taxon-name>, and differs from their representatives in having a different shape, ramification and modifications associated to the paracymbium, the general structure and arrangement of the embolous, as well as of the p1 and p2 TTA processes. Yet, the shape and disposition of the spermathecas and vulval glands shows markedly differences.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description of the male"><title>Description of the male</title>
                    <p>(Holotype). <italic>Coloration:</italic> carapace uniform yellowish. Opisthosoma grayish, with some clearly-marked darker patches. Appendages of the same colour as the carapace, slightly darker around distal segments. Sternum yellowish, slightly paler than the carapace. <italic>Carapace</italic>: approximately circular in dorsal view. Cephalic region not raised but differentiated from the rest of the prosoma. Fovea and thoracic grooves clearly visible. Significantly reduced eyes, more evident in the AM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Eye size and interocular distances: AM = 0.03; AL = 0.07; PM = 0.06; PL = 0.07; AM - AL = 0.14 AL; AM - AM = 0.03; PM - PL = 0.14; PM - PM = 0.18 PM; PL - AL almost touching. <italic>Opisthosoma</italic>: sub-elliptical in dorsal view. <italic>Appendages</italic>: prolateral margin of the chelicerae with 3 teeth, the two distal ones larger. <italic>Male palp</italic>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 3–7</xref>). Paracymbium large (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 3–5</xref>) with well-developed dorsal and ventral processes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 8–10</xref>). Broad, translucent dorsal process with a saw-toothed upper edge (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 8–10</xref>). Dorsomedial apophysis small and pointed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 9</xref>). Ventral region apically notched (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 10</xref>). Short paradistal region, almost conical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 8–9</xref>). Distal apophysis long, acuminate and slightly curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 8–10</xref>). Poorly developed MA, reduced to a small fingerlike process fused to the tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">11–12</xref>). Conductor absent. TTA with two processes, TTA p1 and TTA p2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 11–12</xref>) (homologous to p1-p6 processes of conductor complex in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Huber 1993</xref>). TTA p1 is saddle-shaped, longer than wide, slightly curved and serrated in the central area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">figs 11, 12</xref>). TTA p2 is located in apical position and serves as a conductor of embolus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">figs 11–13</xref>). Embolus filamanteous with a semicircular course progressively acuminate towards the apex and partially bordering the tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 3–5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">12</xref>). <italic>Measurements</italic>: PL: 3.3; PW: 3.1; OL: 3.1; OW: 2.4; total body length = 6.4. Leg I&gt;leg IV&gt;leg II&gt; leg III.</p>
                    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leg</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">coxa</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">troc.</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">femur</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">patella</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">tibia</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">meta.</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">tarsus</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">total</th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.8</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description of the female"><title>Description of the female.</title>
                    <p>All characters as in male except: cephalic region scarcely differentiated, much less marked than in male. Fovea visible and thoracic grooves not clearly marked. <italic>Epigynum and vulva.</italic> Epigynum wide and convex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 14–16</xref>). Median septum wide and prominent, caudally projected by a bell-shaped flap. Vulva (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 17</xref>, drawing is based on specimen 3812-150) with well-developed lateral pockets divided by a ventral fold in two, the lateral and medial part. <italic>Measurements:</italic> PL: 2.9; PW: 2.9; OL: 3.4; OW: 2.6; total length = 6.3. Leg I&gt;leg IV&gt;leg II&gt; leg III.</p>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 14–17.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., female. <bold>14</bold> epigynum (1530) ventral view <bold>15</bold> ditto, caudal view <bold>16</bold> epigynum (1619) ventral view <bold>17</bold> vulva ventral view. Abbreviations: <bold>CO</bold> copulatory orifice <bold>ID + FD</bold> insemination duct + fertilization duct <bold>MS</bold> median septum <bold>S</bold> spermathecae <bold>VPL</bold> vulval pocket lateral <bold>VPM</bold> vulval pocket medial. Scale bar in μm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-001-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leg</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">coxa</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">troc.</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">femur</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">patella</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">tibia</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">meta.</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">tarsus</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">total</th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.6</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. inhabits the karst landscapes of the high part of the Cazorla, Segura and Las Villas Natural Park (NE Jaén, Spain) where it has been found in 8 caves. Most of the material studied comes from the area surrounding the Tranco’s Reservoir, in Hornos, Jaén. The area is calcareous, lush and quite humid, with numerous, medium-sized caves, both horizontal and vertical. The specimens were generally located within the first few meters of the dark zone, their presence reaching towards the cave interiors, which were sampled more intensively.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Specimens and sequences, with corresponding Genbank accession numbers, analyzed in the present study, are listed in Appendix 1. Alignments of two mitochondrial genes and gap scores as presence/absence were merged resulting in a combined data matrix of 950 characters (<italic>cox1</italic>=472, <italic>rrnL</italic>=456 and 22 gap characters). Uncorrected <italic>cox1</italic> genetic divergences among terminal taxa are summarized in Appendix 2. Parsimony analyses of the combined data matrix yielded a single most-parsimonious tree of 705 steps (CI = 73 and RI = 62) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>)<!--PageBreak-->.</p>
            <p>The results show that the Iberian species do not constitute a monophyletic group. <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus luquei</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus lusitanicus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. form a clade with high bootstrap support (99%), while <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus cellulanus</tp:taxon-name> is nested within a clade that also includes <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus ionescui</tp:taxon-name>, from Romania, and <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus eremita</tp:taxon-name>, from Croatia. <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus obcaecatus</tp:taxon-name> is the sister group of the remaining species of the ingroup. This topology, along the high genetic divergences observed between <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus obcaecatus</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus cellulanus</tp:taxon-name> and the remaining Iberian species suggest the existence of tree independent colonization to the Iberian Peninsula. Preliminary results of a more extensive phylogenetic analysis, including almost all the Mediterranean species of <tp:taxon-name>Nesticidae</tp:taxon-name> (our work in progress), support this hypothesis.</p>
            <p>The morphology of both the male and female copulatory organs of this Iberian group of species (<tp:taxon-name>Nesticus luquei</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus lusitanicus</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus murgis</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.) shows important differences as compared to <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus cellulanus</tp:taxon-name>, the type species of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus</tp:taxon-name>, as well as to the <tp:taxon-name>Carpathonesticus</tp:taxon-name> species. Thus, the absence of paracymbial ramification, the shape and size of the median apophysis, plus clear differences in size and arrangement of the TTA processes constitute the major differences in the males. The number of spermathecae is the most noticeable character in the females.</p>
            <p>With regards to <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus obcaecatus</tp:taxon-name>, significant differences in the shape and structure of the paracymbium, the median apophysis and the TTA (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Ribera 1988</xref>), as well as in the shape of the epigynum and the arrangement of the spermathecae (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Fage 1931</xref>), indicate that this species is most distantly-related to all the Iberian endemics known to date. On the basis of the aforementioned characters <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus obcaecatus</tp:taxon-name> seems to be more closely-related to <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus idriacus</tp:taxon-name> Roewer, 1931 known from the eastern area of the Alps and to <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus morisii</tp:taxon-name> Brignoli, 1975 known from Italy. Besides, the conformation of the copulatory organs of these three species are very similar to <tp:taxon-name>Typhlonesticus absoloni</tp:taxon-name> (Kratochvil, 1933) known from Montenegro. Thus, all three species are likely to belong with <tp:taxon-name>Typhlonesticus</tp:taxon-name> as well. Yet, in order to prove or reject this assumption, a molecular phylogeny of all the Mediterranean Nesticidae is to be performed. Our future research is focused on resolving the phylogeny of the Mediterranean <tp:taxon-name>Nesticidae</tp:taxon-name> (work in progress) and will include most of the Mediterranean species to test the monophyletic status of current genera.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus obcaecatus</tp:taxon-name> shows highly troglomorphic characters, such as complete depigmentation, reduction of the eye size and their number (only six eyes), and is known from a single cave. These data alongside its phylogenetic uniqueness (basal position and a deep genetic distance from other Iberian congeners) suggest that this species may be considered a relict representative of an old colonization to Iberia, and should be a candidate for protection.</p>
            <p>Climatic relict hypothesis assume that adaptation and speciation to caves are mainly driven by climatic factors. The Pleistocene glacial cycles has been identified as de main driver of the evolution of cave-dwelling fauna in the Paleartic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Barr 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Vandel 1958</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">1964</xref>). The uncorrected genetic distances between <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus lusitanicus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Nesticus luquei</tp:taxon-name> range between 14.3 and 15.5%. Assuming an average substitution rate for arthropod mitochondrial genes between 2% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">DeSalle et al. 1987</xref>) to 2.3% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Brower 1994</xref>) we can conclude that the origin of these species preceded the Pleistocene glacial <!--PageBreak-->cycles and, hence that other climatic or environmental factors may have been responsible for the evolution of these taxa.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We would like to thank representatives of the caving groups who gave us support: Grupo de espeleología de Villacarrillo (GEV) and Grupo de Espeleología de Priego (GESP). Dr. Manuel Baena and Toni Pérez Fernández are thanked for providing us with most of the studied specimens, guiding us to some caves and for useful comments regarding the new species. We also want to thank Dr. M.A. Arnedo and Dr. S. Carranza for their helpful comments about the first draft. The Spanish Ministry of Education and Science grants CGL2004-05771 and CGL2006-13374/BOS supported this research. Alberto Lopez was supported by a grant (BES-2005-9591) from the Ministerio de Ciencia y Tecnología, Spain</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Agnarsson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coddington</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knoflach</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Morphology and evolution of cobweb spider male genitalia (Araneae, Theridiidae)</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Arachnology</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>334</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnedo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agnarsson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coddington</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> From a comb to a tree: phylogenetic relationships of the comb-footed spiders Araneae, Theridiidae) inferred from nuclear and mitochondrial genes.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source> <volume>31</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>225</fpage>-<lpage>245</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnedo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Species diversification patterns in the Polynesian jumping spider genus Havaika Prószyński, 2001 (Araneae, Salticidae).</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source> <volume>41</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>472</fpage>-<lpage>495</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> Cave ecology and the evolution of troglobites.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobzhansky</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname> et al.</surname></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Evolutionary biology</source>. <publisher-name>K. Holland Pub. Co.</publisher-name>, <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brower</surname><given-names>AVZ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Rapid morphological radiation and convergence among races of the butterfly <italic>Heliconius erato</italic> inferred from patterns of mitochondrial DNA evolution.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source> <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>6491</fpage>-<lpage>6495</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>DeSalle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prager</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Tempo and mode of sequence evolution in mitochondrial DNA of Hawaiian Drosophila.</article-title> <source>Journal of Molecular Evolution</source> <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>-<lpage>164</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Clerck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1757</year>)<source> Svenska spindlar, uti sinahufvud-slågter indelte samt under några och sextio särskildte arter beskerfne och med illuminerade figurer upliste.</source> <publisher-name>Stockoholmiae:</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>15</publisher-loc> <lpage>4</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> “Digital inking”: How to make perfect line drawings on computer. Organisms Diversity and Evolution 3.</article-title> <source>Electronic Supplement</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coyle</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGarity</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Two new species of <italic>Nesticus</italic> spiders from the southern Appalachians (Araneae, Nesticidae).</article-title> <source>The Journal of Arachnology</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>-<lpage>168</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fage</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1931</year>)<article-title> Araneae, 5e série, précédée d’un essai sur l’évolution souterraine et son déterminisme. In Biospeologica LV.</article-title> <source>Archives de Zoologie Expérimentale et générale</source> <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>291</lpage>.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap.</article-title> <source>Evolution</source> <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>783</fpage>-<lpage>791</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Giribet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muona</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> DNA multiple sequence alignments</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>DNA Multiple Sequence Alignments</source>. <publisher-loc>Basel</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Birkhauser-Verlag</publisher-name>, <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>114</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT.</article-title> <source>Nucleic Acids Symposium Series</source> <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Genital mechanics and sexual selection in the spider <italic>Nesticus cellulanus</italic> (Araneae: Nesticidae).</article-title> <source>Canadian journal of zoology</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>2437</fpage>–<lpage>2447</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> PartTree: an algorithm to build an approximate tree from a large number of unaligned sequences.</article-title> <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>372</fpage>-<lpage>374</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> MEGA3: Integrated software for Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis and sequence alignment.</article-title> <source>Briefings in bioinformatics</source> <volume>5</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>150</fpage>-<lpage>163</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> WinClada</article-title>. In: <publisher-loc>Ithaca</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>New York</publisher-name>: Published by the Author.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>The world spider catalog, Version 11.0.</source> <publisher-name>American Museum of Natural History</publisher-name>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://research.amnh.org/entomology/spiders/catalog/index.html" xlink:type="simple">http://research.amnh.org/entomology/spiders/catalog/index.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pons</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Size, frequency, and phylogenetic signal of multiple-residue indels in sequence alignment introns.</article-title> <source>Cladistics</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>-<lpage>156</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> Distribution des Nesticidae cavernicoles de la Péninsule Ibérique.</article-title> <source>Revue Arachnologique</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>291</fpage>-<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> Descripción del macho de Nesticus lusitanicus Fage 1931. (Araneae, Nesticidae). Publicaciones del. Departamento de Zoología.</article-title> <source>Barcelona</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> Nesticus luquei sp. n. (Arachnida, Araneae) une nouvelle espèce cavernicole du nord de l’espagne. Mémoires de.</article-title> <source>Biospéologie</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>-<lpage>124</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Mas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barranco</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Araneidos cavernícolas de la provincia de Almeria (I) y descripción de cuatro especies nuevas</article-title>. <source>Revista Ibérica Aracnología</source>. <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochoterena</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Gaps as Characters in Sequence-Based Phylogenetic Analyses.</article-title> <source>Systematic Biology</source> <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>369</fpage>-<lpage>381</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1907</year>)<article-title> Araneae, Chernetes et Opiliones (Première série). In: Biospeologica III.</article-title> <source>Archives de Zoologie Expérimentale et générale</source> <volume>6</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>537</fpage>-<lpage>553</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frati</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckenbach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crespi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flook</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Evolution, weighting, and phylogenetic utility of mitochondrial gene sequences and a compilation of conserved polymerase chain reaction primers</article-title>. <source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>651</fpage>–<lpage>701</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>)<article-title> La répartition des cavernicoles et la paleogéographie. Proceedings 2 Congress.</article-title> <source>International of Speleology</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<source> Biospeologie.</source> <publisher-name>La biologie des animaux cavernicoles. Gauthier-Villars. Paris.</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>61</publisher-loc> <lpage>9</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>GapCoder. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.trinity.edu/nyoung/GapCoder/Download.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.trinity.edu/nyoung/GapCoder/Download.html</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
        </ref-list>
        <app-group>
        		<app id="App1"><title>Appendix 1</title>
			           	 <p>Species included in the cladistic analysis and GenBank accession numbers for the cox1 and <italic>rrnL.</italic> All accession numbers starting with EU are new sequences obtained in the present study.</p>
			           	 <table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
			           	 <table>
			           	     <tbody>
			           	         <tr>
			           	             <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">species</th>
			           	             <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locality</th>
			           	             <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">cox1</th>
			           	             <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrnL</th>
			           	         </tr>
			           	         <tr>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus obcaecatus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cueva del Molino de Aso, Valle de Añisclo, Huesca, Spain</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746428</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746437</td>
			           	         </tr>
			           	         <tr>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus luquei</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cueva de la Picona, San Pedro de Carmona, Cabuerniga, Cantabria, Spain</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746430</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746439</td>
			           	         </tr>
			           	         <tr>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus lusitanicus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Algar de Marradinhas II Concelho de Alcanena, Portugal</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746429</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746438</td>
			           	         </tr>
			           	         <tr>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sima Irene, Hornos, Jaén, Spain</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746431</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746440</td>
			           	         </tr>
			           	         <tr>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sima del Campamento, Hornos, Jaén, Spain</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746432</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746441</td>
			           	         </tr>
			           	         <tr>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus baeticus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sima de los Alhaurinos, Hornos, Jaén, Spain</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746433</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746442</td>
			           	         </tr>
			           	         <tr>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus ionescui</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pestera Tismana, Tismana, Romania</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746434</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746443</td>
			           	         </tr>
			           	         <tr>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus cellulanus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manantiales Monte Castro, Sueras, Castellón, Spain.</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746435</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746444</td>
			           	         </tr>
			           	         <tr>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nuesticus eremita</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cave Pishurka (=Paganetijeva Pécina), Korcula Is., Croatia.</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746436</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EU746445</td>
			           	         </tr>
			           	         <tr>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">“<italic><tp:taxon-name>Nesticus</tp:taxon-name></italic>” X130</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AY231024</td>
			           	             <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AY230941</td>
			           	         </tr>
			           	     </tbody>
			           	 </table>
			           	 </table-wrap>
			      </app>
			      <app id="App2"><title>Appendix 2.</title>
				            <p>Uncorrected genetic distances of <italic>cox 1</italic> gene between terminal taxa analyzed in the present study. Numbers on terminals refers to different localities (see material examined)</p>
				            <table-wrap id="T4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
				            <table>
				                <tbody>
				                    <tr>
				                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">obcaeca</th>
				                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">lusitan</th>
				                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">luquei</th>
				                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">baet5014</th>
				                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">baet3860</th>
				                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">baet3812</th>
				                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ionescui</th>
				                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">cellula</th>
				                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">eremita</th>
				                    </tr>
				                    <tr>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lusitanicus</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                    </tr>
				                    <tr>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">luquei</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.180</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                    </tr>
				                    <tr>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">baeticus5014</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.197</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.153</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                    </tr>
				                    <tr>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">baeticus3860</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.155</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                    </tr>
				                    <tr>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">baeticus3812</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.155</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                    </tr>
				                    <tr>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ionescui</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.159</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.164</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.160</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.161</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.161</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                    </tr>
				                    <tr>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cellulanus</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.153</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.168</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.176</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.168</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                    </tr>
				                    <tr>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">eremita</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.159</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.155</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.161</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.153</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.115</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
				                    </tr>
				                    <tr>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NesticusX130</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.193</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.195</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.204</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.206</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.206</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.174</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td>
				                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170</td>
				                    </tr>
				                </tbody>
				            </table>
				            </table-wrap>
				    </app>
        </app-group>
    </back>
</article>