<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.77.769</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                On the placement of the Cretaceous orthopteran Brauckmannia groeningae from Brazil, with notes  on the relationships of Schizodactylidae  (Orthoptera, Ensifera)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Heads</surname>
                        <given-names>Sam W.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
								</contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Leuzinger</surname>
                        <given-names>Léa</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
								</contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>Illinois Natural History Survey, Institute of Natural Resource Sustainability, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Illinois, USA</label></aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>Department of Geosciences, University of Fribourg, Switzerland</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Sam W. Heads (<email xlink:type="simple">swheads@illinois.edu</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Michael Engel</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>26</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>77</issue>
            <fpage>17</fpage>
            <lpage>30</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>30</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>18</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Sam W. Heads, Léa Leuzinger</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The fossil orthopteran <tp:taxon-name>Brauckmannia groeningae</tp:taxon-name> Martins-Neto (<tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Ensifera</tp:taxon-name>) from the Early Cretaceous Crato Formation of Brazil, currently misplaced at both the genus and family level, is transferred to the family <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name> and assigned to the extant genus <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name> Brullé; ergo, <tp:taxon-name>Brauckmannia</tp:taxon-name> enters synonymy under <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Brauckmanniidae</tp:taxon-name> enters synonymy under <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name>. <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus groeningae</tp:taxon-name> (Martins-Neto), <bold>comb. n.</bold> agrees in size and general habitus with extant members of the genus, but can be readily separated by the robust, subovoid form of the metatibiae and the distinctive morphology of the lateral metabasitarsal processes. This species represents the first fossil occurrence of <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name> and the only New World record of this ancient lineage. Phylogenetic relationships of the schizodactylids are reviewed and a sister-group relationship with <tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name> advocated based on a reappraisal of morphological and molecular evidence.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Orthoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Ensifera</kwd>
                <kwd>Gryllidea</kwd>
                <kwd>Schizodactylidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Brauckmanniidae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Brauckmannia</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Schizodactylus</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>phylogeny</kwd>
                <kwd>Crato Formation</kwd>
                <kwd>Early Cretaceous</kwd>
                <kwd>Brazil</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The Lower Cretaceous Crato Formation of northeastern Brazil is famous for the truly exquisite preservation of its remarkable fossil assemblage (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Grimaldi and Engel 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Heads et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Martill et al. 2007</xref> and contributions therein). Of the many animal and plant taxa hitherto reported from the Crato palaeobiota, insects are without doubt the most diverse and account for more than 75 percent of the total number of species described from the formation to date. Insect fossils occur in superabundance within the laminated limestones of the Nova Olinda Member, where they are frequently preserved as complete, fully articulated individuals with wings, setae, soft tissues and even original colour patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Grimaldi 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Martill and Frey 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Heads et al. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Martill et al. 2007</xref>). More than 300 species representing over 20 insect orders have been described from the Crato Formation to date (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Martill et al. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Heads et al. 2008</xref>) and given that the most diverse groups (notably <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Hemiptera</tp:taxon-name>) remain almost entirely unstudied, the total number of species is certain to be much higher. Indeed, this remarkable deposit is perhaps the most important source of fossil insects yet encountered in the Cretaceous of Gondwana (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Heads et al. 2008</xref>), with the potential to shed light on the evolution and biogeography of the insects during what is arguably one of the most dynamic periods in their history.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name> (crickets, katydids, grasshoppers and their kin) are well-represented in the Crato Formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Heads and Martins-Neto 2007</xref>) and constitute the most frequently encountered insect fossils in the Nova Olinda laminites. Both orthopteran suborders are present, including a diverse assemblage of Ensifera comprising the superfamilies <tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name>, “<tp:taxon-name>Hagloidea</tp:taxon-name>” and <tp:taxon-name>Stenopelmatoidea</tp:taxon-name> <italic>sensu lato</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Martins-Neto 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Heads and Martins-Neto 2007</xref>). Caelifera are represented by primitive <tp:taxon-name>Tridactyloidea</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Eumastacoidea</tp:taxon-name> and stem-acridomorphs of the paraphyletic ‘locustopsoid’ complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Martins-Neto 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Heads 2008</xref>). Crickets (<tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name>) are perhaps the most diverse component of this assemblage, though the <tp:taxon-name>Elcanidae</tp:taxon-name> are by far the most abundant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Heads and Martins-Neto 2007</xref>). Fossil <tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name> are rare in most Mesozoic deposits, though in the Crato Formation they represent as many as 30 per cent of all fossil insect specimens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bechly 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Martill et al. 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Heads et al. 2008</xref>). This remarkable diversity and abundance highlight the importance of the assemblage and yet, despite over 20 years of research, a comprehensive treatment of the <tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name> is still unavailable. Nevertheless, a detailed taxonomic revision is now underway (Heads in prep.) and will undoubtedly shed much-needed light not only on the evolution and biogeography of Cretaceous <tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name>, but also on the origins of the modern fauna.</p>
            <p>The unusual orthopteran <tp:taxon-name>Brauckmannia groeningae</tp:taxon-name> was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Martins-Neto (2007</xref>: 3–4, fig. 1) based on a single specimen from a large quarry complex<!--PageBreak--> to the northeast of Mina Pedra Branca, 4–5 km west of Nova Olinda on the northern flanks of the Chapada do Araripe (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Martill et al. 2007</xref> for locality details). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Martins-Neto (2007)</xref> assigned the genus to its own family, <tp:taxon-name>Brauckmanniidae</tp:taxon-name>, which he assigned to the superfamily <tp:taxon-name>Stenopelmatoidea</tp:taxon-name> <italic>sensu lato</italic>; a group comprising the <tp:taxon-name>Anostostomatidae</tp:taxon-name> (king crickets and wetas), <tp:taxon-name>Cooloolidae</tp:taxon-name> (Cooloola monsters), <tp:taxon-name>Gryllacrididae</tp:taxon-name> (leaf-rolling or raspy crickets) and <tp:taxon-name>Stenopelmatidae</tp:taxon-name> (Jerusalem crickets). However, Martins-Neto’s original description (2007) is cursory at best and suffers from numerous errors in the identification and interpretation of morphological structures critical to the proper placement of the fossil. Here, we present a detailed redescription of <tp:taxon-name>Brauckmannia groeningae</tp:taxon-name> based on a new and near-complete specimen, allowing us to establish its true identity as a species of the extant genus <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name> Brullé, 1835 and thus, the first fossil representative of the <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name>, or splay-footed crickets.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The holotype of <tp:taxon-name>Brauckmannia groeningae</tp:taxon-name> is in the private collection of Rafael Gioia Martins-Neto, referred to in his publications as the ‘Coleção de Sociedad Brasileira de Paleoartropodologia’ with the number RGMN 500. This collection was apparently stored at his home in Ribeirão Preto, São Paulo, though since his death in August 2010 its whereabouts are unknown. As a result, any discussion of the holotype presented herein is based entirely on the illustrations in the original description (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Martins-Neto 2007</xref>). However, we were recently able to examine a second, more completely preserved specimen in the Museum für Naturkunde, Berlin, Germany (MfNB). This new specimen is evidently conspecific with the holotype and allows us to redescribe the species and more accurately determine its systematic placement.</p>
            <p>The MfNB specimen was studied using a Zeiss Stemi SV11 zoom stereomicroscope and drawings produced with the aid of a camera lucida. Macro photographs were taken using a Nikon D700 digital SLR with a 60 mm macro objective. In addition, the following extant material was also examined: <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus brevinotus</tp:taxon-name> Ingrisch, 2002; <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name> (Werner, 1901); <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus burmanus</tp:taxon-name> Uvarov, 1935; <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus monstrosus</tp:taxon-name> (Drury, 1773); <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus hesperus</tp:taxon-name> Bei-Bienko, 1967; <tp:taxon-name>Comicus arenarius</tp:taxon-name> Ramme, 1931; <tp:taxon-name>Comicus calcaris</tp:taxon-name> Irish, 1986; <tp:taxon-name>Comicus campestris</tp:taxon-name> Irish, 1986; and <tp:taxon-name>Comicus capensis</tp:taxon-name> Brunner von Wattenwyl, 1888. Terminology used follows that normally employed for <tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name>, with the following distinctions concerning tibial armature: ‘spine’ refers to elongate, distally pointed, unsocketed processes; and ‘spur’ refers to all socketed processes of variable form (e.g. spine-like, blade-like, lobate, etc.). The geology, stratigraphy, environment and palaeobiota of the Crato Formation were most recently reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Martill et al. (2007)</xref> and contributions therein.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics"><title>Systematics</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature><label>Family</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Blanchard, 1845</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylites</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Blanchard 1845</xref>: 249.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylinae</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Ramme 1931</xref>: 163.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Ander 1939</xref>: 622.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Brauckmanniidae</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Martins-Neto 2007</xref>: 3, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                    <p> The <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name>, or splay-footed crickets, are a relict group of primitive Ensifera notable for their uniquely modified tarsi, which bear distinctive lobe-like lateral processes that serve to support the insects as they walk around their sandy habitats. The family is traditionally subdivided into two monotypic subfamilies: <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylinae</tp:taxon-name> Blanchard, 1845 containing the type genus <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name> Brullé, 1835 found primarily in India, Pakistan, Afghanistan and parts of Southeast Asia; and <tp:taxon-name>Comicinae</tp:taxon-name> Ander, 1939 containing the apparently paedomorphic genus <tp:taxon-name>Comicus</tp:taxon-name> Brunner von Wattenwyl, 1888 found only in southern parts of Africa. Schizodactylids are primarily nocturnal and are thought to be active predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Fletcher 1914</xref>). Indeed, species of <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name> have an intimidating habitus and clear predatory adaptations including raptorial prothoracic legs and powerful, enlarged mouthparts. Sub-social behaviour and cannibalism have been observed in populations of <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus monstrosus</tp:taxon-name> (Drury, 1773) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Choudhuri and Bagh 1974</xref>) and <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name> (Werner, 1901) was recently the subject of a detailed biological and ecological study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Aydin and Khomutov (2008)</xref>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature><label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Brullé, 1835</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Brullé 1835</xref>: 161. Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Gryllus monstrosus</tp:taxon-name> Drury, 1773.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Schizocephalus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Brunner von Wattenwyl 1888</xref>: 313, lapsus calami.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Dactylocomicus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Karny 1931</xref>: 102. Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Comicus inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name> Werner, 1901.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Brauckmannia</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Martins-Neto 2007</xref>: 4. Type species: <tp:taxon-name>Brauckmannia groeningae</tp:taxon-name> Martins-Neto, 2007, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> The genus <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name> as presently defined comprises all large and robust schizodactylids with wings developed and, with the exception of <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name> in which the wings are reduced, extending beyond the apex of the abdomen where they terminate in a conspicuous coil. <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name> species are further characterised by greatly enlarged mouthparts, a broad diamond-shaped labrum, and strong laterally compressed pro- and mesothoracic legs. The genus is readily separated from <tp:taxon-name>Comicus</tp:taxon-name>, the only other genus in the family, which is characterised by a markedly smaller and more gracile body (usually less than 25 mm in length), long, slender legs, and complete reduction of the wings.</p>
                    <!--PageBreak-->
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                    <p> Given the presence of distinctively coiled wings and well-developed lateral processes on the tarsi, there can be no doubt as to the placement of <tp:taxon-name>Brauckmannia groeningae</tp:taxon-name> in <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name>. In addition, there are no characters preserved in either the holotype (so far as can be seen from Martins-Neto’s illustrations) or the new material described below to exclude the species from the genus <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name>. Both fossil specimens match closely the general habitus, tarsal morphology and metatibial armature of extant <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name> species, and there are no convincing apomorphies to support separate generic placement.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">groeningae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Martins-Neto, 2007)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status>comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–2</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Brauckmannia groeningae</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Martins-Neto 2007</xref>: 4, fig 1.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p> Near-complete adult (sex indet.), MfNB-I.2079. Brazil, Ceará, Chapada do Araripe; Crato Formation, Nova Olinda Member, Lower Cretaceous.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus groeningae</tp:taxon-name> is distinguished from all congeners by the following characters: [1] robust and acutely subovoid metatibiae (in all extant species the metatibiae are of equal width along their entire length); and [2] distinctive blade- or paddle-like lateral processes arising in the distal half of the metabasitarsus (in all extant species these processes are triangular with a broad base and acute, posteriorly directed apex, and arise within the proximal half of the metabasitarsus).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description of MfNB-I.2079"><title>Description of MfNB-I.2079.</title>
                    <p> Large, near-complete specimen preserved in slightly oblique, dorsal aspect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2</xref>). Head capsule robust, 8.46 mm wide at genae; vertex short, c. 2.43 mm from occipital margin as preserved; occipital foramen large, broad; interocular distance 3.98 mm; compound eyes large, c. 2.61 mm wide dorsally. Pronotum markedly wider than long with distinctive marginal sulci; medial length 3.41 mm; width 9.36 mm. Pterothorax poorly preserved, c. 9.20 mm long. Wings incompletely preserved basally, extending posteriorly beyond abdominal apex, tightly folded in a distinctive apical coil. Abdomen somewhat crushed dorsolaterally, c. 16.12 mm long as preserved (apical part missing); first tergite (tg1) largely indistinct, at least 1.45 mm long; tg2 1.96 mm long; tg3 1.83 mm long; tg4 2.17 mm long; tg5 2.35 mm long; remaining tergites incompletely preserved but shorter than previous tergites; right lateral parts of abdominal sternites 1 through 5 visible next to corresponding tergal sclerites; pleural margin distinct. Total body length measured from fastigium verticis to abdominal apex 34.91 mm. Profemora robust and laterally compressed, 12.33 mm long; left profemur preserved in dorsal aspect, with distinct longitudinal dorsal carina; right profemur preserved in lateral aspect, with prominent transverse dorsolateral striae and distinct longitudinal inferior carina. Protibiae robust and lateral compressed, markedly inflated and acutely subovoid in form, 10.24 mm long; left protibia incompletely preserved in oblique dorsal aspect, bearing at least three spur sockets on outer lateral margin, spurs themselves not preserved; right protibia preserved in lateral aspect and somewhat crushed. Left prothoracic leg <!--PageBreak-->(L1 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>) with distal part missing, only apical part of ungues preserved. Right prothoracic leg (R1 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>) with tarsus incompletely preserved, at least 6.52 mm in total length; basitarsus subcylindrical in form, inflated apically, at least 1.75 mm long; second tarsomere short, c. 1.21 mm long, with prominent blade-like lateral process, 2.35 mm long; third tarsomere 2.10 mm long, with stout lateral process, 0.95 mm long; fourth tarsomere indistinctly preserved; ungues incompletely preserved, strongly curved, 1.44 mm long. Mesotrochantora small, c. 2.40 mm long and c. 2.20 mm wide. Mesofemora very slender, somewhat curved, inflated slightly at both the base and geniculae, 11.26 mm long and 1.46 mm wide at midlength. Mesotibiae similar in form to protibiae but somewhat larger and more acutely subovoid in lateral aspect, 10.75 mm long; left mesotibia incompletely preserved in dorsal aspect; right mesotibia preserved in lateral aspect, 3.36 mm wide at midlength, with two short subapical spurs preserved. Left mesothoracic leg (L2 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>) with tarsus preserved in dorsal aspect, 8.17 mm long; basitarsus small, 1.15 mm long; second tarsomere 1.25 mm long with broad, incomplete lateral processes at least 1.49 mm long; third tarsomere 1.28 mm long with stout lateral processes at least 0.62 mm long; fourth tarsomere basally inflated, apically slender, 2.18 mm long; ungues at least 2.08 mm long. Right mesothoracic leg (R2 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>) with tarsus preserved<!--PageBreak--> in lateral aspect, c. 8.10 mm long; basitarsus small, 1.55 mm long; second tarsomere 1.15 mm long with broad, apically incomplete lateral process at least 1.58 mm long; third tarsomere 1.23 mm long with incompletely preserved lateral process at least 0.95 mm long; margin between fourth tarsomere and ungues indistinct, combined length c. 3.91 mm. Metafemora large, robust, 19.78 mm long. Metatibiae markedly shorter than metafemora, 12.58 mm long; acutely subovoid in form, though more elongate than pro- and mesotibiae. Left metatibia preserved in dorsal aspect, somewhat crushed, with poorly preserved spines along dorsolateral margins; first apical spur 3.62 mm long; second apical spur 3.07 mm long; third apical spur incompletely preserved and visible only as a thin, 0.86 mm long fragment immediately adjacent and inferior to the second apical spur; sixth apical spur partially preserved in lateral aspect, 2.88 mm long and 0.96 mm wide apically. Right metatibia preserved in lateral aspect, 3.29 mm wide at midlength, with bases of poorly preserved spines visible along the dorsal margin; first apical spur blade-like, 3.80 mm long; second apical spur incompletely preserved immediately adjacent and inferior to the first apical spur, 2.06 mm long. Left metathoracic leg (L3 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>) with tarsus preserved in dorsal aspect, at least 8.76 mm long; basitarsus well-developed, at least 2.80 mm long, with large, broadly paddle-like lateral processes at least 2.41 mm long and 1.78 mm wide; second tarsomere short, 0.98 mm long, with large, blade or paddle-like lateral processes at least 2.28 mm long and 0.94 mm wide; third tarsomere incomplete, at least 1.98 mm long; combined length of fourth tarsomere and ungues c. 2.98 mm. Right metathoracic leg (R3 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>) with tarsus preserved in lateral aspect, at least 9.50 mm long; basitarsus well-developed, at least 2.66 mm long, with large, paddle-like lateral process at least 2.37 mm long; second tarsomere short, 1.04 mm long, incompletely preserved; third tarsomere indistinct, with basal part of small lateral process visible; fourth tarsomere and ungues poorly preserved, combined length 3.97 mm.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 1–2.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus groeningae</tp:taxon-name> (Martins-Neto, 2007), comb. n. from the Lower Cretaceous Crato Formation of Brazil. <bold>1</bold> Photograph of MfNB-I.2079 <bold>2</bold> Camera lucida drawing of MfNB-I.2079. Abbreviations: <bold>R1</bold> – right prothoracic leg; <bold>L1</bold> – left prothoracic leg; <bold>R2</bold> – right mesothoracic leg; <bold>L2</bold> – left mesothoracic leg; <bold>R3</bold> – right metathoracic leg; <bold>L3</bold> – left metathoracic leg; <bold>bt</bold> – basitarsus; <bold>fm</bold> – femur; <bold>pn</bold> – pronotum; <bold>tb</bold> – tibia; <bold>tr</bold> – trochanter; <bold>ug</bold> – ungues. Scale bars represent 10 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__000_@_1.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                    <p> The photograph of the holotype provided by Martins-Neto (2007: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1A</xref>) is of rather poor quality, though it is obvious that the specimen is not as well preserved as MfNB-I.2079. Moreover, the accompanying drawing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1B</xref>) is not only incomplete (for reasons that are unclear, the drawing only depicts part of the specimen) but does not correspond entirely with features clearly visible in the photograph. Nevertheless, the photograph shows sufficient details for the identification of the holotype as a schizodactylid; namely the presence of distinctive paddle-like lateral processes on the tarsi (clearly visible on both metatarsi though misidentified as ‘well-developed pulvilli’ by Martins-Neto), and apically coiled wings (not mentioned in the original description). Moreover, the holotype is clearly conspecific with MfNB-I.2079, agreeing with it not only in the relative proportions of the legs and overall size and habitus, but also in the distal origin of the metabasitarsal processes.</p>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus groeningae</tp:taxon-name> represents the only fossil record of <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name> and confirms the antiquity of an extant lineage hitherto unknown from the fossil record. Especially significant is that the species belongs to an extant, albeit relict genus, suggesting that the initial radiation of the <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name> occurred at least during the Jurassic if not earlier. Moreover, the presence of <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus groeningae</tp:taxon-name> represents the only record of <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name> from the New World, confirming presence of the family in the Atlantic<!--PageBreak--> rift zone of South America prior to its complete separation from Africa. An arid or semi-arid local environment for the Crato hinterland was first suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Martill (1993)</xref> and later supported by the discovery of solifuges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Selden and Shear 1996</xref>) and diplurid spiders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Selden et al. 2006</xref>). The development of thick and laterally extensive sandstones within the Crato Formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Heimhofer and Martill 2007</xref>) provides direct evidence for the existence of large local sand bodies and the preserved root balls of fossil plants often consist largely of sand-rich palaeosols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Mohr et al. 2007</xref>). Evidence for seasonal flash flooding is also well attested (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Martill et al. 2007</xref> and contributions therein) and might explain how the terrestrial elements of the biota were transported into the Crato lagoon. The presence of <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylus</tp:taxon-name> in sandy, xeric monsoonal environments today is therefore, entirely consistent with the hypothesised palaeoenvironment and would suggest that the habitat preferences of schizodactylids have changed little in over 100 million years.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>The relationships of the splay-footed crickets have proven somewhat controversial (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>), with the group generally regarded as a subfamily within <tp:taxon-name>Gryllacrididae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Ramme 1931</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Karny 1937</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Zeuner 1939</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Gorochov 1995a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">b</xref>) or as a subfamily close to <tp:taxon-name>Gryllacridinae</tp:taxon-name> but within <tp:taxon-name>Stenopelmatidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gorochov 2001</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Sharov (1968: 71)</xref> considered the group a ‘<italic>reliktovyǐ oskolok</italic>’ or ‘relictual fragment’ of <tp:taxon-name>Hagloidea</tp:taxon-name>, closest to <tp:taxon-name>Prophalangopsidae</tp:taxon-name> amongst the extant Ensifera. In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Ragge (1955)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Gwynne (1995)</xref> considered the <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name> as occupying a basal position within <tp:taxon-name>Gryllidea</tp:taxon-name> as sister-group to the <tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Ander (1939)</xref> included the family in his ‘<tp:taxon-name>Tettigonioidea</tp:taxon-name>’ (= <tp:taxon-name>Tettigoniidea</tp:taxon-name>), basal to a lineage giving rise to the <tp:taxon-name>Gryllacrididae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Stenopelmatidae</tp:taxon-name> <italic>sensu lato</italic>, <tp:taxon-name>Prophalangopsidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Tettigoniidae</tp:taxon-name>. This view was upheld at least in part by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Desutter-Grandcolas (2003)</xref> who, in her landmark cladistic study of ensiferan relationships, recovered <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name> as sister-group to a clade comprising <tp:taxon-name>Cooloolidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Stenopelmatidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Anostostomatidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Prophalangopsidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Tettigoniidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3g</xref>). However, recent molecular analyses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Jost 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Jost and Shaw 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Legendre et al. 2010</xref>) have consistently failed to support such a relationship, instead recovering <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name> (represented in all three studies only by <tp:taxon-name>Comicus</tp:taxon-name>) as sister-group to the <tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name> as proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Ragge (1955)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Gwynne (1995)</xref>.</p>
            <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                <label>Figure 3.</label>
                <caption><p>Competing hypotheses of ensiferan relationships, after: a – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Ander (1939)</xref>; b – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Zeuner (1939)</xref>; c – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Ragge (1955)</xref>; d – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Sharov (1968)</xref>; e – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Gorochov (1995a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">b)</xref>; f– <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Gwynne (1995)</xref>; g– <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Desutter-Grandcolas (2003)</xref>; h– <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Jost and Shaw (2006)</xref>; i – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Legendre et al. (2010)</xref>.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__000_@_2.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Morphological support for a schizodactylid–grylloid relationship comes primarily from the morphology and venation of the wings, namely: [1] marked reduction or loss of costal veins; [2] development in the tegmina of a longitudinal fold; [3] concurrent development of a distal medial fan in the tegmina; [4] development of fan-like folding in the cubital and medial systems of the hind wings; and [5] hind wing CuA two-branched. In addition, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Gwynne (1995</xref>; following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Ander 1939</xref>) noted the fusion of abdominal ganglion 7 with the posterior ganglionic mass (comprising fused abdominal ganglia 8 through 10) in both <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name> as a potential autapomorphy of <tp:taxon-name>Gryllidea</tp:taxon-name> <italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Ragge (1955)</xref>. Such an arrangement is also known in certain <tp:taxon-name>Rhaphidophoridae</tp:taxon-name><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> (e.g. <tp:taxon-name>Dolichopoda</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Hadenoecus</tp:taxon-name> and all <tp:taxon-name>Rhaphidophorini</tp:taxon-name>) though in other members of the family the 7th ganglion is free (e.g. <tp:taxon-name>Ceuthophilus</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Neonetus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Pristoceuthophilus</tp:taxon-name>). Indeed, the <tp:taxon-name>Rhaphidophoridae</tp:taxon-name> have traditionally been considered transitional between <tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name> and the other Ensifera (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Snodgrass 1937</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Ander 1939</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Desutter-Grandcolas 2003</xref>). The optimal tree recovered by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Legendre et al. (2010)</xref> in their reanalysis of the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Jost and Shaw (2006)</xref> molecular data set, placed the rhaphidophorids as sister-group to the rest of Ensifera (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3i</xref>). However, both <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Desutter-Grandcolas (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Legendre et al. (2010)</xref> noted that none of the existing morphological or molecular datasets are adequate to test rhaphidophorid monophyly and the group could be paraphyletic with respect to <tp:taxon-name>Gryllidea</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name> + <tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name>), <tp:taxon-name>Tettigoniidea</tp:taxon-name> (the so-called ‘katydid clade’ comprising <tp:taxon-name>Tettigoniidae</tp:taxon-name> and the various ‘stenopelmatoid’ families), or both (<italic>contra</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Béthoux and Nel 2002</xref>). Clearly, comprehensive and integrated morphological-molecular and neontological-palaeontological analyses are necessary and will undoubtedly shed much-needed light on ensiferan phylogeny.</p>
            <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 4</xref> shows a tentative reconstruction of relationships among major ensiferan groups based on a review of hypotheses presented in the various studies summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>. The phylogenetic relationships of the gryllidean taxa are based primarily on the molecular phylogeny of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Legendre et al. (2010</xref>; refer to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3i</xref> herein) with minor modification regarding the uncertain position of the obscure and highly derived <tp:taxon-name>Myrmecophilidae</tp:taxon-name>. We mapped phylogenetically informative morphological characters onto this topology and lists of character transformations are provided for each node in the figure caption. As discussed above, there appears to be considerable congruence between morphological and molecular data. Moreover, our attempt to place fossil <tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Protogryllidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Baissogryllidae</tp:taxon-name>) on this phylogeny did not radically alter the topology. Indeed, whilst the monophyly of these taxa is questionable, their relationships are clearly delimited in the current hypothesis. In particular, the <tp:taxon-name>Protogryllidae</tp:taxon-name> almost certainly represent a paraphyletic grade of basal crickets that gave rise to all other <tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name> sometime between the Late Triassic and Late Jurassic. The oldest protogryllids are known from the mid-Triassic (Carnian, <italic>c</italic>. 225 Ma) Molteno Formation of South Africa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Gorochov and Rasnitsyn 2002</xref>) which would suggest that the schizodactylid lineage is at least mid-Triassic in age. Such an extensive ‘ghost lineage’ is not uncommon among orthopterans, which are often frustratingly rare as fossils.</p>
            <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                <label>Figure 4.</label>
                <caption><p>Possible relationships among major ensiferan groups (both fossil and extant), with an emphasis on the infraorder <tp:taxon-name>Gryllidea</tp:taxon-name>. Thick lines indicate known geological ranges whilst thinner lines project likely ranges based on sister-group relationships. Arabic numerals at nodes indicate autapomorphic character transformations as follows: <bold>1</bold> (i) reduction or loss of cubitus; (ii) development of longitudinal radio-medial fold in tegmina; (iii) development of a distal medial fan in tegmina; (iv) development of fan-like folding in cubital and medial systems of hind wings; (v) hind wing CuA two-branched; (vi) fusion of abdominal ganglion 7 with posterior ganglionic mass <bold>2</bold> (i) hind wings, when developed, tightly folded at rest and apically coiled in a distinctive ring; (ii) well-developed, blade or paddle-like lateral processes present on the 2nd and 3rd tarsomeres of the pro- and mesotarsi and also on the metabasitarsus; (iii) predatory <bold>3</bold> (i) tarsi reduced to three tarsomeres; (ii) loss of the fastigium verticis; (iii) development of stridulatory file on ventral surface of tegminal CuP; (iv) presence of a dividing vein and harp between CuA2 and CuP <bold>4</bold> (i) tegminal medial fan expanded, forming a subapical medial lobe <bold>5</bold> (i) prothoracic legs fossorial; (ii) ovipositor vestigial <bold>6</bold> (i) compound eyes markedly reduced; (ii) all coxae large and closely approximated; (iii) pseudosegmented cerci; (iv) reduced ovipositor; (v) obligate inquilines of ants <bold>7</bold> (i) development of a tegminal mirror <bold>8</bold> (i) migration of dividing veins in the mirror to a position perpendicular with respect to long axis of tegmen.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="/lib/show_pic_by_filename.php?filename=__000_@_3.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Whilst it is clear that major group relationships within Ensifera remain largely unresolved (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Legendre et al. 2010</xref>), the morphological and molecular support for a <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name>–<tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name> sister-group relationship is compelling. Moreover, evidence for a close relationship between <tp:taxon-name>Schizodactylidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Gryllacrididae</tp:taxon-name> or any of the other ‘stenopelmatoid’ families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Zeuner 1939</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Sharov 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Gorochov 1995a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">2001</xref>) is based either on misinterpretation of non-homologous structures as homologous autapomorphies (e.g. gryllacridid pulvilli and the lateral processes of schizodactylid tarsi) or characters known to be plesiomorphic in Ensifera (e.g. four-segmented tarsi, ventral subapical spurs on the metatibiae etc.). A sister-group relationship between <tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name> and the Triassic <tp:taxon-name>Gryllavidae</tp:taxon-name> as proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Gorochov (1995a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">b</xref>) is difficult to demonstrate given that the latter family are known only from fossil wings. However, the tegminal venation of <tp:taxon-name>Gryllavidae</tp:taxon-name><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> is similar to that of <tp:taxon-name>Cyrtophyllitinae</tp:taxon-name> and it is likely that <tp:taxon-name>Gryllavus</tp:taxon-name> and related genera are closer to the paraphyletic “hagloid” assemblage than to the <tp:taxon-name>Grylloidea</tp:taxon-name>. With this in mind, and given the lack of convincing morphological or molecular autapomorphies for <tp:taxon-name>Stenopelmatoidea</tp:taxon-name> <italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Gorochov (2001)</xref>, it seems reasonable to accept a schizodactylid–grylloid clade as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 4</xref> until evidence is presented to the contrary.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We are grateful to Christian Neumann and Jason Dunlop for providing access to material and facilities; Hwaja Goetz for kindly taking photographs of the specimen; Michael Engel, David Martill, Torsten Wappler, Barbara Mohr and Rolf Kohring for valuable discussion; and two anonymous referees for insightful commentary on an early version of the manuscript. Support was provided by an Orthoptera Research Foundation Fellowship at the Illinois Natural History Survey (to SWH).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ander</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1939</year>)<article-title> Vergleichend-Anatomische und Phylogenetische Studien über die Ensifera (Saltatoria)</article-title>. <source>Opuscula Entomologica Suplementum</source> <volume>II</volume>, <publisher-loc>Lund</publisher-loc>, <lpage>306</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khomutov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> The biology, nymphal stages, and life habits of the endemic sand dune cricket <italic>Schizodactylus inexpectatus</italic> (Werner, 1901) (Orthoptera: Schizodactylidae).</article-title> <source>Turkish Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>427</fpage>-<lpage>432</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechly</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> New fossil dragonflies from the Lower Cretaceous Crato Formation of north-east Brazil (Insecta: Odonata).</article-title> <source>Stuttgarter Beiträge zur Naturkunde, Serie B (Geologie und Paläontologie)</source> <volume>264</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bei-Bienko</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> On the taxonomy and biology of a new <italic>Schizodactylus</italic> from Afghanistan.</article-title> <source>Acta Musei Moraviae</source> <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>194</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Béthoux</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Venation patterns and revision of Orthoptera sensu nov. and sister groups. Phylogeny of Palaeozoic and Mesozoic Orthoptera sensu nov.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1845</year>)<source> Histoire Naturelle des Insectes, leurs Moeurs, leurs Métamorphoses et leur Classification, ou Traité Élémentaire d’Entomologie</source>, Tome <volume>II</volume>. <publisher-name>Savy</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <lpage>524</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brullé</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1835</year>)<article-title> Cinquième Ordre. Orthoptères.</article-title> <source>In: Audouin JV, Brullé GA (Eds) Histoire Naturelle des Insectes</source> <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>225</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunner von Wattenwyl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1888</year>)<article-title> Monographie der Stenopelmatiden und Gryllacriden.</article-title> <source>Verhandlungen der Kaiserlich-Königlicen Zoologisch-Botanischen Gesellschaft in Wien</source> <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>-<lpage>394</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhuri</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagh</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<article-title> On the sub-social behaviour and cannibalism in <italic>Schizodactylus monstrosus</italic> (Orthoptera: Schizodactylidae).</article-title> <source>Revue d’Ecologie et de Biologie du Sol</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>569</fpage>-<lpage>573</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Desutter-Grandcolas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny and the evolution of acoustic communication in extant Ensifera (Insecta, Orthoptera).</article-title> <source>Zoologica Scripta</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>525</fpage>-<lpage>561</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Drury</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1773</year>)<source> Illustrations of Natural History, wherein are exhibited upwards of 240 figures of Exotic Insects</source>. <publisher-name>White</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, [vii] + <lpage>90</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1914</year>)<source> Some South Indian Insects and Other Animals of Importance Considered Especially from an Economic Point of View</source>. <publisher-name>Government Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Madras</publisher-loc>, <lpage>547</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorochov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> System and evolution of the suborder Ensifera (Orthoptera)</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Zoological Institute</source>, <publisher-name>Russian Academy of Sciences</publisher-name>, <volume>260</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage> [in Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
          	
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorochov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> System and evolution of the suborder Ensifera (Orthoptera)</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Zoological Institute</source>, <publisher-name>Russian Academy of Sciences</publisher-name>, <volume>260</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>212</lpage> [in Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorochov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> The higher classification, phylogeny and evolution of the superfamily Stenopelmatoidea</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>The Biology of Wetas, King Crickets and their Allies</source>. <publisher-name>CABI Publishing</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Wallingford</publisher-loc>, <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorochov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasnitsyn</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Superorder Gryllidea Laicharting, 1781 (=Orthopteroidea Handlirsch, 1903)</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasnitsyn</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quicke</surname><given-names>DLJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>History of Insects</source>. <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>, <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimaldi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> Insects from the Santana Formation, Lower Cretaceous, of Brazil.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</source> <volume>195</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>191</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimaldi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Evolution of the Insects</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, [xv] + <lpage>755</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gwynne</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of the Ensifera (Orthoptera): a hypothesis supporting multiple origins of acoustical signalling, complex spermatophores and maternal care in crickets, katydids and weta.</article-title> <source>Journal of Orthoptera Research</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>-<lpage>218</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heads</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> The first fossil Proscopiidae (Insecta, Orthoptera, Eumastacoidea) with comments on the historical biogeography and evolution of the family.</article-title> <source>Palaeontology</source> <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>499</fpage>-<lpage>507</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heads</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins-Neto</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Orthopterida</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martill</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechly</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loveridge</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>The Crato Fossil Beds of Brazil, Window into an Ancient World</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>, <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heads</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martill</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loveridge</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> An exceptionally preserved antlion (Insecta, Neuroptera) with colour pattern preservation from the Cretaceous of Brazil.</article-title> <source>Palaeontology</source> <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1409</fpage>-<lpage>1417</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heads</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martill</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loveridge</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Palaeoentomological paradise: the Cretaceous Crato Formation of Brazil.</article-title> <source>Antenna</source> <volume>32</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heimhofer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martill</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> The sedimentology and depositional environment of the Crato Formation</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martill</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechly</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loveridge</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>The Crato Fossil Beds of Brazil, Window into an Ancient World</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>, <fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingrisch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Orthoptera from Bhutan, Nepal and North India in the Natural History Museum Basel.</article-title> <source>Entomological Basiliensia</source> <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Irish</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> The species of <italic>Comicus</italic> Brunner v. Wattenwyl (Orthoptera: Schizodactylidae) with a discussion of their origin.</article-title> <source>Navorsinge Nasionale Museum Bloemfontein</source> <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>253</fpage>-<lpage>276</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jost</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<source> Phylogeny of Crickets (Orthoptera: Ensifera: Gryllidae) with Comparative Studies on the Evolution of Acoustic Communication. Unpublished Ph.D. Thesis</source>, <publisher-name>Harvard University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Massachusetts</publisher-loc>, [ix] + <lpage>222</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jost</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of Ensifera (Hexapoda: Orthoptera) using three ribosomal loci, with implications for the evolution of acoustic communication.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source> <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>510</fpage>-<lpage>530</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Karny</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1937</year>)<article-title> Orthoptera Fam. Gryllacrididae Subfamiliae Omnes</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wytsman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Genera Insectorum</source>, <volume>206</volume>. <publisher-name>Devrien</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>, <lpage>317</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B47"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Karny</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1931</year>)<article-title> On the geographical distribution of the Indo-African and Mediterranean Gryllacrids</article-title>. <source>Transactions of the Royal Society of South Africa</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Legendre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robillard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desutter-Grandcolas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> One hundred years of instability in ensiferan relationships.</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology</source> <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>475</fpage>-<lpage>488</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martill</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Fossils of the Santana and Crato Formations, Brazil</article-title>. <source>Field Guide to Fossils</source> <volume>5</volume>. <publisher-name>Palaeontological Association</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>159</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martill</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> Colour patterning preserved in Lower Cretaceous birds and insects: the Crato Formation of N. E. Brazil.</article-title> <source>Neues Jarhbuch für Geologie und Paläontologie, Monatshefte</source> <volume>1995</volume>:<fpage>118</fpage>-<lpage>128</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martill</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechly</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loveridge</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> The Crato Fossil Beds of Brazil, Window into an Ancient World</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>, [xvi] + <lpage>625</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins-Neto</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> Sistemática dos Ensifera (Insecta, Orthopteroida) da Formação Santana, Cretáceo Inferior do Nordeste do Brasil.</article-title> <source>Acta Geologica Leopoldensia</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>160</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins-Neto</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Systematics of the Caelifera (Insecta, Orthopteroidea) from Santana Formation, Araripe Basin (Lower Cretaceous, Northeast Brazil), with a review of the Family Locustopsidae Handlirsch.</article-title> <source>Acta Zoologica Cracoviensia</source> <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>-<lpage>228</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins-Neto</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> New Orthoptera Stenopelmatoidea and Hagloidea (Ensifera) from the Santana Formation (Lower Cretaceous, northeast Brazil) with description of new taxa.</article-title> <source>Gaea</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>BAR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardes-de-Oliveira</surname><given-names>MEC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loveridge</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> The macrophyte flora of the Crato Formation</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martill</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechly</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loveridge</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>The Crato Fossil Beds of Brazil, Window into an Ancient World</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>, <fpage>537</fpage>–<lpage>565</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ragge</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1955</year>)<source> The Wing-Venation of the Orthoptera Saltatoria, with Notes on Dictyopteran Wing-Venation</source>. <publisher-name>British Museum (Natural History)</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>159</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramme</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1931</year>)<article-title> Systematisches, Verbreitung und Morphobiologisches Aus der Gryllacriden-Unterfamilie Schizodactylinae (Orth).</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift für Morphologie und Ökologie der Tiere</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>-<lpage>172</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Selden</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shear</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> The first Mesozoic solifuge (Arachnida) from the Cretaceous of Brazil, and a redescription of the Palaeozoic solifuges.</article-title> <source>Palaeontology</source> <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>583</fpage>-<lpage>604</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Selden</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa Casado</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mesquita</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Mygalomorph spiders (Araneae: Dipluridae) from the Lower Cretaceous Crato Lagerstätte, Araripe Basin, north-east Brazil.</article-title> <source>Palaeontology</source> <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>817</fpage>-<lpage>826</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharov</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> Filogeniya ortopteroidnykh nasekomykh (Phylogeny of the Orthopteroidea)</article-title>. <source>Trudy Paleontologicheskogo Instituta</source>, <publisher-name>Akademiya Nauk SSSR</publisher-name> <volume>118</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage> [in Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Snodgrass</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1937</year>)<article-title> The male genitalia of Orthopteroid insects.</article-title> <source>Smithsonian Miscellaneous Collection,</source> <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B44"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Uvarov</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1935</year>)<article-title> A new species of the genus <italic>Schizodactylus</italic> from Burma (Orthoptera, Gryllacrididae).</article-title> <source>Annals and Magazine of Natural History</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>150</fpage>-<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B45"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1901</year>)<article-title> Die Dermapteren- und Orthopterenfauna Kleinasiens.</article-title> <source>Sitzungsberichte der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, Mathematisch-Naturwissenschaftliche Klasse (Abteilung 1)</source> <volume>110</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>306</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B46"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeuner</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1939</year>)<source> Fossil Orthoptera Ensifera</source>. <publisher-name>British Museum (Natural History)</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, [xiii] + <lpage>321</lpage> pp. + 80 pls.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>