<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
		    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.64.403</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new species of Stenobiella Tillyard (Neuroptera, Berothidae) from Australia</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Winterton</surname>
                        <given-names>Shaun L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:37F5AC48-EC3A-47ED-902B-2BD1467CCA72</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>California State Collection of Arthropods, California Department of Food &amp; Agriculture, 3294 Meadowview Rd. Sacramento, CA, USA 95832-1148</aff>
           
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Shaun L. Winterton (<email xlink:type="simple">wintertonshaun@gmail.com</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: A. Contreras-Ramos </p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
						
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>64</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>8</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>2</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Shaun L. Winterton</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:2DC68952-8896-4E71-A4FE-15A3D25D9D47</self-uri>
            <abstract>
        			
                <label>Abstract</label>                	
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella variola</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, a new species of beaded lacewing (<tp:taxon-name>Neuroptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Berothidae</tp:taxon-name>), is described and figured from south-eastern Australia. A preliminary key to <tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella</tp:taxon-name> species is presented.</p>
                	
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Berothidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Neuroptera</kwd>
                <kwd>lacewing</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <!--PageBreak-->
        </article-meta>
    </front>

    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Beaded lacewings (<tp:taxon-name>Berothidae</tp:taxon-name>) are a small family of <tp:taxon-name>Neuroptera</tp:taxon-name> comprising approximately 100 species occurring throughout most biogeographical regions. Members of the family are recognised by elongation of the pronotum, female usually with hypocaudae and substantial cubital veins in both wings. The larvae are associated with termites, and undergo a degree of hypermetamorphosis during development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Brushwein 1987</xref>).</p>
            <p>Four subfamilies of <tp:taxon-name>Berothidae</tp:taxon-name> are recognised: <tp:taxon-name>Rhachiberothinae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Cyrenoberothinae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Berothinae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Nosybinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Aspöck 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">MacLeod and Adams 1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">New 1989</xref>).<!--PageBreak--> <tp:taxon-name>Rhachiberothinae</tp:taxon-name> have been considered by some authors as a separate family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Aspöck and Mansell 1994</xref>) or as a subfamily of <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Willmann 1990</xref>). A fifth subfamily, <tp:taxon-name>Nyrminae</tp:taxon-name>, was erected by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Aspöck (1989)</xref> based on a highly autapomorphic species (<tp:taxon-name>Nyrma kervillea</tp:taxon-name> Navás) previously placed in <tp:taxon-name>Hemerobiidae</tp:taxon-name>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Penny and Winterton (2007)</xref> recently rediscovered the enigmatic genus <tp:taxon-name>Ormiscocerus</tp:taxon-name> Blanchard from Chile and placed it in <tp:taxon-name>Cyrenoberothinae</tp:taxon-name> based on various wing and genitalic characteristics; a placement also supported in phylogenetic analyses by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Winterton et al. (2010</xref>). Like <tp:taxon-name>Nyrma</tp:taxon-name> Navás, <tp:taxon-name>Ormiscocerus</tp:taxon-name> was also previously placed in <tp:taxon-name>Hemerobiidae</tp:taxon-name> and the wing venation of both species show numerous similarities, indicating that <tp:taxon-name>Nyrma</tp:taxon-name> should be placed in <tp:taxon-name>Cyrenoberothinae</tp:taxon-name> rather than as a separate subfamily. In a cladistic analysis of <tp:taxon-name>Berothidae</tp:taxon-name> using morphology <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Aspöck and Nemeschkal (1998)</xref> proposed a major reordering of the internal hierarchy and classification of the family with five subfamilies (<tp:taxon-name>Cyrenoberothinae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Trichomatinae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Protobiellinae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Nosybinae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Berothinae</tp:taxon-name>).</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella</tp:taxon-name> Tillyard (<tp:taxon-name>Berothinae</tp:taxon-name>) is an endemic Australian genus originally described based on two species (<tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella hirsutissima</tp:taxon-name> Tillyard and <tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella gallardi</tp:taxon-name> Tillyard) from Queensland and New South Wales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Tillyard 1916</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Kimmins (1930)</xref> described a third species of (<tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella pulla</tp:taxon-name> Kimmins) from the Northern Territory and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Aspöck and Aspöck (1984)</xref> subsequently described seven new species, bringing the total number of species to 10. An eleventh species is described and figured herein (<tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella variola</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.) from western New South Wales. A preliminary key to species is presented.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
            <p>Genitalia were macerated in 10% KOH at room temperature for one day to remove soft tissue, then rinsed in distilled water and dilute acetic acid and dissected in 80% ethanol. Preparations were then placed into glycerine, with images made with the aid of a digital camera mounted on a stereomicroscope. Genitalia preparations were placed in glycerine in a genitalia vial mounted on the pin beneath the specimen. Terminology follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">MacLeod and Adams (1967)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Aspöck and Aspöck (1984)</xref>. Specimen images were taken using a digital camera with a series of images montaged using Helicon Focus (©HeliconSoft) and links provided to Morphbank for high-resolution images. All new nomenclatural acts and literature are registered in Zoobank as per the recent proposed amendment to the International Code of Zoological nomenclature for a universal register for animal names (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Polaszek et al., 2005a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Pyle et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">ICZN 2008</xref>).<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Stenobiella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">variola</tp:taxon-name-part>
		                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1F7A88BE-C893-4737-A852-6DD0E569937B</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"/>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype"><title>Holotype</title><p> male, AUSTRALIA: New South Wales: Tintinallogy Station, 15.i.2010, light sheet, -31.9994°, 143.01706°, S.L. Winterton &amp; N.B. Hardy, light sheet (Australian National Insect Collection).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p>AUSTRALIA: New South Wales: 2 males, 1 female, same data as holotype (California Academy of Science Collection).</p>

                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella variola</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Female habitus. Photo credit: Shaun L. Winterton.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/403/supp/ZooKeys-064-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
 
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Distinctively contrasted variegated wing pattern; numerous white non-tapered setae on wings and body, pale patch basally in pterostigma, darker distally; dark scale-like setae absent from wings and abdomen; dark, elongate setae absent from mid coxa; single R1-Rs cross-vein; dark, elongate setae along entire posterior margin of both wings; female hypocaudae well developed; male paramere-mediuncus complex relatively large.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body length = 5.0–6.0 mm (male), 6.1 mm (female). <italic>Head</italic>. Black to light brown; anterior tentorial pits distinct; clypeus with dark band and minute pale pubescence; vertex irregularly covered with elongate, non-tapered white setae, multidirectional and partially appressed; raised lateral tubercle with elongate white setae admixed with several longer and more tapered black setae; antenna dark brown to black, scape covered with elongate white setae admixed with dark setae; pedicel with ring of <!--PageBreak-->dark setae basally, closely approximating a distal ring of white setae; 51 flagellomeres covered with fine dark setae; mouthparts brown with sparse black setae.</p>
                    <p><italic>Thorax</italic>. Pronotum wider than long, dark brown; two latitudinal depressions extending from midline, each with white setae along length; white setae along midline and around margin; admixed with slightly longer and tapered black setae along lateral and anterior margins; mesonotum light brown, blackish posterolaterally, white setae anteromedially in ‘V’ pattern, admixed with patch of dark setae; dark area glabrous; metathorax light brown with dark patches laterally, posterior portio with tapered pale setae; pleuron with extensive white, non-tapered setae. <italic>Wing</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Forewing length = 6.1 mm. Hind wing length = 5.2 mm. Forewing hyaline with extensive infuscate mottling; venation brown and tan mottled, numerous dark tapered macrosetae along wing veins with infuscate area around base of each seta; rows of white non-tapered setae extensive along all wing veins, admixed with dark, non-tapered setae, distribution of white and dark non-tapered setae relative to surrounding infuscation (i.e. more white setae in hyaline areas); costal and subcostal areas with extensive infuscation, white areas along costal margin with dark mark basad of pterostigma; pterostigma dark with white either side; dark, elongate along entire posterior margin of wing; single cross-vein between R1 and anterior trace of Rs; 4–5 gradate series cross-veins; distal CuA-MP cross-vein perpendicular to CuA and originating on anterior branch of distal CuA fork; hindwing hyaline; venation light brown to yellow; macrosetae absent, extensive fine tapered setae on all veins, more numerous in distal<!--PageBreak--> area of wing and much longer along entire posterior margin of wing. <italic>Legs</italic>. Uniform dark brown with extensive covering of elongate, white setae; setae shorter and darker on tarsomeres.</p>
                    <p><italic>Abdomen</italic>. Uniform brown to light brown; extensive pile of dark setae admixed with white setae, denser on sternites; stripe of white, non-tapered setae laterally from segment one to terminalia</p>
                    <p><italic>Male genitalia</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A–D</xref>). Tergite 9 + ectoproct rounded posteriorly, slightly acuminate distally; paramere-mediuncus complex very large with well sclerotised guide; hypandrium internum triangular.</p>
                    <p><italic>Female genitalia</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref>). Hypocaudae well developed, elongate; spermatheca large and highly convoluted in shape.</p>

                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella variola</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <bold>A</bold> forewing <bold>B</bold> hindwing. Scale line = 0.5 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/403/supp/ZooKeys-064-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>

                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 3.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella variola</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> Genital segments, lateral <bold>B</bold> paramere-mediuncus complex, lateral <bold>C</bold> same, ventral <bold>D</bold> hypandrium internum, ventral. Female genitalia: <bold>E</bold> spermatheca, ventral. Scale line = 0.2 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/403/supp/ZooKeys-064-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>

                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific epithet is derived from Latin, <italic>variola</italic>; spotted, mottled.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella variola</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is a distinctive species based on wing mottling and extensive wing and body covering of white, non-tapered setae. The male genitalia are similar in structure to <tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella theischingerorum</tp:taxon-name> Aspöck &amp; Aspöck, to which <tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella variola</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. appears to be closely related. No key to species of <tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella</tp:taxon-name> exists. The following key is based largely on the published descriptions by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Aspöck and Aspöck (1984)</xref><!--PageBreak--> and examination of additional non-type material in various collections; considering the high likelihood of new species being collected, it should be considered preliminary only. Both sexes are required for the key to work most effectively for some species.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to Stenobiella species"><title>Key to Stenobiella species</title>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing mostly or completely pale; relatively large species (ca. 8.0–10.0 mm forewing length); hypocauda present as a relatively short, blunt process</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing dark infuscate to stark maculate; size variable, but usually less than 9.0 mm forewing length; hypocauda as elongate process (rarely greatly reduced to a knob)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing with costal field dark</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella kaikai</tp:taxon-name> Aspöck &amp; Aspöck</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing uniformly pale</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella arrunja</tp:taxon-name> Aspöck &amp; Aspöck</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male paramere-mediuncus complex relatively small (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Aspöck and Aspöck 1984: figs 21, 31</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male paramere-mediuncus complex relatively large (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A–B</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black scale-like setae present on both wings</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella cardaleae</tp:taxon-name> Aspöck &amp; Aspöck</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black scale-like setae absent on both wings</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella muellerorum</tp:taxon-name> Aspöck &amp; Aspöck</td>
                                </tr>
																			
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female hypocauda knob-like; spermatheca large; paramere-mediuncus complex shape as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Aspöck and Aspöck (1984: fig. 11)</xref></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella pindana</tp:taxon-name> Aspöck &amp; Aspöck</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female hypocauda elongate; spermatheca smaller; paramere-mediuncus complex shape as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3 A–C</xref></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scales on forewing present</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella moma</tp:taxon-name> Aspöck &amp; Aspöck</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scales on forewing absent</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing largely uniform infuscate but not distinctly maculate</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella pulla</tp:taxon-name> Kimmins, <tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella gallardi</tp:taxon-name> Tillyard, <tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella hirsutissima</tp:taxon-name> Tillyard</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing distinctly maculate</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Costal field with alternating dark and pale regions to forewing tip (cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Aspöck and Aspöck 1984: fig. 46–47</xref>); hypandrium apex relatively tapered; paramere-mediuncus shape as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Aspöck and Aspöck 1984: figs 3–4</xref> (Northern Territory)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella theischingerorum</tp:taxon-name> Aspöck &amp; Aspöck</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Costal field with alternating dark and pale regions to forewing tip but with distinct pale area midway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>); hypandrium apex not as acutely tapered; paramere-mediuncus shape as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3A–C</xref> (New South Wales)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stenobiella variola</tp:taxon-name>  sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>Thank you to Dr Martin Hauser for help with translation of descriptions.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspöck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspöck</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Die Berothiden Australiens I: Neue spezies des genus <italic>Stenobiella</italic> Tillyard (Neuropteroidea: Planipennia: Berothidae). Zeitschrift der Arbeitsgemeinschaft Österr.</article-title> <source>Entomolgen</source> <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspöck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> The present state of knowledge of the family Berothidae (Neuropteroidea: Planipennia)</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gepp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspöck</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hölzel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <article-title>Recent Research in Neuropterology</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the 2nd International Symposium on Neuropterology (21–23 August 1984, Hamburg, Germany; held in association with the XVII International Congress of Entomology)</source>, <publisher-loc>Graz, Austria</publisher-loc>, <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspöck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemeschkal</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> A cladistic analysis of the Berothidae (Neuroptera).</article-title> <source>Acta Zoologica Fennica</source> <volume>209</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspöck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> <italic>Nyrma kervillea</italic> Navás – eine Berothide! (Neuropteroidea: Plannipennia). Zeitschrift der Arbeitsgemeinschaft Österr.</article-title> <source>Entomolgen</source> <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspock</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansell</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> A Revision of the Family Rhachiberothidae Tjeder, 1959, stat. n. (Neuroptera).</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>-<lpage>206</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brushwein</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Biomonics of <italic>Lomamyia hamata</italic> (Neuroptera: Berothidae).</article-title> <source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</source> <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>671</fpage>-<lpage>679</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature</surname></name> </person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Proposed amendment of the International Code of Zoological Nomenclature to expand and refine methods of publication.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1908</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimmins</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1930</year>)<article-title> A new Australian berothid (Neuroptera).</article-title> <source>Entomologist’s Monthly Magazine</source> <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>-<lpage>163</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>MacLeod</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> [1968] A review of the taxonomy and morphology of the Berothidae, with the description of a new subfamily from Chile (Neuroptera).</article-title> <source>Psyche</source> <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>265</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>New</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Planipennia. Lacewings.</article-title> <source>Handbuch der Zoologie (Berlin)</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>132</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Penny</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winterton</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Rediscovery of the unusual genus <italic>Ormiscocerus</italic> (Neuroptera: Berothidae: Cyrenoberothinae).</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences</source> <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Polaszek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agosti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Zarazaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beccaloni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Place Bjørn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brothers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Earl of</surname><given-names>Cranbrook</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evenhuis</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godfray</surname><given-names>HCJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krell</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipscomb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyal</surname><given-names>CHC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mawatari</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>PKL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyle</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taverne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Tol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>QD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005a</year>)<article-title>Commentary: A universal register for animal names</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>437</volume>: <lpage>477</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Polaszek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Zarazaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brothers</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evenhuis</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krell</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyal</surname><given-names>CHC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyle</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Tol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005b</year>)<article-title> ZooBank: the open-access register for zoological taxonomy: technical discussion paper.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of Zoological Nomenclature</source> <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>-<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyle</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Earle</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Five new species of the damselfish genus <italic>Chromis</italic> (Perciformes: Labroidei: Pomacentridae) from deep coral reefs in the tropical western Pacific.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1671</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tillyard</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1916</year>)<article-title> Studies in Australian Neuroptera. No. iv. The families Ithonidae, Hemerobiidae, Sisyridae, Berothidae, and the new family Trichomatidae; with a discussion of their characters and relationships, and descriptions of new and little-known genera and species.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Linnean Society of New South Wales</source> <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>332</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Willmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> The Phylogenetic position of the Rhachiberothinae and the basal sister-group relationships within the Mantispidae (Neuroptera).</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology</source> <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>253</fpage>-<lpage>265</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Winterton</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiegmann</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> On wings of lace: phylogeny and Bayesian divergence time estimates of Neuropterida (Insecta) based on morphological and molecular data.</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology</source> <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>349</fpage>-<lpage>378</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>