<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.251.3709</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new species of 
                    <italic>Lathrolestes</italic> (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae) from Ecuadorian Amazonia, with a key to the Neotropical species of the genus
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Reshchikov</surname>
                        <given-names>Alexey</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:CB7D7449-FF41-4268-B594-D85D8032A91F</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Veijalainen</surname>
                        <given-names>Anu</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:2A9B042E-9513-4670-B75D-C9BD9F19F90B</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Sääksjärv</surname>
                        <given-names>Ilari E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:2B80E7A4-FEA6-4493-80C1-5B28FB0CDB8F</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>The Insect Growth, Development and Behaviour Regulators Laboratory, Institute of Plant Protection, The Russian Academy of Agricultural Sciences, 3 Podbelsky shosse, Pushkin, St. Petersburg, Russia, 189620
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Zoological Museum, Section of Biodiversity and Environmental Sciences, Department of Biology, FIN-20014, University of Turku, Finland
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Alexey Reshchikov (<email xlink:type="simple">reshikov@gmail.com</email>)
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: G. Broad</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>18</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>251</issue>
            <fpage>21</fpage>
            <lpage>27</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>17</day>
                    <month>7</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>30</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Alexey Reshchikov, Anu Veijalainen, Ilari E. Sääksjärv</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:5F3240F1-0F6A-4F69-9825-9AA7B7AF9C3E</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Here we describe and illustrate a new parasitoid wasp species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes gauldi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> from the lowland rainforest of eastern Ecuador and provide a key to the Neotropical species of the genus. This is the first record of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Ctenopelmatinae</tp:taxon-name> from Ecuador.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Amazonia</kwd>
                <kwd>canopy</kwd>
                <kwd>Ctenopelmatinae</kwd>
                <kwd>parasitoid wasp</kwd>
                <kwd>tropical rainforest</kwd>
                <kwd>Yasuní
<!--PageBreak--></kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The <tp:taxon-name>Ctenopelmatinae</tp:taxon-name> is a species-rich subfamily that includes mostly koinobiont endoparasitoids of sawfly larvae (<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Symphyta</tp:taxon-name>). The subfamily is expected to be more diverse in temperate than tropical zones as the primary host groups are relatively scarce in tropical rainforest habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Gauld et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Veijalainen et al. 2012</xref>). In the Neotropics, the subfamily’s distribution extends across the entire region, but ctenopelmatines are still rarely encountered in Neotropical arthropod samples. The region’s ctenopelmatine fauna is very poorly known – there are only 69 described species from South America, Central America and Mexico (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Cresson 1874</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Townes 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Lanfranco 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Graf et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Barron 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Gauld et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Reshchikov 2011</xref>). In the most recent large study on Neotropical ctenopelmatines, 42 species from Costa Rica belonging to 14 genera were reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Gauld et al. 1997</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>In the present study, we describe a new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Foerster from Ecuadorian Amazonia. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a large genus of the ctenopelmatine tribe <tp:taxon-name>Perilissini</tp:taxon-name> with 85 described species including 4 species from Costa Rica (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Yu et al. 2012</xref>). The new species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes gauldi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., was collected by canopy fogging in the lowland rainforests of Ecuadorian Amazonia. This represents the first record of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Ctenopelmatinae</tp:taxon-name> from Ecuador and the Neotropical rainforest canopy. We also provide a key to four species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes</tp:taxon-name></italic> occurring in the Neotropical region and six closely related species from the southern United States and Mexico.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The holotype specimen was collected by Dr. Terry L. Erwin and his research team from the canopy of a lowland <italic>tierra firme</italic> rainforest at Onkone Gare, Department of Orellana, Ecuador, on the 2nd of July, 1995. The site is located near the Yasuní National Park 216 m.a.s.l. in primary rainforest where the vegetation is old and diverse. The annual precipitation exceeds 2500 mm and the temperature always remains above 10 degrees Celsius. For a more specific description of the study site, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Lucky et al. 2002</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Erwin et al. 2005</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>The lateral illustration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes gauldi</tp:taxon-name></italic> shows the habitus and coloration of the species. In addition, we provide more detailed illustrations of the face (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>), propodeum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>), ovipositor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>) and areolet of the fore wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>) of the holotype specimen. All digital pictures were taken using an Olympus SZX16 stereomicroscope attached to an Olympus E520 digital camera and combined using the CombineZP program created by Alan Hadley (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hadleyweb.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/index.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://www.hadleyweb.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/index.htm</ext-link>). The key below is modified from the one presented in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Gauld et al. (1997)</xref>. The morphological terminology follows mainly that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Gauld et al. (1997)</xref>, wing vein nomenclature is based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Ross (1936)</xref>.<!--PageBreak-->
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
                <title>Taxonomy</title>
                <p>Key to the Central and South American species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                </p>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metasoma entirely black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Wings strongly infuscate. Fore wing with resemblance of areolet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>). First metasomal tergite short, almost as wide as long. Area superomedia twice as wide as long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>). Ecuador
                                </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes gauldi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metasoma with yellow coloration or black with base of first tergite yellowish. Wings not infuscate or only slightly infuscate. Fore wing with areolet. First metasomal tergite longer, 1.25–2 times as long as wide. Area superomedia elongate</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesoscutum with notaulus strongly impressed anteriorly; upper part of head and mesosoma granulate, matt; first tergite of metasoma anteriorly slender with lateromedian longitudinal carinae separated by about the diameter of the spiracle. Costa Rica</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes karenae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Gauld, 1997
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesoscutum with notaulus vestigial; upper part of head and mesosoma fairly smooth and polished; first metasomal tergite anteriorly moderately stout with lateromedian longitudinal carinae separated by far more than the diameter of the spiracle</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tergites of metasoma uniformly reddish-yellow</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tergites of metasoma black and yellow or only some tergites reddish-yellow</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fore wing hyaline at apex. First tergite of metasoma short, 1.25 times as long as wide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fore wing infuscate at apex. First tergite of metasoma longer, 1.6–1.7 times as long as wide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area superomedia 1.4 times as long as wide. Costula arises from lateromedian longitudinal carina at the middle of area superomedia. White ring of antenna wide, approximately at flagellomeres 11–27. USA</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes asperatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Barron, 1994
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area superomedia 1.8 times as long as wide. Costula arises from lateromedian longitudinal carina at upper part of area superomedia. White ring of antenna narrower, approximately at flagellomeres 11–18. Mexico</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes tepeyollotlis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Reshchikov, 2011
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area superomedia twice as long as wide. Costula absent. First tergite of metasoma without lateromedian longitudinal carinae. USA</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes erugatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Barron, 1994
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area superomedia as long as wide. Costula present. First tergite of metasoma with lateromedian longitudinal carinae. Mexico</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes quetzalcoatlus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Reshchikov, 2011
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennal flagellum orange-brown basally. Pterostigma translucent golden. Area superomedia 1.5 times as long as wide. Costa Rica</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes haroldi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Gauld, 1997
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennal flagellum black basally. Pterostigma dark brown or black. Area superomedia shorter, 1.1–1.4 times as long as wide or longer, 1.6 times as long as wide</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Middle of face black. Area superomedia 1.6 times as long as wide. Posterior transverse carina straight. First tergite of metasoma twice as long as wide, with weak lateromedian longitudinal carina. Mexico</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes kukulcanis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Reshchikov, 2011
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Face entirely yellow. Area superomedia 1.1–1.4 times as long as wide. Posterior transverse carina curved. First tergite of metasoma 1.6–1.9 times as long as wide with lateromedian longitudinal carina defined</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propodeum with posterior transverse carina formicate (curved towards metasoma). Area superomedia 1.1 times as long as wide. Mexico</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes xochiquetzalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Reshchikov, 2011
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propodeum with posterior transverse carina concave or straight</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propleuron yellow. First tergite of metasoma with weak lateromedian longitudinal carinae. Propodeum with posterior transverse carina straight. Hind coxa and femur entirely yellow. Costa Rica</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes irenea</tp:taxon-name></italic> Gauld, 1997
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propleuron black. First tergite of metasoma with strong lateromedian longitudinal carinae. Propodeum with posterior transverse carina concave. Hind coxa yellow, ventrally black, hind femur yellow, externally black. Costa Rica</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes jennyae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Gauld, 1997
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Description">
                <title>Description</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Lathrolestes</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">gauldi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9887C02B-B24F-415A-9E02-8D8254148620</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Lathrolestes_gauldi</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">–5</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype female: <bold>Ecuador</bold>, Department of Orellana, Onkone Gare (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">00°39'25.7&quot;S, 76°27'10.8&quot;W</named-content>), 2.vii.1995, T.L. Erwin (NMNH, Smithsonian institution).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>This species differs from other speciesof the genusby the following character states: an entirely black metasoma and hind legs, dark wings, short first metasomal tergite, and short area superomedia (half as long as wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>)).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Female. Body length 8.0 mm, pubescent with white hairs. Antenna with 22 flagellomeres. Scape 0.54 times as long as wide. Head narrowed behind eyes, polished. Maximal length of temple equal to transverse eye diameter; minimum length of temple 0.67× transverse eye diameter. Face 1.08× height of eye; convex centrally. Clypeus separated from face by groove; at apex projecting strongly anteriorly; apical margin of clypeus moderately obtuse, with line of deep punctures. Clypeal foveae small, placed in impressions. Malar space 0.7× as long as basal mandible width. Occipital carina dorsally not broadly interrupted. Lower mandible tooth longer and narrower than upper.</p>
                        <p>Mesosoma smooth, polished, without punctures. Notaulus shallowly impressed at base. Epicnemial carina high. Hind tibia compressed. Claws elongate, not pectinate.<!--PageBreak--> Hind tarsus as long as hind tibia. Vein 3rs-m vestigial (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>). Second recurrent vein with a single bulla. Nervulus strongly postfurcal. Hind wing with nervellus intercepted below middle. Propodeal carinae complete, strongly raised; area superomedia half as long as wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Metasoma compressed apically, polished, sparsely pubescent. First metasomal tergite 0.86× as long as apically wide; without shallow median longitudinal impression; with lateromedian longitudinal carinae, slightly curved at spiracles; with slightly enlarged epipleurae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>). Second metasomal tergite transverse. Metasomal sternites small, sclerotized. Subgenital plate slightly notched at apical margin. Ovipositor straight, thin, stout at base, slightly up-curved, approximately as long as metasomal height, without notch (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>Coloration. Female. Head black. Clypeus and mandibles orange (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Mesosoma, fore and middle legs (except of apical part of middle tarsus) orange (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Hind legs and apical part of middle tarsus, metasoma black. Wings infuscate.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Host">
                        <title>Host.</title>
                        <p>unknown.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Ecuador.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The new species is dedicated to the late Dr. Ian D. Gauld.</p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 1.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes gauldi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.♀, holotype, habitus.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-021-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 2–5.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes gauldi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. ♀, holotype. <bold>2</bold> face <bold>3</bold> propodeum and first metasomal tergite <bold>4</bold> ovipositor <bold>5</bold> areolet of the fore wing.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-021-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Only one specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes gauldi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. has been found despite the large sampling effort taking place in many Amazonian study localities (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Veijalainen et al. 2012</xref>). However, this is a normal situation with rainforest ichneumonids which are relatively difficult to sample, even by using long-term sampling programs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Sääksjärvi et al. 2004</xref>). Thus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathrolestes gauldi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. seems to be a rare species, and further sampling is needed to clarify its distribution in the Western Amazonia.
            </p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We thank Terry L. Erwin for access to the material, Shelby Stedenfeld for checking the language of the manuscript and Gavin Broad for valuable notes and comments.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barron</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> A new species of the <italic>Perilissus anatinus</italic> species group and notes on the relationships of the species groups of <italic>Perilissus</italic> (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Ctenopelmatinae).</article-title> <source>Canadian Entomologist </source> <volume>126</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>224</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/Ent126219-2" xlink:type="simple">10.4039/Ent126219-2</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cresson</surname> <given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1874</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of Mexican Ichneumonidae.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia </source> <volume>1873</volume>: <fpage>374</fpage>-<lpage>413</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Erwin</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pimienta</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murillo</surname> <given-names>OE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aschero</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Mapping patterns of ß-diversity for beetles across the Western Amazon Basin: a preliminary case for improving inventory methods and conservation strategies.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences </source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>72</fpage>-<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradshaw</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> The Ichneumonidae of Costa Rica, 2. The Ichneumonidae of Costa Rica, 2. Introduction and keys to species of the smaller subfamilies, Anomaloninae, Ctenopelmatinae, Diplazontinae, Lycorininae, Phrudinae, Tryphoninae (excluding <italic>Netelia</italic>) and Xoridinae, with an appendices on the Rhyssinae.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>485</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Graf</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumagai</surname> <given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dutra</surname> <given-names>RRC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> Ichneumonidae (Hymenoptera) do sul do Brasil: um novo gênero de Ctenopelmatinae.</article-title> <source>Acta Biologie Paranaense</source> <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1/4</issue>): <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanfranco</surname> <given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Contribución al conocimiento de los Icneumonidos de Chile (Hymenoptera – Ichneumonidae).</article-title> <source>Revista Chilena de Entomologia </source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucky</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erwin</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witman</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Temporal and spatial diversity and distribution of arboreal Carabidae (Coleoptera) in a Western Amazonian rain forest.</article-title> <source>Biotropica </source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>376</fpage>-<lpage>386</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Reshchikov</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Mexican species of <italic>Lathrolestes</italic> Förster (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae; Ctenopelmatinae), with descriptions of four new species and an identification key.</article-title> <source>Tijdschrift voor Entomologie </source> <volume>154</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/22119434-900000305" xlink:type="simple">10.1163/22119434-900000305</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname> <given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1936</year>)<article-title> The ancestry and wing venation of the Hymenoptera.</article-title> <source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America </source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sääksjärvi</surname> <given-names>IE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haataja</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neuvonen</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jussila</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salo</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marmol</surname> <given-names>Burgos A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> High local species richness of parasitic wasps (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae; Pimplinae and Rhyssinae) from the lowland rainforests of Peruvian Amazonia.</article-title> <source>Ecological Entomology </source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>-<lpage>743</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.0307-6946.2004.00656.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.0307-6946.2004.00656.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Townes</surname> <given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> The genera of Ichneumonidae, Part 3.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>307</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Veijalainen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sääksjärvi</surname> <given-names>IE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erwin</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Longino</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> Subfamily composition of Ichneumonidae (Hymenoptera) from western Amazonia: Insights into diversity of tropical parasitoid wasps.</article-title> <source>Insect Conservation and Diversity </source> <volume>2012</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1752-4598.2012.00185.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1752-4598.2012.00185.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Achterberg</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horstmann</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> World Ichneumonoidea 2011. Taxonomy, Biology, Morphology and Distribution.</source> CD/DVD, <publisher-name>Taxapad</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Vancouver</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>