<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.181.2984</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A synopsis of the genus 
                    <italic>Cypholoba</italic> Chaudoir (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Anthiini) known  to occur in the Republic of South Africa
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Mawdsley</surname>
                        <given-names>Jonathan R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Erwin</surname>
                        <given-names>Terry L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Sithole</surname>
                        <given-names>Hendrik</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Mawdsley</surname>
                        <given-names>Alice S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Entomology, MRC 187, National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, P. O. Box 37012, Washington, DC 20013-7012 USA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Research Manager: Invertebrates, South African National Parks, P. O. Box 110040 Hadison Park, Kimberley South Africa
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Cleveland State University, 2121 Euclid Avenue, Cleveland, OH 44114 USA
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Jonathan R. Mawdsley (<email xlink:type="simple">mawdsley@heinzctr.org</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: A. Casale</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>6</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>181</issue>
            <fpage>23</fpage>
            <lpage>43</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>21</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>27</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Jonathan R. Mawdsley, Terry L. Erwin, Hendrik Sithole, Alice S. Mawdsley</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Nearly one third of the described species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chaudoir (<tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name>) are known to inhabit the Republic of South Africa. A key and diagnostic notes are provided for their identification, as well as notes about way of life for some of the species based on observations in the Kruger National Park. Fifteen species and subspecies of the genus are recorded from the Republic of South Africa; adult specimens of each species and subspecies are illustrated and information about the distribution of each species in the Republic of South Africa is summarized and mapped: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alstoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Péringuey), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alveolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Brême), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba amatonga</tp:taxon-name></italic> Péringuey, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba fritschi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Chaudoir), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Dejean), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Bertoloni), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis zuluana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Basilewsky, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Guérin-Méneville), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba leucospilota semilaevis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Chaudoir), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Perroud), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba oberthueri seruana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Strohmeyer, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba opulenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Boheman), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba rutata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Péringuey), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba tenuicollis aenigma</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Dohrn).</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Identification key</kwd>
                <kwd>distribution</kwd>
                <kwd>savanna and woodland ecosystems</kwd>
                <kwd>conservation</kwd>
<!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chaudoir is one of the most diverse lineages within the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Anthiini</tp:taxon-name> of the beetle family <tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name>, with 156 described species and subspecies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Lorenz 2005</xref>) distributed throughout southern and eastern Africa. These beetles are conspicuous elements of savanna and woodland ecosystems, where they are typically found running in bright sunshine over bare ground, or in short grasses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Marshall and Poulton 1902</xref>). Like most other members of the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Anthiini</tp:taxon-name>, species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> have the ability to excrete formic acid from their pygidial glands as a defensive behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey 1896</xref>). Most species in this genus are black and many species have white setal patches or setal tufts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) that are thought to have evolved through mimicry of <tp:taxon-name>Mutillidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Formicidae</tp:taxon-name>, and other stinging <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Marshall and Poulton 1902</xref>). These beetles are of potential interest to entomologists and evolutionary biologists studying phenomena such as mimicry, aposematic coloration, and the evolution of chemical defenses. Species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic>, like many other <tp:taxon-name>Anthiini</tp:taxon-name>, also show close associations with particular ecosystems or vegetation communities and their activity patterns are closely tied with environmental variables such as temperature and rainfall, and overall climate patterns such as seasonal monsoons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Schmidt 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Mawdsley et al. 2011</xref>). Given the relatively large adult body size of most <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> species (length 15–33 mm), their diagnostic color and setal patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer 1928</xref>) and their conspicuous activity patterns and behaviors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Schmidt 2001</xref>), these beetles could easily be incorporated into environmental monitoring programs which track overall ecosystem condition, status, and trends.</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption><p>. Adult female of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Guérin-Méneville), photographed in a dry sandy streambed adjacent to the Sabie River in the Kruger National Park, RSA.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-181-023-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <p>As with other <tp:taxon-name>Anthiini</tp:taxon-name>, the taxonomic history of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> is rather convoluted. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Chaudoir (1850)</xref> initially established two genera, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> on p. 43 for the single species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthia alveolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Brême and a second, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma</tp:taxon-name></italic>, on p. 44 for the group of species that included <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Olivier, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthia gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dejean, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthia intermedia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Boheman, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthia ferretti</tp:taxon-name></italic> Reiche, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthia tetrastigma</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chaudoir, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthia leucospilota</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bertoloni, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthia caillaudi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Gory, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Anthia polioloma</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chaudoir. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey (1896)</xref> combined these two genera in his revision of southern African <tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name>, treating <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> as a synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma</tp:taxon-name></italic> and recognizing 27 species-level taxa, ten of which were recorded from what is now the Republic of South Africa. Further descriptive work by other workers, primarily in the east African fauna, led to the recognition of 102 species in the genus by the time of Csiki’s (1929) comprehensive catalogue. In the “Coleopterorum Catalogus,” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Csiki (1929)</xref> followed Péringuey in placing <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> in synonymy with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928)</xref> was the first to recognize the page priority of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> and also the first to attempt a comprehensive revision of this group. His revision radically altered the taxonomy of the genus, recognizing just 16 species and relegating most of the former species to subspecies status. This approach came under criticism from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Basilewsky (1948</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">1955</xref>) who pointed out a number of errors in Strohmeyer’s revision and argued that many of the so-called “subspecies” of Strohmeyer were separated by characteristics that suggested they were in fact perfectly good species. Basilewsky published a series of studies in which he argued against Strohmeyer’s reductionist approach while at the same time continuing to describe new species and subspecies of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Basilewsky 1948</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">1955</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">1983</xref>).<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <p>This paper is intended to provide an overview of the species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> currently known from the Republic of South Africa (RSA). This is a fauna very much in need of good diagnostic materials, particularly keys and illustrations that can be used by non-specialists. Most of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> species in RSA have never been illustrated and none of the published keys include all of the taxa now known to occur in RSA. The government of RSA has taken recent positive steps towards protecting certain carabid beetles under the South African Biodiversity Act of 2004 (Harrison and Müller, pers. comm.) and carabid beetles are increasingly being incorporated into ecosystem and agricultural monitoring programs in southern Africa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Kotze 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Magagula 2003</xref>). Both types of conservation approaches (carabid beetles as the subject of direct conservation efforts, and carabid beetles as environmental monitoring targets and ecological indicators) are clearly contingent on the availability of high-quality identification materials for the carabid fauna of interest. Fortunately, development of these identification materials is relatively straightforward. The species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> from RSA are well represented in museum collections, as a result of large-scale survey activities that began in the 1950s and have continued more or less until the present day. The species-level taxonomy of the RSA fauna is also reasonably well known; there have been only modest changes in the taxonomy of the RSA species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> since the first revision by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey (1896)</xref>, despite the major changes introduced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928)</xref> in other parts of the genus. In the synopsis that follows, we follow the classification of this genus presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Lorenz (2005)</xref> in the most recent catalogue of world <tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name>. It is hoped that this short communication will help to inspire further interest and field studies of these remarkable beetles.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>We examined collections of adult <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chaudoir and allied genera in the following institutional collections: Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago, Illinois (FMNH); Kruger National Park Museum (Scientific Services), Skukuza, South Africa (KNPC); South African National Collection of Insects, Pretoria, South Africa (SANC); National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C. (NMNH); Transvaal Museum, Pretoria, South Africa (TMSA). In the case of NMNH and TMSA, the specimens examined were authoritatively identified by the late P. Basilewsky, who studied this genus for many years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Basilewsky 1948</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">1955</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">1983</xref>).</p>
            <p>Museum collections were augmented by a series of field visits in 2007, 2008, 2009, 2010, and 2011 to the Kruger National Park in northeastern South Africa, where adults of three species (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alveolata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic>) were collected. Survey methods for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> species and other <tp:taxon-name>Anthiini</tp:taxon-name> involved systematic walking along roads, dry river washes, or sandy areas adjacent to major rivers. Surveys in the main park area were conducted from dawn until dusk and under all available weather conditions. Head-lamping surveys were conducted at night for <tp:taxon-name>Anthiini</tp:taxon-name> and other <tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name> in the N’waswitshaka Research Camp at Skukuza. Pitfall traps were also widely deployed throughout the Skukuza Ranger District of the Kruger National Park, to study the distribution of species of <tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name> across different vegetation communities and to record the responses of carabid assemblages to common landscape-scale disturbances such as mammalian grazing and ground fire. Driving surveys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Mawdsley et al. 2011</xref>) were also employed as a survey technique for larger <tp:taxon-name>Anthiini</tp:taxon-name>, as well as species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tefflus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Leach (<tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Panagaeini</tp:taxon-name>); adults of larger species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be detected during driving surveys. When encountered during diurnal surveys, the individual beetles were highly conspicuous and could be easily captured by hand. Further information about our survey methods is available in papers by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Mawdsley and Sithole (2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">2009</xref>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Mawdsley (2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">2011</xref>), and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Mawdsley et al. (2011)</xref>.</p>
            <p>Methods and species concepts follow those previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Erwin and Kavanaugh 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">1991</xref>). The species validation and diagnosis format follows as closely as possible that suggested in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Erwin and Johnson (2000)</xref>. Measurements of length (ABL) and width (TW) follow those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Ball (1972)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Kavanaugh (1979)</xref>: ABL (apparent body length), measured from apex of labrum to apex of longer elytron.</p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Chaudoir, 1850</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name><comment> Chaudoir, 1850:43, type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alveolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Brême, 1844:293</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma</tp:taxon-name><comment> Chaudoir, 1850:44; synonymy by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:298)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Diabatus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Gistel 1857</xref>:36; synonymy by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Csiki (1929</xref>:381)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Medium to large <tp:taxon-name>Anthiini</tp:taxon-name> (length 15–33 mm) with the following combination of adult attributes: head with distinct basal constriction or “neck;” second labial pa<!--PageBreak-->lpomere distinctly longer than third; pronotum rectangular or cordiform (heart-shaped), not at all markedly elevated or swollen, lacking lateral or basal flanges; elytron with rows of elevated costae which alternate with rows of large, deep punctures (in most species); elytral punctures with brown, yellow, or orange setae at bottom in many species; rows of punctures and setae not extending to apex of elytron in most species; apex of elytron flat or planate in most species; elytron often with patterned setae and/or pubescence; posterior margin of elytron usually obliquely truncate; elytron lacking an apical spine.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Southern and eastern Africa.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Included species in the Republic of South Africa"><title>Included species in the Republic of South Africa.</title>
                    <p>The species list below and the arrangement of descriptions that follow are ordered alphabetically.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alstoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Péringuey), Botswana, Namibia, Republic of South Africa (RSA)</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alveolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Brême), Botswana, RSA, Zimbabwe</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba amatonga</tp:taxon-name></italic> Péringuey, Mozambique, RSA</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba fritschi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Chaudoir), Botswana, Namibia, RSA, Zambia</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Dejean), Botswana, Mozambique, Namibia, RSA</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Bertoloni), Mozambique, RSA</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis zuluana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Basilewsky, RSA</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Guérin-Méneville), Mozambique, RSA, Zimbabwe</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba leucospilota semilaevis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Chaudoir), Mozambique, RSA</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier), Lesotho, RSA, Zimbabwe</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Perroud), RSA, Swaziland</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba oberthueri seruana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Strohmeyer, Botswana, RSA</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba opulenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Boheman), Namibia, RSA</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba rutata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Péringuey), Mozambique, RSA, Zimbabwe</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba tenuicollis aenigma</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Dohrn), Botswana, RSA, Zambia, Zimbabwe</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to adults of Cypholoba Chaudoir species from the Republic of South Africa"><title>Key to adults of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chaudoir species from the Republic of South Africa.</title>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytron without white or yellow patches or linear bands of setae in apical half; basal half of elytron along suture at base with at most a narrow white or yellow patch or band of setae</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytron with distinct white or yellow patches or linear bands of setae in apical half; basal half of elytron typically also with basal patches of white or yellow setae</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum elongate, slender, spindle-shaped</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum broader, either rounded, rectangular, or heart-shaped</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum with well-defined longitudinal median impression; elytral punctures round</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Dejean)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum with median line feebly impressed at base and otherwise not at all impressed along most of length, sometimes with a narrow raised ridge; elytral punctures oval</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><!--PageBreak-->4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum median line with a round impression at base and becoming obsolete on disc</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Bertoloni)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum median line with a narrow impression at base and a narrow, slightly raised ridge on disc</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis zuluana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Basilewsky</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral punctures large, those on disc with orange-red setae deep within each puncture</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral punctures small, those on disc without orange-red setae deep within each puncture</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apparent body length (ABL) 24–28 mm; pronotum elongate and somewhat heart-shaped, width of pronotum less than width of eyes; elytra with six costae and large alveolate punctures</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba amatonga</tp:taxon-name></italic> Péringuey</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apparent body length (ABL) 31–33 mm; pronotum broader and distinctly heart-shaped, width of pronotum distinctly greater than width of eyes; elytra with six costae, fifth costa as measured from lateral margin short, only reaching to basal sixth of elytra; elytral punctures large, alveolate</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alveolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Brême)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytra and pronotum without patterned pubescence or setae of any kind; elytral costae and rows of punctures continuing to apex</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alstoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Péringuey)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytra and often pronotum with small setal tufts or patches at base; elytral costae and rows of punctures usually becoming obsolete on disc, apex of elytra smooth</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotal base, scutellum and base of elytra each with a small white or yellow setal tuft, barely noticeable; elytral costae broad, smooth, and shining, becoming obsolete at apical third; apical third of elytra shining</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba fritschi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Chaudoir)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum and/or elytra with more extensive setal patches; elytral costae narrow; apical third of elytra matte, not shining</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral surface markedly rugose, each elytron with a narrow linear band of yellow setae along suture on basal third</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba rutata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Péringuey)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral punctures very small, costae present but not markedly elevated, elytral surface largely smooth; each elytron with an ovate or rectangular patch of yellow setae adjacent to suture on basal fifth</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba opulenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Boheman)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytra with patches of grey or white setae on disc at apical third or apical fourth</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytra with patches of pale setae at base and/or apex of elytra only, adjacent to the suture</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apparent body length (ABL) 15-17 mm; pronotum elongate, slender, spindle-shaped; each elytron with a second transverse band of white setae at mid-elytron</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba tenuicollis aenigma</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Dohrn)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apparent body length (ABL) 24-28 mm; pronotum broader, heart-shaped; each elytron with a patch of setae at apical third and a narrow line of white<!--PageBreak--> setae along the suture on the basal third of elytra; no second band of white setae at mid-elytron</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotal and elytral setae uniformly greyish-white; a narrow linear band of setae along midline of pronotum, a narrow linear band of setae along elytral suture on basal two-fifths, and a pair of arcuate patches located at apical third</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Guérin-Méneville)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotal setae and the setal band at the base of the elytra yellowish orange; elytral setal patch placement similar to above, except for coloration, discal patches bright white</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba leucospilota semilaevis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Chaudoir)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytra with apical third smooth, shining, except for apical patch of white setae; basal two-thirds of elytra with rows of costae and large punctures, which lack reddish-orange pubescence</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Perroud)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytra with apical fourth or fifth smooth, shining, except for apical patch of white setae; basal three-quarters of elytra with rows of costae and large punctures, reddish-orange pubescence present deep inside each puncture</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytra with apical fourth smooth, shining, except for apical patch of white setae; each elytron with seven costae, of which the sixth is very short</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytra with apical fifth smooth, shining, except for apical patch of white setae; each elytron with seven costae subequal in size</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba oberthueri seruana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Strohmeyer</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">alstoni</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_alstoni</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Péringuey, 1892a)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"> 29</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma alstoni</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Péringuey (1892a</xref>:14; type locality “British Bechuanaland,” syntype series in South African Museum, Cape Town)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alstoni</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Péringuey) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Lorenz (2005</xref>:513)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 23-24 mm; easily separated from all other species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> in RSA by the lack of patterned pubescence on the elytra and the continuation of the rows of elytral punctures and costae until the elytral apices. The sympatric species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba fritschi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is similar but is larger in ABL (25-31 mm in length) and its elytral costae become obsolete on the disc shortly after mid-elytron, leaving the apical third of the elytra almost entirely smooth.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 2–15.</label>
                        <caption><p>Adult specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> species, from the TMSA collection unless otherwise indicated. <bold>2</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alstoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Péringuey), male, Niekerk’s Hope in Griqualand West, Northern Cape Province, RSA <bold>3</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alveolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Brême), male, Warmbath, Limpopo Province, RSA <bold>4</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba amatonga</tp:taxon-name></italic> Péringuey, male, Soutpansberg, Limpopo Province, RSA <bold>5</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba fritschi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Chaudoir), male, Twee Rivieren, Northern Cape Province, RSA <bold>6</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Dejean), male, Zoutpan, Gauteng Province, RSA <bold>7</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Dejean), female, Vanwyksfontein Farm, Northern Cape Province, RSA <bold>8</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Bertoloni), male, Zoutpansberg, Limpopo Province, RSA <bold>9</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Bertoloni), female, Inhambane, Mozambique <bold>10</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis zuluana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Basilewsky, male, “E. Zululand,” KwaZulu/Natal Province, RSA <bold>11</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Guérin-Méneville), male, 20-26 km NE of Pietersburg, Limpopo Province, RSA <bold>12–15</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> collected at sites along the Sabie River west of Paul Kruger Gate in the Kruger National Park, showing intrapopulational variation in elytral setal patterns (NMNH collection).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-181-023-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>107 specimens from the following localities: RSA: Northern Cape Province: Farm Brulpan, Marydale, Mata Mata, Niekerk’s Hope in Griqualand West, 30 km E Pofadder, 46 km N Pofadder, Tswalu Nature Reserve, Twee Rivieren.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        	
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">alveolata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_alveolata</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Brême, 1844)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 3</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">25</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">29</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">34</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Anthia alveolata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Brême (1844</xref>:293, pl. 7 f. 5, type locality “Port-Natal,” holotype in Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma alveolata</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Brême) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey (1896</xref>:351)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba caillaudi alveolata</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Brême) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:322)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alveolata</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Brême) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:448)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 31–33 mm; one of the largest species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> in RSA and the largest species that has the distinctive alveolate elytral<!--PageBreak--> punctures with reddish-orange pubescence at the bottom of the punctures (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>). It can be separated from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba oberthueri seruana</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the lack of a white patch of setae across both elytral apices and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba amatonga</tp:taxon-name></italic> by its larger ABL (24–28 mm length in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba amatonga</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and the differences in elytral surface sculpture mentioned in the key above. Some specimens have a patch of white setae on each elytron immediately adjacent to the scutellum, while others also have a patch of white setae on the scutellum and/or a line of white setae along the midline of the pronotum.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>159 specimens from the following localities: RSA: Gauteng Province: Johannesburg, Moloto, Pienaars River Dam, Pretoria, Rosslyn, Zoutpan. KwaZulu/Natal Province: Duku duku, Durban, Ndumu, Pongola River, St. Lucia Bay, Umfolozi, Waterval, “E Zululand.” Limpopo Province: Bandelierkop, 25 km NE Ellisras, Farm Scrutton, Haenertsburg, Klein Letaba, 18 miles W Letaba Rest Camp, Letaba Rest Camp in Kruger National Park, Marblehall, Messina, Mokeetse, Pietersburg, 22 miles E Pietersburg, 20-26 km N Pietersburg, Potgietersrus, Sedula near Leydsdorp, Shilouvane, Warmbath, Woodbush. Mpumalanga Province: Barberton, 3 km NW Barberton, Grootdraai, Lydenburg, Nelspruit, Nkuhlu Plots in Kruger National Park, Sabie River road west of Paul Kruger Gate, Skukuza. North West Province: Marico River, Rustenburg, Vryberg. Province not specified: “Transvaal.”</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes on biology"><title>Notes on biology.</title>
                    <p>During our surveys (see Materials and Methods above), adults of this species were found in riverine and upland areas of the Kruger National Park. Specific vegetation communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Gertenbach 1983</xref>) where adults were collected included riverine gallery forest and upland <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acacia nigrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> Olivier <italic>- Combretum apiculatum</italic> Sonder savanna. Adults were collected diurnally, in pitfall traps, and with headlamps at night.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 16–28.</label>
                        <caption><p>Adult specimens and diagnostic features of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> species, from the TMSA collection unless otherwise indicated <bold>16</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba leucospilota semilaevis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Chaudoir), male, “E. Zululand,” KwaZulu/Natal Province, RSA <bold>17</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Olivier), male, Groenkloof, Gauteng Province, RSA <bold>18</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Perroud), male, Shilouvane, Limpopo Province, RSA <bold>19</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Perroud), male, Empangeni, KwaZulu/Natal Province, RSA (NMNH collection) <bold>20</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Perroud), male, Pongola River, KwaZulu/Natal Province, RSA <bold>21</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba oberthueri seruana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Strohmeyer, male, Allemanskraal, Free State Province, RSA <bold>22</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba opulenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Boheman), male, Us Pass, Khomas Hochland, Namibia <bold>23</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba rutata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Péringuey), male, Pafuri, Kruger National Park, Limpopo Province, RSA <bold>24</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba tenuicollis aenigma</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Dohrn), Zimbabwe <bold>25</bold> base of elytra showing punctures, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alveolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>26</bold> base of elytra showing punctures, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>27</bold> base of elytra showing punctures, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>28</bold> base of elytra showing punctures, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba opulenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-181-023-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 29–32.</label>
                        <caption><p>Maps showing distributions of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> species in RSA <bold>29</bold> black squares for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alstoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>, black circles for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alveolata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, white star for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba amatonga</tp:taxon-name></italic>, white triangles for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba fritschi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>30</bold> white circles for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, black star for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, question marks (indeterminate localities) for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis zuluana</tp:taxon-name></italic>, white squares for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba tenuicollis aenigma</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>31</bold> black triangles for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic>, question marks (indeterminate localities) for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba leucospilota semilaevis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, black diamond for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba oberthueri seruana</tp:taxon-name></italic>, white arrow for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba opulenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, white X for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba rutata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>32</bold> white diamonds for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, black arrows for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-181-023-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        	
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">amatonga</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_amatonga</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Péringuey, 1892b</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 4</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">29</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba amatonga</tp:taxon-name><comment> Péringuey (1892:102b, type locality “Amatongaland, Delagoa Bay,” syntype series in South African Museum, Cape Town)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma amatonga</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Péringuey) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey (1896</xref>:350)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba chaudoiri amatonga</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Péringuey) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:321)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba amatonga</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Péringuey) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:448)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 24-28 mm; similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alveolata</tp:taxon-name></italic> but separated from that species by the smaller ABL (31-33 mm in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alveolata</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and by the differences in elytral surface sculpture mentioned in the key above.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined. </title>
                    <p>2 specimens from the following locality: RSA: Limpopo Province: Soutpansberg.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">fritschi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_fritschi</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Chaudoir, 1883)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 5</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">29</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma fritschi</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Chaudoir (1883</xref>:27, type locality “Kuruman,” holotype in Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba opulenta fritschi</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Chaudoir) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:368)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba fritschi</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Chaudoir) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:450)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 25–31 mm; distinctive for its large body size and for the lack of patterned pubescence or setae on the elytra, although some specimens may have a small patch of yellow setae adjacent to the scutellum. As noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey (1896)</xref>, there is also a tuft of pubescence on the scutellum. The elytral surface sculpture is also diagnostic, with the rows of costae becoming obsolete shortly after mid-elytron and the apical third smooth and strongly shining.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>11 specimens from the following localities: RSA: Northern Cape Province: Niekerk’s Hope in Griqualand West, Twee Rivieren.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes on taxonomy"><title>Notes on taxonomy.</title>
                    <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928)</xref> had placed this species as a subspecies of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba opulenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> but as pointed out by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Basilewsky (1948)</xref> this is clearly an error as the two species are quite distinct and have different proportions, vestiture, and surface sculpture.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subspecies">gracilis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">gracilis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_gracilis_gracilis</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Dejean, 1831)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 6, 7</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">30</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Anthia gracilis</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Dejean (1831</xref>:468, type locality “cap de Bonne-Espérance,” holotype in Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma gracilis</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Dejean) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey (1896</xref>:342-343)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis gracilis</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Dejean) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:303)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 17-20 mm; easily recognized by its slender body form, spindle-shaped pronotum, and lack of white setae or pubescence on the elytra. The shape and size of the elytral punctures (described in the key) will separate this subspecies from both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis zuluana</tp:taxon-name></italic>. In both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> the shape of the elytra is sexually dimorphic and thus both forms are illustrated here.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>35 specimens from the following localities: RSA: Eastern Cape Province: Aliwal North, Dorset. Free State Province: Bothaville. Gauteng Province: 11 km SE Bronkhorstspruit, Bronkhorstspruit, Brooklyn, Florida, Pretoria, Roodeplaat, Rosslyn, Welgedacht, Zoutpan, Zusterstroom. KwaZulu/Natal Province: W<!--PageBreak-->aterval. Limpopo Province: Messina, Moordrift, Naboomspruit, Nylsvley, Pietersburg, Rhenosterpoort, Smith Farm. Mpumalanga Province: Argent, 14 miles E Middelburg, Middelburg, Moloto, Waterval Onder. Northern Cape Province: Niekerk’s Hope in Griqualand West, Vanwyksfontein Farm. North West Province: Lichtenburg, Rustenburg.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subspecies">gracilis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_gracilis_scrobiculata</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Bertoloni, 1847)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 8, 9</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"> 30</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Anthia scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Bertoloni (1847</xref>:90, type locality “in provincia Inhambanensi Monzambici,” holotype in Accademia della Scienze dell’Istituto Bologna, Italy)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Bertoloni) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey (1896</xref>:342)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Bertoloni) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:315)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 19–20 mm; similar in general body form and appearance to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> but differing from that subspecies in having the median line of the pronotum not markedly impressed and in having the elytral punctures oval rather than round.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>1 specimen from the following locality: RSA: Limpopo Province: Zoutpansberg.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes on taxonomy"><title>Notes on taxonomy.</title>
                    <p>Based on the rather significant differences in the pronotal and elytral surface sculpture, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> may ultimately prove to represent a species distinct from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. A thorough review of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> species complex with a rigorous evaluation of the 41 subspecific taxa proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928)</xref> is needed.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subspecies">gracilis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">zuluana</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_gracilis_zuluana</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Basilewsky, 1948</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 10</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"> 30</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis zuluana</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Basilewsky (1948</xref>:111, type locality “Zululand,” syntype series in Naturhistoriska Riksmuseet, Stockholm)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 19–20 mm; similar in general body form and appearance to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis scrobiculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> but differing from those two subspecies in the pronotal surface sculpturing, as noted in the key. There are also subtle differences in the arrangement and size of the elytral punctures and elytral costae between all three subspecies (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 6–10</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>6 specimens from the following localities: RSA: KwaZulu/Natal Province: “E. Zululand,” “Zululand.”</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subspecies">graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_graphipteroides_graphipteroides</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Guérin-Méneville, 1845)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"> 11, 12, 13, 14, 15</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"> 26</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"> 31</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5"> 33</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Anthia graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Guérin-Méneville (1845</xref>:285, type locality “in regione Massilicatzi,” holotype in Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Guérin-Méneville) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey (1896</xref>:346)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Guérin-Méneville) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:343)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 24–27 mm; this species is easily separated from most of the other sympatric species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the distinctive pattern of pubescence and setae on the elytra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 11</xref>). Adults could potentially be confused with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba leucospilota</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but in that species the pubescence on the pronotum and elytral suture is yellowish and the patches of setae at apical third are brilliant white (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>77 specimens from the following localities: RSA: Gauteng Province: Pretoria, Rosslyn. KwaZulu/Natal Province: Hluhluwe, Mkuze Game Reserve, Ndumu, St. Lucia Bay. Limpopo Province: Alma, Koedoesrivier, Letaba Rest Camp in the Kruger National Park, 9–14 miles E Louis Trichardt, 75 km W Messina, Nylstroom, Nylsvley, Pietersburg, 9 miles N Pietersburg, 20–26 miles NE Pietersburg, Potgietersrus, Punda Maria Rest Camp in the Kruger National Park, Rust de Winter, Shilouvane, Thabina, Warmbath. Mpumalanga Province: Kaapmuiden, 20 km SW Kaapmuiden, Louws Creek, Lydenburg, N’waswitshaka Research Camp, Pretoriuskop, Sabie river banks west of Paul Kruger Gate, Skukuza. Province uncertain: Lebombo Mountains.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes on biology"><title>Notes on biology.</title>
                    <p>This is easily the most abundant and frequently encountered species of <tp:taxon-name>Anthiini</tp:taxon-name> in the Kruger National Park, RSA. Adults (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) emerge in the early rainy season (November-December) and can be locally abundant. Adults are active both nocturnally and diurnally and are typically found in riverine or riparian areas near flowing water. The charactistic behavior observed in this species, as with most <tp:taxon-name>Anthiini</tp:taxon-name>, is a rapid walking behavior which appears to be associated primarily with foraging but also is likely involved in searching for conspecifics and prospective larval habitats. We have observed adults of this species in several distinct vegetation communities (riverine gallery forest, open <italic><tp:taxon-name>Combretum apiculatum</tp:taxon-name></italic> – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acacia nigrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> savanna, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phragmites</tp:taxon-name></italic> reed beds) and microhabitats (sand or dirt roads adjacent to riverine communities, dry sand wash, and riverine sand bars). This species also occasionally enters human-inhabited areas; we have found individuals in the N’waswitshaka Research Camp at Skukuza and also in the main tourist areas at the Skukuza tourist camp. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Marshall and Poulton (1902)</xref> suggest that this species may be a mimic of <tp:taxon-name>Mutillidae</tp:taxon-name> and other stinging <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>. Our observations suggest that, while there are certainly similarities in color pattern and behavior between adults of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> and sympatric <tp:taxon-name>Mutillidae</tp:taxon-name>, adults of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> are actually significantly larger in size than most of the sympatric black-and-white mutillid wasps, rendering the resemblance less than exact. We infer from these observations that selection pressures may not be operating as intensely<!--PageBreak--> on this species as on other <tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name> (for examples of carabid beetles which are much more convincing mimics of <tp:taxon-name>Mutillidae</tp:taxon-name>, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Marshall and Poulton 1902</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 33.</label>
                        <caption><p>Riverine/riparian area along the south bank of the Sabie River west of Paul Kruger Gate in the Kruger National Park, RSA. A collecting site for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-181-023-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 34.</label>
                        <caption><p>Upland <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acacia nigrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Combretum apiculatum</tp:taxon-name></italic> savanna near Skukuza in the Kruger National Park, RSA. A collecting site for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba alveolata</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-181-023-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes on taxonomy"><title>Notes on taxonomy.</title>
                    <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928)</xref> recognized 20 subspecies in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic>, many of which were separated on the basis of differences in the setal patterns of the elytra. Many of these taxa are doubtfully distinct from the nominate form and the whole group is in need of a careful revision. Such a revision should include examination of extensive series in order to determine the extent of intrapopulational variation in the elytral setal patterns. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 12–15</xref> illustrate the variation in elytral setal patterns within a single population of this species, located west of Paul Kruger Gate along the Sabie River in the Kruger National Park.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subspecies">leucospilota</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">semilaevis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_leucospilota_semilaevis</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Chaudoir, 1861)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 16</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"> 31</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma semilaevis</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Chaudoir (1861</xref>:571–572, type locality “de la baie Delagoa,” syntype series in Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma semilevis</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey (1896</xref>:344–345), unjustified emendation</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba leucospilota semilaevis</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Chaudoir) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:351)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 22–28 mm; similar in general appearance to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> but distinguished from that species by the color of the pronotal and elytral pubescence and setae. The bands of pubescence on the pronotum and elytral base are yellow in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba leucospilota</tp:taxon-name></italic> (white or grey in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic>), and the bands of pubescence on the apical third of the elytra are a much brighter white in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba leucospilota</tp:taxon-name></italic> than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>5 specimens from the following localities: RSA: KwaZulu/Natal Province: “E. Zululand,” “Zululand.”</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">macilenta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_macilenta</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Olivier, 1795)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 17</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"> 32</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Carabus macilentus</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Olivier (1795</xref>:26, pl. 11 f. 130, type locality “Cap de Bonne-Espérance,” holotype in Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma macilenta</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Olivier) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey (1896</xref>:348)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba macilenta</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Olivier) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:335)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 20–23 mm; similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba oberthueri</tp:taxon-name></italic> but differing from both species in the length of the elytral costae. The elytral costae are roughly equal in length in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 17</xref>) while the lateral costae <!--PageBreak-->are distinctly longer than those on the disc in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba oberthueri</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 18</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">–21</xref>). Adults could potentially also be confused with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba amatonga</tp:taxon-name></italic> but that species lacks the patch of white pubescence at the apex of the elytra and the apical portion of the elytra is more rugosely punctate, not flat and strongly shining as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>127 specimens from the following localities: RSA: Eastern Cape Province: De la Rey. Free State Province: Boshof, Bothaville, H. F. Verwoerd Dam, Krugersdrift Dam. Gauteng Province: Bronkhorstspruit, Groenkloof, Johannesburg, Moloto, Muldersdrift, Pretoria, Randfontein, Rosslyn, Valhalla, Zoutpan. KwaZulu/Natal Province: Waterval. Limpopo Province: Messina, Moordrift, Pienaars River, Pietersburg, 20–26 km NE Pietersburg, Shilouvane, Woodbush. Mpumalanga Province: Lydenburg, Middelburg, 14 miles E Middelburg, Waterval Onder. Northern Cape Province: Kimberley, Niekerk’s Hope in Griqualand West, Vanwyksfontein Farm. North West Province: Lichtenburg, Marico, Rustenburg.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">notata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_notata</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Perroud, 1846)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 18, 19, 20, 27</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"> 32</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Anthia notata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Perroud (1846</xref>:50–56, type locality “de l’ intérieur de Natal,” syntypes in Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma notata</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Perroud) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey (1896</xref>:348)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba semisuturata notata</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Perroud) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:337)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Perroud) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:452)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 21–23 mm; elytral surface sculpture distinctive with the entire apical third lacking the rows of punctures and costae found on the more basal portions of the elytra. The lateral elytral costae are longer than the costae on mid-disc or the suture. The patterns of pubescence vary in this species; some specimens possess white linear bands of setae on the head, pronotum, and base of the elytra while <!--PageBreak-->other specimens lack these bands (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 14, 15</xref>). We have also examined highly abraded specimens that lack all of the elytral and pronotal setae but in these specimens the elytral surface sculpturing is still diagnostic.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>96 specimens from the following localities: RSA: Gauteng Province: Malvern, Pretoria. KwaZulu/Natal Province: Empangeni, 30 miles N of Empangeni, Hluhluwe, Maritzburg, Mkuze, “Natal,” Ntambanana, Pinetown, Pongola, Pongola River, St. Lucia Bay, Thorny Bush, Ubombo Mountains, Weenen, “Zululand,” “E. Zululand.” Limpopo Province: Koedoes Rivier, Sedula near Leydsdorp, Shilouvane, Thabina, Zoutpansberg. Mpumalanga Province: Barberton, Grootdraai, Lydenburg, Nelspruit, Sabie River bank west of Paul Kruger Gate, Waterval River Pass. Northern Cape Province: Kimberley. North West Province: Marico River, Vryburg.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes on biology"><title>Notes on biology.</title>
                    <p>We observed adults of this species running along dirt roads in bright sunshine through open <italic><tp:taxon-name>Combretum apiculatum</tp:taxon-name></italic> – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acacia nigrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> savanna in close proximity to the Sabie River in the Kruger National Park, RSA.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subspecies">oberthueri</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">seruana</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_oberthueri_seruana</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Strohmeyer, 1928</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 21</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"> 31</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba semisuturata seruana</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:337, type locality “Ost-Betschuanaland,” one syntype from “Sogosse” the other syntype from “Serue” in Museum für Naturkunde, Berlin)<!--PageBreak--></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 21–24 mm; similar in appearance to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba notata</tp:taxon-name></italic> but differing from both species in the length of the elytral costae (as noted in the key) and the elytral proportions which are somewhat longer and narrower in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba oberthueri seruana</tp:taxon-name></italic> than in the other two species. This is apparently a rare form, at least in collections; it is known at present from two localities in Botswana and the nominate subspecies is known only from Zimbabwe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer 1928</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>1 specimen from the following locality: RSA: Free State, Allemanskraal.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">opulenta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_opulenta</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Boheman, 1860)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 22, 28</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"> 31</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma opulenta</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Boheman (1860</xref>:9, type locality “juxta fluvium Svakop,” holotype in Naturhistoriska Riksmuseet, Stockholm)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba opulenta</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Boheman) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:367)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 18–24 mm; easily recognized by the golden-yellow pubescence on the head, pronotum, and base of elytra adjacent to the suture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 22</xref>). The elytral surface sculpturing is also diagnostic, with small narrow costae separated by flat intervals with a single row of minute punctures in each interval (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 28</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>45 specimens from the following localities: Eastern Cape Province: Nduma, Willowmore. KwaZulu/Natal Province: Maritzburg, Melmoth, Mkuze, St. Lucia, “E. Zululand.” North West Province: Lichtenburg, 30 km W Vryberg.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">rutata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_rutata</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Péringuey, 1892b)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 23</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"> 31</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma rutata</tp:taxon-name><comment> Péringuey (1892b:101, type locality “Zambeze,” syntype series in South African Museum, Cape Town)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba divisa rutata</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Péringuey) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:359–360)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba rutata</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Peringuey) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:453)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 22–27 mm; similar in body proportions and surface sculpturing to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba graphipteroides</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba leucospilota</tp:taxon-name></italic> but lacking the oblique bands of white setae and pubescence that are found at the apical third of the elytra in those species (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 11</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">–16</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>1 specimen from the following locality: RSA: Limpopo Provice: Pafuri in Kruger National Park.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cypholoba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subspecies">tenuicollis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">aenigma</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cypholoba_tenuicollis_aenigma</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Dohrn, 1881)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 24</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"> 30</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Anthia aenigma</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Dohrn (1881</xref>:326, type locality not indicated, type material originally in Natural History Museum, Stettin, and apparently destroyed in World War II)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Polyhirma aenigma</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Dohrn) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey (1896</xref>:343-344, pl. 4 f. 6)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis aenigma</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Dohrn) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:303)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba aenigma</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Dohrn) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer (1928</xref>:447)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Apparent body length (ABL) 15–17 mm; similar in size, body proportions, and surface sculpturing to smaller individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> but easily separated from that species by its patterned elytral pubescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 19</xref>) and smaller body size (adults of all subspecies of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cypholoba gracilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are 17–22 mm in ABL). Adults are also superficially similar to those of species in the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eccoptoptera</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chaudoir but in species of that genus the pronotum is broadly rounded and markedly convex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Péringuey 1896</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Strohmeyer 1928</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Materials examined"><title>Materials examined.</title>
                    <p>84 specimens from the following localities: RSA: KwaZulu/Natal Province: Entabeni. Limpopo Province: Haenertsburg, Moddernek, Pietersburg, Shilouvane, Woodbush, Wylie’s Poort.</p>
                    <!--PageBreak-->
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>For assistance with the fieldwork associated with this project, we thank F. Venter, V. Ndlovu, J. Baloyi, O. Sithole, P. Khoza, A. Manganyi, and T. Khoza of South African National Parks. For additional field assistance we thank R. D. and J. L. Mawdsley, as well as J. du G. Harrison and his family. For assistance with visits to museum collections, we thank A. Newton and M. Thayer (FMNH), G. Zambatis (KNPC), R. Staals and B. Grobbelaar (SANC), and J. du G. Harrison and Ruth Müller (TMSA). For assistance with additional specimen imaging and image editing, we thank K. Darrow (NMNH). For comments on the manuscript during the review process, we thank A. Casale as well as two anonymous reviewers.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Classification of the species of <italic>Harpalus</italic> subgenus <italic>Glanodes</italic> Casey (Carabidae: Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Coleopterists Bulletin </source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>204</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Basilewsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1948</year>)<article-title> Descriptions de Coleoptérès Carabiques nouveaux d’Afrique et notes diverses sur des espèces déjà connues, III.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Société Entomologique de France </source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Basilewsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1955</year>)<article-title> Notes sur les Cypholobini (Col. Carabidae Anthiinae), I.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de l’Institut Royal des Sciences naturelles de Belgique </source> <volume>31</volume> (<issue>25</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Basilewsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<article-title> Notes sur les Cypholobini (Col. Carabidae Anthiinae), II.</article-title> <source>Bulletin et Annales de la Société Royale d`Entomologie de Belgique </source> <volume>99</volume> (<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>150</fpage>-<lpage>158</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Basilewsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<article-title>Notes sur les Cypholobini (Col. Carabidae Anthiinae). III. Sur les <italic>Cypholoba</italic> du groupe <italic>divisa</italic>.</article-title> <source>Bulletin et Annales de la Société Royale d`Entomologie de Belgique </source> <volume>100</volume> (<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Basilewsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> Coleoptérès Carabidae africains nouveaux 16.</article-title> <source>Revue de Zoologie et de Botanique Africaines </source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>330</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Basilewsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Note sur les Cypholobini 4 (Coleoptera Carabidae Anthiinae).</article-title> <source>Revue de Zoologie Africaines </source> <volume>94</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>489</fpage>-<lpage>503</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Basilewsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> Note sur les Cypholobini 5 (Coleoptera Carabidae Anthiinae).</article-title> <source>Revue de Zoologie Africaines </source> <volume>97</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>563</fpage>-<lpage>566</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertoloni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1847</year>)<article-title> Sezione di zoologia anatomia comparata e fisiologia.</article-title> <source>Diario dell’ottavo Congresso degli scienziati Italiani convocati in Genova </source> <volume>1847</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Boheman</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1860</year>)<article-title> Coleoptera samlade af J. A. Wahlberg i Syd-Vestra Afrika.</article-title> <source>Öfversigt af Kongliga Vetenskaps-Akademiens Förhandlingar </source> <volume>17</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brême F le Marquis de</surname></name></person-group> (<year>1844</year>)<source> Insectes Coleoptérès nouveaux ou peu connus, première et deuxième décades. Annales de la Société Entomologique de France, Ser. 2 2: 287–313 + pls. 7–9.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudoir M Baron de</surname></name></person-group> (<year>1850</year>)<article-title> Mémoire sur la famille des Carabiques, 2<sup>o</sup> partie.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Société Impériale des Naturalistes de Moscou </source> <volume>23</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudoir M Baron de</surname></name></person-group> (<year>1861</year>)<article-title> Matériaux pour servir à l’étude des Cicindélètes et des Carabiques.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Société Impériale des Naturalistes de Moscou </source> <volume>34</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>491</fpage>-<lpage>576</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudoir M Baron de</surname></name></person-group> (<year>1883</year>)<article-title> Descriptions de Carabiques nouveaux.</article-title> <source>Coleopterorum Novitates </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Csiki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1929</year>)<article-title> Carabidae: Harpalinae III.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schenkling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>, Coleopterorum Catalogus, Pars 104.</issue-title> <source>W. Junk, Berlin</source>: <fpage>347</fpage>-<lpage>528</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dejean</surname><given-names>PFMA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1831</year>)<source> Species général des Coléoptères de la Collection de M. le Baron Dejean, Tome V. Mequignon-Marvis Pére et Fils, Paris, viii + 883 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dohrn</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1881</year>)<article-title> Exotisches.</article-title> <source>Entomologische Zeitung [Stettin] </source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>327</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Naming species, a new paradigm for crisis management in taxonomy: Rapid journal validation of scientific names enhanced with more complete descriptions on the internet.</article-title> <source>The Coleopterists Bulletin, </source> <volume>54</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>278</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1649/0010-065X(2000)054[0269:NSANPF]2.0.CO;2" xlink:type="simple">10.1649/0010-065X(2000)054[0269:NSANPF]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kavanaugh</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<article-title> Systematics and zoogeography of <italic>Bembidion</italic> Latreille: I. The <italic>carlhi</italic> and <italic>erasum</italic> groups of western North America (Coleoptera: Carabidae, Bembidiini).</article-title> <source>Entomologica Scandinavica, Supplement </source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kavanaugh</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> The tribe Cicindini Banninger (Coleoptera: Carabidae): comparative morphology, classification, natural history, and evolution.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington </source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>356</fpage>-<lpage>389</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gertenbach</surname><given-names>WPD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> Landscapes of the Kruger National Park.</article-title> <source>Koedoe </source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>121</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gistel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1857</year>)<source> Achthundert und zwanig neue oder unbeschriebene wirbellose thiere.</source> <publisher-name>Schoner’sche Buchhandulung</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Straubing</publisher-loc>, <lpage>94</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guérin-Méneville</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1845</year>)<article-title> Description de quelques-uns des Insectes les plus remarquable découverts par M. A. Delegorgue dans les pays des Boschimans, des Ama Zoulous, des Massilicatzi et au Port Natal, pendant les années 1838, 39, 40, 41, 42, 43 et 44.</article-title> <source>Revue Zoologique, par la Société Cuvierienne </source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>-<lpage>286</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kavanaugh</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<source> Studies on the Nebriini (Coleoptera: Carabidae), III. New Nearctic <italic>Nebria</italic> species and subspecies, nomenclatural notes, and lectotype designations. Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences, Ser. 4 42: 87–133.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotze</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Ground beetle diversity patterns across Afromontane forest/grassland ecotones in KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandmayr,</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lövei</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zetto Brandmayr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>and Vigna – Taglianti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Natural history and applied ecology of carabid beetles.</issue-title> <source>Pensoft, Sofia</source>: <fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>240</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Nomina Carabidarum, a directory of the scientific names of ground beetles (Insecta, Coleoptera “Geadephaga:” Trachypachidae and Carabidae incl.</source> <publisher-name>Paussinae, Cicindelinae, Rhysodinae), second edition. Lorenz</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Tutzing</publisher-loc>, <lpage>993</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Magagula</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Changes in carabid beetle diversity within a fragmented agricultural landscape.</article-title> <source>African Journal of Ecology </source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2028.2003.00403.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1046/j.1365-2028.2003.00403.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>GAK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulton</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1902</year>)<source> Five years’ observations and experiments (1896–1901) on the bionomics of South African insects, chiefly directed to the investigation of mimicry and warning colors. Transactions of the Entomological Society of London 1902: 287–584 + pl. 9–23.</source><!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mawdsley</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Taxonomy, ecology, and phylogeny of species of <italic>Lophyra</italic> Motschulsky 1859, subgenus <italic>Eriolophyra</italic> Rivalier 1948 (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Tropical Zoology </source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mawdsley</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Taxonomy, identification, and phylogeny of the African and Madagascan species of the tiger beetle genus <italic>Chaetodera</italic> Jeannel 1946 (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Insecta Mundi </source> <volume>0191</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mawdsley</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sithole</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Dry season ecology of riverine tiger beetles in Kruger National Park, South Africa.</article-title> <source>African Journal of Ecology </source> <volume>46</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>126</fpage>-<lpage>131</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2028.2007.00820.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1365-2028.2007.00820.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mawdsley</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sithole</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Natural history of the African riverine tiger beetle <italic>Chaetodera regalis</italic> (Dejean) (Coleoptera: Cicindelidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History </source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>1891</fpage>-<lpage>1908</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222930903015816" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/00222930903015816</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mawdsley</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sithole</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mawdsley</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Peaceful giant ground beetles: The genus <italic>Tefflus</italic> Latreille (Coleoptera: Carabidae) in the Republic of South Africa.</article-title> <source>Insecta Mundi </source> <volume>0181</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivier</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1795</year>)<source> Entomologie, ou histoire naturelle des insectes, avec leurs caractères génériques et spécifiques, leur description, leur synonymie, et leur figure enluminée, Coléoptères, tome troisième.</source> <publisher-name>De l’Imprimerie de Lanneau</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <lpage>557</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Péringuey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1892a</year>)<article-title> Third contribution to the South-African coleopterous fauna; On beetles collected in tropical south-west Africa by Mr. A. W. Eriksson.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the South African Philosophical Society </source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Peringuey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1892b</year>)<article-title> Fourth contribution to the South African coleopterous fauna: Description of new Coleoptera in the South African Museum.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the South African Philosophical Society </source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/21560382.1889.9526257" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/21560382.1889.9526257</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Péringuey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1896</year>)<article-title> Descriptive catalogue of the Coleoptera of South Africa, part II.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the South African Philosophical Society </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>623</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Perroud</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1846</year>) <article-title>Description de quelques Coléoptères nouveaux ou peu connus (Tribu des Carabiques, famille des Truncatipennes, section des Anthiaires)</article-title>. <source>Annales de la Société Linnéenne de Lyon</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<source> Experimentelle und freilandökologische Untersuchungen zu Aktivitätrhythmik und mikroklimatischem Präferenzverhalten ausgewählter afrikanischer Laufkäferarten der Gattung <italic>Anthia</italic> und <italic>Thermophilum</italic>. Mitteilungen des Internationalen Entomologischen Vereins Frankfurt 26(1/2): 53–84.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Strohmeyer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1928</year>)<source> Systematisches und Zoogeographisches über die Cypholobini (Carab. Anthiinae), ein Beitrag zur Kenntnis der Fauna des afrikanischen Trockenwaldes. Mitteilungen aus dem Zoologischen Museum in Berlin 14(2): 287–462 + 17 pls.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>