<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.89.903</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>First record of the adventive oriental aphid <italic>Schizaphis piricola</italic> (Matsumura, 1917) (Hemiptera, Aphididae) in Europe</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Nicolás</surname> 
                        <given-names>Pérez Hidalgo</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Ángel</surname> 
                        <given-names>Umaran</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>M. Pilar</surname> 
                        <given-names>Mier Durante</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>1</label><italic>Departamento de Biodiversidad y Gestión Ambiental, Universidad de León. 24071. León, España</italic></aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>2</label><italic>Asociación “Fotografía y Biodiversidad”, Torrejón de Ardoz. 28850 Madrid, España</italic></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Nicolás Pérez Hidalgo (<email xlink:type="simple">nperh@unileon.es</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Mike Wilson</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>11</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>89</issue>
            <fpage>41</fpage>
            <lpage>48</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>14</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>22</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Nicolás Pérez Hidalgo, Ángel Umaran, M. Pilar Mier Durante</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The oriental aphid <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis piricola</tp:taxon-name> (Matsumura) is recorded for the first time in Europe, on the ornamental pear tree <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name> in landscaped areas in Madrid (Spain). Data on the morphology of the forms on primary host (apterous and alate fundatrigeniae and fundatrices), and their biology and distribution are given. The keys for identifying species of <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Schizaphis)</tp:taxon-name> in the Iberian Peninsula are updated. Two species of aphids are also recorded for the first time on <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis piricola</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Aphis pomi</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><italic>Schizaphis piricola</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>aphids</kwd>
                <kwd>adventive species</kwd>
                <kwd>Spain</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name> Börner contains approximately 36 Palearctic species and 6 Nearctic ones. Is a genus resembling <tp:taxon-name>Rhopalosiphum</tp:taxon-name> Koch with little differences between both genus, and for this reason require further taxonomical and molecular study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Blackman and Eastop 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Foottit et al. 2008</xref>). The species of <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name> are characterised by more or less cylindrical siphunculi slightly constrained at the apex, ultimate rostral segment short and heart size, absence of dorsal cuticular ornamentation, and alatae with two branches on the medial vein of the wings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Pérez Hidalgo and Mier Durante 2005</xref><!--PageBreak-->). Most of the species in the genus are monoecious on species of <tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Juncaceae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Cyperaceae</tp:taxon-name> but a few mainly oriental species, are dioecious with species of <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus</tp:taxon-name> as the primary host, where they lay their cold-resistant eggs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Blackman and Eastop 2006</xref>).</p>
            <p>Twenty-seven species have been recorded in Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Holman 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Nieto Nafría et al. 2010</xref>): 21 in the nominal subgenus, 5 in the subgenus <tp:taxon-name>Paraschizaphis</tp:taxon-name> and one in the subgenus <tp:taxon-name>Euschizaphis</tp:taxon-name>. Eight of them were recorded in the Iberian Peninsula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Pérez Hidalgo and Mier Durante 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Blackman and Eastop 2006</xref>): <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis graminum</tp:taxon-name> (Rondani), <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis longicaudata</tp:taxon-name> Hille Ris Lambers, <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis pyri</tp:taxon-name> Shaposhnikov, <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis rotundiventris</tp:taxon-name> (Signoret), <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Euschizaphis) palustris</tp:taxon-name> (Theobald), <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Paraschizaphis) caricis</tp:taxon-name> (Schouteden), <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Paraschizaphis) rosazevedoi</tp:taxon-name> (Ilharco) and <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Paraschizaphis) scirpi</tp:taxon-name> (Passerini). Of these, only <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis pyri</tp:taxon-name>, has <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus communis</tp:taxon-name> as its primary host and <tp:taxon-name>Cyperaceae</tp:taxon-name> as its secondary host; the rest live on <tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name> or <tp:taxon-name>Cyperaceae</tp:taxon-name> without causing financial loss, except for <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis graminum</tp:taxon-name> which can be a cereal pest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Blackman and Eastop 2000</xref>).</p>
	            <p>A photograph of a colony of aphids on the pear tree of oriental origin <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name> Decne in “Juan Carlos I park”, Barajas (Madrid, Spain) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) taken on 26th April, 2009 and posted on the “Biodiversidad Virtual” portal (http://www.biodiversidadvirtual.org/) enabled the oriental species <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis piricola</tp:taxon-name> (Matsumura) to be detected for the first time in Europe. Its presence was confirmed in a study of samples collected the following spring on the same host and in the same place. Its route of entry into Europe is probably linked to when the host plant was imported, as is the case of many other species introduced into Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Coeur d’acier et al. 2010</xref>).</p>
            <p>This finding is yet another example of how social networks play an important role in our knowledge of biodiversity and the detection and/or monitoring of invasive or endangered species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Pérez Hidalgo et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Silverton 2010</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Studied material"><title>Studied material</title>
            <p>Samples containing several apterae (3 fundatrices and 15 fundatrigeniae, measured) and alatae (15 measured) were collected between 11th April and 4th May, 2010 in “Juan Carlos I park”, Barajas (Madrid, Spain) [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">40°28'12.77"N, 3°35'6.22"W</named-content>] (reference M-222). Several populations were also located on the same host on 7th May, 2010 in Torrejón de Ardoz (Madrid, Spain) [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">40°27'23.17"N, 3°28'3.02"W</named-content>] (M-224) and at the “Vallecas Villa” railway station (Madrid, Spain) [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">40°22"6.23"N, 3°37'1.15"W</named-content>] (M-225) on 17th May, 2010. These samples are deposited in the aphid collection of the University of León, Spain and the samples of associated ants in the Collection of the Universidad Autónoma de Barcelona, Spain (Dr. Xavier Espadaler).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Description of the forms of Schizaphis piricola on primary host"><title>Description of the forms of Schizaphis piricola on primary host</title>
            <p>The apterous fundatrigeniae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B, E, H</xref>) are between 1.47 and 2.50 mm long and yellowish green to green, with pale antennae and siphunculi bearing dark tips<!--PageBreak--> and dark tarsi. Antennae 0.65 to 0.90 times the body; processus terminalis of antennal segment VI 3.13 to 3.92 times its base, and 0.97 to 1.13 times antennal segment III. Antennae without secondary rhinaria. Apical rostral segment 0.90 to 1.09 times second segment of posterior tarsi and usually with 2 accessory setae. Dorsal sclerotization absent. Marginal papillae on abdominal segments I to VII, absent on III to V in some specimens. Dorsoabdominal setae of anterior terguites shorter (17 to 30 μm) than those of posterior (55 to 90 μm), ventral setae intermediate in size (45 to 60 μm). Siphunculi cylindrical, with weakly defined subapical constriction, 0.12 to 0.19 times body and 1.84 to 2.12 times cauda. Cauda 0.17 to 0.19 mm, 1.21 to 1.46 times basal width, bearing 7 to 9 setae. Tibiae of posterior legs 0.44 to 0.50 times body.</p>
            <p>The fundatrices (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A, D, G</xref>) resemble the apterous fundatrigeniae except for the characteristics of the “fundatrix facies” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Lees 1961</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Miyazaki 1987</xref>): shorter antennae (1.05–1.25 mm and 0.40 to 0.47 times body), processus terminalis of antennal segment VI (1.82 to 2.18 times base and 0.71 to 0.72 times antennal segment III), siphunculi (approximately 0.10 times body and 1.47 to 1.53 times cauda) and legs (posterior tibiae 0.35 to 0.37 times body).</p>
            <p>Alatae fundatrigeniae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C, F, I</xref>) 2.10 to 2.52 mm, green, antennae and siphunculi dark, cauda lighter in colour. Well-pigmented marginal sclerites in ter<!--PageBreak-->guites II to IV, postsiphuncular sclerites fully developed and spinopleural pigmented bands always present on abdominal segments VI to VIII and also occasionally on III to V. Antennae 0.71 to 0.80 times body; processus terminalis of antennal segment VI 3.41 to 5.18 times base; antennal segments III, IV and V bearing 15–32, 7–18, 0–6 secondary rhinaria, respectively. Siphunculi 1.68 to 1.80 times cauda. The remaining characters are similar to those of the apterae.</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name> with fruit (<bold>A</bold>), malformation caused by <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis piricola</tp:taxon-name> (Matsumura) on <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name> leaves (<bold>B</bold>), apterous fundatrigeniae (<bold>C</bold>) and alate fundatrigeniae (<bold>D</bold>) of <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis piricola</tp:taxon-name>, the arrows indicate the tips of the two branches of the medial vein.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-049-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 2.</label>
                <caption><p>Fundatrix (<bold>A</bold>), apterous fundatrigenia (<bold>B</bold>) and alate fundatrigenia (<bold>C</bold>).</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-049-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 3.</label>
                <caption><p>Antennae (<bold>A, B, C</bold>), siphunculi (<bold>D, E, F</bold>) and cauda (<bold>G, H, I</bold>) of fundatrix (<bold>A, D, G</bold>), apterous fundatrigenia (<bold>B, E, H</bold>) and alate fundatrigenia (<bold>C, F, I</bold>) of <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis piricola</tp:taxon-name> (Matsumura).</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-049-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution</title>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis piricola</tp:taxon-name> (Matsumura) is an aphid of oriental origin which, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Holman (2009)</xref>, had only been recorded in China (north east, south east and Taiwan), Japan and Korea, though <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Lee et al. (2002)</xref> have records for India and Pakistan.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, it is possible that <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis piricola</tp:taxon-name> is now more widely distributed because <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name> is a very commonly planted ornamental tree species. For example, in the United States there is evidence that this tree species is rapidly becoming invasive in much of its horticultural range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Vincent 2005</xref>) and it is possible that the aphid is present at this moment.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Biology"><title>Biology</title>
            <p>It is a holocyclic dioecious species with species of pear tree (<tp:taxon-name>Pyrus</tp:taxon-name> sp.) as its primary host and <tp:taxon-name>Cyperaceae</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Carex</tp:taxon-name> spp. and <tp:taxon-name>Cyperus rotundus</tp:taxon-name> L.) as secondary host (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Miyazaki 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Blackman and Eastop 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Eastop and Blackman 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Blackman and Eastop 2006</xref>). It has been recorded on <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus</tp:taxon-name> x<italic> bretschneideri</italic> Rehder, <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus communis</tp:taxon-name> L., <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus pyrifolia</tp:taxon-name> (Burm. Fil.) Nakai and <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus ursuriensis</tp:taxon-name> Maxim. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Blackman and Eastop 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Holman 2009</xref>). There are also records on <tp:taxon-name>Prunus persica</tp:taxon-name> (L.) Batsch in Japan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Higuchi and Miyazaki 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Moritsu 1983</xref>) which we believe should be confirmed. Based on all of these data, this is the first record of an aphid species on <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
            <p>In spring in Spain, colonies of this species cause the leaves of <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name> to curl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>) as occurs in <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus pyrifolia</tp:taxon-name> in Japan, Korea and China (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Essig and Kuwana 1918</xref>), and are attended by the ant <tp:taxon-name>Tapinoma nigerrimum</tp:taxon-name> (Nylander). The fundatrices appear at the beginning of April and the alatae leave the primary host in mid June to colonize their secondary hosts. Efforts to locate the virginogeniae in these hosts in summer, or alatae re-migrating to the primary hosts in autumn, have so far produced no results.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Damage to the host plant"><title>Damage to the host plant</title>
            <p>The direct action of sucking by the aphids (clearly seen in the curling of the leaves), and indirect damage caused by the honeydew they excrete, which covers the leaves, can affect the normal growth of the trees, all the more so if other aphid species (<tp:taxon-name>Aphis pomi<!--PageBreak--></tp:taxon-name> De Geer 1773 and <tp:taxon-name>Dysaphis</tp:taxon-name> sp.) sometimes forming mixed colonies with <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis piricola</tp:taxon-name>, are present.</p>
            <p>The trees of <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name> in “Juan Carlos I park” (Barajas, Madrid, Spain), which have been monitored more carefully, were planted two years ago and do not seem to have reached the height and size expected for this species. In any case, a more in-depth study of the population dynamics and auxiliary fauna (coccinellidae, syrphids, etc…) is necessary, taking into account other variables (humidity, temperature, etc…), to be able to reach conclusions on possible damage.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Identification keys"><title>Identification keys</title>
            <p>The following keys enable all the species in the subgenus <tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis</tp:taxon-name> recorded in the Iberian Peninsula to be separated.</p>
            <sec sec-type="Species key (apterae viviparae females)"><title>Species key (apterae viviparae females)</title>
            <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi pale with pigmented apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A, B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D, E</xref>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi entirely dark</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi 0.8 times cauda at most. Usually on <tp:taxon-name>Phalaris arundinacea</tp:taxon-name></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Schizaphis) longicaudata</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi at least 0.9 times cauda. On many species of <tp:taxon-name>Gramineae</tp:taxon-name> and on <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi 1.1 to 1.6 times cauda. On many species of <tp:taxon-name>Gramineae</tp:taxon-name></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Schizaphis) graminum</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi 1.82 to 2.1 times cauda in apterous fundatrigeniae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref>) and 1.47–1.53 in fundatrices (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>). On <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name> (primary host)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Schizaphis) piricola</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Processus terminalis of antennal segment VI 3.6 to 4.5 times its base. Siphunculi 2.5 times cauda at most. Marginal papillae on abdominal segments I, VI and VII. On <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus communis</tp:taxon-name> (primary host) or <tp:taxon-name>Ciperaceae</tp:taxon-name> (secondary host)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Schizaphis) pyri</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Processus terminalis of antennal segment VI 4.7 to 6.8 times its base. Siphunculi at least 2.5 times cauda. Marginal papillae on abdominal segments I and VII only. On <tp:taxon-name>Cyperus</tp:taxon-name> and seldom other plants</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Schizaphis) rotundiventris</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Species key (alate viviparous females)"><title>Species key (alate viviparous females)</title>
            <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi pale with pigmented apex</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi entirely dark (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3F</xref>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi 0.8 times cauda at most. Normally on <tp:taxon-name>Phalaris arundinacea</tp:taxon-name></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Schizaphis) longicaudata</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi at least 0.9 times cauda. On many species of <tp:taxon-name>Gramineae</tp:taxon-name> and on <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi same size as cauda. Bearing 4–10, 0–4 and 0–1 secondary rhynaria on antennal segments III, IV and V, respectively. On many species of <tp:taxon-name>Gramineae</tp:taxon-name></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Schizaphis) graminum</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3F</xref>) 1.6 to 1.8 times cauda. Bearing 18 to 32, 7–18 and 2–6 secondary rhynaria on antennal segments III, IV and V, respectively. On <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus calleryana</tp:taxon-name> (primary host)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Schizaphis) piricola</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi 0.1 times body at most and 1.5 to 1.8 times cauda. Processus terminalis of antennal segment VI 3.6 to 5.0 times its base and 1.1 to 1.6 times antennal segment III, and approximately 2.0 times siphunculi. On <tp:taxon-name>Pyrus communis</tp:taxon-name> (primary host) and <tp:taxon-name>Ciperaceae</tp:taxon-name> (primary host)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Schizaphis) pyri</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siphunculi at least 0.1 times body and 1.1 to 3.0 times cauda. Processus terminalis of antennal segment VI 4.7 to 6.0 times its base and 1.3–1.8 times antennal segment III. On <tp:taxon-name>Cyperus</tp:taxon-name></td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Schizaphis (Schizaphis) rotundiventris</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowlegements</title>
            <p>The authors would like to express their gratitude to Xavier Espadaler (Unidad de Ecología y CREAF, Universidad Autónoma de Barcelona) for identifying the ants associated to this species. This study was carried out as part of the “Proyecto Fauna Ibérica IX” (CGL2007-66786-C08-03).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastop</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<source> Aphids on the World’s Trees. An Identification and Information Guide.</source> <publisher-name>CAB International</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Wallingford</publisher-loc>, 8 + <lpage>987</lpage> pp. + 16 pl.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastop</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<source> Aphids on the World’s Crops. An identification guide (second edition).</source> <publisher-name>J. Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc>, 8 + <lpage>466</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastop</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> Aphids on the World’s Herbaceous Plants and Shrubs. (Volume 1 Host Lists and Keys / Volume 2 The aphids).</source> <publisher-name>J. Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc>, 8 + <lpage>1439</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coeur d’acier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez Hidalgo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrović-Obradović</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Aphids (Hemiptera, Aphididae). Chapter 9.2. In: Roques A et al. (Eds) Alien terrestrial arthropods of Europe.</article-title> <source>BioRisk</source> <volume>4</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>435</fpage>-<lpage>474</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastop</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Some new synonyms in Aphididae (Hemiptera: Sternorrhyncha).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1089</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Essig</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuwana</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1918</year>)<article-title> Some Japanese Aphididae.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences</source> <volume>8</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>112</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Foottit</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maw</surname><given-names>HEL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Dohlen</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>DPN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Species identification of aphids (Insecta: Hemiptera: Aphididae) through DNA barcodes.</article-title> <source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source> <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1189</fpage>-<lpage>1201</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>)<article-title> A tentative catalogue of host plants of Aphidoidea in Japan.</article-title> <source>Insecta Matsumurana</source> <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Host plant catalog of aphids – Palaearctic Region.</source> <publisher-name>Springer Science + Business Media B.V</publisher-name>, <lpage>1216</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Havelka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<source> Illustrated Catalogue of Aphididae in the Korean Peninsula. Part I, Subfamily Aphidinae (Hemiptera: Sternorrhyncha). Insects of Korea Series 9.</source> <publisher-name>Korea Research Institute of Bioscience and Biotechnology &amp; Center for Insect Systematics</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Seoul</publisher-loc>, <lpage>239</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>)<article-title> Clonal polymorphism in aphids.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Insect Polymorphims. Symposia of the Royal Entomological Society of London 1</source>, <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Forms and Morphs of Aphids.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Minks</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrewijn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Aphids, their biology, natural enemies and control.</source> Volume <volume>2A</volume>. <publisher-name>Research Institute for Plant Protection</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Wageningen</publisher-loc>, <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> <italic>Schizaphis</italic> (Homoptera, Aphididae) of Japan with descriptions of two new species.</article-title> <source>Kontyû</source> <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moritsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<source> Aphids of Japan in Colors.</source> <publisher-name>Taito-ku</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Tokio</publisher-loc>, <lpage>545</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieto Nafría</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andreev</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Binazzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mier Durante</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez Hidalgo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakauskas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stekolshchikov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source> Aphidoidea. Fauna Europaea version 2.2.</source> <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.faunaeur.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.faunaeur.org</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez Hidalgo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mier Durante</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Género <italic>Schizaphis</italic>. Hemiptera, AphididaeIII. Nieto Nafría JM, Mier Durante MP, García Prieto F, Pérez Hidalgo N.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> et al.(<role>Eds</role>) <source>Fauna Ibérica</source>, vol. <volume>28</volume>, <publisher-name>Museo de Ciencias Naturales, CSIC</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Madrid</publisher-loc>, <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez Hidalgo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Umaran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mier Durante</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieto Nafría</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Aportaciones a la afidofauna íbero-balear (Hemiptera, Aphididae) a partir de las fotografías (y de sus metadatos) depositadas en el “Banco Taxonómico Faunístico Digital de los Invertebrados Ibéricos (B.T.F.D.I.I.)”.</article-title> <source>Graellsia</source> <volume>65</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>171</fpage>-<lpage>181</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Silverton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Taxonomy: include social networking.</article-title> <source>Nature</source> <volume>467</volume>: <lpage>788</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> On the spread and current distribution of <italic>Pyrus calleryana</italic> in the United States.</article-title> <source>Castanea</source> <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>