<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.112.1110</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Review of the genus <italic>Plistobunus</italic> Pocock, 1903, with description of a new species from Hainan Island, China (Opiliones, Laniatores, Epedanidae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Lian</surname>
                        <given-names>Wei-Guang</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:E2EFBC5F-448D-490F-8326-6CD2648FF317</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Zhang</surname>
                        <given-names>Chao</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7BF197AF-0B03-4F35-81C7-1E4AD1DE77EE</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Zhang</surname>
                        <given-names>Feng</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:904C4445-AAEA-40BC-B418-502053EF39B8</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Laboratory Animal Science, Hebei Medical University; Key Lab of Laboratory Animal Science of Hebei Province, Shijiazhuang, 050017, China
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>College of Life Sciences, Hebei University, Baoding, Hebei 071002, China
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Feng Zhang (<email xlink:type="simple">dudu06042001@163.com</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Christine Rollard</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>112</issue>
            <fpage>39	</fpage>
            <lpage>52</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>9</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>7</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Wei-Guang Lian, Chao Zhang, Feng Zhang</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:D1D92EF4-1997-4C0D-BE8B-567186C1F145</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pocock, 1903 and its type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus rapax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pocock, 1903 are redescribed based on the type material deposited in the British Museum of Natural History (BMNH), London. In addition, a new <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species from Hainan Island is described and illustrated of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus columnarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> The new species is diagnosed by having a row of 12 setiferous tubercles on anterior margin of carapace, and the femur of pedipalpus ventrally with 13 setiferous tubercles in male.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>Arachnida</kwd>
                <kwd>harvestmen</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Plistobunus</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>China</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The <tp:taxon-name>Epedanidae</tp:taxon-name> Sørensen, 1886 includes 73 genera and 188 species, and they are endemic to Asia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Kury 1993</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Pinto-da-Rocha and Giribet (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Kury (2007)</xref>, no systematic research to this family in the later decades, although four <!--PageBreak-->new species are occasionally being proposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Kury 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Zhu and Lian 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Lian et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Zhang and Zhang 2010</xref>).</p>
            <p>This family was removed from the <tp:taxon-name>Phalangodidae</tp:taxon-name> Simon, 1879 by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Kury (1993)</xref>, based mainly on the presence of a well developed immovable sac (which he called ‘follis’) and the absence of complex introverting structures in the penis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Lian et al. 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Kury (2003)</xref> recognized the following four subfamilies under <tp:taxon-name>Epedanidae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Acrobuninae</tp:taxon-name> Roewer, 1912; <tp:taxon-name>Sarasinicinae</tp:taxon-name> Roewer, 1923; <tp:taxon-name>Epedaninae</tp:taxon-name> Sørensen, 1886 and <tp:taxon-name>Dibuninae</tp:taxon-name> Roewer, 1912.</p>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name></italic> of <tp:taxon-name>Epedaninae</tp:taxon-name> was erected by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Pocock in 1903</xref> based on a single male, the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus rapax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pocock, 1903. The original description provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Pocock (1903)</xref> was brief and the figure was very schematic. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Roewer (1912)</xref> failed to examine the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus rapax</tp:taxon-name></italic>, he redescribed the genus characters in detail with the helps of Hirst who was an arachnologist in London. Moreover, the description was mentioned again in Roewer’s voluminous book, as well as the only figure which is from Pocock (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Roewer 1923</xref>). In 1937, Roewer finally examined, redescribed and illustrated the type specimen. So far, there is no further report for this genus and species.</p>
            <p>In 2009, we explored Hainan Island, China, and collected some laniatorid harvestmen specimens by sieving the leaf in the forest. Among the collected specimens, we recognized a species new to science, and describe it under the name <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus columnarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. here. Additionally, we loaned the type specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus rapax</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the British Museum of Natural History (BMNH), London, examined, redescribed and illustrated it, and revised the generic characters based on the two species above.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>Taxonomic methods follow outline proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Acosta et al. (2007)</xref>. The type materials of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was loaned from the British Museum of Natural History, London, British (BMNH) and was preserved in 75% Industrial Methylated Spirit (IMS), also was examined, drawn and measured under a Tech XTL-II stereomicroscope equipped with an Abbe drawing device. Type specimens of the new species were preserved in 75% ethanol (deposited in the Museum of Hebei University, Baoding, China (MHBU)) and were examined and drawn under a Leica M165c stereomicroscope equipped with drawing tube. The male genitalia were placed firstly in hot lactic acid, followed by distilled water to expand those parts for observation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Schwendinger and Martens 2002</xref>). The terminology of the setae on penis follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Ubick and Briggs (2004)</xref>, except for basal setae of glans, which is presented by current authors. All measurements are given in mm.</p>
            <p>The following abbreviations are used in the text: BS, basal sac; DP, dorsal plate; DS, dorsal setae; DSL, dorsal stylar lobe; G, glans; GBS, basal setae of glans; LP, lateral plate; LS, lateral setae; S, stylus; SL, stylar lobe; VP, ventral plate; VS, ventral setae; VSL, ventral stylar lobe.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Plistobunus</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Pocock, 1903</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name>
                             <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Pocock 1903</xref>: 447; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Roewer 1912</xref>: 232; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">1923</xref>: 207; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">1938</xref>: 124.</comment>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species:</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus rapax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pocock, 1903, by original designation.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Medium-sized epedanines (3.03–3.57) with a long median spine on the ocularium. Carapace with a row of 4–6 setiferous tubercles on each side of the frontal margin. Area II with a pair of spines. Area IV with a median spine. Area IV and all free tergites with a transverse row of hair-tipped tubercles. The proximal segment of chelicera elongated and armed above with numerous tubercles, of which distal one enlarged the largest on the dorsal surface. Pedipalpus elongated; femur of male with 9–13 setiferous tubercles ventrally, a longitudinal row of 7–9 setiferous tubercles dorsally, and with two tubercles on medial side distally; patella of male with two setiferous tubercle disto-medially and three setiferous tubercles ectally. Distitarsus of leg I with two segments. Shaft of penis widened distally. DP conspicuous, VP complex. G protrude sideways beyond the distal penis and near the DP. S is surrounded and protected by SL. BS globular, immovable and entire hidden into truncus.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution:</title>
                    <p>China (Hongkong, Hainan).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>The male genitalia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus rapax</tp:taxon-name></italic> remains unknown, because the penis was lost (see remarks below). According to study of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus columnarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., we tentatively supplemented the male genital structure to the generic characters.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">rapax</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Plistobunus_rapax</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Pocock, 1903</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–6</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus rapax</tp:taxon-name>
                            <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Pocock 1903</xref>: 447, fig. 2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Roewer 1912</xref>: 232; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">1923</xref>: 207, fig. 236; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">1938</xref>: 124, fig. 43.</comment>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material examined"><title>Type material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype <italic>♂</italic>, in 75% Industrial Methylated Spirit (IMS), labelled as follows: “56. 113, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus rapax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pocock, Hong Kong” (BMNH 56. 113).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Redescription"><title>Redescription.</title>
                    <p>Male holotype (habitus see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>): Coloration. Body yellowish brown and appendages yellow. Lateral margins and free tergites banded with dark brown. Chelicerae dorsally reticulated with dark brown.</p>
                    <sec sec-type="Dorsum"><title>Dorsum.</title>
                        <p>Dorsal scutum nearly trapezoid in shape; widest portion at fourth scutal area; anterior margin of carapace armed with a transverse row of four to five setiferous tubercles. Ocularium long oval, armed with a short median spine. Opisthosomal region of scutum with four areas, first area completely smooth, without a median furrow or line; second area has four hair-tipped tubercles, of which two median ones are <!--PageBreak-->longer than others; third area covered with two relatively tubercles; fourth area with a transverse row of seven tubercles, of which the median one is longest. Free tergites with hair-tipped granules arraged in a transverse; each lateral margin of the scutum with a longitudinal row of granules.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Venter"><title>Venter.</title>
                        <p>Coxae I–III armed with a row of hair-tipped tubercles, additionally coxa I covered with a row of relatively small hair-tipped tubercles. Coxa III with a row of low humps along front and hind margins. Coxa IV with a row of small hair-tipped granules. Some small hair-tipped granules scttered over surfaces of coxae I–IV. Tracheal stigma clearly visible.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Chelicera"><title>Chelicera (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2–4</xref>).</title>
                        <p>Proximal segment fairly strong, distinctly armed with two prominent spines dorsally, numerous hair-tipped tubercles scattered over ventral and lateral surface. Second segment distinctly expanded, armed with a row of four strong hair-tipped bifid tubercles on the prodorsal surface. A few hair-tipped granules scattered over the prodorsal surface. Fingers relatively strong, cutting edges dentate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Pedipalpus"><title>Pedipalpus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 5–6</xref>).</title>
                        <p>Relatively long and slender. Trochanter with a single setiferous tubercle dorsally, three ventrally. Femur dorsally with a longitudinal row of seven setiferous tubercles; ventrally with a longitudinal row of nine setiferous tubercles; distally with two setiferous tubercles medially. Patella ectally with three setiferous tubercles, disto-medially with two ones. Tibia with three medial and five ectal setiferous tubercles. Tarsus with four setiferous tubercles on both sides of ventral surface. Tibia with a longitudinal row of three granules ventrally. Tarsal claw long, strongly curved.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Legs"><title>Legs.</title>
                        <p>All of legs were destroyed and missing but their trochanters ventrally with two hair-tipped tubercles, their femora armed with a row of setiferous tubercles.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Penis"><title>Penis.</title>
                        <p>Lost.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Measurements"><title>Measurements.</title>
                        <p>Body 3.03 long, scutum 2.64 long, 2.25 with at the widest portion; ocularium 0.65 long, 0.35 wide.</p>
                    </sec>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China: Hong Kong.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus rapax</tp:taxon-name></italic> is only known from the type specimen. To make matters worse, the type specimen is in an incomplete state. All legs were missing and the penis is lost. Roewer at first (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1912</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">1923</xref>) did not examine the holotype by himself, and learned from Hirst that all the tarsi of legs in type specimen were missing. According to the description of Pocock, he assumed that the species should be placed in the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Epedaninae</tp:taxon-name>, family <tp:taxon-name>Phalangodidae</tp:taxon-name>. Later Roewer (1937) examined the type specimen, he found that all legs were lost, then he (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">1938</xref>) listed it also in the family <tp:taxon-name>Epedanidae</tp:taxon-name>, merely based on the original description and Hirst’s information. We can not confirm when the penis was lost, as Roewer did not usually describe and illustrate the structure of penis, because he was unaware of the importance of genital diagnostic characters.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–6.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus rapax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pocock, 1903, male (holotype) <bold>1</bold> Body, dorsal view <bold>2</bold> Left chelicera, medial view <bold>3</bold> Same, ectal view <bold>4</bold> Distal segment of the left chelicera, frontal view <bold>5</bold> Left pedipalpus, ectal view <bold>6</bold> Same, medial view. Scale bars: 0.5 mm (1–6).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-112-039-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 7–14.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus columnarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. male <bold>7</bold> Body, dorsal view <bold>8</bold> Same, lateral view <bold>9</bold> Left chelicera, medial view <bold>10</bold> Same, ectal view <bold>11</bold> Distal segment of the left chelicera, frontal view <bold>12</bold> Proximal cheliceral segment, dorsal view <bold>13</bold> Left pedipalpus, ectal view <bold>14</bold> Same, medial view. Scale bars: 1 mm (7–14).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-112-039-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">columnarius</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1E2AB18D-7941-495F-A8C5-1406864D6F79</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Plistobunus_columnarius</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–23</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male (Opi.11061601), CHINA: Hainan Province, Tunchang County, Xichang Town [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">N19°26´, E 110°02´</named-content>], June 16, 2009, C. Zhang leg. (MHBU), paratype 1♀(Opi.11061602), same data as holotype.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>The new species is similar to the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus rapax</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pocock, 1903, but can be easily distinguished from the latter by: 1) anterior margin of carapace with a row of six setiferous tubercles on either side; 2) the femur of pedipalpus ventrally with 13 setiferous tubercles in male and seven setiferous tubercles in female; 3) the medial surface of cheliceral proximal segment with a huge protuberance at base.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific name is derived from the Latin adjectives “columnaris” meaning columnar, refers to shape of the stylus in male penis.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Male (holotype) habitus as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–8</xref>. Coloration: entire body rusty yellow, with somewhat dark brown to blackish brown patches on the dorsum; median area of carapace with blackish brown reticulations; each side of carapace dark brown; lateral ridges of the scute margined with blackish brown; venter concolorous with dorsum; coxae with dark brown reticulations; free sternites with transverse band of blackish brown; chelicerae rusty yellow, with blackish brown reticulate markings above; pedipalpus dark brown, tibia and tarsus paler, tarsus with dark brown reticulations dorsally; legs brown, trochanters yellow, femur, patella and tibia with blackish brown reticulations, metatarsus and tarsus lighter.</p>
                    <sec sec-type="Dorsum"><title>Dorsum.</title>
                        <p>Dorsal scutum trapezoid in shape; widest portion of body at forth scutal area. Carapace with a row of six small setiferous tubercles on each side of front margin. Surface of dorsum almost smooth. Ocularium wide oval, remote from anterior border of scutum, armed with a long erect median spine. Opisthosomal region of scutum with four areas, first area well defined, entire. Second area with two long median spines. Third with a pair of hair-tipped tubercles removed from each other. Fourth with a transverse row of nine tubercles, median tubercle enlarged into a spine. Each lateral margin of the scutum with a longitudinal row of minute hair-tipped granules. Free tergites each with a transverse row of hair-tipped granules spread over its entire width.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Venter"><title>Venter.</title>
                        <p>All coxae and genital operculum granulate. Coxae I–III disto-dorsally with two coarse tubercles on anterior and posterior sides respectively. Coxa IV with a reduced one on medio-prolaterally. Coxa I medio-ventrally and prolaterally with transverse rows of hair-tipped tubercles. Coxae II–III medio-ventrally with a transverse row of same tubercles. Coxa III with prolateral and retrolateral rows of small humps. Coxa IV widened, with hair-tipped granules. Free sternites each with a transverse of hair-tipped granules. Tracheal stigma clearly visible.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Chelicera"><title>Chelicera (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9–12</xref>).</title>
                        <p>Fairly strong. Proximal segment elongated and with numerous hair-tipped tubercles above; the dorsal surface centrally with six hair-tipped tubercles, of which distal one the largest, three medium-sized tubercles posterior to it, and two smaller ones toward the medial side; the ventral surface and the medial surface with rows of eight hair-tipped tubercles respectively, the medial surface with a huge protuberance at base; the ectal surface with a row of seven tubercles. Second segment considerably widened, medially with five enlarged hair-tipped bifid tubercles and ectally with five reduced ones on prodorsal surface, medially with many small hair-tipped granules on ventral surface, the largest one towards the base of fingers. Fingers relatively strong, inner edges toothed as illustrated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 11</xref>): moveable finger with four teeth, the proximal one square, the middle with two crest teeth, the distal one rectangular; fixed finger with five teeth, the proximal two formed one bifid tooth, the middle with one conical tooth, the distal with two lower than the middle one.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Pedipalpus"><title>Pedipalpus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 13–14</xref>)</title>
                        <p>Coxa dorsally with one proximal and one strong distal bifurcate setiferous tubercles, ventrally with a row of five setiferous tubercles, two enlarged ones additionally at base. Trochanter ventrally with three setiferous tubercles, dorsall<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->y with one. Femur elongate, ventrally with 13 setiferous tubercles, dorsally with nine ones of which the distal two inconspicuous, distally on medial side with two setiferous tubercles of which the distal one tipped and the other one conical. Patella very long, widening abruptly distally, with two setiferous tubercle disto-medially and three setiferous tubercles ectally, dorsally with five inconspicuous granules. Tibia with three medial and five ectal setiferous tubercles, with a row of six hair-tipped granules in the ventral surface. Tarsus with four setiferous tubercles on both sides of ventral surface, with three granules in the ventral surface. Tarsal claw nearly as long as tarsus, strongly curved.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Legs"><title>Legs.</title>
                        <p>Legs I–II slender and legs III–IV strong. Trochanters I–II each with one hair-tipped tubercles arising distally on the dorsal surface, the ventral surface with three hair-tipped tubercles. Trochanters III-IV smooth dorsally, with inconspicuous granules ventrally. Femur I–II ventrally with a row of 10 or 17 setiferous tubercles respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 15</xref>). Femur III ventrally with two rows of 12 and 14 setiferous tubercles respectively. Femur IV ventrally with two rows of many granules. The remaining leg-segments unarmed, smooth, with hairs. Tarsi III–IV with bare double claws, without scopulae. Tarsal formula: 8/17/7/8. Distitarsus of the first and second tarsi with two segments.</p>
                     </sec>
                     <sec sec-type="Penis"><title>Penis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 25–31</xref>).</title>
                        <p>slender, its shaft widened distally. The apical structure is divided by lateral incisions into both DP and VP. The VP with complex structures, is separated again by a median cleft, consists of two LPs and the membrane between both sides. The DP simple, distal margin corrugate. G protruding beyond the anterior margin of the dorsal surface. SL somewhat as the shape of tulip ventrally and dorsally, consists of VSL and DSL. The VSL slightly curved toward ventral surface and with a labiate protrusion distally. The DSL petaloid. S smooth, columnar and arising straight from the glans, SL almost entire surrounding the S. BS globular, well developed, immovable and entire sunken into truncus. Setae arranged as follow: 11 VS, four DS, four LS, four GBS.</p>
                     </sec>
                     <sec sec-type="Female"><title>Female (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 16</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">–24</xref>).</title>
                        <p>In general appearance similar to the male but smaller and with abdomen more rounded posteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 17</xref>). Chelicera (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 18–20</xref>) smaller and with reduced tubercles, the proximal segment shorter than those of the male, the second segment is not so greatly enlarged as in the male, inner edges of finger toothed as illustrated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 20</xref>). The pedipalpus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 21–22</xref>) femur with seven reduced setiferous tubercles ventrally and two conspicuous setiferous tubercles dorsally, distally on medial side without any setiferous tubercle; Patella with two setiferous tubercle disto-medially and one setiferous tubercles disto-ectally. Setiferous tubercles of leg I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>), as well as leg II–IV inconspicuous. Tarsal formula: 7/17/7/8. Distitarsus of the first and second tarsi with two segments.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Ovipositor"><title>Ovipositor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 23–24</xref>).</title>
                        <p>Ventral surface with five setae and dorsal surface with six setae. Tip of each seta pinpoint (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 23</xref>).</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Measurements"><title>Measurements.</title>
                    <p>Male holotype (female paratype): body 3.57 (3.37) long, 2.70 (2.65) wide at the widest portion, scutum 3.21 (2.75) long. Ocularium 0.38 (0.33) long, 0.90 (0.68) wide. Pedipalpus claw 0.90 (0.83) long. Penis 1.55 long. Measurements of left pedipalpus and legs as in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
                    </sec>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Habitat"><title>Habitat.</title>
                    <p>Collected by leaf litter sieving in the rubber forest.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China: Hainan (Tunchang County).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>A certain similarity in ornamentation of the new species may be noted with that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus rapax</tp:taxon-name></italic> as figured and described by (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Roewer (1912</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">1923</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">1938</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Pocock (1903)</xref>, e. g., the high erect spine on ocularium, fused scutal areas I–II, a pair of spines on the second opisthosomal area, a spine on the fourth opisthosomal area of the dorsal scutum, the greatly elongate pedipalpus and almost identical chelicera. The style of the ornament of the new species is typical of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Based on above we believe it should be a new species.</p>
                    <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Martens (1988)</xref> suggested that “an intensive search, not only for diverse morphological structures in laniatorid penes, but even more for the function of their movable parts under hemolymph pressure will reveal a wealth of structures up to now largely undiscovered”. Many families (e. g., <tp:taxon-name>Assamiidae</tp:taxon-name> Sørensen, 1884; <tp:taxon-name>Biantidae</tp:taxon-name> Thorell, 1889; <tp:taxon-name>Fissiphalliidae</tp:taxon-name> Martens, 1988; <tp:taxon-name>Oncopodidae</tp:taxon-name> Thorell, 1876; <tp:taxon-name>Phalangodidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Podoctidae</tp:taxon-name> Roewer, 1912) were studied in genital morphology and function. At the meantime, some laniatorid structure cannot be homologized completely. <tp:taxon-name>Epedanidae</tp:taxon-name> is restricted in Asia, among of these known species, Suzuki porvided drawings of genital morphology, however, he failed to give the expanded the structures of the penis.</p>
                    <p>In this paper, we tentatively explain the movement of the penis in the new species briefly. The S is mainly exposed by the movement of VSL and DSL in the opposite direction, DSL tends to move dorsally wider than that of VSL. DSL and VSL like the petal, S is similar to the stamen. The expansion of G resembles the blooming flower (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 31</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 15–22.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus columnarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>15</bold> Right first leg, male, retrolateral view <bold>16</bold> Left first leg, female, retrolateral view <bold>17</bold> Female body, dorsal view <bold>18</bold> Left chelicera, female, medial view <bold>19</bold> Same, ectal view <bold>20</bold> left cheliceral fingers, female, frontal view <bold>21</bold> Left pedipalpus, ectal view <bold>22</bold> Same, medial view. Scale bars: 1 mm (15–19, 21–22); 0.5 mm (20).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-112-039-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 23–31.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus columnarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>23</bold> Ovipositor, dorsal view <bold>24</bold> Ditto, ventral view <bold>25</bold> Entire penis, dorsal view <bold>26</bold> Penis tip, ventral view <bold>27</bold> Ditto, lateral view <bold>28</bold> Ditto, dorsal view <bold>29</bold> Expanded penis, dorsal view <bold>30</bold> Ditto, ventral view <bold>31</bold> Ditto, lateral view. Abbreviations: <bold>BS</bold> basal sac <bold>DP</bold> dorsal plate <bold>DS</bold> dorsal setae <bold>DSL</bold> dorsal stylar lobe <bold>G</bold> glans <bold>GBS</bold> basal setae of glans <bold>LP</bold> lateral plate <bold>LS</bold> lateral setae <bold>S</bold> stylus <bold>SL</bold> stylar lobe <bold>VP</bold> ventral plate <bold>VS</bold> ventral setae <bold>VSL</bold> ventral stylar lobe. Scale bars: 0.5 mm (25); 0.20 mm (26–31); 0.25 (23–24).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-112-039-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <table-wrap position="float" orientation="portrait" id="T1">
                        <label>Table 1.</label>
                        <caption><p>Pedipalpus and leg measurements of the male holotype (female paratype).</p></caption>
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trochanter</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Femur</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patella</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tibia</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metatarsus</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tarsus</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pedipalpus</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63(0.50)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63(2.00)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35(1.13)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18(1.00)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95(0.88)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.74(5.51)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leg I</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50(0.45)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10(1.68)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80(0.58)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50(1.25)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48(1.88)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38(1.20)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.76(7.04)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leg II</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50(0.45)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98(2.45)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83(0.75)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35(1.88)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.13(2.43)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60(2.38)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.39(10.34)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leg III</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50(0.45)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38(2.00)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85(0.63)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63(1.38)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95(2.45)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43(1.25)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.74(8.16)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leg IV</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50(0.45)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00(2.70)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95(0.75)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00(1.75)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95(3.25)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75(1.45)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.15(10.35)</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Kury (1993)</xref> detached the family <tp:taxon-name>Epedanidae</tp:taxon-name> which included four subfamilies (i. e., <tp:taxon-name>Epedaninae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Acrobuninae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Dibuninae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Sarasinicinae</tp:taxon-name>) from the <tp:taxon-name>Phalangodidae</tp:taxon-name> for the first time. Most genera and species were created by Roewer, based on external morphological characters. Suzuki finely described and redescribed some species of <tp:taxon-name>Epedanidae</tp:taxon-name>, especially for the male penis. However, internal relationships of the four subfamilies have not been investigated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Kury 2007</xref>).</p>
            <p>It is obvious to assign <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name></italic> to the <tp:taxon-name>Epedanidae</tp:taxon-name> because its penis possesses immovable sac, and protruding glans which only consists of stylus and stylar lobe. Furthermore, according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Kury (2007)</xref>, the genus should belong to the subfamil<!--PageBreak-->y <tp:taxon-name>Epedaninae</tp:taxon-name> based on morphological characters such as eyes placed laterally at the base of a well-marked common ocularium, tarsi III–IV without scopula and distitarsus I with two tarsomeres.</p>
            <p>The external morphology of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is similar to the genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Euepedanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Roewer, 1915 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoepedanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Suzuki, 1969. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is distinct from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Euepedanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseuduoepedanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the number of tubercles on the femur of pedipalpus ventrally and dorsally. The most significant difference concerns the male genitalia. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Euepedanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has conspicuous ventral plate which is absent in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name></italic>; and glans in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Euepedanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> protrude from the center at the top of penis, while glans in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name></italic> protrude sideways beyond the distal penis and near the dorsal plate; dorsal plate of penis has incision in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudonepedanus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, while absent incision in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name></italic>; and the shape of glans are different in both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudonepedanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <p>The male genitalia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus columnarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is very similar to some other species of <tp:taxon-name>Epedaninae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Acrobuninae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Sarasinicinae</tp:taxon-name> and even <italic>incertae sedis</italic> of <tp:taxon-name>Epedanidae</tp:taxon-name>, respectively <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alloepedanus robustus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Suzuki, 1985 (<tp:taxon-name>Epedaninae</tp:taxon-name>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zepedanulus ishikawai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Suzuki, 1971 (<tp:taxon-name>Epedaninae</tp:taxon-name>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zepedanulus watanabei</tp:taxon-name></italic> Suzuki, 1981 (<tp:taxon-name>Epedaninae</tp:taxon-name>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Toccolus chibai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Suzuki, 1976 (<tp:taxon-name>Epedaninae</tp:taxon-name>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Toccolus globitarsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Suzuki, 1969 (<tp:taxon-name>Epedaninae</tp:taxon-name>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paracrobunus bimaculatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Suzuki, 1977 (<tp:taxon-name>Acrobuninae</tp:taxon-name>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Opelytus spinichelis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Roewer, 1938 (<tp:taxon-name>Sarasinicinae</tp:taxon-name>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pasohnus bispinosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Suzuki, 1976 (<tp:taxon-name>Sarasinicinae</tp:taxon-name>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tokunosia tenuipes tenuipes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Suzuki, 1964 (<italic>incertae sedis</italic>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tokunosia tenuipes taiwana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Suzuki, 1977 (<italic>incertae sedis</italic>).</p>
            <p>Moreover, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alloepedanus robustus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Suzuki, 1985</xref>: 87–89, fig. 10) which is distributed in the Doi Sutep (Thailand, Chieng Mai Province) has similar external morphology with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus columnarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (e.g., ocularium with a long median spine, spination of chelicerae, pedipalpus femur with a row of more than 10 setiferous tubercles dorsally and ventrally, tarsi I–IV with more than six segments, distitarsus I–II with two segments, tarsi III–IV with bare double claws). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alloepedanus robustus</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus columnarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by penis without dorsal plate and the scutal area II without two long median spines.</p>
            <p>Similar concerns apply to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Toccolus globitarsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Suzuki, 1969</xref>: 91–96, figs 9–11), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Toccolus chibai</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Suzuki, 1976</xref>: 15–18, fig. 5), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Opelytus spinichelis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Suzuki, 1976</xref>: 18–20, fig. 6) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pasohnus bispinosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Suzuki, 1976</xref>: 21–23, fig. 8), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Toccolus globitarsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is distributed in the Paktong Chai (Thailand) and others in the Pasoh Forest Reserve (Malaysia). However, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus bispinosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be easily distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus columnarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by two long median spines on the scutal area III instead of the scutal area II.</p>
            <p>The external morphology of other four species (i. e., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zepedanulus watanabei</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zepedanulus ishikawai</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tokunosia tenuipes tenuipes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tokunosia tenuipes taiwana</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paracrobunus bimaculatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> ) is distinct from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus columnarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Alloepedanus robustus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Toccolus globitarsis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Toccolus chibai</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pasohnus bispinosus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. They are all absent a long median spine on ocularium and without conspicuous enlarged tubercles on proximal segment of chelicera. They are distributed mainly in the Thailand (e. g., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zepedanulus watanabei</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Suzuki, 1981</xref>: 268–269, fig. 1)), Ryukyus (e. g., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zepedanulus ishikawai</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Suzuki, 1971</xref>: 196–200, figs 22–30), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tokunosia tenuipes tenuipes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Suzuki, 1971</xref>: 193–196, figs 12–21)), Taiwan Island (e. g., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tokunosia tenuipes taiwana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Suzuki, 1977b</xref>: 124–125, fig. 1)), Philippines (e. g., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paracrobunus bima culatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Suzuki, 1977a</xref>: 17–20, figs 5–6)).</p>
            <p><!--PageBreak-->Based on the references cited above, these species are distributed mainly in Southeast Asia. Furthermore, the male genital morphology of most species also shows great similarity to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Plistobunus columnarius</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., although they belong to different subfamilies presently. For these reasons, we presume they may have a relatively close phylogenetic relationship, not depend only on the external morphological characters which currently support the subfamilies.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack><title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We are grateful to Mrs. Janet Beccaloni for the loan of the valuable type specimen. This work was supported by the Ministry of Science and Technology of the People’s Republic of China (MOST Grant No. 2006FY110500), and in part by the Open Project Program of Key Laboratory of Hebei University (09265631D–10) and the Program of Science &amp; Technology Bureau of Baoding City (11ZF071) to Chao Zhang.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list><title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Acosta</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>González</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tourinho</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Methods for taxonomic study.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto-da-Rocha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giribet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Harvestmen: The Biology of Opiliones.</source> <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Massachusetts and London</publisher-loc>, <fpage>494</fpage>–<lpage>510</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirst</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1911</year>)<article-title> On some new Opiliones from Japan and the Loo-Choo Islands.</article-title> <source>Annals and Magazine of Natural History</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>47</issue>): <fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>636</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kury</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<source> Análise filogenética de Gonyleptoidea (Arachnida, Opiliones, Laniatores).</source> Unpublished Ph. D. Thesis, <publisher-name>Instituto de Biociências, Universidade de São Paulo</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>São Paulo</publisher-loc>, <lpage>73</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kury</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Annotated catalogue of the Laniatores of the New World (Arachnida, Opiliones). Revista Ibérica de Aracnologìa, vol.</article-title> <source>especial monográfico, n°</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>337</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kury</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Epedanidae Sørensen, 1886.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto-da-Rocha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giribet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Harvestmen: The Biology of Opiliones.</source> <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Massachusetts and London</publisher-loc>, <fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kury</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> On the systematic position of <italic>Dino</italic> Loman and <italic>Toccolus</italic> Roewer (Opiliones, Laniatores, Epedanidae), with the description of a new species from western Java, Indonesia.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1932</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kury</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> A new species of the genus <italic>Tithaeus</italic> from China (Arachnida: Laniatores: Epedanidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1841</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> Fissiphalliidae, a new family of South American laniatorean harvestmen (Arachnida: Opiliones).</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift für zoologische Systematik und Evolutionsforschung, Hamburg</source> <volume>26</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>114</fpage>-<lpage>127</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto-Da-Rocha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giribet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Taxonomy.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto-da-Rocha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giribet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Harvestmen: The Biology of Opiliones.</source> <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Massachusetts and London</publisher-loc>, <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1903</year>)<article-title> Fifteen new species and two new genera of tropical southern Opiliones.</article-title> <source>The Annals and Magazine of Natural History, London, Series 7</source>, <volume>11</volume>(<issue>65</issue>): <fpage>433</fpage>-<lpage>450</lpage>, pl. 11-12.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roewer</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>)<article-title> Die Familien der Assamiiden und Phalangodiden der Opiliones-Laniatores. (= Assamiden, Dampetriden, Phalangodiden, Epedaniden, Biantiden, Zalmoxiden, Samoiden, Palpipediden anderer Autoren). Archiv für Naturgeschichte, Berlin, Abt.</article-title> <source>A, Original-Arbeiten</source> <volume>78</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>242</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roewer</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1923</year>)<source> Die Weberknechte der Erde. Systematische Bearbeitung der bisher bekannten Opiliones.</source> <publisher-name>Gustav Fischer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Jena</publisher-loc>, <lpage>1116</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roewer</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1938</year>)<article-title> Über Acrobuninae, Epedaninae und Sarasinicinae. Weitere Weberknechte IX. (9. Erganzung der "Weberknechte der Erde" 1923).</article-title> <source>Veröffentlichungen aus dem Deutschen Kolonial- und Übersee-Museum in Bremen</source>, <publisher-loc>Bremen</publisher-loc>, <volume>2</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>, plates 1–10.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwendinger</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> A taxonomic revision of the family Oncopodidae III: Further new species of <italic>Gnomulus</italic> Thorell (Opiliones, Laniatores). Rev.</article-title> <source>Suisse Zool</source> <volume>109</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>)<article-title> Some phalangids from Thailand.</article-title> <source>Journal of Science of the Hiroshima University, Series B, Division 1 (Zoology)</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>101</lpage> + pl. I.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<article-title> Opiliones of the Ryukyus.</article-title> <source>Journal of Science of the Hiroshima University, Series B, Division 1 (Zoology)</source> <volume>23</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>213</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>)<article-title> Report on a collection of opilionids from Pasoh Forest Reserve, West Malaysia.</article-title> <source>Nature and Life in Southeast Asia</source> <source>7</source>: <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>, 13 Figs</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977a</year>)<article-title> Report on a collection of opilionids from the Philippines.</article-title> <source>Journal of Science of the Hiroshima University, Series B, Division 1 (Zoology)</source>, <publisher-loc>Hiroshima</publisher-loc> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>, figs 1–56, map 1.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977b</year>)<article-title> Opiliones from Taiwan (Arachnida).</article-title> <source>Journal of Science of the Hiroshima University, Series B, Division 1 (Zoology)</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>, figs 1–4.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<article-title> Three opilionids from Thailand.</article-title> <source>Annotationes Zoologicae Japonenses</source> <volume>54</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>267</fpage>-<lpage>272</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> A synopsis of the Opiliones of Thailand (Arachnida) I. Cyphophthalmi and Laniatores.</article-title> <source>Steenstrupia</source> <volume>11</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> A new <italic>Tithaeus</italic> species from Hainan Island, China (Arachnida, Opiliones, Laniatores, Epedanidae), with a key to the Chinese species.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys</source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.67.705" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.3897/zookeys.67.705</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> First record of the genus <italic>Euepedanus</italic> from China, with the description of a new species (Opiliones: Laniatores: Epedanidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1367</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ubick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> The harvestman family Phalangodidae. 5. New records and species of <italic>Texella</italic> Goodnight and Goodnight (Opiliones: Laniatores).</article-title> <source>Texas Memorial Museum, Speleological Monographs</source> <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>141</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>