<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.229.3678</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new fossil cricket of the genus 
                    <italic>Proanaxipha</italic> in Miocene amber from the Dominican Republic (Orthoptera, Gryllidae, Pentacentrinae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Heads</surname>
                        <given-names>Sam W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:6AA1941C-335C-42E9-A542-CD2A01EE1F16</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Penney</surname>
                        <given-names>David</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:5D403689-0F2E-4AE5-AFC4-DA85ACA60257</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Green</surname>
                        <given-names>David I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:3732D6E5-0173-4A59-8E29-4E6F6FF2FCF0</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Illinois Natural History Survey &amp; Department of Entomology, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 1816 South Oak Street, Champaign, Illinois 61820, USA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Faculty of Life Sciences, University of Manchester, Manchester M13 9PT, UK
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Department of Geology, Amgueddfa Cymru–National Museum Wales, Cathays Park, Cardiff CF10 3NP, UK
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Sam W. Heads (<email xlink:type="simple">swheads@illinois.edu</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Michael Engel</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>229</issue>
            <fpage>111</fpage>
            <lpage>118</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>12</day>
                    <month>7</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>15</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Sam W. Heads, David Penney, David I. Green</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:D8EC9B9D-9B68-4B8C-91F2-C17F44737DF1</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new species of the cricket genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> Vickery &amp; Poinar (Orthoptera: Gryllidae: Pentacentrinae) from Early Miocene Dominican amber is described and illustrated. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha madgesuttonae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> is distinguished from congeners by: (1) head capsule bearing a distinctive posteriorly bilobed colour spot on the vertex; (2) presence of crossveins in the proximal part of the mediocubital area; (3) apical field of tegmen entirely dark; and (4) median process of epiphallus short. The poorly known <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha bicolorata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Vickery &amp; Poinar, of questionable affinity and status, is herein regarded as a <italic>nomen inquirendum</italic>.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Orthoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Grylloidea</kwd>
                <kwd>Gryllidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Pentacentrinae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Proanaxipha</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>Dominican amber</kwd>
                <kwd>Miocene</kwd>
                <!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> was established by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Vickery and Poinar (1994)</xref> to accommodate two fossil species from Early Miocene Dominican amber; namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha latoca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Vickery &amp; Poinar, 1994 (the type species) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha bicolorata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Vickery &amp; Poinar, 1994. Originally placed in the <tp:taxon-name>Trigonidiinae</tp:taxon-name>, the genus was recently moved to <tp:taxon-name>Pentacentrinae</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov (2010)</xref> based on close similarities with modern Neotropical pentacentrines. The placement of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> within <tp:taxon-name>Pentacentrinae</tp:taxon-name> is well supported by strong dorsoventral flattening of the head capsule, presence of small spines above the metatibial spurs (never present in <tp:taxon-name>Trigonidiinae</tp:taxon-name> or <tp:taxon-name>Nemobiinae</tp:taxon-name>) and all veins in the lateral tegminal field running parallel to the costal margin. Moreover, females tentatively identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha latoca</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov (2010)</xref> clearly possess ovipositors typical of pentacentrines; i.e. slender and only very slightly curved with a narrow, sharply pointed apex. This differs markedly from the trigonidiine condition, in which the ovipositor is more strongly curved and has a broad, serrated apex. While the inclusion of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> in <tp:taxon-name>Pentacentrinae</tp:taxon-name> is beyond doubt, its relationships to other pentacentrine genera have yet to be addressed. In this paper, we describe a new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Early Miocene (Burdigalian) Dominican amber and briefly compare the genus with other Neotropical <tp:taxon-name>Pentacentrinae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The specimen described here is deposited in the Department of Palaeontology, The Natural History Museum, London (NHM) with the accession number NHM II 3048. Photomicrographs were assembled by D.I.G. from a stacked series of digital images captured using a Nikon Coolpix 4500 digital camera mounted on a Leica M10 stereomicroscope with 0.63× and 1.6× planapochromatic objectives. The specimen was studied by S.W.H. using an Olympus SZX12 zoom stereomicroscope and drawings produced with the aid of a <italic>camera lucida</italic>. Morphological terminology generally follows that established by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Otte and Alexander (1983)</xref> with minor modifications (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Heads 2010a</xref>). The age and origin of Dominican amber has been reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Itturalde-Vinent and MacPhee (1996)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Grimaldi and Engel (2005)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Penney (2010)</xref>. The <tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name> from Dominican amber have been reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Heads (2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">2010a</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">, b</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics">
            <title>Systematics</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:orthoptera.speciesfile.org:TaxonName:30586</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Vickery &amp; Poinar, 1994</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name><comment> Vickery &amp; Poinar, 1994: 15. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha latoca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Vickery &amp; Poinar, 1994 by original designation – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Perez-Gelabert 2001</xref>: 72 – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Arillo and Ortuño 2005</xref>: 8 – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Otte and Perez-Gelabert 2009</xref>: 142 – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov 2010</xref>: 78 [442]. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Penney and Green 2011</xref>: 108.<!--PageBreak--></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">madgesuttonae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2894AEE9-AD50-48FE-918C-46D86E4F9B0E</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:orthoptera.speciesfile.org:TaxonName:76032</object-id>
                <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Proanaxipha_madgesuttonae</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Heads &amp; Penney</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">–8</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Distinguished from congeners by the following characters: (1) head capsule with distinctive posteriorly bilobed colour spot on vertex; (2) presence of crossveins in the proximal part of the mediocubital area; (3) apical field of tegmen entirely dark; and (4) median process of epiphallus short.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Male</italic>: Total body length measured from fastigium verticis to abdominal apex 5.97 mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–2</xref>). Head capsule (length 1.26 mm) compressed dorsoventrally; vertex with distinct posteriorly bilobed colour spot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>); fastigium verticis broadly rounded; median ocellus situated dorsally, between antennal torulae; compound eyes large, interocular distance 0.64 mm; antennae filiform, scape approximately four times larger than pedicel; maxillary palpi long with apical palpomere triangular and distally concave (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>).Pronotum (length 1.02 mm) wider than long, with lateral and marginal areas covered with long setae; disc largely dark with a pale median line not reaching anterior margin; posterior margin sinuous and slightly wider than anterior margin; marginal areas well-demarcated with prominent carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>). Thoracic sternites polygonal, plate-like and densely pilose, increasing in size posteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>). Terminalia obscured dorsally by hind wings (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>); subgenital plate pale, broadly rounded with an indistinct median ridge flanked by shallow depressions and the posterior margin shallowly emarginate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>); cerci densely setose; epiphallus triangular with pointed apex directed dorsally; ectoparameres lobate.</p>
                    <p>Tegmen 3.78 mm long with distinct coloration and stridulatory apparatus only partially reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>); harp elongate, without multiple harp veins; mirror small, lacking dividing vein; lateral field dark with veins running parallel to the costal margin; dorsal field with six crossveins in the basalmost part of the mediocubital area with dark patches running along the stridulatory and harp veins and merging with a large dark spot encompassing most of the proximal cells in the cubital system; apical field entirely dark (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>). Hind wing long and tightly folded, extending well beyond abdominal apex, with dark remigium and hyaline anal lobe. Prothoracic leg short and robust with a single dark band on the distal half of the profemur and ovoid tympana on both sides of the protibia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>). Mesothoracic leg longer than prothoracic leg; mesofemur with single dark band and a prominent ventral sulcus distally; mesotibiae with two dark bands. Metafemur (length 3.54 mm) with a dense covering of setae and bearing two dark spots; one situated just distad of femoral midlength and the second situated apically, encompassing the genicula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>). Metatibia (length 2.61 mm) approximately 25% shorter than metafemur and quadrate in cross section, with two small dark spots situated basally; dorsal longitudinal carinae armed with rows of small denticles interspersed distally with stout subapical spurs (3 inner and 3 outer); metatibial apex bearing 2 inner and 3 outer apical spurs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 5–6</xref>); median outer apical spur twice as long as the <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->other outer spurs. Metabasitarsus elongate with rows of sharp denticles along the dorsal longitudinal carinae and two apical spurs (1 inner and 1 outer); second metatarsomere much reduced; third metatarsomere long, slender and slightly curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–2.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha madgesuttonae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Heads &amp; Penney, sp. n. Photomicrographs of holotype ♂. <bold>1</bold> dorsal view <bold>2</bold> ventral view.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-111-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 3–8.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha madgesuttonae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Heads &amp; Penney, sp. n. Drawings of holotype ♂. <bold>3</bold> dorsal field of right tegmen <bold>4</bold> head capsule and pronotum in dorsal view <bold>5</bold> outer view of right metathoracic leg <bold>6</bold> inner view of right metatibia <bold>7</bold> outer view of right prothoracic leg <bold>8</bold> terminalia in oblique ventral view. Abbreviations: <bold>CuA</bold> anterior cubitus; <bold>ecpL</bold> left ectoparamere; <bold>ecpR</bold> right ectoparamere; <bold>eph</bold> epiphallus; <bold>M</bold> media; <bold>mbt</bold> metabasitarsus; <bold>sgp</bold> subgenital plate; <bold>tym</bold> tympanum. All scale bars 0.5 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-111-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype">
                    <title>Holotype.</title>
                    <p>♂: Dominican Republic: Early Miocene (Burdigalian) amber (NHM II 3048).</p>
                    <p><bold>Etymology.</bold> Named in honour of Madge Sutton at the request of Dr Susan Shawcross.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha madgesuttonae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is clearly congeneric with the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha latoca</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sharing the partially reduced stridulatory apparatus, a long and straight metabasitarsus, similar metatibial armature and the presence of auditory tympana on bot<!--PageBreak-->h faces of the protibia (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov 2010</xref>). Nevertheless, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha madgesuttonae</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs markedly from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha latoca</tp:taxon-name></italic> in its colouration. The new species is altogether darker than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha latoca</tp:taxon-name></italic>, bearing a distinctive posteriorly bilobed colour spot on the vertex of the head capsule (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>) and a much darker tegmen. The apical field of the tegmen in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha latoca</tp:taxon-name></italic> is either pale or bears a few diffuse dark patches (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov 2010</xref>, p. 443, fig. 6). In contrast, the apical field in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha madgesuttonae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is entirely dark (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>). The holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha latoca</tp:taxon-name></italic> bears two dark spots on the vertex between the eyes but the rest of the head capsule is pale (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Vickery and Poinar 1994</xref>, p. 21, fig. 9). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov (2010)</xref> briefly described a number of additional specimens that he tentatively assigned to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha latoca</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However, all of these differ from the holotype in coloration and Gorochov (<italic>op. cit</italic>.,p. 444) remarked that they likely represent a complex of distinct species. While the original colouration of the specimen cannot be known with certainty, arthropod colour patterns are often extremely well preserved in amber (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Poinar 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Grimaldi and Engel 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Penney 2010</xref> and contributions therein). Given the remarkable preservation of the specimen as well as the obvious symmetry of the patterns, it is highly unlikely that they have been altered taphonomically. Morphologically, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha madgesuttonae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is very similar to the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha latoca</tp:taxon-name></italic> and to the specimens recently described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov (2010)</xref>. However, the tegminal venation of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha madgesuttonae</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs in the presence of six crossveins in the basal half of the mediocubital area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>). The tegmina are not clearly illustrated in the original description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha latoca</tp:taxon-name></italic> making it impossible to determine whether or not these crossveins are present. However, the illustrations of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha ?latoca</tp:taxon-name></italic> presented by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov (2010)</xref> show no mediocubital crossveins. The distal parts of the phallic complex visible in the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha madgesuttonae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>) are very similar to those illustrated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov (2010)</xref> though the median process of the epiphallus is shorter in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha madgesuttonae</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">bicolorata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:orthoptera.speciesfile.org:TaxonName:30588</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Proanaxipha_bicolorata</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Vickery &amp; Poinar, 1994</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">nomen inquirendum</tp:taxon-status>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha bicolorata</tp:taxon-name><comment> Vickery &amp; Poinar, 1994: 16, fig. 4 – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Perez-Gelabert 2001</xref>: 72 – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Otte and Perez-Gelabert 2009</xref>: 142 – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov 2010</xref>: 80 [442].</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>Based on Vickery and Poinar’s (1994) photograph of the holotype (a nymph), it is clear that this species does not belong in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> or even within <tp:taxon-name>Pentacentrinae</tp:taxon-name>. Unfortunately, neither the illustration nor the original description are sufficient to determine the subfamilial placement of this species, a situation that is further complicated by the nymphal condition of the specimen. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov (2010)</xref> suggested a possible affinity with <tp:taxon-name>Nemobiinae</tp:taxon-name> or <tp:taxon-name>Eneopterinae</tp:taxon-name> and while both seem possible, neither can be confirmed. Therefore, the species is herein regarded as a <italic>nomen inquirendum</italic> until the type can be redescribed.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>The relationships of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> with other Neotropical <tp:taxon-name>Pentacentrinae</tp:taxon-name> have yet to be adequately investigated and in the absence of a formal analysis, remain largely unknown. Four extant pentacentrine genera are known from the Neotropical region, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Aphemogryllus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Rehn, 1918, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bolívar, 1890, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigonidomimus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Caudell, 1912 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Velapia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Otte &amp; Perez-Gelabert, 2009. Of these, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sharing with the latter an almost identical arrangement of the metatibial spurs. In particular, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov (2010)</xref> drew comparisons between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis eugethes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Otte, 2006 from Costa Rica and suggested that the latter species may in fact belong within <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis eugethes</tp:taxon-name></italic> shares with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> the presence of tympana on both sides of the protibia, the metabasitarsus elongate and almost completely straight, the male stridulatory apparatus only partially reduced and the somewhat shortened median epiphallic process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Otte 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gorochov 2010</xref>). Moreover, while the presence of tympana on both faces of the protibia appears to be unique to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis eugethes</tp:taxon-name></italic>,a long and straight metabasitarsus and partially reduced stridulatory apparatus are present in a number of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> species (e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis cavicola</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bonfils, 1981, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis cortico</tp:taxon-name></italic> Otte &amp; Perez-Gelabert, 2009, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis decui</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bonfils, 1981, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis diadromos</tp:taxon-name></italic> Otte &amp; Perez-Gelabert, 2009 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis metanasticos</tp:taxon-name></italic> Otte &amp; Perez-Gelabert, 2009). Whether or not these species are more closely allied to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> remains unclear. Indeed, the status of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nemobiopsis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proanaxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Grossoxipha</tp:taxon-name></italic> Vickery &amp; Poinar, 1994 (also from Dominican amber) as separate, monophyletic genera is itself questionable and careful revision of the Neotropical <tp:taxon-name>Pentacentrinae</tp:taxon-name> will undoubtedly shed much-needed light on these problems.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>S.W.H. acknowledges support from the Illinois Natural History Survey (University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign) and the Herbert H. Ross Foundation. D.P. acknowledges support from the Systematic Research Fund (jointly administered by the Linnean Society of London and the Systematics Association) and Dr Susan Shawcross (University of Manchester).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Arillo</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortuño</surname> <given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Catalogue of fossil insect species described from Dominican amber (Miocene).</article-title> <source>Stuttgarter Beiträge zur Naturkunde Serie B </source> <volume>352</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolívar</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1890</year>)<article-title> Diagnosis de ortópteros nuevos.</article-title> <source>Anales de la Sociedad Española de Historia Natural </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>333</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonfils</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<article-title> Orthoptères récoltés par les expéditions biospéologiques cubano-roumaines à Cuba 1969 à 1973.</article-title> <source>Resultats des expéditions biospéologiques cubano-roumaines à Cuba </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>-<lpage>112</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Caudell</surname> <given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>)<article-title> A new genus and species of Gryllidae from Texas.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington </source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorochov</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> New and little known orthopteroid insects (Polyneoptera) from fossil resins: communication 3.</article-title> <source>Paleontologicheskii Zhurnal </source> <volume>2010</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>-<lpage>87</lpage> [in Russian; English translation published separately in Paleontological Journal 44: 434–450].</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimaldi</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Evolution of the Insects. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, London &amp; New York, xv + 755 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heads</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> New pygmy grasshoppers in Miocene amber from the Dominican Republic (Orthoptera: Tetrigidae).</article-title> <source>Denisia </source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heads</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010a</year>)<source> The first fossil spider cricket (Orthoptera: Gryllidae: Phalangopsinae): 20 million years of troglobiomorphosis or exaptation in the dark? Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society 158: 56–65. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.2009.00587.x">10.1111/j.1096-3642.2009.00587.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heads</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010b</year>)<article-title> New Tridactyloidea in Miocene amber from the Dominican Republic (Orthoptera: Caelifera).</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société Entomologique de France </source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>-<lpage>210</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Itturalde-Vinent</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacPhee</surname> <given-names>RDE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Age and paleogeographical origin of Dominican amber.</article-title> <source>Science </source> <volume>273</volume>: <fpage>1850</fpage>-<lpage>1852</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.273.5283.1850">10.1126/science.273.5283.1850</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Otte</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Eighty-four new cricket species (Orthoptera: Grylloidea) from La Selva, Costa Rica.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the American Entomological Society </source> <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>418</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Otte</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> The Australian crickets (Orthoptera: Gryllidae).</article-title> <source>Monographs of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia </source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>477</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Otte</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Gelabert</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Caribbean Crickets.</source> <publisher-name>Publications on Orthopteran Diversity, The Orthopterists’ Society</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>, <lpage>792</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
          <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Penney</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> <role>(Ed)</role> (<year>2010</year>)<source> Biodiversity of fossils in amber from the major world deposits.</source> <publisher-name>Siri Scientific Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Manchester</publisher-loc>, <lpage>304</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Penney</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname> <given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> Fossils in amber: snapshots of prehistoric forest life.</source> <publisher-name>Siri Scientific Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Manchester</publisher-loc>, <lpage>226</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Gelabert</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Preliminary checklist of the Orthoptera (Saltatoria) of Hispaniola.</article-title> <source>Journal of Orthoptera Research </source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1665/1082-6467(2001)010[0063:PCOTOS]2.0.CO;2">10.1665/1082-6467(2001)010[0063:PCOTOS]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poinar</surname> <given-names>GO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Insects in amber.</article-title> <source>Annual Review of Entomology </source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.en.38.010193.001045">10.1146/annurev.en.38.010193.001045</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehn</surname> <given-names>JAG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1918</year>)<article-title> On a collection of Orthoptera from the state of Pará, Brazil.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences, Philadelphia </source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>144</fpage>-<lpage>236</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vickery</surname> <given-names>VR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poinar</surname> <given-names>GO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Crickets (Grylloptera: Grylloidea) in Dominican amber.</article-title> <source>Canadian Entomologist </source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/Ent12613-1">10.4039/Ent12613-1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>