<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.159.2219</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Revision of the world species of 
                    <italic>Zambion</italic> (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Tryphoninae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Bennett</surname>
                        <given-names>Andrew M.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:044FC632-2219-4A9F-BDDB-9E6C214E2D97</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Barnes</surname>
                        <given-names>Diana I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:87E4B2EA-7C0D-46D9-BF4B-40D75CF78630</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada, Canadian National Collection of Insects, 960 Carling Avenue, Ottawa, Ontario, Canada K1A 0C6
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Andrew M.R. Bennett (<email xlink:type="simple">Andrew.Bennett@AGR.GC.CA</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: G. Broad</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>23</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>159</issue>
            <fpage>19</fpage>
            <lpage>48</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>7</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>14</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Andrew M.R. Bennett, Diana I. Barnes</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:0D96B0D0-3AA1-4EF9-8722-29100C3A06D4</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The world species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kasparyan (<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Tryphoninae</tp:taxon-name>) are revised including re-descriptions of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kasparyan and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Delobel. Five new species are described: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion kasparyani</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion eileenae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> and<italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> A key to species is provided. The genus is endemic to Africa (Angola to Kenya) and is one of only three genera of the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Tryphonini</tp:taxon-name> recorded from the Afrotropical region.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic></kwd>
                <kwd><tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name></kwd>
                <kwd><tp:taxon-name>Tryphoninae</tp:taxon-name></kwd>
                <kwd>Afrotropical</kwd>
                <kwd>revision</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The tribe <tp:taxon-name>Tryphonini</tp:taxon-name> is poorly represented in the Afrotropical region with only 3 of 21 extant genera recorded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Yu et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bennett 2002</xref>): <italic><tp:taxon-name>Boethus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Förster (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Scaramozzino 1991</xref>) and two endemic genera: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibornia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seyrig (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Seyrig 1935</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kasparyan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kasparyan 1993</xref>). In total, there are only eight described species of <tp:taxon-name>Tryphonini</tp:taxon-name> recorded from the Afrotropical region: two species each of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Boethus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> and four <!--PageBreak-->species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibornia</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Yu et al. 2009</xref>). It was speculated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Gauld (1987)</xref> that a reason for the lack of ctenopelmatine ichneumonids from tropical regions is because their hosts (sawflies) are rare in the tropics in terms of species and biomass. The same hypothesis could explain the low number of species of Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Tryphonini</tp:taxon-name> because almost all known host records for the tribe are from sawflies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Gauld et al. 1997</xref>). The hosts of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibornia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> are not known, but they likely parasitize tenthredinid sawflies based on the known host range of related genera (e.g., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dyspetes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Förster and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Otoblastus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Förster) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Gupta 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Kasparyan 1973</xref>). Of the 10 genera of <tp:taxon-name>Tryphonini</tp:taxon-name> for which hosts are known, only two have been reared from hosts other than <tp:taxon-name>Tenthredinidae</tp:taxon-name>: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Boethus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species have been consistently reared from <tp:taxon-name>Argidae</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Gauld et al. 1997</xref>) and some species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Grypocentrus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ruthe have been reared from <tp:taxon-name>Eriocraniidae</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Jordan 1998</xref>) (most rearing records of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Grypocentrus</tp:taxon-name></italic> are from <tp:taxon-name>Tenthredinidae</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Kasparyan 1973</xref>).</p>
            <p>Apart from the presumed lower number of potential hosts, another factor that definitely contributes to the small number of species of Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Tryphonini</tp:taxon-name> (and <tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name> in general) is the relatively little amount of taxonomic research on the ichneumonids of the region. In other regions such as the Neotropical, recent active research programmes have greatly elucidated the ichneumonid fauna (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gauld 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Gauld et al. 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">2002</xref>). In the Afrotropical region, some excellent work has been done in the past, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Seyrig (1932</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">1934</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">1935</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">1952</xref>) on various subfamilies, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Heinrich (1967a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">c</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">1968a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">b</xref>) on <tp:taxon-name>Ichneumoninae</tp:taxon-name>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Gauld and Mitchell (1978)</xref> on <tp:taxon-name>Ophioninae</tp:taxon-name>, but recently, taxonomic studies including Afrotropical species have been uncommon. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Yu et al. (2009)</xref> listed only 8 taxonomic papers that included Afrotropical species published between 2000 and 2008 (compared to 65 for the Neotropical region and 46 for the Oriental). In terms of described species, the Afrotropical ichneumonid fauna is not as speciose as the Neotropical and Oriental regions (1,946 described species in the Afrotropical compared to 3,803 in the Neotropical and 3,595 in the Oriental) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Yu et al. 2009</xref>). But based on examination of unidentified material at the American Entomological Institute, Canadian National Collection of Insects and the Natural History Museum, London, there are large numbers of undescribed species in the Afrotropical region, especially from the tropics and South Africa. Without additional taxonomic studies of the fauna, well-founded assessments of species diversity and biological patterns for sub-Saharan Africa will be difficult to achieve. The purpose of this paper is to revise the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> including description of five new species. It is hoped that the revision of such a beautiful and morphologically distinct genus will encourage other researchers to spend much-needed time working on this interesting, but under-studied fauna.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
            <title>Methods</title>
            <p>All terms of ichneumonid morphology follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Townes (1969)</xref> with the following modifications: hypostomal carina for ‘oral carina’, supra-antennal area for ‘frons’, suprac<!--PageBreak-->lypeal area for ‘face’, gena for ‘temple’, occiput for ‘postocciput’, malar space for ‘cheek’, epicnemial carina for ‘prepectal carina’, laterotergites for ‘epipleura’, gonoforceps for ‘claspers’, and hypopygium for ‘subgenital plate’. The term ‘mesosoma’ is used for the body region that includes the thorax and first abdominal segment (the propodeum). The term ‘metasoma’ is used for the apparent abdomen, with MS1, MS2, etc. referring to metasomal segments 1, 2, etc., T1, T2, etc. referring to the tergites of metasomal segments 1, 2, etc. and S1 referring to the sternite of metasomal segment 1. The term T2+ refers to tergite 2 and all tergites posterior to T2. Terms of relative position of the body follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Goulet and Huber (1993)</xref>. Wing venation terms follow the Comstock-Needham system as updated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Ross (1936)</xref> and incorporate the recommendations of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Goulet and Huber (1993)</xref> except for naming of the vein that forms the distal edge of fore wing cell 1+2Rs (the ‘areolet’ of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Townes 1969</xref>). This vein is of uncertain origin and is here referred to as ‘vein 3rs-m’ in conformity with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Wahl and Gauld (1998)</xref>. The following terms for specialized structures are defined: epomia: a raised ridge (carina) on pronotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 30–31</xref>); glymma: lateral depression sub-basally on T1; notaulus: longitudinal groove sublaterally on mesoscutum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 29</xref>); sternaulus: longitudinal groove subventrally on mesopleuron; ventral transverse carina of propodeum: a carina that extends from the metasomal foramen of the propodeum to the pleural carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 35</xref>).</p>
            <p>Measurements for particular structures were made as follows: supraclypeal width was measured at midheight compared to height in the middle (laterally); horn length measured in dorsal view versus pedicel width at middle in lateral view; gena width measured at lower (narrowest) point versus transverse width of eye at midheight (both in lateral view); length of scutellar carina measured from base of scuto-scutellar groove to apex of scutellum; point of union of posterior transverse carina of propodeum (ptc) and pleural carina (pc) was estimated by measuring the distances shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 35–37</xref>: from the propodeal spiracle to the ptc and from the ptc to the ventral transverse carina (vtc) (or in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion kasparyani</tp:taxon-name></italic>, where the vtc would be, if present); hind femur dimensions were calculated by dividing the maximum length including the distal trochantellus by the height at midpoint; length of T1 measured in lateral view compared to width of T1 measured in dorsal view at posterior edge. Measurements of holotypes are shown in parentheses after range. Characters listed in the generic description are those deemed relevant to distinguish <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> from all other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Tryphonini</tp:taxon-name> as defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Kasparyan (1973)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Kasparyan and Tolkanitz (1999)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bennett (2002)</xref>.</p>
            <p>Specimens are deposited at the following institutions (acronyms according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Evenhuis 2011</xref>):</p>
            <p>Canadian National Collection of Insects (CNC); The Natural History Museum, London (NHM); Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle, Paris (MNHN), Finnish Museum of Natural History, Helsinki (MZH), California Academy of Sciences, San Francisco (CAS). Label data for holotypes is reported <italic>verbatim</italic> from the labels, with our comments about the labels indicated in square brackets. Locality data for other specimens are provided in a standardized format.</p>
            <p>Digital photos were taken using a Leica MZ16 stereomicroscope with motorized focus drive attached to a Leica DFC420 digital camera. Photos were combined and edited <!--PageBreak-->using Leica Application Suites Montage Multifocus software V3.8, Auto-Montage Pro 5.01 and Adobe Photoshop CS4. Authorship of all species is by Bennett and Barnes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonony">
            <title>Taxonony</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zambion</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zambion</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Kasparyan</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name><comment> Kasparyan, 1993: 86. Type: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kasparyan. By monotypy.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Differentiated from other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Tryphoninae</tp:taxon-name> by combination of both of the following characters: 1) unidentate mandibles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 22</xref>); 2) supra-antennal area with a medial horn (not a vertical lamella) slightly ventral to medial ocellus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 16–21</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">24–27</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> would most easily be mistaken for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibornia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Seyrig, but <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibornia</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a supra-antennal vertical lamella instead of a horn and T1 and T2 are fused (not fused in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Adult.</bold> Fore wing length 4.9 to 7.2 mm. Clypeus separated from supraclypeal area by a strong groove (most species) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 11</xref>) or weakly separated in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Delobel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 10</xref>); strongly convex or moderately flat in profile; not divided into dorsal and ventral faces by a transverse line (most species) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 11</xref>) or divided (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 12</xref>). Apical edge of clypeus not projecting ventroanteriorly in lateral view, truncate to slightly convex medially in anterior view, without a pair of medial denticles. Mandible unidentate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 22</xref>), outer face (anterior surface) basally flat and coarsely punctate (not inflated and impunctate as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ctenochira</tp:taxon-name></italic>). Glossa slightly to strongly elongated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 15</xref>). Posterior mandibular condyles separated by greater width than inner margins of eyes at level of clypeal foveae. Malar space 0.4 to 0.7 times basal width of mandible. Occipital carina present only dorsally (between inner margins of eyes), therefore not joining hypostomal carina, the latter not directed posteriorly into a tooth. Supra-antennal area with or without a glabrous depression, if present then just as a deep dimple directly ventral to medial ocellus, not an elongate groove as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cosmoconus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Förster. Supra-antennal area with a medial horn (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 16–21</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">24–27</xref>). Vertex posterior to medial ocellus without a rounded, conical protuberance. Distance between inner edges of toruli 0.1 to 0.4 times width of one torulus.</p>
                    <p>Dorsal edge of pronotum (seen in dorsal view) strongly thickened laterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 28</xref>). Epomia present only as a slight sharpening of ventroanterior ridge of pronotum (not crossing pronotal groove) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 30–31</xref>). Notaulus weak (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 29</xref>) or absent. Subtegular ridge slightly protruding laterally, not extending dorsally as a vertical lamina that nearly touches tegula, without a posterior longitudinal slot. Epicnemial carina not joined by an auxiliary carina that extends from anterior edge of mesopleuron. Vertical portion of epicnemial carina close to anterior edge of mesopleuron and dorsally curving anteriorly to meet anterior edge of mesopleuron (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 32–33</xref>). Longitudinal carinae of mesopleuron and mesoscutum (as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibornia</tp:taxon-name></italic>) absent. Sternaulus weak and wide<!--PageBreak--> to 0.2 to 0.3 length of mesopleuron. Angular flange on posterolateral edges of mesoscutum and associated ‘axillary tongue’ both present and strongly angulate. Scutellum completely black (most species), completely yellow (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion kasparyani</tp:taxon-name></italic>) or black with yellow apically (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>), lateral carinae present only basally or up to 0.5. Propodeum with all carinae present except anterior transverse carina completely absent in all species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 34</xref>), medial longitudinal carinae absent anteriorly in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and posterior transverse carina interrupted medially in the males of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Posterior transverse carina angulate where it intercepts medial longitudinal carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 34</xref>). Foretibia with a strong tooth on apex of anterior side or tooth weak to absent. Trochantelli not fused on middle and hind legs. Hind tarsal claws stoutly pectinate in basal 0.4 to 0.6. Fore wing vein 3rs-m present. Cell 1 + 2Rs subrectangular or subrhombic, width not greater than 1.4 times height, petiolate anteriorly. Fore wing vein 2m-cu with an angulation (zig-zag) that is strong in most species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 38–39</xref>) or weak (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 7</xref>) and with one wide or two narrowly spaced bullae. Fore wing hyaline basally and infumate apically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 38–39</xref>) or completely moderately infumate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 7</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">8</xref>).</p>
                    <p>T1 gradually widening from anterior to posterior, 1.2 to 1.8 times as long as posterior width, with moderate anterolateral projections (as seen in dorsal view). Glymma present as a depression ventral to anterolateral projections. Dorsal longitudinal carinae of T1 present basally or extending up to 0.7 of segment. Dorsolateral longitudinal carinae of T1 present (most species) or absent; if present, not extending posterior to spiracle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 40, 41</xref>) or extending up to 0.7 of segment, not bifurcated into two branches above and below spiracle. Spiracle of T1 just anterior to middle. T1 and T2 not fused. T2 without a postmedial transverse groove or grooves that delineate anterolateral corners. T2 to T4 completely yellow/orange, completely black, or black with yellow at posterior of each segment. Laterotergites wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 42</xref>), of MS3 divided from tergite by a crease, of MS4 not divided. T7 and T8 not turned anteriorly under metasoma. Ovipositor straight, about equal to apical height of metasoma or a little shorter, carrying one egg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">45</xref>) or no eggs, dorsal valve tapered to a sharp point (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 44</xref>). Ovipositor sheath in profile, widest basally, gradually tapering from base to apex, flexible from 0.3 to 0.6.</p>
                    <p>Body polished, face and supraclypeal area coarsely punctate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 10–15</xref>); pronotum, mesopleuron and metapleuron with fine, sparse, but distinct punctures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 30–33</xref>); all other body regions almost impunctate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 34–37</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">40–43</xref>). Body covered in dense setae, particularly long on supraclypeal area, shorter on pleura of mesosoma and metasomal tergites.</p>
                    <p><bold>Mature larva.</bold> Unknown.</p>
                    <p><bold>Egg.</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 45</xref>): Stalk apical, anchor unknown, surface reticulate. Egg known only for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> (holotype).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Hosts">
                    <title>Hosts.</title>
                    <p>Unknown, but probably parasitoids of tenthredinoid sawflies (<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>) (see Introduction).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Afrotropical (Republic of Congo, Uganda, Kenya, Zambia and Angola).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Species included">
                    <title>Species included.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Delobel and five new species described below.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibornia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibetoides</tp:taxon-name></italic> are all closely related based on seven synapomorphies, especially the thickened dorsoposterior corner of the pronotum and the supra-antennal prominence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bennett 2002</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kasparyan (1993)</xref> speculated that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibornia</tp:taxon-name></italic> must be sister genera because of the unidentate mandibles and because they are both Afrotropical, but <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bennett (2002)</xref> found that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibornia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibetoides</tp:taxon-name></italic> are sister taxa based on seven characters including the fusion of T1 and T2 and the ventral curving of T7 and T8 under the metasoma which makes <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> the sister of these two genera.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to the world species of Zambion">
                    <title>Key to the world species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic></title>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal lamella present between toruli (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 23</xref>). Mesosoma yellow to orange (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>) AND head with dark markings dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 16</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Delobel</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lamella absent between toruli. Mesosoma with dark markings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 5</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">9</xref>), OR if mesosoma completely yellow to orange (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 46</xref>), then head also yellow to orange, without dark markings dorsally near ocelli and horn (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 47</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                		<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(1)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propodeum lacking a ventral transverse carina extending from metasomal foramen to pleural carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 36</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">48</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propodeum with a ventral transverse carina extending from metasomal foramen to pleural carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 35, 37</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                		<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(2)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesopleuron with dorsal half black and ventral half yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>). Notaulus weak, but present</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kasparyan</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesopleuron completely yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 46</xref>). Notaulus absent</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion kasparyani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                		<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4(2)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propodeum with medial longitudinal carinae absent or incomplete anterior to posterior transverse carina. Supra-antennal area with a long, sub-parallel-sided/ weakly tapering horn in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 20, 21</xref>), length 1.2 to 1.3 times width of pedicel at midheight in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 27</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propodeum with medial longitudinal carinae strong and complete anterior to posterior transverse carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 34</xref>). Supra-antennal area with a short triangular horn in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 18, 19</xref>) length 0.3 to 0.5 times width of pedicel at midheight in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 26</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                		<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(4)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propodeum black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 8</xref>). Clypeus black, except brown at extreme apical edge (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 14</xref>). Lateral abscissa of posterior transverse carina of propodeum roughly straight, meeting pleural carina at right angle at about midpoint between propodeal spiracle and posterior end of pleural carina (similar to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 36</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propodeum orange except brown basolaterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 9</xref>). Clypeus with apical half orange and basal half black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 15</xref>). Lateral abscissa of posterior transverse carina of propodeum strongly curving posteriorly where it meets pleural<!--PageBreak--> carina at an acute angle near posterior 0.2 of pleural carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 37</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                		<td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6(4)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Legs completely dark brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 7</xref>). Tergites 3 to 7 completely brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 7</xref>). Malar space 0.7 times basal width of mandible. Carina extending from pleural carina of propodeum to propodeal spiracle complete</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion eileenae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fore and mid legs orange, hind coxa, trochanter and femur orange, hind tibia and tarsus dark brown, except yellow at base of hind tibia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 6</xref>). Tergites 3 to 7 with medioposterior ivory bands (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 6</xref>). Malar space 0.4 to 0.5 times basal width of mandible. Carina extending from pleural carina of propodeum to propodeal spiracle absent</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zambion</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">monodon</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zambion_monodon</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Kasparyan</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–3</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">5</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">11</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">17</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">25</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">36</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">41, 42, 45</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name><comment> Kasparyan, 1993: 86.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. by having the mesopleuron approximately half black (dorsally) and half yellow (ventrally) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>) (all other species are concolourous on mesopleuron – either all brown to black or all yellow to orange). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> is unusual in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> in that it lacks the ventral transverse carina of the propodeum extending from the metasomal foramen to the pleural carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 36</xref>). The only other species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> that lacks this carina is <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion kasparyani</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but the latter species has a mesopleuron that is completely yellow to orange (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 46</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Adult</bold>. Female (based on holotype only – see comments below). Fore wing length 7.2 mm. Clypeus separated from supraclypeal area by a strong groove (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 11</xref>). Malar space 0.5 times basal width of mandible. Supraclypeal area 2.0 times as wide as high (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 11</xref>), dorsomedially without a short, narrow, longitudinal lamella between the antenna. Supra-antennal horn moderately long and triangular in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 17</xref>), about equal in length to width of pedicel at midheight in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 25</xref>). Ocello-ocular distance 1.4 times ocellar diameter. Gena 0.6 times transverse diameter of the eye. Antennal flagellum with 37 segments.</p>
                    <p>Notaulus present, but weak. Epicnemial carina medially curving slightly away from anterior edge of mesopleuron near ventral corner of pronotum (intermediate between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 32</xref> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 33</xref>). Scutellum with lateral carinae 0.4 length of scutellum. Medial longitudinal carinae of propodeum complete and strong anterior to posterior transverse carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>). Carina extending from pleural carina to spiracle complete (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 36</xref>). Posterior transverse carina of propodeum with lateral abscissa roughly straight, joining pleural carina at about 0.4 distance from posterior end of pleural carina to propodeal spiracle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 36</xref>). Ventral transverse carina extending <!--PageBreak-->from metasomal foramen to pleural carina absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 36</xref>). Fore tibia with a strong apical point on dorsal surface. Hind femur 3.4 times as long as medial width (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Hind tarsal claw pectinate to about 0.5. Angulation of fore wing vein 2m-cu strong (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p>Tergite 1 of metasoma 1.7 times as long as apical width. Dorsal longitudinal carinae of T1 extending posterior to spiracle (0.6 length of tergite), dorsolateral longitudinal carinae extending about half way to spiracle (0.3 distance of T1) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 41</xref> of male, similar to female).</p>
                    <p>Yellow. Legs and metasoma become slightly darker yellow apically/ posteriorly. Scape, pedicel except apically, supra-antennal area except orbits ventral to medial ocellus, vertex, gena dorsal to ventral edge of eye, occiput, apex of mandibles, pronotum dorsal to furrow, mesoscutum, dorsal half of mesopleuron except subtegular ridge and scutellum except basolaterally black/ dark brown. Apex of pedicel, flagellum and distal tarsomere of hind leg brown. Entire membrane of fore wing moderately infumate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>). Body covered with dense golden setae.</p>
                    <p>Male (based only on single male paratype noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kasparyan 1993</xref>): As female except fore wing length 7.0 mm. Malar space 0.4 times basal width of mandible. Width of supraclypeal area 1.7 times medial height. Ocello-ocular distance 1.2 times ocellar diameter. Gena 0.7 times transverse diameter of eye. Lateral abscissa of posterior transverse carina of propodeum joining pleural carina at 0.3 distance from posterior end of pleural carina. (Both antennae missing or incomplete).</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–3.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>,holotype female <bold>1</bold> habitus <bold>2</bold> head, anterior view <bold>3</bold> propodeum and first metasomal segment, dorsal view. Figure reproduced from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kasparyan (1993)</xref>.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-019-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 4–5.</label>
                        <caption><p>Habitus <bold>4</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>,holotype female <bold>5</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>,holotype female.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-019-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype: ♀, Label 1: ZAMBIA, Kitwe, Chati, 27.3.1979, K. Löyttyniemi leg. Label 2: window trap with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eucalyptus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Label 3: Holotypus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kasparyan. Label 4: coll. Dept. Agr. Forest. Zool. Univ. Helsinki. [MZH]. Condition: intact except missing distal tarsomere of right foreleg and left mid leg detached and glued to top locality label. Paratypes: ♂, same data as holotype, except 8.iii.1979; ♀ same data except 15.iii.1979. (♀ paratype strongly damaged by <tp:taxon-name>Dermestidae</tp:taxon-name>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> appears related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion kasparyani</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> on the basis of the similar moderately long, triangular-shaped supra-antennal horn (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 16, 17</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">47</xref>). Within this grouping, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion kasparyani</tp:taxon-name></italic> both lack the ventral transverse carina of the propodeum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 36</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">48</xref>). Outgroup comparison with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibornia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibetoides</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp., reveals that this character varies between species within these two genera as well, therefore its polarity (and phylogenetic utility) in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> is unclear. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the only species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> for which the egg is known. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kasparyan (1993)</xref> stated that the dermestid damaged paratype was a female. Because the metasoma posterior to T3 is missing, it is difficult to confirm the sex; however, the length of T1 (1.8 times posterior width) and ocellar-ocular distance (1.2 times ocellar diameter) suggest that this specimen may be a male based on comparison with the dimensions of these structures in the female holotype and male paratype.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zambion</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">kasparyani</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C1C0F597-7D1C-4591-9E8C-4705AAE8F0AB</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zambion_kasparyani</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 46–48</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion kasparyani</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. by combination of both of the following characters: 1) absence of a ventral transverse <!--PageBreak-->carina on the propodeum extending from the metasomal foramen to the pleural carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 48</xref>) (contrast with condition in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 35</xref>); 2) mesosoma completely yellow to orange (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 46</xref>) (no dark colour).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Adult.</bold> Female unknown.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p>Male: Fore wing length 5.8 mm. Clypeus separated from supraclypeal area by a strong groove. Malar space 0.4 times basal width of mandible. Supraclypeal area 1.7 times as wide as high, dorsomedially without a short, narrow, longitudinal lamella between the antenna. Supra-antennal horn moderately long and triangular in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 47</xref>), about equal in length to width of pedicel at midheight in lateral view. Ocello-ocular distance 1.2 times ocellar diameter. Gena 0.8 times transverse diameter of the eye. Antennal flagellum with 32 segments.</p>
                    <p>Notaulus absent. Epicnemial carina mostly straight medially, not curving away from anterior edge of mesopleuron near ventral corner of pronotum (similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 32</xref>). Scutellum with lateral carinae extending 0.4 length of scutellum. Medial longitudinal carinae of propodeum complete and strong anterior to posterior transverse carina (as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>). Carina extending from pleural carina to spiracle complete (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 48</xref>). Posterior transverse carina of propodeum with lateral abscissa roughly straight, joining pleural carina at about 0.4 distance from posterior end of pleural carina to propodeal spiracle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 48</xref>). Ventral transverse carina extending from metasomal foramen to pleural carina absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 48</xref>). Fore tibia with a moderately strong apical point on dorsal surface. Hind femur 3.6 times as long as medial width. Hind tarsal claw pectinate to about 0.5. Angulation of fore wing vein 2m-cu strong.</p>
                    <p>Tergite 1 of metasoma 1.6 times as long as apical width. Dorsal longitudinal carinae of T1 extending to spiracle (0.4 length of tergite), dorsolateral longitudinal carinae extending just over half way to spiracle (0.3 distance of T1).</p>
                    <p>Yellow. Legs and metasoma slightly darker yellow apically/ posteriorly. Vertex and supra-antennal area medially, scape and mesoscutum orange. Pedicel and apex of mandible dark brown. Flagellum medium brown except base of first flagellomere orange. Entire membrane of fore wing moderately infumate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 46</xref>). Body covered with dense golden setae.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype ♂, Label 1: KENYA: Rift Valley Province. Marich Pass Field Studies Centre, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°32.2'N, 35°27.4'E</named-content>, 13–14 June 2000. Label 2: M.H. Bourbin, V.H. Lee &amp; W.J. Pulawski collectrs [CAS]. Condition: intact.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>This species is named in honour of Dr. Dmitriy Kasparyan (Zoological Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences, St. Petersburg) for his contributions to ichneumonid taxonomy especially being the first to recognize and describe the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p>see comments for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zambion</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">hirtum</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zambion_hirtum</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Delobel</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 4</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">10</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">16</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">22–24</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">30</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">34–35, 38</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">40, 43–44</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name><comment> Delobel, 1993: 267.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. in that the supraclypeal area dorsomedially has a short, longitudinal lamella between the an<!--PageBreak-->tennae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 23</xref>) (lamella absent in all other species). In addition, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the only species that has the following colour combination: mesosoma and metasoma completely light coloured (yellow or orange) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>) AND head yellow with black markings dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 16</xref>).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Adult.</bold> Female (only holotype known). Fore wing length 7.1 mm. Clypeus separated from supraclypeal area by a weak groove (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 10</xref>). Malar space 0.5 times basal width of mandible. Supraclypeal area 1.7 times as wide as high (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 10</xref>), dorsomedially with a short, narrow, longitudinal lamella between the antenna (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 23</xref>). Supra-antennal horn triangular in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 16</xref>), 1.0 times as long as width of pedicel at midheight in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 24</xref>). Ocello-ocular distance 1.6 times ocellar diameter. Gena 0.7 times transverse diameter of the eye. Antennal flagellum with 40 segments.</p>
                    <p>Notaulus absent. Epicnemial carina mostly straight medially (similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 32</xref>), not curving away from anterior edge of mesopleuron near ventral corner of pronotum. Scutellum with lateral carinae at base only. Medial longitudinal carinae of propodeum strong and complete anterior to posterior transverse carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 34</xref>). Carina extending from pleural carina to spiracle absent. Posterior transverse carina of propodeum with lateral abscissa roughly straight (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 34</xref>), point of union with pleural carina at about 0.2 distance from posterior end of pleural carina to propodeal spiracle. Ventral transverse carina extending from metasomal foramen to pleural carina present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 35</xref>). Fore tibia with a weak apical point on dorsal surface. Hind femur 3.2 times as long as medial width (original description = 3.8). Hind tarsal claw pectinate to 0.6 times length of claw. Angulation of fore wing vein 2m-cu strong (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 38</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Tergite 1 of metasoma 1.6 times as long as apical width. Dorsal longitudinal carinae of T1 extending close to spiracles (about 0.4 times length of tergite), dorsolateral longitudinal carina extending just over half way to spiracles (similar to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 40</xref> of male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>).</p>
                    <p>Yellow. Pedicel, medial 0.5 of supra-antennal area except dorsomedial part of horn (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 16</xref>) and medial 0.3 of occiput black to dark brown. Flagellum and dorsomedial area of supra-antennal horn brown. Medial 0.5 of vertex posterior to ocelli, mesoscutum and apical 2 tarsomeres of fore and mid legs and apical 3 tarsomeres of hind leg brownish yellow. Membrane of fore wing hyaline, except slightly infumate in apical 0.3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 38</xref>). Body covered with dense golden setae.</p>
                    <p>Male: as female except fore wing length 4.9 to 7.1 mm. Malar space 0.4 times basal width of mandible. Width of supraclypeal area 1.7 to 2.0 times height. Ocello-ocular distance 1.7 to 1.9 times ocellar diameter. Gena 0.6 times transverse diameter of eye. Flagellum with 36 to 40 segments. Notaulus weak anteriorly in some specimens. Lateral abscissa of posterior transverse carina of propodeum slightly sinuous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 35</xref>) or completely straight (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 34</xref>), joining pleural carina at 0.2 to 0.4 distance from posterior end of pleural carina. Hind femur length 3.0 to 3.4 times medial width. Hind tarsal claw pectinate in basal 0.4 to 0.5 of claw. Tergite 1 1.3 to 1.7 times as long as apical width. Dorsolateral longitudinal carina of T1 extending less than half way to spiracle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 40</xref>) or a little bit more than half. Colour as female except, in some specimens medial 0.5 of vertex light brown to dark brown and occiput more extensively brown (up to medial 0.5). Supra-antennal horn completely black to dark brown in some specimens.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype: ♀, Label 1: CONGO, Brazzaville, Centre ORSTOM, 8 novembre 1986, A. DELOBEL coll. Label 2: Holotype. Label 3:<!--PageBreak--> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> A. DELOBEL det 1993. Label 4: Muséum Paris EY6006. [MNHN]. Condition: intact except left antenna missing distal 12 flagellomeres and right mid leg missing distal tarsomere. Paratypes: 3 ♂, same data as holotype except: 18.i.1987 [EY 6008]; 17–24.v.1987 [EY6009] and 21.xii.1986 [EY6011] [MNHN]; ♂ same data as<!--PageBreak--> holotype except: 17–24.v.1987 [EY 6012] [CNC]. Non-type material: ♂, ANGOLA: Quirimbo. v.1934. K. Jordan. B.M. 1934–1935 [NHM].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a mostly pale-coloured species, most similar in colour to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion kasparyani</tp:taxon-name></italic>, although the latter species is completely yellow to orange dorsomedially on the head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 47</xref>), whereas <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> is extensively black in this area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 16</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the species with the most known specimens (eight) and is the only species known from two countries. Note that only six of the eight specimens were examined in this study. Also note that the supraclypeal longitudinal lamella of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> is not homologous with the supra-antennal lamella of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibornia</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The latter is positioned much more dorsally on the head (extending nearly to the medial ocellus) and its dorsal margin is strongly thickened with a longitudinal groove (Townes, 1969).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zambion</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">rogeri</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B4429CF0-E964-4A22-A273-944742403D9A</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zambion_rogeri</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 6</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">12</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">18</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">32</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. by having tergites 3 to 7 of metasoma black with ivory bands in posterior 0.1 to 0.2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 6</xref>). No other species have banded metasomal segments.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Adult.</bold> Female: Unknown.</p>
                    <p>Male: Fore wing length 6.4 to 7.0 (6.4) mm. Clypeus separated from supraclypeal area by a strong groove (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 12</xref>). Malar space 0.4 to 0.5 (0.5) times basal width of mandible. Supraclypeal area 1.7 to 1.9 (1.7) times as wide as high (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 12</xref>), dorsomedially without a short, narrow, longitudinal lamella between the antenna. Supra-antennal horn short and broadly triangular in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 18</xref>), 0.3 to 0.5 (0.3) times as long as width of pedicel at midheight in lateral view. Ocello-ocular distance 1.8 to 2.3 (1.8) times ocellar diameter. Gena 0.6 to 0.7 (0.6) times transverse diameter of the eye. Flagellum with 35 to 37 (35) segments.</p>
                    <p>Notaulus absent. Epicnemial carina mostly straight medially, not curving away from anterior edge of mesopleuron near ventral corner of pronotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 32</xref>). Scutellum with lateral carinae 0.4 to 0.5 (0.5) length of scutellum. Medial longitudinal carinae of propodeum complete and strong anterior to posterior transverse carina (as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 34</xref>). Carina extending from pleural carina to propodeal spiracle absent. Posterior transverse carina of propodeum with lateral abscissa roughly straight, point of union with pleural carina at about 0.4 distance from posterior end of pleural carina to propodeal spiracle (similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 36</xref>). Ventral transverse carina extending from metasomal foramen to pleural carina present (as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 35</xref>). Fore tibia with a weak apical point on dorsal surface. Hind femur 3.5 to 3.7 (3.6) times as long as medial width. Hind tarsal claw pectinate to 0.4 times length of claw. Angulation of fore wing vein 2m-cu moderate.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->Tergite 1 of metasoma 1.6 to 1.8 (1.6) times as long as apical width. Dorsal longitudinal carinae of T1 extending to about the level of spiracle or a bit beyond, 0.4 to 0.6 (0.6) times length of T1, dorsolateral longitudinal carinae extending to<!--PageBreak--> spiracle, or in holotype to at least 0.7 times length of T1 (posterior to this, present as a rounded ridge).</p>
                    <p>Black to dark brown. Extreme apex of hind femur, basal 0.2 of hind tibia and posterior 0.2+ of T3–T7 ivory (the ivory bands longer medially than laterally and increasing in length from T3 to T7) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 6</xref>). Scape, pedicel and flagellum ventrally, mandibles except at apex, palpi, pronotal collar medially, tegula, posterior of subtegular ridge, fore leg, mid leg, hind coxa, trochanter and femur orange (middle and hind trochanters and femora brownish orange, especially medial surface of hind trochanter and femur). Flagellum dorsally, apical 0.8 of hind tibia and all of hind tarsus brown (flagellum darkening from base to apex). Membrane of fore wing slightly infumate except moderately infumate in apical 0.3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 6</xref>). Body covered with dense silver setae.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 6–7.</label>
                        <caption><p>Habitus <bold>6</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic>,holotype male <bold>7</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion eileenae</tp:taxon-name></italic>,holotype female.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-019-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 8–9.</label>
                        <caption><p>Habitus <bold>8</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic>,holotype female <bold>9</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic>,holotype male.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-019-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 10–15.</label>
                        <caption><p>Head, anterior view <bold>10</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>,paratype male <bold>11</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>, paratype male <bold>12</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic>,paratype male <bold>13</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion eileenae</tp:taxon-name></italic>,holotype female <bold>14</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic>,paratype male <bold>15</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype male.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-019-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 16–21.</label>
                        <caption><p>Vertex showing supra-antennal horn, dorsal view <bold>16</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, paratype male <bold>17</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>, paratype male <bold>18</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic>, paratype male <bold>19</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion eileenae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotypefemale <bold>20</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotypefemale <bold>21</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype male.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-019-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype: ♂, Label 1: BRIT, E, AFRICA [KENYA], Masai Reserve, 29.i.1914, Cap. A.O.Luckman. Label 2: 1919-10. [NHM]. Condition: intact except left antennal flagellum missing all but basal 24 flagellomeres. Paratypes: ♂, BRIT. E. AFRICA [KENYA], 30 miles from Magadi Junc., iv.1912. F.G. Hamilton [NHM]; ♂, BRIT. E. AFRICA [KENYA], Mogorr River, v.1913 [CNC].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>This species is named in honour of the senior author’s father, Dr. Roger Bennett, for his support and encouragement during the long (and sometimes dark) journey towards becoming a systematic entomologist.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> is most closely related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion eileenae</tp:taxon-name></italic> on the basis of the similar short triangular horn of the supra-antennal area and the length of the longitudinal carinae of T1. Even though <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> is only known from males, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion eileenae</tp:taxon-name></italic> from a single female, it is highly unlikely that they are conspecific. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> has extensive yellow colouration on the legs and ivory bands on the metasoma, whereas <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion eileenae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is completely dark. In the three species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> for which both males and females are known, there are minimal sex-related colour differences and this is also the case for species in the related genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibornia</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Seyrig 1935</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thibetoides</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Kasparyan 1973</xref>). In addition, the malar space of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> is 0.4 to 0.5 times the basal width of the mandible compared to 0.7 for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion eileenae</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> also lacks the carina extending from the pleural carina to the propodeal spiracle, whereas this carina is complete in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion eileenae</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zambion</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">eileenae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E90E33CB-A2B1-4B1C-8A80-E0FCC2CD187</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zambion_eileenae</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>sp. n.</tp:taxon-authority>                    
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 7</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">13</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">19</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">26</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion eileenae</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. by having all legs completely dark (brown or black), without any orange or yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 7</xref>). All other species have some orange or yellow in some parts of the legs.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Adult.</bold> Female. Fore wing length 6.0 mm. Clypeus separated from supraclypeal area by a strong groove (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 13</xref>). Malar space 0.7 times basal width of <!--PageBreak-->mandible. Supraclypeal area 1.9 times as high as wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 13</xref>), dorsomedially without a short, narrow, longitudinal lamella between the antenna. Supra-antennal horn short and triangular in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 19</xref>), 0.3 times as long as width of pedicel at<!--PageBreak--> midheight in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 26</xref>). Ocello-ocular distance 1.8 times ocellar diameter. Gena 0.8 times transverse diameter of the eye. Flagellum with 29 segments on left, 28 on right.</p>
                    <p>Notaulus absent. Epicnemial carina mostly straight medially, not curving away from anterior edge of mesopleuron near ventral corner of pronotum (similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 32</xref>). Scutellum with lateral carinae extending 0.5 length of scutellum. Medial longitudinal carinae of propodeum complete and strong anterior to posterior transverse carina (as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 34</xref>). Carina running from pleural carina to propodeal spiracle complete. Posterior transverse carina of propodeum with lateral abscissa roughly straight, point of union with pleural carina at about 0.4 distance from posterior end of pleural carina to propodeal spiracle (similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 36</xref>). Ventral transverse carina extending from metasomal foramen to pleural carina present (as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 35</xref>). Fore tibia without an apical point on dorsal surface. Hind femur 3.6 times as long as medial width. Hind tarsal claw pectinate to about 0.5 times length of claw. Angulation of fore wing vein 2m-cu weak.</p>
                    <p>Tergite 1 of metasoma 1.8 times as long as apical width. Dorsal longitudinal carinae of T1 extending to 0.7 length of T1, dorsolateral longitudinal carinae extending beyond spiracles up to 0.7 length of segment.</p>
                    <p>Black. Legs, metasomal sternites and ovipositor sheaths at base brown, the legs lightening from base to apex except hind leg with tibia and tarsus darker brown. Flagellomere 1 at extreme base and flagellomeres 2+ on ventral surface yellow brown, gradually lightening towards apex, dorsal surface of flagellum brown, lightening to yellow brown apical to middle. Apical 0.3 of clypeus orange-brown. Membrane of fore wing strongly infumate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 7</xref>), slightly less imfumate basally. Body covered with dense silver setae.</p>
                    <p>Male: unknown.</p>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 22–27.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold>22</bold> Head, anterior view, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, paratype male showing unidentate mandible <bold>23</bold> Supraclypeal area, anterolateral view, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male (non-type) (arrow points to longitudinal lamella between antennae) <bold>24–27</bold> head, lateral view <bold>24</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, paratype male <bold>25</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype female <bold>26</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion eileenae</tp:taxon-name></italic>,holotype female <bold>27</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotypefemale.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-019-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype: ♀, Label 1: UGANDA, Ruwenzori Range [Rwenzori Mountains], xii.1934-i.1935., B.M. E. Afr. Exp. B.M. 1935-203. Label 2: Namwamba Valley, 6,500 ft., F.W. Edwards. [NHM]. Condition: intact.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>This species, collected in the “Mountains of the Moon”, is named in honour of the senior author’s mother, Mrs. Eileen Bennett, for her support and understanding, especially when finding dead caterpillars and grasshoppers in jars or worse (live ones wandering through the house).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p>See comments for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zambion</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">wahli</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:14B25D7C-F198-4BEE-B1C4-93FC0CAD4D41</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zambion_wahli</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 8</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">14</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">20, 27</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">28, 31, 33</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. by combination of all of the following characters: 1) mesopleuron completely black (no yel<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->low) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 8</xref>); 2) supra-antennal horn long and sub-parallel-sided in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 20</xref>), 1.2 to 1.3 times as long as pedicel at midheight in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 27</xref>); 3) propodeum completely black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 8</xref>) (not orange).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Adult.</bold> Female. Fore wing length 6.1 mm. Clypeus separated from supraclypeal area by a strong groove (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 14</xref>). Malar space 0.5 times basal width of mandible. Supraclypeal area 2.1 times as wide as high (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 14</xref>), dorsomedially without a short, narrow, longitudinal lamella between the antenna. Supra-antennal horn long and sub-parallel-sided in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 20</xref>), 1.2 times as long as width of pedicel at midheight in lateral view. Ocello-ocular distance 1.6 times ocellar diameter. Gena 0.8 times transverse diameter of the eye. Antenna incomplete (see Material examined).</p>
                    <p>Notaulus present, but weak. Epicnemial carina medially curving away from anterior edge of mesopleuron near ventral corner of pronotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 33</xref>) (not mostly straight medially as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 32</xref>). Scutellum with lateral carinae to 0.3 length of scutellum. Medial longitudinal carinae of propodeum incomplete anterior to posterior transverse carina (present between posterior transverse carina and the level of the propodeal spiracles, but absent anterior to this point). Carina running from pleural carina to spiracle absent. Posterior transverse carina of propodeum with lateral abscissa roughly straight, point of union with pleural carina at about 0.4 distance from posterior end of pleural carina to propodeal spiracle (similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 36</xref>). Ventral transverse carina extending from metasomal foramen to pleural carina present (as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 35</xref>). Fore tibia with a moderately strong apical point on dorsal surface. Hind femur 3.8 times as long as medial width. Hind tarsal claw with pectination not known (both distal tarsomeres missing). Angulation of fore wing vein 2m-cu strong.</p>
                    <p>Tergite 1 of metasoma 1.2 times as long as apical width. Dorsal longitudinal carina of T1 extending to about level of spiracle (0.4 length of segment), dorsolateral longitudinal carina absent (no obvious carina visible between anterior part of dorsal longitudinal carina and spiracle).</p>
                    <p>Black. Distal trochantelli of fore and middle legs, hind trochanter except at base, all femora and tibiae except apical 0.1 of hind tibia, fore tarsomeres 1 - 4, middle tarsomeres 1 – 3, basal 0.8 of hind basal tarsomere, T1 – 4, T5 sublaterally, T6 except anteriorly and all sternites yellow. Palpi, glossa, basal trochantelli of fore and middle legs, base of hind basal trochantellus, apical 0.1 of hind tibia, distal tarsomere of fore and middle leg, all of hind tarsus except basal 0.8 of basal tarsomere, T5 medially and laterally, T6 anteriorly and ovipositor sheaths brown. Membrane of fore wing moderately uniformly infumate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 8</xref>). Body covered with dense, golden setae.</p>
                    <p>Male as female except: Fore wing length 6.2 to 6.3 mm. Malar space 0.4 to 0.5 times basal width of mandible. Supraclypeal area 1.9 to 2.0 times as wide as high. Supra-antennal horn 1.3 times width of pedicel at middle. Ocello-ocular distance 1.8 to 2.0 times ocellar diameter. Gena 0.8 to 0.9 times transverse diameter of eye. Flagellum with 27 segments. Hind femur length 3.7 to 3.8 times medial width. Hind tarsa<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->l claw pectinate to 0.5 to 0.6 length of claw. Posterior transverse carina of propodeum incomplete in middle. Tergite 1 1.3 to 1.4 times as long as apical width. Dorsal longitudinal carina extending to just anterior to spiracles or to level of spiracles (0.3 to 0.4 length of T1). Dorsolateral longitudinal carina of T1 absent or present as a thin, weak ridge that extends half way to spiracle. Colour as female except apical 0.2 of hind tibia, apical 0.5 to 0.9 of hind basal tarsomere brown. Tergites 1 to 4 yellow brown with irregular brown mottling, especially medially and anteriorly on each segment. Tergite 5 yellow laterally. Gonoforceps basally yellow, apically brown.</p>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 28–33.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold>28–29</bold> Head, pronotum and anterior of mesoscutum, dorsal view <bold>28</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype female (double arrow shows widening of pronotum) <bold>29</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype male (arrow shows weak notaulus) <bold>30–31</bold> Pronotum, lateral view <bold>30</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, paratype male <bold>31</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype female <bold>32–33</bold>Mesopleuron, lateral view (arrow points to dorsal part of epicnemial carina) <bold>32</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion rogeri</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype male <bold>33</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype female.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-019-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype: ♀, Label 1: A43. Label 2: AFRICA, UGANDA, Mt. Elgon, Butandiga, 7,000 ft. Label 3: J. Ford, B.M.1935-459. [NHM]. Condition: intact except both antenna with only basal flagellomere attached, right flagellomeres 2 to 14 glued to double-mount block, left hind leg missing distal 3 tarsomeres, right hind leg missing distal tarsomere, apical half of right ovipositor sheath missing. Paratypes: 2 ♂, same data as holotype except: A47 on upper label [NHM, CNC].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>This species is named in honour of Dr. David Wahl (American Entomological Institute) (AEIC) for his contributions to ichneumonid taxonomy and his hospitality to the senior author during many visits to the AEIC.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic> is most closely related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic> on the basis of the long, sub-parallel-sided horn (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 20, 21</xref>), the curved epicnemial carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 33</xref>) and the lack of a complete medial, longitudinal carina of the propodeum anterior to the posterior transverse carina. See comments under the latter species for distinction of these two species.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zambion</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">broadi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:920ECA3B-CC89-4A2E-B959-DD852CD33D7E</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zambion_broadi</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 9</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">15</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">21</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">29</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">37</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp. by combination of all of the following characters: 1) mesopleuron completely black (without yellow) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 9</xref>); 2) supra-antennal horn long and sub-parallel-sided in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 21</xref>), 1.2 times as long as pedicel at midheight in lateral view; 3) propodeum orange (not black) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 9</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Adult.</bold> Male. Fore wing length 6.4 mm. Clypeus separated from supraclypeal area by a strong groove. Malar space 0.4 times basal width of mandible. Supraclypeal area 1.9 times as wide as high (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 15</xref>), dorsomedially without a short, narrow, longitudinal lamella between the antenna. Supra-antennal horn long and sub-parallel-sided in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 21</xref>), 1.2 times as long as width of pedicel at midheight in lateral view. Ocello-ocular distance 2.1 times ocellar diameter. Gena 0.6 times transverse diameter of the eye. Flagellum with 30 segments.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->Notaulus present, but weak (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 29</xref>). Epicnemial carina medially curving away from anterior edge of mesopleuron near ventral corner of pronotum (similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 33</xref>). Scutellum with lateral carinae at base only. Medial longitudinal carinae of propodeum absent anterior to posterior transverse carina. Posterior transverse carina incomplete medially. Carina extending from pleural carina to propodeal spiracle absent. Posterior transverse carina of propodeum with lateral abscissa strongly curving posteriorly where it joins pleural carina, point of union at about 0.2 distance from posterior end of pleural carina to propodeal spiracle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 37</xref>). Ventral transverse carina extending from metasomal foramen to pleural carina present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 37</xref>). Fore tibia apical point not examined (both fore tibiae absent). Hind femur 3.6 times as long as medial width. Hind tarsal claw pectinate to 0.4 times length of claw. Angulation of fore wing vein 2m-cu strong.</p>
                    <p>Tergite 1 of metasoma 1.2 times as long as apical width. Dorsal longitudinal carinae of T1 extending to about level of spiracle (0.4 length of tergite), dorsolateral longitudinal carinae present only as a short stub bifurcating near base of dorsal longitudinal carina.</p>
                    <p>Black. Apical half of clypeus, glossa, apex of scutellum, propodeum, metasoma, except as noted below, orange. Tegula, coxae, apical 0.2 of hind tibia, hind tarsus except basal 0.3 of basal tarsomere, T2+ in spots laterally and sublaterally, T5 to T6 medially and hypopygium brown. Palpi, hind trochanter, femur, basal 0.8 of hind tibia and basal 0.3 of basal tarsomere, sternites and gonoforceps brownish yellow. Note that the distinction between orange and brownish yellow is not always clear. The hind leg is slightly more yellowish than the propodeum, the latter being slightly more yellow (and slightly less orange) than the scutellum and tergites. Membrane of fore wing uniformly, moderately infumate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 9</xref>). Body covered with dense golden setae.</p>
                    <p>Female: unknown.</p>
                    <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 34–39.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold>34</bold> Propodeum, dorsal view. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype female<bold>35–37</bold> Propodeum, dorsolateral view (double-headed arrows indicate length of pleural carina anterior and posterior to point of union with posterior transverse carina) <bold>35</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, paratype male <bold>36</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype female (note lack of ventral transverse carina) <bold>37</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype male <bold>38–39</bold> Fore wing <bold>38</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype female <bold>39</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>,paratype male. <bold>llc</bold> – lateral longitudinal carina, <bold>mlc</bold> – medial longitudinal carina, <bold>pc</bold> – pleural carina, <bold>ptc</bold> – posterior transverse carina, <bold>ps</bold> – propodeal spiracle, <bold>vtc</bold> – ventral transverse carina.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-019-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 40–45.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold>40–41</bold> First metasomal segment, lateral view (hollow arrow marks posterior end of dorsal longitudinal carina, solid arrow denotes posterior end of dorsolateral longitudinal carina) <bold>40</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, paratype male <bold>41</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>, paratype male <bold>42</bold> Anterior of metasoma, lateral view, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>, paratype male (arrow points to laterotergite of second metasomal segment) <bold>43</bold> Tergites 2 and 3, dorsal view, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype female <bold>44</bold> Posterior of metasoma, lateral view showing ovipositor, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion hirtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype female <bold>45</bold> Egg, lateral view, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype female.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-019-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 46–48.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion kasparyani</tp:taxon-name></italic>, holotype male <bold>46</bold> Habitus <bold>47</bold> Head, dorsal view <bold>48</bold> Propodeum, dorsolateral view (note lack of ventral transverse carina similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Fig. <bold>36</bold>).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-159-019-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype: ♂, Label 1: BRIT. E. AFRICA [KENYA], 30 miles from Magadi Junc., April.1912, F.G. Hamilton. Label 2: 1915-98. [NHM]. Condition: right flagellum with only basal 15 flagellomeres, left flagellum with basal 5 flagellomeres attached, fore and middle legs missing except for coxae, left flagellomeres 6 to 15 and right hind leg glued on card below specimen.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>This species is named in honour of Dr. Gavin Broad (NHM) in recognition of his contributions to ichneumonid taxonomy and for finding the type specimen of this species within the unidentified ichneumonids of the Natural History Museum, London.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is most closely related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic> as noted under the comments for that species. The differences are the colour of the propodeum (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 8 and 9</xref>), the shape and location of the lateral abscissa of the posterior transverse carina of the propodeum, and the complete lack of the medial longitudinal carina dorsal to the posterior transverse carina of the propodeum in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (present, but incomplete in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic>). It is possible that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion broadi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is conspecific with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion wahli</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but we think this unlikely given the difference in both colour and propodeal carination. When both of these characters differ in related taxa, it is a good indicator that two species are present (e.g., in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dyspetes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Förster) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">He and Wan 1987</xref>)<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>The authors would like to thank the curators of the following institutions for loan of specimens: Dr. C. Villemant (MNHN); Dr. P. Malinen, (MZH), Dr. R. Zuparko (CAS) and Dr. G. Broad (NHM), the latter, especially, because of sorting through decades of unidentified specimens to find additional material for this study. Dr. L. Masner (CNC) hand-carried specimens to MNHM. Dr. D. Kasparyan (Zoological Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences, St. Petersburg) and Dr. N. Bogutskaya (Zoosystematica Rossica) provided permission to copy line drawings of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zambion monodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Ms. J. Read (Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada) and Ms. Bonnie O’Halloran (Leica Microsystems) were invaluable in helping with preparation of digital photographs.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname> <given-names>AMR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<source> Cladistics of the Tryphoninae (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae) with a discussion of host use and the evolution of parasitism in the Ichneumonidae.</source> <publisher-name>PhD thesis, Toronto</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Ontario: University of Toronto</publisher-loc>, <lpage>366</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Delobel</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Une nouvelle espéce afrotropicale de Tryphoninae: <italic>Zambion hirtum</italic> sp. n. (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Société entomologique de France </source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>-<lpage>270</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Evenhuis</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> The insect and spider collections of the world website. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hbs.bishopmuseum.org/codens/">http://hbs.bishopmuseum.org/codens/</ext-link> [accessed: 27.VII.2011]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Some factors affecting the composition of tropical ichneumonid faunas.</article-title> <source>Biological Journal of the Linnean Society </source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>312</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1095-8312.1987.tb00304.x">10.1111/j.1095-8312.1987.tb00304.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> The Ichneumonidae of Costa Rica, 1. Introduction, keys to subfamilies, and keys to the species of the lower Pimpliform subfamilies Rhyssinae, Poemeniinae, Acaenitinae and Cylloceriinae.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute </source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>589</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>)<source> The taxonomy, distribution and host preferences of African parasitic wasps of the subfamily Ophioninae.</source> <publisher-name>CAB:Slough. Commonwealth Institute of Entomology</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>287</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sithole</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez</surname> <given-names>JU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godoy</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> The Ichneumonidae of Costa Rica. 4. Introduction and keys to species of the subfamilies: Metopiinae and Banchinae.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute </source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>768</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradshaw</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> The Ichneumonidae of Costa Rica, 2. Introduction and keys to species of the smaller subfamilies, Anomaloninae, Ctenopelmatinae, Diplazontinae, Lycorininae, Phrudinae, Tryphoninae (excluding <italic>Netelia</italic>) and Xoridinae, with an appendices on the Rhyssinae.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute </source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>485</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallet</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<source> The Ichneumonidae of Costa Rica, 3. Introduction and keys to species of the subfamilies Brachycyrtinae, Cremastinae, Labeninae and Oxytorinae, with an appendix on the Anomaloninae. Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute (Gainesville) 63: 1- 453.</source></mixed-citation></ref><!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Goulet</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>eds</role>) (<year>1993</year>)<source> Hymenoptera of the world: an identification guide to families. Research Branch of Agriculture Canada, Publication 1894/E. 668 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname> <given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> A review of the world species of <italic>Dyspetes</italic> (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae).</article-title> <source>Contributions to the American Entomological Institute </source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname> <given-names>XS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of five new species of the genus <italic>Dyspetes</italic> (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae).</article-title> <source>Acta Zootaxonomica Sinica </source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>. [in Chinese with English summary.]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrich</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967a</year>)<source> Synopsis and reclassification of the Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae of Africa south of Sahara (Hym.). Vol.I. Farmington State College Press, 250 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrich</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967b</year>)<source> Synopsis and reclassification of the Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae of Africa south of Sahara (Hym.).Vol.II. Farmington State College Press., 251–480.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrich</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967c</year>)<source> Synopsis and reclassification of the Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae of Africa south of Sahara (Hym.).Vol.III. Farmington State College Press, 481–692.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrich</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968a</year>)<source> Synopsis and reclassification of the Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae of Africa south of Sahara (Hym.).Vol.IV. Farmington State College Press, 693–942.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrich</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968b</year>)<source> Synopsis and reclassification of the Ichneumoninae Stenopneusticae of Africa south of Sahara (Hym.).Vol.V. Farmington State College Press, 943–1258.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordan</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> Eiformen und Lebenweise zweier Artengruppen der Gattung <italic>Grypocentrus</italic> (Ichneumonidae: Tryphoninae), spezifische Parasitoiden der im Frühjahr an Birken minierenden Trugmotten-Arten (Lepidoptera: Eriocraniidae).</article-title> <source>Entomologia Generalis </source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>-<lpage>231</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasparyan</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>)<source> Fauna of the USSR Hymenoptera Vol III Number 1. Ichneumonidae (Subfamily Tryphoninae) Tribe Tryphonini. Nauka Publishers, Leningrad. [Translated from Russian. Amerind Publishing Co. Ltd., New Delhi, 1981, 414 pp.]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasparyan</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> <italic>Zambion</italic>, a new tryphonine genus from Africa (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae).</article-title> <source>Zoosystematica Rossica </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>86</fpage>-<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasparyan</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolkanitz</surname> <given-names>VI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> Ichneumonidae subfamily Tryphoninae: tribes Sphinctini, Phytodietini, Oedemopsini, Tryphonini (Addendum), Idiogrammatini. Subfamilies Eucerotinae, Adelognathinae (addendum), Townesioninae. [Fauna of Russia and Neighbouring Countries. Insecta Hymenoptera.] Volume III. Number 3. Saint Petersburg. Nauka, 404 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname> <given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1936</year>)<article-title> The ancestry and wing venation of the Hymenoptera.</article-title> <source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America </source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Scaramozzino</surname> <given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> Two new species of the genus <italic>Boethus</italic> Foerster, 1869 from Africa. (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Tryphoninae).</article-title> <source>Bollettino della Societa Entomologica Italiana </source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Seyrig</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1932</year>)<source> Les Ichneumonides de Madagascar. I Ichneumonidae Pimplinae. Mémoires de l’Académie Malgache 11 : 1–183.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Seyrig</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1934</year>)<article-title> Les Ichneumonides de Madagascar. II Ichneumonidae Tryphoninae et Supplement aux I. Pimplinae.</article-title> <source>Mémoires de l’Académie Malgache </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>111</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Seyrig</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1935</year>)<article-title> Mission scientifique de l’Omo. Tome III. Fascicule 18. Hymenoptera, II. Ichneumonidae: Cryptinae, Pimplinae, Tryphoninae et Ophioninae.</article-title> <source>Mémoires du Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris, </source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>100</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Seyrig</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1952</year>)<article-title> Les Ichneumonides de Madagascar.</article-title> <source>IV Ichneumonidae Cryptinae. Mémoires de l’Académie Malgache.</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>213</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Townes</surname> <given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>)<article-title> The genera of Ichneumonidae, Part 1.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute </source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> The cladistics and higher classification of the Pimpliformes (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae).</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology </source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>-<lpage>298</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-3113.1998.00057.x">10.1046/j.1365-3113.1998.00057.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Achterberg</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horstmann</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> World Ichneumonoidea 2008. Taxonomy, biology, morphology and distribution. [CD/DVD]. Taxapad®, Vancouver, Canada. [Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.taxapad.com">http://www.taxapad.com</ext-link>].</source></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>