<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.299.4970</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>The genus 
                    <italic>Myrmarachne</italic> (Araneae, Salticidae) in Flores, Indonesia</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Yamasaki</surname>
                        <given-names>Takeshi</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:804886B5-C951-490C-95C4-D2CA7F4F94D7</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Edwards</surname>
                        <given-names>G. B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:92CCEF1B-823D-413A-A3A9-8699750759B1</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Graduate School of Science and Engineering, Kagoshima University, Kagoshima, 890-0065 Japan
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Florida State Collection of Arthropods, FDACS/Division of Plant Industry, P.O.Box 147100, Gainesville, FL 32614-7100, USA
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Takeshi Yamasaki (<email xlink:type="simple">k0468874@kadai.jp</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Jeremy Miller</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>14</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>299</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>20</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>5</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>7</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2013</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Takeshi Yamasaki, G. B. Edwards</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:4C20A280-C9F8-4A20-B5FF-3C564DCEB226</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Two new species of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne</tp:taxon-name></italic> are described (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne acutidens</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne epigealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne macrognatha</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne melanocephala</tp:taxon-name></italic> are redescribed from Flores specimens. The females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne macrognatha</tp:taxon-name></italic> are recorded for the first time.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>New species</kwd>
                <kwd>ant-mimicking jumping spiders</kwd>
                <kwd>Java</kwd>
                <kwd>Malay Archipelago</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne</tp:taxon-name></italic> MacLeay, 1839 is one of the largest groups in the family <tp:taxon-name>Salticidae</tp:taxon-name>, including around 250 species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Prószyński 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Platnick 2012</xref>). The members of the genus generally resemble ants morphologically and behaviorally, and the resemblance is considered to be due to Batesian mimicry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Wanless 1978</xref>). The area from Southeast Asia to Australia through the Malay Archipelago harbors many <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. Wallacea, the non-continental transition zone between the Oriental (Sundan) and Australian (Sahulian) zoogeographical regions, is bounded to the west by Wallace’s line and to the east by Lydekker’s line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Hill 2010</xref>). The <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne</tp:taxon-name></italic> faunas of Wallacean islands have not been studied and revealed sufficiently although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Thorell (1877)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Yamasaki (2012)</xref> together record ten species from Sulawesi.</p>
            <p>Flores forms part of a series of active volcanoes between Java and Timor, and its climate is relatively dry, strongly affected by monsoon and trade winds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Monk et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">van der Geer 2010</xref>). Until now, no <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne</tp:taxon-name></italic> species have been recorded from the island. In the present study, we describe two new species and redescribe two species known elsewhere, reported from Flores for the first time.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods">
            <title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>Collection sites are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. Morphological observations were made with a Nikon SMZ 1000 stereoscope. Multi-focused montage images were produced using Helicon Focus 4.75 Pro from a series of source images taken by Cannon EOS Kiss x 4 digital camera attached to a Nikon ECLIPSE E600 microscope. Measured parts of the carapace follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Yamasaki (2010)</xref>. Chelicera length was measured in lateral view, and only for males.</p>
            <p>All measurements are given in millimeters. The ranges from the minimum to maximum are shown when more than two specimens were measured. For some species, figures for the holotypes are shown in parentheses. Abbreviations used in the present <!--PageBreak-->paper are as follows: AME, anterior median eye; ALE, anterior lateral eye; PME, posterior median eye; PLE, posterior lateral eye; pd, prodorsal; pv, proventral; rd, retrodorsal; RTA, retrolateral tibial apophysis of palp; rv, retroventral.</p>
            <p>The type material examined in the present study was borrowed from Naturhistoriska riksmuseet, Stockholm, Sweden (NRM). The type specimens designated here are deposited at Museum Zoologicum Bogoriense, Research Center for Biology, Indonesian Institute of Science, Cibinong, Indonesia (MZB), and at the Florida State Collection of Arthropods, Gainesville, Florida, USA (FSCA).</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Collection sites. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne acutidens</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne epigealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> were collected from Mego and Moni, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne macrognatha</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Moni, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne melanocephala</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Mego.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-299-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Myrmarachne</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">acutidens</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E48ED428-C691-4C0E-B862-A6E9E0D8E9CD</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Myrmarachne_acutidens</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">–19</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                    <title>Type material.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male (MZB. Aran. 503), Mego [=<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°40'S, 122°2'E</named-content>], Sikka, Flores, East Nusa Tenggara Prov., INDONESIA, 16.X.2012, T. Yamasaki leg. Paratypes: 1 male and 2 females (1 male and 1 female, FCSA; 1 female, MZB. Aran. 504), same data as holotype; 1 male and 1 female (FSCA), Moni [=<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°45'S, 121°51'E</named-content>], Flores, East Nusa Tenggara Prov., INDONESIA, 17.X.2012, T. Yamasaki leg.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Blackish species; total length approximately 3.0–4.0 mm in males and 3.5–5.1 mm in females. Males distinguished from other species by structure of chelicera, which is anteriorly swollen and posteriorly narrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>); further distinguished from other species by first and second apical prolateral teeth of chelicera, which are long compared to other teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>), and fang bearing short tooth-like apophysis submedially on its venter and weak protuberance on dorsum at its base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>). Females distinguished from other species except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne macrognatha</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thorell, 1894) by shape of dorsum of cephalic and thoracic parts, which are roundly convex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 11</xref>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne acutidens</tp:taxon-name></italic> distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne macrognatha</tp:taxon-name></italic> by shape of proximal part of sclerotized copulatory ducts of epigyne, which is narrower in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne acutidens</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 13</xref> vs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">44</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Measurements</title>
                    <p>(male/female). Carapace length 1.50–2.00 (1.90) /1.88–2.20, width 0.83–1.17 (1.10) /0.88–1.07. Chelicera length 1.08– (1.83). ALE–PLE 0.58–0.77 (0.75) /0.65–0.75; ALE–PME 0.26– (0.35) /0.30–0.37. Width of eye row I 0.78–1.05 (1.02) /0.86–1.03; II 0.73–0.98 (0.95) /0.80–0.93; III 0.84–1.13 (1.08) /0.93–1.10. Eye size: AME 0.25–0.37 (0.33) /0.28–0.33; ALE 0.13–0.16 (0.15) /0.13–0.17; PME (0.05) /0.05; PLE 0.14–0.19 (0.16) /0.14–0.16.</p>
                    <p><bold>Male</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2–9</xref>). Cephalic part almost flat dorsally, distinctly higher than thoracic part; lateral surface of carapace strongly incised behind PLE; dorsum of thoracic part weakly convex in middle part, and then sloping downward (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2–3</xref>). Chelicera almost as long as carapace, its anterior part weakly swollen dorsally and wider than posterior part; venter of chelicera bearing seven to ten prolateral and two to four retrolat<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->eral teeth; apical two prolateral and one retrolateral teeth large, especially second prolateral tooth counted from apex very long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>). Fang weakly sinuous, bearing short tooth-like apophysis on venter near its middle, and weak protuberance on dorsum of its base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>); proximal part of fang strongly arched. Pedicel short (0.25–0.32 mm). Abdomen oval without distinct constriction, and with two contiguous dorsal scuta; each lateral margin of where scuta are contiguous strongly incised at anterior third.</p>
                    <p>With palp in dorsal and ventral views, cymbium elongate-oval, with one apical spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>). Tegulum oval, with ejaculatory duct along proximal and prolateral margins, and rounded V-shaped ejaculatory duct at distal retrolateral margin of tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>). Embolus forming two oval coils; embolus coils occupying more than half of venter of cymbium, and basal coil as wide as venter of cymbium, while more ventral <!--PageBreak-->coil is slightly smaller (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>). With palp in dorsal and ventral views, RTA curved outward, with well-developed its flange; with palp in retrolateral view, RTA strongly s-curved with tip slightly spiraled (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7, 9</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Number of spines on legs. Femur I pd 0–1, rd 0; tibia I pv 1–3, rv 2–3; metatarsus I pv 2, rv 2; tibia II pv 0, rv 0–2; metatarsus II pv 1, rv 1; femur III pd 1, rd 0; femur IV pd 1, rd 0–1.</p>
                    <p>Coloration in alcohol and pilosity. Carapace covered with white setae; cephalic part black and thoracic part dark brown; lateral surface of carapace above coxae I and II densely fringed with white setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2–3</xref>). Chelicera dark brown; boundary between anterior swollen part and posterior narrow part fringed with white setae; anterior swol<!--PageBreak-->len part covered with long setae. Endite brownish cream. Labium and sternum dark brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>). Coxa and trochanter I dark yellow suffused with gray, coalesced into lateral dark stripe; coxae II and III black, distal prolateral part of coxa II yellowish suffused with gray, trochanter II like trochanter I except lighter yellow, trochanter III with more extensive lateral stripe and yellowish venter suffused with gray; coxa IV dark yellow with gray lateral stripes, trochanter IV white with short lateral gray marks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>). Abdomen and its dorsal scuta black, covered with fine setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2–3</xref>).</p>
                    <p><bold>Female</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 10</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">19</xref>). With carapace in lateral view, cephalic part roundly convex dorsally, slightly higher than thoracic part; dorsal concavity behind PLE distinct; dorsum of thoracic part roundly convex overall (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 10–11</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">15–16</xref>). Chelicera bearing four to six prolateral and seven to eight retrolateral teeth on its venter. Pedicel usually short, but sometimes long (0.23–0.95 mm). Abdomen oval, without distinct constriction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 10–11</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">15–16</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 13–14</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">18–19</xref>). Copulatory atria containing openings round. Median copulatory structure in front of epigastric furrow divided into lateral pockets; each lateral margin anteroposteriorly flattened. Sclerotized copulatory ducts emerging from oval spermathecae with complex twists, then extending between atria to vicinity of lateral pockets.</p>
                    <p>Number of spines on legs. Tibia I pv 4–5, rv 4; metatarsus I pv 2, rv 2; tibia II pv 0–1, rv2; metatarsus II pv 1–2, rv 2.</p>
                    <p>Coloration in alcohol and pilosity. Carapace black; cephalic part covered with fine setae; thoracic part sparsely covered with white setae; lateral surface of carapace above coxae I and II densely fringed with white setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 10–11</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">15–16</xref>). Chelicera light brown. Endite brownish yellow, tinged with gray (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 12</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">17</xref>). Labium cream, tinged with black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 12</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">17</xref>). Sternum black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 12</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">17</xref>). Coxae and trochanters similar to male pattern but lighter in color; coxae and trochanters I and II white, coxa II with variable black retrolateral stripe; coxa and trochanter III black, trochanter lighter ventrally suffused with black; coxa IV yellow with extensive lateral black stripe, trochanter IV white (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 12</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">17</xref>). Abdomen black, covered with fine setae; some white setae roughly forming transverse white band in anterior dorsum of abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 10–11</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">15–16</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 2–9.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne acutidens</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male. <bold>2</bold> Body in dorsal view <bold>3</bold> body in lateral view <bold>4</bold> endites, labium, coxae and trochanters in ventral view <bold>5</bold> left chelicera in ventral view <bold>6</bold> left fang in retrolateral view <bold>7</bold> left palp in retrolateral view <bold>8</bold> left palp in ventral view <bold>9</bold> left palpal tibia in dorsal view. (Scales. Figs <bold>2–6</bold>: 1 mm; <bold>7–9</bold>: 0.25 mm)</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-299-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 10–14.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne acutidens</tp:taxon-name></italic>, female. <bold>10</bold> Body in dorsal view <bold>11</bold> body in lateral view <bold>12</bold> endites, labium, coxae and trochanters in ventral view <bold>13</bold> internal structure of epigyne in ventral view <bold>14</bold> internal structure of epigyne in dorsal view. (Scales. Figs <bold>10–12</bold>: 1 mm; <bold>13–14</bold>: 0.1 mm)</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-299-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 15–19.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne acutidens</tp:taxon-name></italic>, hairy female. <bold>15</bold> Body in dorsal view <bold>16</bold> body in lateral view <bold>17</bold> endites, labium, coxae and trochanters in ventral view <bold>18</bold> internal structure of epigyne in ventral view <bold>19</bold> internal structure of epigyne in dorsal view. (Scales. Figs <bold>15–17</bold>: 1 mm; <bold>18–19</bold>: 0.1 mm)</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-299-001-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific name is derived from the second prolateral tooth counted from the apex in males.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology">
                    <title>Biology.</title>
                    <p>The species is arboreal, and collected from trees in secondary forests or plantation areas.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Flores.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Myrmarachne</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">epigealis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F33ED9E3-EC1F-4211-96FA-86927ADF099E</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Myrmarachne_epigealis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">–32</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                    <title>Type material.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male (MZB. Aran. 505), Moni [=<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°45'S, 121°51'E</named-content>], Flores, East Nusa Tenggara Prov., INDONESIA, 18–19.X.2012, T. Yamasaki leg. Paratypes: <!--PageBreak-->1 male (FSCA), Mego [=<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°40'S, 122°2'E</named-content>], Sikka, Flores, East Nusa Tenggara Prov., INDONESIA, 16.X.2012, T. Yamasaki leg.; 2 females (FSCA), same as holotype; 1 female (MZB. Aran. 506), same loc., 18.X.2012, Rijal Satria leg.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Black species; total length approximately 5.3–5.8 mm in males, 6.2–7.2 mm in females. Males distinguished from other species by prolateral dorsal margin of chelicera diverted toward retrolateral side in distal half, exposing prolateral surface of chelicera in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 20</xref>). Females distinguished from other species except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne grossa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Edmunds &amp; Prószyński, 2003 by thoracic part, which is longer than cephalic part (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 28–29</xref>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne epigealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne grossa</tp:taxon-name></italic> by sclerotized copulatory ducts, which are narrower and longer than those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne grossa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (cf. figs 78–79 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Edmunds and Prószyński 2003</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Measurements</title>
                    <p>(male/female). Carapace length 2.63– (2.83) / 3.20–3.35, width 1.35– (1.40) /1.33–1.48. Chelicera length 1.90– (2.07). ALE–PLE 0.95– (1.00) /1.03–1.13; ALE–PME 0.45– (0.47) / 0.50–0.55. Width of eye row I 1.28– (1.33) / 1.38–1.45; II 1.13– (1.18) /1.20–1.28; III 1.33– (1.38) / 1.43–1.53. Eye size: AME (0.43) / 0.43–0.45; ALE 0.22– (0.23) /0.22–0.23; PME 0.06– (0.08) /0.08; PLE 0.23– (0.24) / 0.25–0.26.</p>
                    <p><bold>Male</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–27</xref>). Cephalic part weakly convex dorsally, distinctly higher than thoracic part; in lateral view, dorsum of carapace sloping downward behind PLE, and concave between cephalic and thoracic parts; lateral surface between cephalic and thoracic parts weakly incised; thoracic part roundly swollen overall (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–21</xref>). Chelicera slightly shorter than carapace; with chelicera in dorsal view, its dorsal prolateral margin diverted toward retrolateral margin in distal half, exposing prolateral surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 20</xref>); venter of chelicera bearing four to five prolateral and eleven to 14 retrolateral teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 23</xref>); apical prolateral corner of venter forming large tooth-like apophysis; with chelicera in ventral view, one retrolateral tooth present next to third retrolateral tooth counted from base, and one prolateral tooth slightly proximal to row of retrolateral teeth. Fang weakly sinuous, without tooth-like apophysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 24</xref>). Pedicel short (0.30–0.43 mm). Abdomen oval with weak constriction at anterior fourth, and its entire dorsum covered with two contiguous dorsal scuta; lateral margins strongly incised where scuta come together (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–21</xref>).</p>
                    <p>With palp in dorsal and ventral views, cymbium elongate-oval with one apical spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 25</xref>). Tegulum oval, with long seminal reservoir along margin of tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 25</xref>). Embolus forming two oval coils; more ventral embolus coil as wide as venter of cymbium, slightly narrower than basal coil (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 25</xref>). RTA well developed with the tip curved inward, and without a distinct its flange (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 26–27</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Number of spines on legs. Patella I pv 0, rv 0–1; tibia I pv 5, rv 5; metatarsus I pv 2, rv 2; tibia II pv 3, rv 3; metatarsus II pv 2, rv 2.</p>
                    <p>Coloration in alcohol and pilosity. Carapace and chelicera black, covered with very short inconspicuous setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–21</xref>). Carapace with pair of light brown spots behind PLE. Endite, labium and sternum light brown, tinged with black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 22</xref>). In ventral view, coxa and trochanter I light yellow, tinged with gray on posterior margin of coxa and laterally on trochanter; coxa II black, trochanter II like trochanter I; coxa and trochanter III black, trochanter yellow ventrally strongly tinged with <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->black; coxa IV blackish with yellow venter strongly tinged with black, trochanter IV light yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 22</xref>). Abdomen and its dorsal scuta black, covered with fine setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–21</xref>).</p>
                    <p><bold>Female</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 28–32</xref>). Cephalic part very weakly convex or almost flat, higher than thoracic part; with carapace in lateral view, dorsal concavity roundly convex behind PLE; thoracic part swollen dorsally overall (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 28–29</xref>). Chelicera bearing seven prolateral and 13 to 14 retrolateral teeth on its venter. Pedicel short (0.43–0.55 mm). Abdomen oval with weak constriction in anterior third, and without obvious dorsal scuta (may be present under pilosity).</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->Epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 31–32</xref>). Copulatory atria containing openings round. Median pocket present in front of epigastric furrow, weakly sclerotized. Sclerotized copulatory ducts extending from oval spermathecae without twists to posterolateral to atria.</p>
                    <p>Number of spines on legs. Patella I pv 0, rv 1; tibia I pv 5, rv 5; metatarsus I pv 2, rv 2; tibia II pv 3, rv 3; metatarsus II pv 2, rv 2.</p>
                    <p>Coloration in alcohol and pilosity. Carapace mainly black, covered with white setae densely; carapace with pair of light brown spots behind PLE; lateral surface of carapace above coxa I white, densely fringed with white setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 28–29</xref>). Chelicera brown. Endite, labium and sternum brownish cream, weakly tinged with black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 30</xref>). Coxae and trochanters in ventral view similar to those of males, except coxa IV with much more yellow ventrally, and trochanter IV yellow with distal retrolateral black spot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 30</xref>). Abdomen covered with golden setae dorsally, and with fine setae ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 28</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 20–27.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne epigealis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male. <bold>20</bold> Body in dorsal view <bold>21</bold> body in lateral view <bold>22</bold> endites, labium, coxae and trochanters in ventral view <bold>23</bold> left chelicera in ventral view <bold>24</bold> left fang in retrolateral view <bold>25</bold> left palp in ventral view <bold>26</bold> left palp in retrolateral view <bold>27</bold> left palpal tibia in dorsal view. (Scales. Figs <bold>20–24</bold>: 1 mm; <bold>25–27</bold>: 0.25 mm)</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-299-001-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 28–32.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne epigealis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, female. <bold>28</bold> Body in dorsal view <bold>29</bold> body in lateral view <bold>30</bold> endites, labium, coxae and trochanters in ventral view <bold>31</bold> epigyne in ventral view <bold>32</bold> internal structure of epigyne in ventral view. (Scales. Figs <bold>28–30</bold>: 1 mm; <bold>31–32</bold>: 0.1 mm)</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-299-001-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific name is derived from the ground microhabitat, where the species often occurs.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology">
                    <title>Biology.</title>
                    <p>The species occurs in lower vegetation and on the ground.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Flores.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Myrmarachne</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">macrognatha</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Myrmarachne_macrognatha</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>(Thorell, 1894)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 33</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">–45</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Salticus macrognathus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Thorell, 1894: 58.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne macrognatha</tp:taxon-name><comment>: Roewer, 1954: 947.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                    <title>Type material.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male (NRM), Java, [INDONESIA], van Hass. [van Hasselt].</p>
                    <p><bold>Non-type material examined</bold>: 16 males and 11 females, Moni [=<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°45'S, 121°51'E</named-content>], Flores, East Nusa Tenggara Prov., INDONESIA, 17–19.X.2012, T. Yamasaki leg.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Blackish species; total length approximately 3.2–5.3 mm in males and 4.0–5.2 mm in females. Males distinguished from other species except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne smaragdina</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ceccarelli, 2010 (cf. fig. 34 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Ceccarelli 2010</xref>) by characteristic dentition of chelicera, of which fourth prolateral tooth counted from apex long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 36</xref>); further distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne smaragdina</tp:taxon-name></italic> by shapes of chelicera and carapace (figs 28–29 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Ceccarelli 2010</xref> vs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 33–34</xref>). Females distinguished from other species except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne melanocephala</tp:taxon-name></italic> MacLeay, 1839 by sclerotized copulatory ducts clearly twisted in “figure 8” (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 44–45</xref>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne macrognatha</tp:taxon-name></italic> distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne melanocephala</tp:taxon-name></italic> by absence of distinct markings on abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 41</xref> vs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">54</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Measurements (male/female).</title>
                    <p>Carapace length 1.63–2.50 (2.23) /1.75–2.10, width 0.93–1.57 (1.38) /0.91–1.08. Chelicera length 1.30–3.85 (3.30). ALE–PLE 0.67–1.02 (0.92) /0.68–0.82; ALE–PME 0.30–0.43 (0.42) /0.26–0.35. Width of eye row I 0.87–1.30 (1.17) /0.93–1.05; II 0.80–1.20 (1.10) /0.85–0.95; III 0.95–1.45 <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> (1.32) /1.02–1.15. Eye size: AME 0.28–0.42 (0.37) /0.31–0.34; ALE 0.15–0.20 (0.18) /0.14–0.16; PME 0.05– (0.08) /0.05–0.06; PLE 0.15–0.23 (0.20) /0.16–0.18.</p>
                    <p><bold>Male</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 33–40</xref>). With carapace in lateral view, cephalic part almost flat dorsally, higher than thoracic part; dorsal concavity behind PLE shallow or indistinct; thoracic part sloping downward, not distinctly convex dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 33–34</xref>). Chelicera distinctly longer than carapace, each lateral margin almost parallel-sided except for distinctly convex prolateral margin near anterior end of chelicera; venter of chelicera bearing nine to twelve prolateral and three to six retrolateral teeth; fourth prolateral tooth counted from apex long and strongly curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 36</xref>). Fang almost straight or very weakly sinuous except for curved tip and base, with long tooth-like apophysis on its venter at about 1/4 the length of fang from its base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 37</xref>). Pedicel short (0.18–0.30 mm). Abdomen oval without distinct constriction, with dorsal two scuta that are clearly separated.</p>
                    <p>With palp in dorsal and ventral views, cymbium elongate-oval, with one apical spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 38</xref>). Tegulum round and small, with s-curved ejaculation duct in distal retrolateral part of tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 38</xref>). Embolus forming two round coils; embolus coils occupying less than half of venter of cymbium; ventral coil much smaller than basal coil, only about half the diameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 38</xref>). RTA strongly curved, and in retrolateral view, somewhat spiraled (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 38–40</xref>). Flange of RTA moderately developed.</p>
                    <p>Number of spines on legs. Femur I pd 1, rd 0; tibia I pv 0–3, rv 1–4; metatarsus I pv 2, rv 2; femur II pd 1, rd 0; tibia II pv 0, rv 0–2; metatarsus II pv 0–2, rv 1–2; femur III pd 0–1, rd 0; femur IV pd 1, rd 0.</p>
                    <p>Coloration in alcohol and pilosity. Carapace black; cephalic part covered with fine white setae, and thoracic part sparsely covered with white setae; lateral carapace not fringed with white setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 33–34</xref>). Chelicera dark brown to black, and long white setae roughly forming transverse band in anterior part of chelicera. Endite and labium brownish orange, tinged with black laterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 35</xref>). Coxae and trochanters I, III, IV yellow with gray lateral stripes; coxa and trochanter II cream-white, coxa with gray lateral stripes; in large specimens, coxae sometimes strongly tinged with black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 35</xref>). Abdomen and its dorsal scuta black, covered with white long setae and fine setae dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 33–34</xref>).</p>
                    <p><bold>Female</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 41–45</xref>). With carapace in lateral view, cephalic part weakly convex dorsally, slightly higher than thoracic part; dorsal concavity behind PLE distinct; thoracic part swollen dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 41–42</xref>). Chelicera bearing five to six prolateral and six retrolateral teeth on its venter. Pedicel relatively longer than that of males (0.35–0.43 mm). Abdomen oval, without distinct constriction and dorsal scutum.</p>
                    <p>Epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 44–45</xref>). Copulatory atria containing openings oval. Lateral pockets present in front of epigastric furrow, anteroposteriorlly flattened. Sclerotized copulatory ducts clearly twisted in “figure 8” adjacent to cylindal spermathecae, then extending between atria to approximately the area of the lateral pockets.</p>
                    <p>Number of spines on legs. Tibia I pv 3–4, rv 3–4; metatarsus I pv 2, rv 2; tibia II pv 0, rv 2; metatarsus II pv 0–2, rv 2.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->Coloration in alcohol and pilosity. Carapace dark brown to black; cephalic part covered with white and fine setae; thoracic part covered with white setae; lateral surface of carapace above coxae I and II densely fringed with white setae; white setae roughly forming white diagonal band from above coxa IV to upper dorsum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 41–42</xref>). Chelicera dark brown. Endite, labium and sternum brownish orange, weakly tinged with black. Coxae and trochanters I and II white; coxa and trochanter III black, trochanter with yellow venter; coxa and trochanter IV pale yellow with lateral gray stripes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 43</xref>). Abdomen gray, covered with fine setae; two spots behind two white partial transverse bands present dorsally in anterior part of abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 41–42</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 33–40.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne macrognatha</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male. <bold>33</bold> Body in dorsal view <bold>34</bold> body in lateral view <bold>35</bold> endites, labium, coxae and trochanters in ventral view <bold>36</bold> left chelicera in ventral view <bold>37</bold> left fang in retrolateral view <bold>38</bold> left palp in ventral view <bold>39</bold> left palp in retrolateral view <bold>40</bold> left palpal tibia in dorsal view. (Scales. Figs <bold>33–37</bold>: 1 mm; <bold>38–40</bold>: 0.25 mm).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-299-001-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 41–45.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne macrognatha</tp:taxon-name></italic>, female. <bold>41</bold> Body in dorsal view <bold>42</bold> body in lateral view <bold>43</bold> endites, labium, coxae and trochanters in ventral view <bold>44</bold> internal structure of epigyne in ventral view <bold>45</bold> internal structure of epigyne in dorsal view. (Scales. Figs <bold>41–43</bold>: 1 mm; <bold>44–45</bold>: 0.1 mm)</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-299-001-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <!--PageBreak-->
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>The specimens from Flores are slightly different from the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne macrognatha</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Java in the cheliceral teeth. The third prolateral tooth counted from the apex of the Flores specimens is shorter than that of the holotype (which has both the third and fourth teeth elongate). Although the number and size of cheliceral teeth is variable, generally corresponding to body size, the short apical third prolateral tooth seems to be a stable character within our specimens collected from Flores regardless of body size. However, we regard the Flores specimens as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne macrognatha</tp:taxon-name></italic> on the basis of many other morphological similarities. To understand geographical variation of the species, a phylogenetic study based on molecular analysis is needed in the future.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology">
                    <title>Biology.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne macrognatha</tp:taxon-name></italic> is an arboreal species, and very common and abundant in eastern Flores.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Java, Flores.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Myrmarachne</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">melanocephala</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Myrmarachne_melanocephala</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>MacLeay, 1839</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 46</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">–58</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne melanocephala</tp:taxon-name><comment> MacLeay, 1839: 11, pl. 1, fig. 4; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Galiano 1969</xref>: 146; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Edwards and Benjamin 2009</xref>: 5, figs. 1A–H, 2A–D, 3A–D, 4A–E, 5A–D.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Mymecia melanocephala</tp:taxon-name><comment> Walckenaer, 1841: 462.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Salticus contractus</tp:taxon-name><comment> Karsch, 1880: 396.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Salticus providens</tp:taxon-name><comment> Peckham &amp; Peckham, 1892: 34.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne providens</tp:taxon-name><comment>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Simon 1901</xref>: 500.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne ramosa</tp:taxon-name><comment> Badcock, 1918: 303, fig. 8; Edmunds and Prószyński 2003: 301, figs. 8–21.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne albicrurata</tp:taxon-name><comment> Badcock, 1918: 306, fig. 9a.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne lateralis</tp:taxon-name><comment> Badcock, 1918: 310, figs. 9b–c.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Non-type material examined">
                    <title>Non-type material examined.</title>
                    <p>1 male and 2 females. Mego [=<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°40’S, 122°2’E</named-content>], Sikka, Flores, East Nusa Tenggara Prov., INDONESIA, 16.X.2012, T. Yamasaki leg.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Slender, light to dark brown species with relatively long pedicel. Males distinguished from other species by pedicel, which is as long as ALE–PLE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 46</xref>); further distinguished from species having long pedicel such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne assimilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Banks, 1930 (cf. figs 7, 13 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Banks 1930</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne cornuta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Badcock, 1918 (cf. figs 30–35 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Edmunds and Prószyński 2003</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne plataleoides</tp:taxon-name></italic> (O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1869) (cf. figs 1–7 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Edmunds and Prószyński 2003</xref>) by shape and dentition of chelicera (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 49</xref>). Females distinguished from others species by long pedicel as in males (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 54</xref>); further distinguished from species having long pedicel such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne assimilis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne cornuta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne glavisi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Prószyński &amp; Deeleman-Reinhold, 2010 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne plataleoides</tp:taxon-name></italic> by markings on abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 54</xref>) and structure of epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 57–58</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Measurements (male/female).</title>
                    <p>Carapace length 2.13/2.18–2.37, width 1.15/1.10–1.18. Chelicera length 1.22. ALE–PLE 0.82/0.77–0.83; ALE–PME 0.40/0.36–0.38. <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->Width of eye row I 1.03/1.03–1.12; II 0.97/1.00–1.08; III 1.13/1.15–1.20. Eye size: AME 0.33/0.33–0.35; ALE 0.18/0.16–0.17; PME 0.06/0.05; PLE 0.19/0.19.</p>
                    <p><bold>Male</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 46–53</xref>). Cephalic part almost flat dorsally, higher than thoracic part; thoracic part swollen dorsally; strongly incised laterally between cephalic and thoracic part (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 46–47</xref>). Chelicera shorter than carapace, bearing eleven prolateral and seven retrolateral teeth on its venter; fang weakly sinuous, without distinct tooth-like apophysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 49–50</xref>). Pedicel relatively long (0.50 mm). Abdomen elongate-oval; two dorsal scuta strongly incised laterally between them (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 46–47</xref>).</p>
                    <p>With palp in dorsal and ventral views, cymbium oval, without distinct spines on its apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 51</xref>). Tegulum round, with C-shaped ejaculatory duct in its distal retrolateral part (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 51</xref>). Embolus forming two round coils; ventral coil much narrower than basal coil, and basal coil slightly narrower than venter of cymbium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 51</xref>). RTA strongly curved and tip spiraled, with well-developed flange (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 52–53</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Number of spines on legs. Femur I pd 1, rd 0; tibia I pv 4, rv 4; metatarsus I pv 2, rv 2; tibia II pv 0, rv 2; metatarsus II pv 2, rv 2.</p>
                    <p>Coloration in alcohol and pilosity. Cephalic part dark brown, covered with white setae; thoracic part light brown, sparsely covered with white setae; lateral surface above coxa II densely fringed with white setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 46–47</xref>). Chelicera dark brown. Endite and labium brownish orange, tinged with black, especially labium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 48</xref>). Sternum brownish orange (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 48</xref>). Coxae and trochanters I, II and IV white, IV with lateral black stripes; coxa and trochanter III black except venter of trochanter light brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 48</xref>). Abdomen covered with fine setae; anterior dorsal scutum grayish pale brown, and posterior dorsal scutum black; white transeverse band between scuta running diagonally from lateral to ventral area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 46–47</xref>).</p>
                    <p><bold>Female</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 54–58</xref>). Carapace strongly incised laterally behind PLE; cephalic part almost flat dorsally, slightly higher than thoracic part; thoracic part swollen dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 54–55</xref>). Chelicera bearing five prolateral and six retrolateral teeth on its venter. Pedicel relatively long (0. 58–0.83 mm). Abdomen elongate-oval, dorsal scuta inconspicuous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 54–55</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 57–58</xref>). Copulatory atria laterally-oriented oval. Lateral pockets present in front of epigastric furrow, rather widely separated. Sclerotized copulatory ducts from “figure 8” adjacent to ovoid spermathecae, then extending between atria to approximate vicinity of widely separated lateral pockets.</p>
                    <p>Number of spines on legs. Tibia I pv 4, rv 4–5; metatarsus I pv 2, rv 2; tibia II pv 1–3, rv 2–3; metatarsus II pv 2, pv 2.</p>
                    <p>Coloration in alcohol and pilosity. Cephalic part black, covered with sparse white setae dorsally; thoracic part light to dark brown, sparsely covered with white setae; lateral surface of carapace above coxa II white, densely fringed with white setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 54–55</xref>). Chelicera light brown. Endite, labium and sternum brownish orange, weakly tinged with black laterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 56</xref>). Coxae and trochanters similar to those of males, except venter of coxa III also light brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 56</xref>). Abdomen covered with white and fine setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 54–55</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 46–53.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne melanocephala</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male. <bold>46</bold> Body in dorsal view <bold>47</bold> body in lateral view <bold>48</bold> endites, labium, coxae and trochanters in ventral view <bold>49</bold> left chelicera in ventral view <bold>50</bold> left fang in retrolateral view <bold>51</bold> left palp in ventral view <bold>52</bold> left palp in retrolateral view <bold>53</bold> left palpal tibia in dorsal view. (Scales. Figs <bold>46–50</bold>: 1 mm; <bold>51–53</bold>: 0.25 mm).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-299-001-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 54–58.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne melanocephala</tp:taxon-name></italic>, female. <bold>54</bold> Body in dorsal view <bold>55</bold> body in lateral view <bold>56</bold> endites, labium, coxae and trochanters in ventral view <bold>57</bold> internal structure of epigyne in ventral view <bold>58</bold> internal structure of epigyne in dorsal view. (Scales. Figs <bold>54–56</bold>: 1 mm; <bold>57–58</bold>: 0.1 mm)</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-299-001-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p><!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne melanocephala</tp:taxon-name></italic> are very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne glavisi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a long-pedicled species, in males (cf. figs 117, 119–120 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Prószyński and Deeleman-Reinhold 2010</xref>). However, the females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne melanocephala</tp:taxon-name></italic> are distinguishable from the females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne glavisi</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the structure of the epigyne (cf. figs 125–126 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Prószyński and Deeleman-Reinhold 2010</xref>). We here consider <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne melanocephala</tp:taxon-name></italic> different from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne glavisi</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However, the taxonomic status of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne glavisi</tp:taxon-name></italic> should be reviewed by a detailed comparison between the type materials of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne glavisi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne melanocephala</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the future.</p>
                    <p>The male specimen examined in the present study has relatively short chelicera compared with specimens from other areas. The male chelicera varies in the length depending on the body size within a species. The female specimens examined here agree with the description of <!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrmarachne melanocephala</tp:taxon-name></italic> and specimens from other areas, in particular the gray abdomen with transverse median black band is typical of populations throughout Southeast Asia, but lighter in color than the mostly black topotypical specimens from India. This seems to be only regional color variation.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology">
                    <title>Biology.</title>
                    <p>The specimens were collected from plantation areas.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Widely distributed in South and Southeast Asia.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We would like to express our deep gratitude to Prof. Seiki Yamane (Kagoshima University, Japan), Dr. Sadaharu Morinaka (Kawaguchi-shi, Japan), Mr. I Ketut Ginarsa (Bali, Indonesia), Prof. Dahermi (Andalas University, Indonesia), Dr. Henny Herwina (Andalas University, Indonesia) and Mr. Rijal Satria (Kagoshima University, Japan) for arranging the field trip to Flores, and to Ms. Marika Källsen (NRM, Sweden) for offering the type material to us. This work was supported by the JSPS International Training Program, Kagoshima University (Leader: Prof. Eizi Suzuki).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Badcock</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1918</year>) <article-title>Ant-like spiders from Malaya, collected by the Annandale-Robinson Expedition, 1901–2.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London</source> <volume>1917</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>-<lpage>321</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Banks</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1930</year>) <article-title>Ant-like spiders of the genus <italic>Myrmarachne</italic> from the Philippines.</article-title> <source>Psyche</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>-<lpage>218</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/1930/97165" xlink:type="simple">10.1155/1930/97165</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceccarelli</surname> <given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>New species of ant-mimicking jumping spiders of the genus <italic>Myrmarachne</italic> MacLeay, 1839 (Araneae: Salticidae) from north Queensland, Australia.</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Entomology</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>-<lpage>255</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1440-6055.2010.00756.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1440-6055.2010.00756.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Edmunds</surname> <given-names>M &amp; Prószyński J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>On a collection of <italic>Myrmarachne</italic> species (Araneae: Salticidae) from peninsular Malaya. Bulletin of the British Arachnological Society 12: 297–323.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname> <given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname> <given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A first look at the phylogeny of the Myrmarachninae, with rediscovery and redescription of the type species of <italic>Myrmarachne</italic> (Araneae: Salticidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2309</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Galiano</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>) <article-title>Salticidae (Araneae) formiciformes. VII. El género <italic>Myrmarachne</italic> Mac Leay, 1839, en America.</article-title> <source>Revista del Museo argentino Ciencias naturales Bernardino Rivadavia (Entomologia)</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>148</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Sunda to Sahul: Trans-Wallacean distribution of recent salticid genera (Araneae: Salticidae).</article-title> <source>Peckhamia</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Karsch</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1880</year>) <article-title>Arachnologische Blätter (Decas I).</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift für die gesammten Naturwissenschaften</source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>409</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1879</year>) <article-title>Die Arachniden Australiens.</article-title> <source>Nürnberg</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1045</fpage>-<lpage>1156</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>MacLeay</surname> <given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1839</year>) <article-title>On some new forms of Arachnida.</article-title> <source>Annals of Natural History</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Monk</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Fretes</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reksodiharjo-Lilley</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>The ecology of Nusa Tenggara and Maluku.</source> <publisher-name>Periplus Editions</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc>, <lpage>966</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickard-Cambridge</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1869</year>) <article-title>Descriptions and sketches of some new species of Araneida, with characters of a new genus.</article-title> <source>The Annals and magazine of natural history including zoology, botany, and geology</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>52</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Peckham</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peckham</surname> <given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1892</year>) <article-title>Ant-like spiders of the family Attidae.</article-title> <source>Occasional Papers of the Natural History Society of Wisconsin</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>83</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname> <given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <source>The World Spider Catalog, version 13.0. American Museum of Natural History, New York. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://research.amnh.org/iz/spiders/catalog/" xlink:type="simple">http://research.amnh.org/iz/spiders/catalog/</ext-link> (accessed 31 August, 2012).</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Prószyński</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <source>Monograph of the Salticidae (Araneae) of the World. Museum and Institute of Zoology, Polish Academy of Sciences, Warszaw. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.peckhamia.com/salticidae/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.peckhamia.com/salticidae/</ext-link> (accessed 31 August, 2012).</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Prószyński</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deeleman-Reinhold</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Description of some Salticidae (Araneae) from the Malay Archipelago. I. Salticidae of the Lesser Sunda Islands, with comments on related species.</article-title> <source>Arthropoda Selecta</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roewer</surname> <given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1954</year>) <source>Katalog der Araneae, vol II (B). Institute Royal des Sciences Naturelles de Belgique, Bruxelles, 927–1751.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1901</year>) <source>Histoire naturelle des araignées, 2. Roret, Paris, 381–668.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorell</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1877</year>) <article-title>Studi sui Ragni Malesi e Papuani. I. Ragni di Selebes raccolti nel 1874 dal Dott. O. Beccari.</article-title> <source>Annali del Museo Civico di Storia naturale di Genova</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>-<lpage>634</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorell</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1894</year>) <source>Förteckning öfver arachnider från Java och närgrändsande öar, insamlade af Carl Aurivillius; jemte beskrifningar å några sydasiatiska och sydamerikanska spindlar. Bihang Till Kongl Svenska Vetenskaps-Akademiens Handlingar 20: 1−63.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>van der</surname> <given-names>Geer A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyras</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Vos</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dermitzakis</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Evolution of Island Mammals: Adaptaion and Extinction of Placental Mammals on Islands. Blackwell Publishing Ltd., 479 pp.</source> doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/9781444323986" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/9781444323986</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Walckenaer</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1841</year>) <source>Histoire naturelle des Insects. <italic>Aptères</italic> 2, Paris, 549 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanless</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>A revision of the spider genera <italic>Belippo</italic> and <italic>Myrmarachne</italic> (Araneae: Salticidae) in the Ethiopian region.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British Museum of Natural History (Zoology)</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>139</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamasaki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Redescription of two Bornean species of the genus <italic>Myrmarachne</italic> (Araneae: Salticidae).</article-title> <source>Acta Arachnologica</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2476/asjaa.59.63" xlink:type="simple">10.2476/asjaa.59.63</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamasaki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Taxonomy of the genus <italic>Myrmarachne</italic> of Sulawesi, based on the Thorell’s types and additional specimens (Araneae: Salticidae). Annali del Museo Civico di Stria Naturale “G.</article-title> <source>Doria”</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>-<lpage>180</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>