<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.113.1402</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Chemosymbiotic bivalves from the mud volcanoes of the Gulf of Cadiz, NE Atlantic, with descriptions of new species of Solemyidae, Lucinidae and Vesicomyidae</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Olive</surname>
                        <given-names>Graham</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:9330128A-D9C0-47E1-991E-438D9B8D4148</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
                        <given-names>Clara F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:D54DAA7A-BE73-4E37-B5A1-760517AF1BA5</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Cunha</surname>
                        <given-names>Marina R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:553A98B5-0AE0-424F-9ED5-EC50F129519C</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>BioSyB, National Museum of Wales, Cathays Park, Cardiff, CF10 3NP, Wales, UK
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>CESAM, Departamento de Biologia, Universidade de Aveiro, Campus Universitário de Santiago, 3810–193 Aveiro, Portugal
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Graham Oliver (<email xlink:type="simple">graham.oliver@museumwales.ac.uk</email>).
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Nathalie Yonow</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>28</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>113</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>38</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>18</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>2</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Graham Oliver, Clara F. Rodrigues, Marina R. Cunha</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:5ECAC0D4-083C-4223-AD2A-01810AA99BCD</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The chemosymbiotic bivalves collected from the mud volcanoes of the Gulf of Cadiz are reviewed. Of the thirteen species closely associated with chemosynthetic settings two <tp:taxon-name>Solemyidae</tp:taxon-name>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax gadirae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, one <tp:taxon-name>Lucinidae</tp:taxon-name>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, and one <tp:taxon-name>Vesicomyidae</tp:taxon-name>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon megadesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> are described and compared to close relatives of their respective families. The biodiversity and distribution of the chemosymbiotic bivalves in the Gulf of Cadiz are discussed and compared to the available information from other cold seeps in the Eastern Atlantic and Mediterranean. Although there is considerable similarity at the genus level between seep/mud volcano fields in the Eastern Atlantic and Mediterranean, there is little overlap at the species level. This indicates a high degree of endemism within chemosymbiotic bivalve assemblages.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Bivalvia</kwd>
                <kwd>chemosymbiotic</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>Gulf of Cadiz</kwd>
                <!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Chemosynthetic bivalves are prominent constituents of the fauna of cold seeps and are represented in that setting by five families: <tp:taxon-name>Solemyidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Lucinidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Vesicomyidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Thyasiridae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Mytilidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">Sibuet and Olu 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">Sibuet and Olu-Le Roy 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Sahling et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Levin 2005</xref>). Recently the presence of bacteria in the gills in species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nucinella</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Huxleyia</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been demonstrated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Oliver and Taylor </xref>in preparation), confirming the previous inclusion of the <tp:taxon-name>Manzanellidae</tp:taxon-name> in this group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Cosel and Bouchet 2008</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>The occurrence of chemosymbiotic bivalves in the extensive mud volcano fields of the Gulf of Cadiz was first reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Pinheiro et al. (2003)</xref>. Then followed a series of more in-depth studies: on polychaete commensals of solemyid hosts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Ravara et al. 2007</xref>); on the distribution and taxonomy of <tp:taxon-name>Thyasiridae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Rodrigues et al. 2008</xref>); on the phylogenetic relationships of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus mauritanicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cosel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Génio et al. 2008</xref>) and on the molecular characterization of chemosymbiotic endosymbionts of solemyids, lucinids, thyasirids and mytilids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Rodrigues et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Rodrigues and Duperron 2011</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>Chemosynthetic bivalve faunas have been discovered elsewhere in the Eastern Atlantic, notably off tropical West Africa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Olu-Le Roy et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Cosel and Olu 2009</xref>) and in the eastern Mediterranean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Salas and Woodside 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Olu-Le Roy et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Carlier et al. 2010</xref>). For the <tp:taxon-name>Vesicomyidae</tp:taxon-name>, at the species level, these faunas are considered disparate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Krylova and Sahling 2010</xref>). Conversely studies on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus</tp:taxon-name></italic> suggest that the species occurring in the Gulf of Cadiz is not only found along the West African margin but is amphi-Atlantic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Génio et al. 2008</xref>). The biogeographic patterns within these faunas are currently unresolved and require further taxonomic characterization, which this paper begins to address.
            </p>
            <p>This paper intends to provide the taxonomic basis for the chemosynthetic bivalves in the Gulf of Cadiz and includes the description of two new species of <tp:taxon-name>Solemyidae</tp:taxon-name>, one new species of <tp:taxon-name>Lucinidae</tp:taxon-name> and one new species of <tp:taxon-name>Vesicomyidae</tp:taxon-name>. Notes on the biogeography of these taxa in the Atlantic are given with special emphasis on the relationships between the Eastern Mediterranean, Gulf of Cadiz and West Africa.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title>
            <sec sec-type="Study area"><title>Study area.</title>
                <p>The Gulf of Cadiz is located in the NE Atlantic Ocean between 34°N and 37°15'N and 6°W to 9°45'W. It is enclosed by the southern Iberian and northern Moroccan margins, west of Gibraltar Strait. The geological history of the Gulf of Cadiz is intimately related to plate tectonic interaction between Southern Eurasia and North Africa and is driven by two major mechanisms: a) subduction associated with the westward emplacement of the Gibraltar Arc and formation of the Gulf of Cadiz accretionary wedge, probably not active at present and b) oblique lithosphere collision<!--PageBreak--> between Iberia and Nubia, active at present and causing active thrusting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">Zitellini et al. 2009</xref>). It is now well established that the whole area is under compressive deformation and that mud volcanism and processes associated with the escape of hydrocarbon-rich fluids sustain a broad diversity of chemosynthetic assemblages. This extensive area encompasses over forty mud volcanoes (here after as MV), at depths ranging from 200 to 4000m (confirmed by coring) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Mazurenko et al. 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Pinheiro et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Magalhães 2007</xref>), and active methane seepage has been documented on several locations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Kenyon et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Gardner 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Niemann et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">Stadnitskaia et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Hensen et al. 2007</xref>). Biological samples were available from 30 sites but for this study only thirteen MVs and one structure (PDE) yielded chemosymbiotic bivalves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).
                </p>
                <p>In the shallow Moroccan margin the El Arraiche field encompasses Renard Ridge (including Pen Duick Escarpment), Vernadsky Ridge and several mud volcanoes (e.g. <!--PageBreak-->Al Idrisi, Mercator, Fíuza, Gemini, Kidd MVs) located at depths from 200 to approximately 600m depth: The proximity to the euphotic zone and to the African coast adds to the great productivity observed in the area. Dead cold-water scleractinean coral reefs, carbonate crusts and exposed carbonate chimneys characterize the Renard and Vernadsky Ridges. Carbonate crusts, rock blocks and clasts are often found in the craters of the shallow mud volcanoes where mild seepage activity has been recorded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">Van Rensbergen et al. 2005</xref>). Mercator MV, one of the shallowest mud volcanoes differs significantly from the other mud volcanoes by the high chloride enrichment of its pore water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">Van Rensbergen et al. 2005</xref>). The top of Mercator MV shows patches of disturbed sediments from which gas venting is occasionally observed. Solitary corals (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Caryophyllia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.), accompanied by <tp:taxon-name>Cidaridae</tp:taxon-name> echinoids and <tp:taxon-name>Onuphidae</tp:taxon-name> polychaetes (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Hyalinoecia</tp:taxon-name></italic>) are the most conspicuous organisms seen during video surveys of the Mercator MV crater.
                </p>
                <p>The western Moroccan field comprises several mud volcanoes (e.g. Meknès, Student, Yuma, Ginsburg, Jesus Baraza, Darwin MVs) at intermediate depths (700–1200m) located along an extensive province of carbonate and mostly dead cold-water coral mounds. The widespread presence of authigenic carbonates and also extensive <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neptunea</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus</tp:taxon-name></italic> graveyards (usually within the crater of the mud volcanoes) suggest that this was a very active seepage area in the past. Darwin MV differs from the others in this area because its crater is completely covered by large carbonate slabs and crusts. The fissures among slabs and depressions with scattered crust are filled with abundant shell ash and occasionally small clumps of living <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus mauritanicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cosel, 2002. Meknès MV is the southernmost Moroccan mud volcano rising isolated among an extensive field of small coral mounds. The crater is formed by stiff, sometimes heavily disturbed, green mud breccia with scattered clasts and a striking large number of empty shells of the gastropod <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neptunea</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Except for a few <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paromola</tp:taxon-name></italic> individuals, living megafauna is rarely sighted in the crater
                </p>
                <p>The deep-water field (1300–4000m), mostly within the Portuguese margin includes several mud volcanoes (e.g. Captain Arutyunov, Carlos Ribeiro, Bonjardim and Porto MVs) that are aligned along major crustal strike–slip faults associated with the African-Eurasian plate boundary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Duarte et al. 2005</xref>). Gas hydrates were recovered from these mud volcanoes and the methane concentrations yield the highest records from the Gulf of Cadiz (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Kenyonet al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Akhmetzhanov et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2008</xref>). Video surveys of these deeper mud volcanoes often show conspicuous siboglinid fields (e.g. Porto MV) in the active craters and exuberant sponge and gorgonian patches at the crater rim and upper flank (e.g. Carlos Ribeiro MV).
                </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Sampling"><title>Sampling.</title>
                <p>Samples were collected between 2002 and 2006 during TTR (Training Through Research) 12, TTR 14, TTR15 and TTR16 cruises onboard RV Prof. Logachev and MSM.01-03 cruise onboard RV Maria S. Merian (IFM–GEOMAR). The material was collected using TV-assisted grabs or USNEL box-corers. Occasionally faunal specimens were also recovered from Reineck box-corer, multiple corer or lander samples that were carried out for different purposes. Whenever possible the specimens were sorted onboard and preserved in 70 or 96% ethanol (the latter preserved for molecular analysis).<!--PageBreak--></p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Deposition of samples"><title>Deposition of samples.</title>
                <p>The majority of specimens are deposited in the Biological Research Collection of the Department of Biology, University of Aveiro but the holotype; some paratypes and selected specimens are deposited in the National Museum of Wales.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Institutional abbreviations"><title>Institutional abbreviations.</title>
                <p><abbrev>DBUA<def><p>Department of Biology, University of Aveiro (Biological Research Collection)</p></def></abbrev>; <abbrev>IFM–GEOMAR<def><p>Institut für Meereskunde - Forschungszentrum für marine Geowissenschaften</p></def></abbrev>; <abbrev>IOC–UNESCO<def><p>Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission – United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization</p></def></abbrev>; <abbrev>NMW.Z<def><p>National Museum of Wales, Cardiff, Great Britain</p></def></abbrev>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Measurements"><title>Measurements.</title>
                <p>All measurements were made using Sylvac™ vernier calipers accurate to 0.01mm but are given to the nearest tenth.</p>
                <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 1.</label>
                    <caption><p>Map of the study area (Gulf of Cadiz) and location of sampling sites. <bold>squares with numbers</bold>, mud volcanoes with chemosymbiotic bivalves: <bold>full black circles</bold>, mud volcanoes visited during the study but bivalves not found: <bold>grey circles</bold>: mud volcanoes and other structures not visited during the study. <bold>Bon</bold>, Bonjardim MV; <bold>CA</bold>, Captain Arutyunov MV; <bold>CR</bold>, Carlos Ribeiro MV; <bold>Dar</bold>, Darwin MV; <bold>Gem</bold>, Gemini MV; <bold>Gin</bold>, Ginsburg; <bold>JB</bold>, Jesus Baraza MV; <bold>Kid</bold>, Kidd MV; <bold>Mek</bold>, Mèknes MV; <bold>Mer</bold>, Mercator MV; <bold>PDE</bold>, Pen Duick Escarpment; <bold>Por</bold>, Porto MV; <bold>Sag</bold>, Sagres MV; <bold>Yum</bold>, Yuma MV. The numbers inside the squares indicate the presence of the following species. <bold>1</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax gadirae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>2</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrasma elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>3</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>4</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>5</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinaxinus sentosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>6</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon megadesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>7</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. indet. <bold>8</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Christineconcha</tp:taxon-name></italic> cf. <italic>regab</italic> <bold>9</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus mauritanicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>10</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Idas</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. <bold>11</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Laubiericoncha chuni</tp:taxon-name></italic> (empty shells only) <bold>12</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callogonia cyrili</tp:taxon-name></italic> (empty shells only) <bold>13</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pliocardia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. (empty shells only).</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-113-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics"><title>Systematics</title>
            <sec sec-type="Order Solemyoida"><title>Order <tp:taxon-name>Solemyoida</tp:taxon-name> Dall, 1889
Superfamily <tp:taxon-name>Solemyoidea</tp:taxon-name> Gray, 1840
Family <tp:taxon-name>Solemyidae</tp:taxon-name> Gray, 1840</title>
                <p>Solemyids are among the most ancient bivalves dating from the Paleozoic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Métivier and Cosel 1993</xref>). They are protobranch in organization and characterized by an elongate shell (up to 220mm) with a posteriorly situated toothless hinge. The thick brown periostracum is much larger than the calcified part of the valve and is folded inwards by the muscular mantle edge upon closing of the valves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Métivier and Cosel 1993</xref>).</p>
                <p><tp:taxon-name>Solemyidae</tp:taxon-name> taxonomy is complex. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">Taylor et al. (2008)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Kamenev (2009)</xref> recognized two extant genera, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic>, with a further four subgenera within <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya</tp:taxon-name></italic>, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrasma</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrosolemya</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemyarina</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zesolemya</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Solemyids, other than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> are generally found at continental shelf and upper-slope depths (0 to 600m), although Solemya (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrasma</tp:taxon-name></italic>) <italic>pervernicosa</italic> has been recorded at 1500m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Kamenev 2009</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> is generally restricted to deep-sea settings from ~400m on the continental slope to the deepest sites of the Japan Trench (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Neulinger et al. 2006</xref>). Shallow dwelling solemyids live in sediments with high organic matter content, often at reduced oxygen concentrations. Hydrogen sulphide is frequently present due to sulphate reduction coupled with organic matter degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Conway et al. 1992</xref>). In contrast, the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been recovered from cold seep locations (see review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">Sibuet and Olu 1998</xref>) and in sediments influenced by hydrothermal venting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Juniper et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Métivier and Cosel 1993</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> species are morphologically similar but molecular data suggests a degree of cryptic speciation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Neulinger et al. 2006</xref>).
                </p>
                <p>Superficially, all solemyids appear so similar that specimens discovered at various deep-sea sites might have been misclassified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see review by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">Sibuet and Olu 1998</xref>).
                </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Genus Solemya Lamarck, 1818"><title>Genus Solemya Lamarck, 1818</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <label>Subgenus</label>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subgenus">Petrasma</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Dall, 1908</tp:taxon-authority>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Totten, 1834
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Definition"><title>Definition.</title>
                        <p>As given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">Taylor et al. 2008</xref>. Ligament wholly internal, supported by a buttress and lacking posterior or lateral extensions.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Solemya</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subgenus"> (Petrasma) </tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:32A6013D-4378-462A-BABA-4AFC4D26FB1E</object-id>
                            <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Solemya_(Petrasma)_elarraichensis</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A–D</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype</italic>: one specimen, TTR14, stn AT528GR, El Arraiche field, Kidd MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°25.304'N, 06°43.972'W</named-content>, 489m, 03 August 2004, NMWZ.2010.4.1
                        </p>
                        <p><italic>Paratypes</italic>: ten specimens, same data as holotype, NMWZ.2010.4.2; seven specimens, TTR15, stn AT569GR, El Arraiche field, Mercator MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°17.917'N, 06°38.717'W</named-content>, 358m, 25 July 2007, DBUA.
                        </p>
                        <p><italic>Other material examined</italic>: eight juveniles specimens, same data as holotype; two specimens, TTR12, stn AT407GR, El Arraiche field, Pen Duick Escarpment, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°17.695'N, 06°47.082'W</named-content>, 560m, 15 July 2002; three specimens, TTR14, stn AT560B, El Arraiche field, Kidd MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°25.306'N, 06°43.976'W</named-content>, 498m, 8 August 2004; one specimen, TTR15, stn AT586GR, Western Moroccan field, Meknès MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°59.146'N, 07°04.380'W</named-content>, 701m, 28 July 2005; four specimens, TTR16, stn AT604GR, Western Moroccan field, Yuma MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°25.820'N, 07°06.330'W</named-content>, 1030m, 29 May 2006; two specimens, TTR16, stn AT607GR, Western Moroccan field, Ginsburg MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°22.677'N, 07°04.979'W</named-content>, 983m, 29 May 2006.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Measurements"><title>Measurements (in mm)</title>
            <table-wrap position="anchor">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Station</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior Length</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT528GR</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.8</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT528GR</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT528GR</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT528GR</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT528GR</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT528GR</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT528GR</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT528GR</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Shell</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>): to 35mm in length. Fragile. Equivalve. Inequilateral, beaks situated at 1/4 length of shell from posterior margin. Outline subcylindrical, compressed, length about 2.6 times height, slightly deeper towards the anterior, dorsal and ventral margins subparallel, anterior margin more broadly rounded than anterior, posterior dorsal margin projecting a little. Beaks indistinct, umbos sunken. Hinge teeth absent. Ligament primarily internal, supported by a prominent chondrophore that extends only slightly as a chondrophore ridge around the posterior adductor, lacking posterior and anterior extensions but a small roughly heart shaped area is present in front of the chondrophore and this is also visible externally just behind the beaks. Periostracum persistent and extending well beyond the shell margin, initially yellowish brown in colour but darkening with growth to a dark chestnut brown. Sculpture of weak radial ridges, 5–6 over the posterior and 10–12 over median and anterior. Adductor scars impressed, dorsal part of posterior scar angulate where bounded by chondrophore ridge, anterior adductor scar larger, spatulate in outline.
                        </p>
                        <p><italic>Anatomy</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3G</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>): The posterior siphonal opening is surrounded by a series of papillae: A single large dorsal papilla (dp) lies above two smaller but still large papillae (dmp) on the dorsal margin of the opening, below these is a short smooth section (sa) followed by a series of papillae increasing in size towards the ventral margin, there are 6 primary papillae (psp) on either side and a single ventral median papillae, between these on the inner side are smaller papillae (ssp); a pair of subsiphonal ridges (ssr) are present below the siphonal crown.
                        </p>
                        <p>The mantle edge is fused from the posterior siphon for half the length of the ventral margin where there is a large anterior pedal gape. The mantle edge surrounding the rear of the foot bears a few tabulate papillae (pgp). The anterior dorsal mantle edge is prominently papillate (dap) and there is a single papilla on the junction of the mantle edge anterior of the anterior adductor muscle (admp). The foot is very large with a broad oval sole, this fringed by large papillae, all equal in size. The ctenidium is large with numerous laminar filaments attached to a prominent gill axis. The palps are short, twisted and flattened with cup shaped terminations. The gut is present but difficult to examine due to its small dimensions but the hind gut and rectum were easily visible.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><italic>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</italic> is presently only known from the mud volcano fields in the Gulf of Cadiz, Eastern Atlantic. The majority of specimens have been taken from the El Arraiche field off the coast of Morocco in Kidd, Fíuza and Mercator MVs and the Pen Duick Escarpment at depths between 358–560m. A few specimens have been taken from the Western Moroccan field at the Meknès, Yuma, Ginsburg and Darwin MVs at the slightly deeper range of 700–1115m.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p><italic>elarraichensis</italic>, denoting the geographic origin of the type locality; the El Arraiche field.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>The form of the ligament, which is primarily internal, supported by a chondrophore and lacks any lateral or anterior extensions, confirms the placement of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrasma</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dall, 1908 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">Taylor et al. 2008</xref>). Some of the specimens carry an initial identification of “cf. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya togata</tp:taxon-name></italic>” as might be expected from the proximity to the Mediterranean but the ligament of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya s.s.</tp:taxon-name></italic> has prominent anterior extensions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>The subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrasma</tp:taxon-name></italic> is not known from the North-East Atlantic but is represented in the Western Atlantic by three species. Two species are known from near shore waters off the northeast coast of the USA: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) velum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Say, 1822) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->(Totten, 1834). The third, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Deshayes 1857</xref>) is known from the warm waters of Florida, Caribbean and S. America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Mikkelsen and Bieler 2008</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>We note that the curvature of the chondrophore and chondrophore ridge is circular in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) velum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3F</xref>) but angular in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A–D</xref>). Furthermore, the siphonal papillae of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) velum</tp:taxon-name></italic> are by comparison less in number and reduced in development (Morse 1913, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">Taylor et al. 2008</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Abbott (1974)</xref> following Morse (1913) noted that the siphon of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> differed markedly from that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) velum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, confirming that siphonal characters were important for distinguishing species. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the ventral-most dorsal marginal papillae are very large, and as big as the dorsal papilla, and much larger than any of the ventral papillae. This contrasts with the condition in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> where the ventral-most dorsal marginal papillae are smaller than the dorsal papilla and where the ventral papillae are fewer in number and distinctly increasing in size ventrally, with the ventral-most papillae equal in size to the dorsal marginal papillae. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Conway et al. (1992)</xref>, following Barnard (in Reid 1980) suggested that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> lacked a gut and this would be in contrast with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) velum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
                        </p>
                        <p>The character of the ligament and chondrophore are rather similar in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
                        </p>
                        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Abbott (1974)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Mikkelsen and Bieler (2008)</xref> note that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> lacks any perceptible chondrophore ridge and give this as the main characteristic separating <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) velum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and, therefore, also from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
                        </p>
                        <p>Ecologically <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) velum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are very different from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in that they are not associated with deep-water methane seeps. In contrast they are found in sublittoral or shallow shelf settings with high organic enrichment (Morse 1913 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Conway et al. 1992</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Mikkelsen and Bieler (2008)</xref> give a similar habitat for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Deshayes, 1857) noting its occurrence in mangrove channels and around sewage outfalls.
                        </p>
                        <p>Given the above differences in habitat and form we conclude that none of the Atlantic species is amphi-Atlantic, unlike <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) pervernicosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kuroda, 1948, which is considered to be amphi-Pacific by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Kamenev (2009)</xref>. If any of the Western Atlantic species were amphi-Atlantic it is unclear why, in the Eastern Atlantic, they should be absent from their typical settings (which are plentiful) and found only in deep water methane seeps.
                        </p>
                        <p>Other North Atlantic species referred to as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya grandis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Verrill and Bush, 1898 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya caribbaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> Vokes, 1970 are excluded here because both belong to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Abbott 1974</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>A solemyid living at a pockmark, at a depth of 1607m, has been reported from the Eastern Mediterranean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Rodrigues et al. 2011</xref>). Unfortunately the small, single specimen was damaged and its taxonomic affinities remain unclear.
                        </p>
                        <p>In conclusion, there are sufficient morphological and ecological grounds for considering the Gulf of Cadiz species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrasma</tp:taxon-name></italic> to be new to science<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->.
                        </p>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 2.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A–E</bold> from Kidd MV; <bold>A–B</bold> lateral and dorsal views of holotype <bold>C–D</bold> lateral and dorsal views of medium sized paratype <bold>E</bold> lateral view of small paratype. <bold>F</bold> paired valves from Pen Duick Escarpment <bold>G</bold> paired valves from Mercator MV <bold>H</bold> lateral view of specimen from Meknès MV <bold>I</bold> lateral view of shell from Yuma MV.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-113-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 3. A–F</label>
                            <caption><p>Internal views of ligament, scale bars = 5mm. <bold>A–D</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. from <bold>A</bold> Kidd MV <bold>B</bold> Pen Duick Escarpment <bold>C</bold> Mercator MV <bold>D</bold> Yuma MV. <bold>E</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya togata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, Mediterranean <bold>F</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) velum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, Rhode Island (from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">Taylor et al. 2009</xref>). c, chondrophore; cr chondrophore ridge; pa, posterior adductor scar; r, resilium. <bold>G</bold> posterior siphon of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. dp, dorsal papilla; dmp, dorsal marginal papillae; psp, primary siphonal papillae; sa, smooth area; ssp, secondary siphonal papillae; ssr, subsiphonal ridge; vp, ventral papilla.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-113-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 4. </label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., Pen Duick, stn. AT407GR, 560m. Anatomy. <bold>A</bold> whole animal viewed from left side <bold>B</bold> papillae on dorsal anterior mantle edge <bold>C</bold> single, large papilla in dorsal median position <bold>D</bold> posterior dorsal dissection showing rectum passing through heart <bold>E</bold> marginal papillae on foot <bold>F</bold> papillae on mantle edge surrounding pedal gape <bold>G</bold> palp. aa, anterior adductor muscle. ct, ctenidium. dap, dorsal anterior papillae. dmp, dorsal median papilla. f, foot. h, heart. k, kidney. me, mantle edge. pa, posterior adductor muscle. pgp, papillae surrounding pedal gape. pp, palp. r, rectum.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-113-001-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <label>Genus </label>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Acharax</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Dall, 1908</tp:taxon-authority>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species:</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya johnsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dall, 1891
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Definition"><title>Definition.</title>
                        <p>As given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">Taylor et al. 2008</xref>. Ligament external, as a high arched band.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                             <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Acharax</tp:taxon-name-part>
                             <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">gadirae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                             <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A2467D10-D03D-4271-9993-0C2A6CD22944</object-id>
                             <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Acharax_gadirae</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5–</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype</italic>: one specimen, TTR12, stn AT391GR, Western Moroccan field, Jesus Baraza MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°35.439'N, 07°12.264'W</named-content>, 1105m, 09 July 2002, NMWZ.2010.4.3.
                        </p>
                        <p><italic>Paratypes</italic>: one specimen, same data as holotype, DBUA; one shell, TTR 12, stn AT392G, deep-water field, Captain Arutyunov MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°39.658'N, 07°20.018'W</named-content>, 1320m, 9 July 2002, DBUA; one shell, TTR 16, stn AT607GR, Western Moroccan field, Ginsburg MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°22.677'N, 07°04.979'W</named-content>, 983m. 29 May 2006, NMWZ.2010.4.4.
                        </p>
                        <p><italic>Other material examined:</italic> one specimen, TTR16, stn AT602GR, El Arraiche field, Pen Duick Escarpment, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°17.693'N, 06°47.089'W</named-content>, 556m, 28 May 2006; one specimen, TTR16, stn AT604GR, Western Moroccan field, Yuma MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°25.820'N, 07°06.330'W</named-content>, 1030m, 29 May 2006; one specimen, TTR16, stn AT605GR, same locality, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°25.046'N, 07°05.450'W</named-content>, 975m, 29 May 2006; one specimen, TTR16, stn AT615GR, deep-water field, Carlos Ribeiro MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°47.238'N, 08°25.272'W</named-content>, 2200m, 31 May 2006; one specimen, TTR16, stn AT617K, same locality, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°47.246'N, 08°25.303'W</named-content>, 2230m, 31 May 2006; two specimens, MSM01.03, stn 145, deep-water field, Porto MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°33.773'N, 09°30.416'W</named-content>, 3902m, 3 June 2006.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Measurements"><title>Measurements (in mm)</title>
            <table-wrap position="anchor">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Station</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcified Shell Length</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcified Shell Height</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcified ShellPosterior Length</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actual length</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior Ribs/Posterior Ribs</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT391GR</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT391GR</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.0</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT392GR</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.0</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.0</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT607 GR</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.8</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.9</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9//4</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>) Calcified shell to 67mm in length, to 85mm including periostracal fringe. Robust. Equivalve. Inequilateral, beaks situated at 1/4 length of shell from posterior margin. Outline subcylindrical, compressed, calcified shell length about 3 times height, slightly deeper towards the anterior, dorsal and ventral margins subparallel, anterior margin more broadly rounded than anterior, posterior dorsal margin projecting a little. Including periostracal fringe, anterior appears greatly expanded compared with posterior. Beaks indistinct, umbos sunken. Hinge teeth absent. Ligament external, as a high arched band posterior of the beaks and supported by a thickened shell margin; an oval area of ligament is present immediately behind the beaks and visible internally, anterior of the beaks shell margins fused by periostracal material along entire dorsal margins. Periostracum persistent and extending well beyond the shell margin, initially yellowish brown in colour but darkening with growth to dark brown and black; periostracal frill thickened over ribs but entire. Sculpture of radial ridges, 4 closely spaced over the posterior; median area almost smooth with 2–3 low ribs; anterior with 8–9 deeply cut ribs. Adductor scars impressed, posterior scar subcircular, anterior adductor scar larger, spatulate in outline. Anterior inner shell margin scalloped corresponding to radial ribs.
                        </p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Posterior siphonal opening surrounded by a series of papillae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5E</xref>): A single large dorsal papilla (dp) lies above 2–3 pairs of slightly smaller papillae (dmp) on the dorsal margin of the opening, below these surrounding the opening is a series of approximately alternating large and small papillae with those most ventral the largest.
                        </p>
                        <p>The mantle edge is fused from the posterior siphon for half the length of the ventral margin where there is a large anterior pedal gape. The mantle edge surrounding the rear of the foot is papillate. The anterior dorsal mantle edge is prominently papillate <!--PageBreak-->(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5D</xref>). The foot is very large with a broad oval sole, the margin interdigitates between large and small blunt papillae. The ctenidium is large with numerous laminar filaments attached to a prominent gill axis. The palps are short, twisted and flattened with cup shaped terminations. The presence or absence of a gut could not be confirmed.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax gadirae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is presently only known from the mud volcano fields in the Gulf of Cadiz, Eastern Atlantic. The specimens have been taken from the Western Moroccan field at Yuma, Ginsburg and Jesus Baraza MVs, and from the deep-water field at Captain Arutyunov, Carlos Ribeiro and Porto MVs at depths between 975 to 3902m. A single specimen was recovered from the shallower El Arraiche field in Pen Duick Escarpment at 556m.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p><italic>gadirae</italic>, from the Phoenician “Gadir” the original name for Cadiz and meaning “walled fortification” and also the root of many Moroccan names such as Agadir. Named to indicate the widespread range across the Moroccan and Iberian margins.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> is recognizable from the large external ligament and the generic placement of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax gadirae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is confirmed.
                        </p>
                        <p>The genus is rare in the Atlantic Ocean unlike the situation in the Pacific where species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> are frequently recorded from chemosynthetic settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Neulinger et al. 2006</xref>). Only two species are known from the Atlantic. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax grandis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">Verrill and Bush 1898</xref>) is known only from the original material collected from depths between 548 and 2926m in the region of the New York Bight. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax caribbaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Vokes 1970</xref>) again is only recorded from the original material collected from a depth of 350m off Colombia in the Caribbean Sea. However, the genus is recorded in recent studies from both the Gulf of Mexico (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Carney 1994</xref>) and the Barbados prism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Olu et al. 1997</xref>) but the species are not identified.
                        </p>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax grandis</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax gadirae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax caribbaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> in being less inequilateral with the beaks distinctly more towards the mid-line. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax caribbaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax gadirae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax grandis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in having very few (4) anterior ribs compared with the 6–8 on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax grandis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and 8–9 on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax gadirae</tp:taxon-name></italic> of similar size. Unfortunately, there are no anatomical data for either <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax grandis</tp:taxon-name></italic> or <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax caribbaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, making a thorough comparison impractical.
                        </p>
                        <p>There are no given ecological data for either <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax grandis</tp:taxon-name></italic> or <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax caribbaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The type locality for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax grandis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, which is the region around the Hudson Shelf and Canyon, has no recorded seep or vent activity. In contrast the region around the type locality of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax caribbaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known for a variety of chemosynthetic settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Carney 1994</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <p>The bathymetric range of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the Gulf of Cadiz is large, 556–3902m and specimens have been taken at many mud volcanoes raising the possibility that more than one species is involved. Unfortunately the specimens from the abyssal sites are all small about 10mm or less making comparison with the large specimens from the bathyal sites inconclusive. The specimens from Carlos Ribeiro MV (2200m) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C–D</xref>) are prominently wedge shaped in outline compared with the specimen from Porto MV (3902m) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>). The latter is not dissimilar to those from Capt. Arutyunov MV (1325m) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6E</xref>) with the specimen from Pen Duick Escarpment (556m) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>) somewhat more elongate but not as wedge shaped as those from Carlos Ribeiro MV.
                        </p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->The specimens from the Capt Arutyunov MV are most problematic in that the siphonal opening appears to be devoid of any surrounding tentacles or papillae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6H</xref>). This does not appear to be a function of size as similar specimens from other sites have siphonal papillae. Should this observation be confirmed in further material it would be appropriate to describe this as a separate species. Comparing the siphonal papillae of specimens from Pen Duick Escarpment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6F</xref>) and Carlos Ribeiro MV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6G</xref>) indicates a more complex arrangement in the latter but, with so few specimens, this is inconclusive.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Superfamily Lucinoidea"><title>Superfamily <tp:taxon-name>Lucinoidea</tp:taxon-name> Fleming, 1828
Family <tp:taxon-name>Lucinidae</tp:taxon-name> Fleming, 1828</title>
                <p>The <tp:taxon-name>Lucinidae</tp:taxon-name> is, by far, the most disparate and species-rich family of chemosymbiotic bivalves and are thoroughly reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">Taylor and Glover (2006)</xref>. Although they occupy a wide range of habitats, they are relatively infrequent in deep-sea settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">Taylor and Glover 2009</xref>). Some species are associated with cold seeps and mud volcanoes, oxygen minimum zones and a single species is known from a hydrothermal vent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">Taylor and Glover 2006</xref>). Of most frequent occurrence in, but not exclusive to, deep-sea settings is the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Salas and Woodside 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Oliver and Holmes 2006a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Cosel 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Cosel and Bouchet 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Oliver and Holmes (2006a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Cosel (2006)</xref> both comment on the considerable variation in shell form observed in some species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma gagei</tp:taxon-name></italic> Oliver and Holmes, 2006a and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma myriamae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cosel, 2006 respectively. This contrasts with the relatively small morphological differences cited for the discrimination of other species, e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Salas and Woodside 2002</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma vestita</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Dautzenberg and Fischer 1906</xref> in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Cosel 2006</xref>). In the latter instances geographic isolation and habitat preferences have played a major role in the in the interpretation of the significance of morphological variation.
                </p>
                <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 5. A–F</label>
                    <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax gadirae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A</bold> Holotype, stn. AT391GR, Jesus Baraza MV <bold>B</bold> Paratype, stn. AT607GR, Ginsburg MV <bold>C</bold> interior view of posterior ligament, stn. AT392GR, Jesus Baraza MV <bold>D</bold> anterior dorsal mantle edge, st. AT391GR <bold>E</bold> posterior siphon, st AT391GR <bold>F</bold> foot, stn. AT391GR</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-113-001-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 6. </label>
                    <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax gadirae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A</bold> stn. AT602GR, Pen Duick Escarpment <bold>B</bold> stn. 145, Porto mud volcano <bold>C–D</bold> stns AT617GR &amp; AT61GR, Carlos Ribeiro mud volcano <bold>E</bold> stn. 199, Capt Arutyunov mud volcano. <bold>F–E</bold> posterior siphon <bold>F</bold> specimen A <bold>G</bold> specimen D <bold>H</bold> specimen E.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-113-001-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <label>Genus</label>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Lucinoma</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Dall, 1901</tp:taxon-authority>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucina filosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Stimpson, 1851</xref>
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Definition"><title>Definition.</title>
                        <p>As given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Oliver and Holmes (2006a)</xref>
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Lucinoma</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">asapheus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E684B2EE-7C97-4FE9-9445-9B00CFE0259B</object-id>
                            <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Lucinoma_asapheus</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype</italic>; one complete specimen, live collected, TTR 15, stn AT569GR, El Arraiche field, Mercator MV. <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°17.917'N, 06°38.717'W</named-content>, 358m, 25 July 2005, NMWZ.2010.4.5.
                        </p>
                        <p><italic>Paratypes</italic>; five specimens, as holotype, NMWZ.2010.4.6.<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Measurements"><title>Measurements (in mm)</title>
            <table-wrap position="anchor">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Width</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior scar length</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior scar angle</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lunule width</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17°</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.7</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.0</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16°</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.8</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18°</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.7</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15°</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). Shell to 34 mm in length. Solid. Equivalve. Equilateral. Tumidity variable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7G, H</xref>) but mostly rather compressed. Umbos low, beaks pointing forward. Outline lenticular; posterior dorsal margin almost straight, sloping gently; posterior margin curved but less so than anterior; anterior dorsal margin short, a little concave. Escutcheon narrow, edges slightly raised, extending the length of the posterior dorsal margin; three-quarters filled by ligament, remainder smooth. Lunule distinct, width dependant on tumidity of shell; edges raised, sharp. Sculpture of numerous, low but erect, thin, concentric lamellae; between lamellae are weak concentric lines. Ligament external as a prominent, raised, arched band. Set on a narrow nymph. Hinge weak; two small cardinal teeth in each valve, RV anterior and LV posterior weakly bifid; anterior lateral protuberance distinct to obscure. Pallial line entire. Anterior adductor scar greatly elongate, approximately 3/4 free from pallial line. Shell white, periostracum thin but persistent, straw coloured (all material collected has been stained in Rose Bengal, thus the pink tinge).
                        </p>
                        <p>The anatomy is essentially that described for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Allen (1958)</xref> and for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Salas and Woodside (2002)</xref>. The inhalant siphon is surrounded by numerous short tentacles and papillae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7I</xref>)
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Variation"><title>Variation.</title>
                        <p>The shell can be rather compressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7H</xref>) or tumid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7G</xref>) and this may be related to age rather than size as suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Oliver and Holmes (2006a)</xref> for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma gagei</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Arabian Sea. Some shells also show distortion with radial depressions developing abruptly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7E</xref>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Molecular data"><title>Molecular data.</title>
                        <p>Tissues were sent to Dr. John Taylor (NHM, London) for inclusion in his survey of <tp:taxon-name>Lucinidae</tp:taxon-name> and the 16S and CO1 genes were compared with those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The results although not entirely conclusive indicate that the two populations are not conspecific. More recently, John Taylor’s group has demonstrated that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are distinct (J. Taylor pers. comm).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Only found live at Mercator MV in the Gulf of Cadiz (358m).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p><italic>asapheus</italic> from <italic>asaphes</italic> Greek: meaning “indistinct” and “baffling”, referring to the lack of distinctive morphological characters and the consequent unsettling taxonomic issues.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>A morphometric analysis was done comparing the Gulf of Cadiz shells with those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> from numerous localities from around the British Isles. This analysis could not demonstrate any statistically valid differences in the outline, the relative size of the anterior adductor scar (aa l on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>) or the angle of divergence of this <!--PageBreak-->scar from the pallial line (aa d on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>). It should be noted that the Cadiz sample size was small and that conclusive probability results were unlikely. However, the variation in tumidity and irregularity of some of the Cadiz shells is not found in samples of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Anatomically <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are alike including the papillae that surround the inhalant aperture. Further evidence for the species level distinction between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> comes from the molecular data but here again the few specimens available curtails the analysis. Ecologically one might expect mud volcanoes and near shore sulphide enriched sediments to support different species. This argument was used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Salas and Woodside (2002)</xref> to support the distinction between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but they also listed some morphological differences and this has been supported by molecular data (J. Taylor pers comm). Some of these, namely the tumidity of the valves, the width of the lunule and the expression of the lateral teeth are found here to be variable and therefore not conclusive. Similar variability was recorded for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma gagei</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Oliver and Holmes 2006a</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma myriamae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Cosel 2006</xref>) suggesting that small morphological differences in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> shells, especially if observed between small samples, may not be reliable taxonomic characters. The papillation of the inhalant siphon does appear to be much less developed in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic> compared with that in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The angle of divergence of the anterior adductor scar also shows a difference with that in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic> having a mean value of ca. 25° and both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> a mean value of ca. 15°. Given that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> both inhabit mud volcano settings one might expect them to be conspecific. However, accepting the morphological differences given by Salas &amp; Woodside between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and that these also hold true for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> then the two must be considered distinct. This may be supported by the wide difference in depth range with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> coming from 358m in contrast to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic> from 1700–2030m.
                        </p>
                        <p>Other Eastern Atlantic species are <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma vestita</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Dautzenberg and Fischer 1906</xref>) from Cape Verde at 600m, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma atalantae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cosel, 2006 from Mauritania at c.2000m and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma myriamae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cosel, 2006 from the Angola margin at c.360m. Comparisons with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> are as follows. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma vestita</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a smaller species not exceeding 16mm in length, more rounded in outline and with a weak sculpture of poorly developed (often absent) comarginal lamellae. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma atalantae</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a distinctly longer and more steeply sloping anterior dorsal margin, a more angular posterior profile and irregular sculpture. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma myriamae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is much larger reaching over 50mm in length and has a distinct angular anterior profile; in this respect, it resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma saldanhae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Barnard, 1964 a species not considered by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Cosel (2006)</xref>.
                        </p>
                        <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 7. </label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. stn. AT569GR, Mercator MV. <bold>A–D</bold> Holotype, aa d, angle of divergence of anterior adductor scar. aa l, length of anterior adductor scar <bold>E</bold> an aberrant specimen <bold>F</bold> a small specimen <bold>G–H</bold> two specimens showing variation in tumidity <bold>I</bold> the inhalant siphon.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-113-001-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Family Thyasiridae"><title>Family <tp:taxon-name>Thyasiridae</tp:taxon-name> Dall, 1901</title>
                <p>The <tp:taxon-name>Thyasiridae</tp:taxon-name> of the Gulf of Cadiz were reported on by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Rodrigues et al. (2008)</xref> and of the seven species recognized only one was closely associated with active mud volcanoes, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name></italic> Rodrigues &amp; Oliver, 2008). Here we report upon an additional species to the Gulf of Cadiz from the Captain Arutyunov MV. Since the<!--PageBreak--> publication of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Rodrigues et al. (2008)</xref> thyasirids from the Eastern Mediterranean mud volcanoes and the REGAB site off West Africa have become available for study. These species will not be described here but are compared with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
                </p>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <label>Genus</label>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Spinaxinus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Oliver &amp; Holmes, 2006b</tp:taxon-authority>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinaxinus sentosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Oliver &amp; Holmes, 2006b
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Definition"><title>Definition.</title>
                        <p>As given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Oliver and Holmes (2006b)</xref>
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Spinaxinus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                             <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="cf.">cf.</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sentosus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Spinaxinus_sentosus</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Oliver &amp; Holmes, 2006b</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A–D</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>One live collected specimen, MSM01.03, Stn 190, deep-water field, Captain Arutyunov MV, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°39.665'N, 07°19.970'W</named-content>, 1322m, 28 April 2006, NMWZ.2010.4.7</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A–D</xref>). This specimen measures only 2.3 mm in length and is damaged. The outline agrees with that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinaxinus sentosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in being extended anteriorly with a long lunule depression and in the presence of a long but shallow posterior sulcus. These features are in contrast to the juveniles of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Rodrigues and Oliver 2008</xref>), which also occurs at similar depths and settings.
                        </p>
                        <p>The periostracal spines are typical of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinaxinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> but are not seen in this specimen. The periostracum is coarse and the vestiges of lamellae and projections can be seen on the extreme edges of the shell especially on the ventral margin.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>Although the identification is not conclusive the likelihood that this shell is a juvenile <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinaxinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is high and as such represents the first finding of this species in a non-anthropogenic setting. The proximity of the type locality (off northern Portugal) to the Cadiz mud volcanoes makes this supposition more reasonable.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Thyasira</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Thyasira_vulcolutre</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Rodrigues &amp; Oliver, 2008</tp:taxon-authority>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name></italic> belongs to a group of thyasirids with relatively large shells with weakly defined posterior sulci. It was concluded that it was most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira southwardae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Oliver and Holmes 2006b</xref>) from the Anyas Garden site. At that time no thyasirid material had been found at cold seep sites along the West African margin. Consequently, unlike the situation for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Cosel 2006</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Cosel and Olu 2008</xref>) no further biogeographic comparisons could be made. Recently we were able to examine a thyasirid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8E–F</xref>) from the REGAB site (courtesy of Karine Olu) and although it superficially <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name></italic> it significantly differs in having a minutely spicate periostracum (Oliver in prep).
                        </p>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira striata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sturany, 1896 has long been known from deep water in the eastern Mediterranean but was recently re-discovered at cold seep sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Olu-Le Roy et al. 2004</xref>). Small specimens resemble <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira flexuosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> but larger examples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8G–H</xref>) are very tumid with prominent lunule and deep posterior sulci quite unlike <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
                        </p>
                        <p>These new data suggest that those thyasirids closely associated with active cold seeps have restricted ranges within the eastern Atlantic/Mediterranean region.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Superfamily Glossoidea"><title>Superfamily <tp:taxon-name>Glossoidea</tp:taxon-name> Gray, 1847
Family <tp:taxon-name>Vesicomyidae</tp:taxon-name> Dall &amp; Simpson, 1901</title>
                <p>The family <tp:taxon-name>Vesicomyidae</tp:taxon-name> has become familiar as a group of large chemosymbiotic clams associated with hot vents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Boss and Turner 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">Tunnicliffe 1991</xref>) and cold seeps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">Turner 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Okutani and Métivier 1986</xref>) and exemplified by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calyptogena magnifica</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Boss and Turner 1980</xref>. Not all taxa are large and the smallest, such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vesicomya atlantica</tp:taxon-name></italic>, are probably not chemosymbiotic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Allen 2001</xref>). Despite their conspicuous presence in many reducing environments, the taxonomy of vesicomyids is far from being settled, at both the species and supraspecific levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Krylova and Sahling 2006</xref>). Different authors estimate that the family includes from 50 to more than 70 recent and fossil species and new species are constantly erected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Krylova and Sahling 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Krylova and Janssen 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Cosel and Olu 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Krylova et al. 2010</xref>). To date, fifteen chemosymbiotic species in the genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Waisiuconcha</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callogonia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wareniconcha</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Elenaconcha</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calyptogena</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Christineconcha</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Laubiericoncha</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Abyssogena</tp:taxon-name></italic> have been reported from the eastern Atlantic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Krylova and Sahling 2010</xref>).
                </p>
                <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 8.</label>
                    <caption><p><bold>A–D</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinaxinus cf. sentosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Oliver &amp; Holmes, 2006b. stn. 190, Captain Arutyunov MV. <bold>A</bold> digital image of right valve <bold>B</bold> SEM, periostracum on posterior margin <bold>C</bold> SEM, periostracum on anterior dorsal margin <bold>D</bold> SEM, periostracum on ventral margin. <bold>E–F</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., Regab pock mark <bold>E</bold> external of right valve <bold>F</bold> periostracum. <bold>G–H</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira striata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, Sturany, MEDINAUT, Eastern Mediterranean <bold>G</bold> external of right valve <bold>H</bold> oblique view showing posterior sulci.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-113-001-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <label>Genus</label>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Sturany, 1896</tp:taxon-authority>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon perplexum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sturany, 1896
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Definition"><title>Definition.</title>
                        <p>As given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas (2001)</xref>
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">megadesmus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:317BA11E-0B29-4396-8696-DEDCAF00B29F</object-id>
                            <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Isorropodon_megadesmus</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10C–D</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype</italic>: one complete specimen, live collected, MSM01.03, stn 218, deep-water field, Captain Arutyunov MV. <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°39.642'N, 07°20.049'W</named-content>, 1321m, 30 April 2006, NMWZ.2010.4.8<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->.
                        </p>
                        <p><italic>Paratypes</italic>: ten specimens, four shells and one valve, same data as holotype, NMWZ.2010.4.9.
                        </p>
                        <p><italic>Other material examined:</italic> over thirty decalcified juvenile specimens, MSM01.03, stn 218, deep-water field, Captain Arutyunov MV. <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°39.642'N, 07°20.049'W</named-content>, 1321m, 30 April 2006; one specimen, MSM01.03, stn 225, same locality, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°39.707'N, 07°20.020'W</named-content>, 1322m, 4 May 2006.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Measurements"><title>Measurements (in mm)</title>
            <table-wrap position="anchor">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TumidityOne valve (paired)</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ratio (L/T)</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 (4.6)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25 (6.5)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 (4.6)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (2.6)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (2.6)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85 (3.7)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">incomplete</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10C–D</xref>). To 15mm in length. Thin. Equivalve. Inequilateral, beaks in front of the midline. Compressed, length to tumidity ratio 2.3 to 2.5. Outline subovate, anterior rounded, posterior a little obliquely truncated; ventral curvature at its maximum well to the posterior of the mid line. Lunule indistinct, not depressed. Escutcheon narrow, deeply excavated but entirely occupied by ligament. Sculpture of dense concentric lines and irregular growth stops or wrinkles. Hinge plate prominent dominated by a long nymph supporting a very large external ligament; ligament rises well above the dorsal margin of the shell and extends posteriorly beyond the nymph to fill the escutcheon. Hinge teeth complex; RV with a single prominent anterior lateral tooth situated in front of the beak in the form of a narrow projecting peg with a flat or slightly excavated dorsal surface; below the beak is an arched laminar tooth its anterior end overlapping the lateral tooth, its posterior slopes steeply and ventrally and merges with a second ridge only noticeable by a weak notch mid way on this combined ridge. LV with a thin laminar posterior cardinal angled obliquely plus two combined cardinals in a horizontal orientation the posterior part larger than the anterior with a distinct notch between the two parts. Pallial line entire with a very small straightened section below the posterior adductor scar; adductor scars of about equal size; anterior pedal retractor scar deeply impressed, situated immediately in front of the hinge plate. Periostracum thin, persistent, glossy. Shell white.
                        </p>
                        <p>Mantle thin, mantle edge unfused except for short inhalant and exhalant siphonal apertures; inhalant aperture with many papillae increasing in size dorsally, exhalant with papillae of equal size. Foot with a distinct finger-like toe and poorly developed heel, pedal retractors prominent, the anterior attached in a deep impression close to the hinge. Anterior adductor muscle oval in cross-section, posterior adductor muscle subcircular, smaller than the anterior one. Ctenidia of a large, single (inner) demibranch, ascending part approximately one half the height of the outer, filaments fine tightly connected.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon megadesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is restricted to Captain Arutyunov MV (1321–1322m).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p><italic>megadesmus</italic> from the Greek <italic>mega</italic> meaning large and <italic>desma</italic> meaning bond; referring to the external ligament.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>The taxonomy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the Atlantic and Mediterranean is complex and potentially confused (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Cosel and Olu 2009</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas (2001)</xref> described two new species from the Eastern Atlantic, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon bigoti</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon curtum</tp:taxon-name></italic>. They transferred a third from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Kelliella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon elongatum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Allen 2001</xref>). In discussing, the Mediterranean, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon perplexum</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas (2001)</xref> stated that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> species are variable with regard to outline, tumidity and development of hinge teeth and this is illustrated in their figures 36–47 for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon perplexum</tp:taxon-name></italic>. They noted similarities in shell morphology between the Eastern Mediterranean species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon perplexum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and the West African <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon bigoti</tp:taxon-name></italic> but suggested that these taxa were isolated geographically and doubtfully could have gene flow between them. They further supported this argument by stating that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon perplexum</tp:taxon-name></italic> had not been found in the Western Mediterranean or Ibero-Moroccan Gulf. In 2009, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Cosel and Olu</xref> described another <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> from West Africa (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon atalantae</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and placed another vesicomyid in this genus (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon striatum</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">Thiele and Jaeckel 1931</xref>). Therefore, before the discovery of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the Gulf of Cadiz there were already five west African species and one from the eastern Mediterranean. With the discovery of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> at the Capt. Arutyunov MV the assertion made by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas (2001)</xref> on genetic isolation can be questioned, as there is the possibility of gene flow between the seeps in the Mediterranean and around the east African coast.
                        </p>
                        <p>In contrast to the variability given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas (2001)</xref> for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon perplexum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, all of the shells from station 218 examined here are constant with regard to features of outline, tumidity and hinge teeth. However, a single shell from station 180 is distinct, being inflated, having a distinct lunule, having a much smaller ligament and in the ventral margin being more convex. The shells from station 218 are distinct from all <!--PageBreak-->the shells of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon perplexum</tp:taxon-name></italic> figured by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas (2001)</xref> in having a much longer nymph with the posterior teeth reaching only about one third of the ligament as opposed to the half distance given for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon perplexum</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas (2001)</xref>. Furthermore, most of the shells illustrated by them have a more convex ventral margin than the shells from station 218. The single shell from station 180 shares more features with the Mediterranean shells in having the small ligament, convex ventral margin and being more inflated.
                        </p>
                        <p>The outline of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon bigoti</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from all of the above in the narrower anterior and distinct angulation of the ventral curve, but is has a short nymph similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon perplexum</tp:taxon-name></italic> and the shell from station 180.
                        </p>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon atalantae</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a more sunken lunule and more angular posterior profile than either of the Gulf of Cadiz taxa. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon curtum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cosel and Salas, 2001, from off Mauritania, is more circular in outline and <italic><tp:taxon-name>I striatum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thiele and Jaeckel, 1931 from off Angola, is a much larger and more elongate form.
                        </p>
                        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas (2001)</xref> reassigned <italic><tp:taxon-name>Kelliella elongata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Allen, 2001 to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Following examination of the type material in the Natural History Museum, London (BMNH 1998180) we conclude that it is not conspecific with any of the taxa discussed here. It is a small species not exceeding 2mm in any of the over 300 specimens listed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Allen (2001)</xref>. It is inflated with a distinct lunule but the demarcating line illustrated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Allen (2001)</xref> is not so apparent. The hinge of the right valve has three distinct teeth including a small posterior tooth (4b in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Allen 2001</xref>), which is not present in either of the species from the Cadiz mud volcanoes. Furthermore, the ligament is small and does not project as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon megadesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. From the ctenidial anatomy there is no indication that this species is chemosymbiotic. In addition to the morphological differences, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon elongatum</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been collected from a wide geographical range, wide bathymetric range and associated with the typical oligotrophic deep-sea bivalve assemblage (derived from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Allen 2008</xref>). It would appear that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon elongatum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, if a chemosymbiotic species is not confined to seep/vent settings but as stated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Allen (2001)</xref> it is absent from the European basin and it was not present in the samples taken in the Gulf of Cadiz away from the vicinity of the mud volcanoes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">Rodrigues 2009</xref>).
                        </p>
                        <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 9.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon megadesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. stn. 218, Captain Arutyunov MV. <bold>A</bold> large right valve, paratype <bold>B–D</bold> holotype, right valve external, left valve internal, right valve internal <bold>E</bold> small right valve, paratype <bold>F</bold> dorsal view, paratype <bold>G</bold> gross anatomy viewed after removal of right valve and mantle.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-113-001-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 10.</label>
                            <caption><p>Comparison between the hinge teeth of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. indet. (<bold>A, B</bold>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon megadesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (<bold>C, D</bold>).</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-113-001-g0010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp indet</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10A–B</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>One complete specimen, live collected, MSM01.03, stn 180, deep-water field, Captain Arutyunov MV. <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°39.740'N, 07°19.960'W</named-content>, 1323m, 27 April 2006, NMWZ.2010.4.10.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Measurements"><title>Measurements.</title>
                        <p>6.4mm (L) × 5.3mm (H) × 3.6mm (T)</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10A–B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>). 6.4 mm in length. Thin. Equivalve. Inequilateral, beaks in front of the midline. Inflated, length to tumidity ratio = 1.8. Outline subovate, anterior bluntly rounded, posterior a little obliquely truncated; ventral curvature at its maximum more or less at the midline. Lunule indistinct, slightly depressed. E<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->scutcheon narrow, deeply excavated. Sculpture of dense, concentric, fine lines and few irregular growth stops. Hinge plate narrow, nymph supporting an external ligament; ligament scarcely rises above the dorsal margin of the shell and extends posteriorly to half the length of the escutcheon. Hinge teeth complex; RV with a single prominent anterior lateral tooth situated in front of the beak in the form of a narrow projecting peg with a flat or slightly excavated dorsal surface; below the beak is weakly arched laminar tooth its anterior end overlapping the lateral tooth, its posterior slopes steeply and ventrally and merges with a second ridge only noticeable by a weak notch mid way on this combined ridge. LV with a thin laminar posterior cardinal angled obliquely plus two combined cardinals in a horizontal orientation the posterior part only slightly larger than the anterior with a distinct notch between the two parts. Pallial line entire with a very small straightened section below the posterior adductor scar; adductor scars of about equal size; anterior pedal retractor scar deeply impressed, situated immediately in front of the hinge plate. Periostracum thin, persistent, glossy. Shell white
                        </p>
                        <p>Mantle thin, mantle edge unfused except for short inhalant and exhalant siphonal apertures; inhalant aperture with few papillae increasing in size dorsally, the latter as short tentacles, exhalant with papillae of equal size. Foot with a blunt finger-like toe and poorly developed heel, pedal retractors prominent, the anterior attached in a deep impression close to the hinge. Anterior adductor muscle pyriform in cross-section, posterior adductor muscle subcircular, smaller than the anterior one. Ctenidia of a large, single (inner) demibranch, filling the majority of the mantle cavity, ascending part approximately one half the height of the outer, filaments fine tightly connected.</p>
                        <p>The numerous crystalline growths seen on and between the filaments are believed to be natural and not an artifact of preservation.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp indetis restricted to Captain Arutyunov MV (1323m).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>As discussed above for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon megadesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
                        </p>
                        <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 11.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. indet., stn. 180 Captain Arutyunov MV. <bold>A–D</bold> External and internal views of right and left valves <bold>E</bold> dorsal view <bold>F</bold> gross anatomy viewed after removal of right valve and mantle <bold>G</bold> Excised ctenidium with crystalline artifacts.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-113-001-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Ecological Discussion"><title>Ecological Discussion</title>
            <sec sec-type="Symbiosis"><title>Symbiosis.</title>
              <p>Twelve bivalve species have been found in close association with chemosynthetic settings in the Gulf of Cadiz (this paper; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Génio et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Rodrigues et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Rodrigues et al. 2010</xref>) with a thirteenth, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callogonia cyrili</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cosel and Salas probable but not proven (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas 2001</xref>). The trophic status of these <tp:taxon-name>Solemyidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Lucinidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Thyasiridae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Vesicomyidae</tp:taxon-name> species has been confirmed by their gross anatomical features (e.g. gills for thyasirids, reduced gut for solemyids) and, in some cases, also by stable isotope analysis and/or molecular analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Rodrigues et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Rodrigues and Duperron 2011</xref>). The δ13C values for solemyids (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax gadirae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrasma</tp:taxon-name></italic>) <italic>elarraichensis</italic>), lucinid (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and thyasirid (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name></italic>) bivalves were found to be in line with data for other bivalves known to host thiotrophic symbionts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Fisher 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Carlier et al. 2010</xref>). On the other hand, δ13C and δ34S values for the bathymodiolid species (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus mauritanicus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) <!--PageBreak-->were compatible with the predominance of methanotrophy. Phylogenetic analysis of bacterial 16S rRNA gene sequences demonstrated that most bacteria were related to known sulfide-oxidizing endosymbionts found in other deep-sea chemosynthetic environments, with the co-occurrence of methane-oxidizing symbionts in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens. The molecular results confirmed the thiotrophic nutrition for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax gadirae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name></italic> and a dual symbiosis for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus mauritanicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Rodrigues et al. 2010</xref>). Nutrition of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon megadesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was not yet confirmed by either isotopic or molecular analyses but other studies suggest that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon perplexum</tp:taxon-name></italic> contain sulphur-oxidizing bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Olu-Le Roy et al. 2004</xref>), a phylotype also present in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinaxinus sentosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Oliver and Holmes 2006b</xref>).
                </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Distribution patterns"><title>Distribution patterns.</title>
                <p>The Gulf of Cadiz mud volcano field is comprised of over thirty seeps of various activity and spread over a bathymetric range of 200–4000m. Of the 25 mud volcanoes sampled, 13 have chemosymbiotic species, which indicates their importance in the structure of the seep assemblages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Most of the thirteen, chemosymbiotic, species found in the Gulf of Cadiz are restricted to one or two mud volcanoes. This patchy distribution can result from physical or physiological constraints such as depth, distance and fluid flow rates. They were more frequent in the shallower mud volcanoes (200–1500m) but were especially diverse in Captain Arutyunov MV where five different species co-occur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Some taxa are confined to single mud volcanoes whereas others are more widespread.
                </p>
                <p>The family most frequently encountered in the chemosynthesis-based assemblages of the mud volcanoes from the Gulf of Cadiz, is the <tp:taxon-name>Solemyidae</tp:taxon-name>. The family is represented by two genera, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrasma</tp:taxon-name></italic>) with a shallower distribution (358–1030m) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> with a deeper distribution (556–3902m) but co-occurring at intermediate depths in the Western Moroccan field. Co-occurrence of these genera has not been reported elsewhere and may be explained by the apparent absence of the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrasma</tp:taxon-name></italic> from seep settings preferring reducing sediments and low oxygen conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Kamenev 2009</xref>).
                </p>
                <p>This is the first record of this family in cold seeps from the North-east Atlantic, although <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya</tp:taxon-name></italic>) <italic>togata</italic> is well known from shallow settings such as sea-grass beds in the Mediterranean. Why this species has not or been unable to colonize the shallow mud volcanoes is unknown. In contrast, the Pacific <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (S.) tagiri</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Okutani et al. (2003)</xref> is thought to be associated with seep settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Kamenev 2009</xref>) suggesting that habitat is not linked to phylogeny.
                </p>
                <p>Unlike <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrasma</tp:taxon-name></italic>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> species are consistently associated with seep or vent settings and some species such as the Pacific <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax johnsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> have extensive bathymetric ranges from 100 to over 5000m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Kamenev 2009</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> species are all rather morphologically similar and given the molecular data given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Neulinger et al. (2006)</xref> it may be found that there are more species than currently recognized. This is suggested here by the morphological differences in the posterior aperture between the shallow and deeper specimens. Some <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens (from Yuma, Ginsburg and Jesus Baraza MVs) host commensal polychaetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Ravara et al. 2007</xref>).
                </p>
                <p>In contrast to the solemyids, the lucinid <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has only been collected at Mercator MV, although video observations revealed presence of lucinids in other<!--PageBreak--> mud volcanoes from the Spanish field (MR Cunha, pers. comm.). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is very similar morphologically to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Eastern Mediterranean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Salas and Woodside 2002</xref>) and both are almost identical with the widespread shelf species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> that is abundant in the North-east Atlantic. Our preliminary molecular data separated <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and further work on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic> confirms that it is also distinct from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (J Taylor, pers comm.). A more detailed study including a wider data set from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic> should elucidate the relationship between it and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The three species so far mentioned are similar but quite distinct from the much larger, deeper water SE Atlantic species such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma myriamae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma saldanhae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and the Indo-Pacific species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma gagei</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma yoshidai</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Oliver and Holmes 2006a</xref>). It is therefore plausible that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus, L. kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma borealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are a clade, but we cannot ascertain their sequence of appearance. Are the mud volcano species independently evolved from shallow water ancestors or are they descended from a common seep dwelling stock?
                </p>
                <p>The thyasirid <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name></italic> was only found in the deep-water mud volcano field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Rodrigues et al. 2008</xref>). Despite the high number of thyasirid species present in the Gulf of Cadiz (eight) only one <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name></italic> is strictly associated with active mud volcanoes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Rodrigues et al. 2008</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinaxinus sentosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been discovered in the organic cargo of a sunken ship in the Atlantic Ocean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Oliver and Holmes 2006b</xref>) and is reported here for the first time associated to a cold seep site. Other chemosymbiotic thyasirids (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) were found associated with <tp:taxon-name>Siboglinidae</tp:taxon-name> fields from the Hakon-Moseby MV (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Gebruk et al. 2003</xref>) and from the eastern Mediterranean mud volcanoes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Olu-Le Roy et al. 2004</xref>).
                </p>
                <p>Small vesicomyids including <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon megadesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon sp.</tp:taxon-name></italic> were very abundant in Captain Arutyunov MV.The species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon perplexum</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known only from the Eastern Mediterranean (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), and was shown to harbour sulphur-oxidizing bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Salas and Woodside 2002</xref>). During TTR17 (2008) a living specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calyptogena</tp:taxon-name></italic> was found for the first time in the Gulf of Cadiz. The specimen collected from Bonjardim has been identified as belonging to the species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Christineconcha regab</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cosel and Olu, 2009, recently found in the Regab region (E Krylova, pers. comm.). Other large vesicomyid shells but no living specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Laubiericoncha chuni</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">Thiele and Jaeckel 1931</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pliocardia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. were also collected at the same mud volcano. The vesicomyids <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calyptogena regab</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma chuni</tp:taxon-name></italic> dominate the faunal assemblages of Congo and Angola Basin cold seeps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Olu-Le Roy et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Cosel and Olu 2008</xref>).
                </p>
                <p>Bathymodioline mussels of the amphi-Atlantic species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus mauritanicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> were only found living in Darwin MV although extensive graveyards of mussel shell ash are also found in other mud volcanoes of the western Moroccan field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Génio et al. 2008</xref>). Although confirmed as chemosymbiotic, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus mauritanicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was first collected during a commercial trawl in the Mauritanian margin where no hydrocarbon seeps have yet been discovered. Nevertheless owing to the repeated appearance of other typical seep molluscs it is likely the existence of seepage in this region might be confirmed in the future (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Cosel 2002</xref>). Another small mytilid <italic><tp:taxon-name>Idas</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. was collected living in a small wood fall retrieved by the ROV Isis at Carlos Ribeiro MV during JC10. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Idas</tp:taxon-name></italic> <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->specimens are present in the mud volcanoes from the Eastern Mediterranean (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) and their symbioses have been studied in detail by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Duperron et al.(2008)</xref>.
                </p>
                <p>When discussing <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Cosel and Salas (2001)</xref> suggested that Mediterranean and SE Atlantic forms were unlikely to be the same species due to their geographic isolation. With the discovery of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the Gulf of Cadiz, this argument can be challenged. Here we review the distributions of all chemosymbiotic taxa found at seeps in the Eastern Atlantic/Eastern Mediterranean and consider the apparent levels of endemism. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> presents the known taxa and their occurrence in the four major seep fields, namely Eastern Mediterranean, Gulf of Cadiz, off Mauritania and the Gulf of Guinea.
                </p>
                <p>The Gulfs of Cadiz and Guinea are most diverse and almost equally so with 13 and 14 species respectively. The less sampled Mauritania basin has only 7 recorded species while the well studied Eastern Mediterranean has only 6 species. The number of species common to more than two fields is zero and the maximum number of shared species is two, that for the Gulfs of Cadiz and Guinea. These data suggest high levels of endemism within fields but where there is overlap, especially with the larger vesicomyids, that this occurs at deeper sites. The vesicomyids are the most diverse family but only one species has colonized the Eastern Mediterranean and they appear to be rare in the Gulf of Cadiz compared with the Gulf of Guinea. From a geological history perspective one can explain the poor diversity in the Eastern Mediterranean from the shorter period of time for colonization since the re-invasion of Atlantic waters post the hyper-saline event. At this time there is no evidence to indicate the origins of the Eastern Atlantic faunas, either by dispersal or local speciation. Molecular data from the species rich genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> may illuminate the relationships and sequence of speciation and we await the study in progress on the <tp:taxon-name>Vesicomyidae</tp:taxon-name> mentioned by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Cosel and Olu (2008)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">Warén and Bouchet (2009)</xref> in discussing seep gastropods stated that the West African fauna was quite distinct from that of the Gulf of Cadiz at both species and generic levels and suggested that the latter was of more recent origin via local radiation. At the generic level, these findings appear at odds with the bivalve data where there are strong similarities between the Gulfs of Guinea and Cadiz. The exceptions are <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma)</tp:taxon-name></italic>, which appears to have a NW Atlantic origin and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> species, where their origin may be local.
                </p>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">Warén and Bouchet (2009)</xref> further indicated strong affinities of the West African fauna with the Western Atlantic and Gulf of Mexico faunas. Relationships among the bivalves with the western Atlantic at the species level are few, if any; only with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus mauritanicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is there a suggestion of an amphi-Atlantic distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Génio et al. 2008</xref>). At the generic level there is considerable over-lap within the solemyids, lucinids and thyasirids but less so with the vesicomyids. This may be in part to the considerable number of new genera erected for eastern Atlantic taxa by (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Cosel and Olu (2008</xref>, 2009)<!--PageBreak-->.
                </p>
                <table-wrap position="float" orientation="portrait" id="T1">
                    <label>Table 1.</label>
                    <caption><p>Distribution of chemosymbiotic taxa known from seep/mud volcano fields in the Eastern Atlantic and Mediterranean.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table>
            	
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taxon</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">East.Mediterranean</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gulfof Cadiz</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MauritaniaBasin</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gulf ofGuinea</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="5"><tp:taxon-name>Solemyidae</tp:taxon-name></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax</tp:taxon-name></italic> indet.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acharax gadirae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Solemya (Petrasma) elarraichensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Solemyidae</tp:taxon-name> Eastern Med</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="5"><tp:taxon-name>Mytilidae</tp:taxon-name></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus mauritanicus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bathymodiolus aff. boomerang</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Idas modiolaeformis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Idas</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="5"><tp:taxon-name>Lucinidae</tp:taxon-name></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma asapheus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma kazani</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma atalantae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Lucinoma myriamae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Myrtea amorpha</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Graecina karinae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Joellina dosiniformis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="5"><tp:taxon-name>Thyasiridae</tp:taxon-name></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira vulcolutre</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira striata</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Thyasira</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Spinaxinus sentosus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="5"><tp:taxon-name>Vesicomyidae</tp:taxon-name></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon perplexum</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X?</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon megadesmus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon bigoti</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon curtum</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon striatum</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Isorropodon atalantae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Callogonia cyrili</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Callogonia mauritanica</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Callogonia valdiviae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Christineconcha regab</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X?</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wareniconcha guineensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Elenaconcha guiness</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Laubiericoncha chuni</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X?</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pliocardia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Abyssogena southwardae</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total( ) shared species</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1?) (0) (0)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1?) 13 (1) (2)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0) (1) 7 (2)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0) (1) (2) 14</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>Thanks are due to the co-chief-scientists Luís Pinheiro (Departamento de Geociências, Universidade de Aveiro) and Michael Ivanov (Moscow State University) for the invitation to participate in the TTR cruises (Training Through Research Programme, IOC–UNESCO), Henk de Haas (chief-scientist of the Microsystems 2007) and to Olaf Pfannkuche (chief-scientist of the MSM01-03. IFMGEOMAR).</p>
            <p>This research was partially supported by the HERMES project (European Commission’s Sixth Framework Programme under the priority “Sustainable Development, Global Change and Ecosystems”, EC contract GOCE–CT-2005-511234) and is a contribution to the project HERMIONE (European Commission’s Framework Seven Programme, contract number 226354).</p>
            <p>The second author was supported by a PhD grant (SFRH/BD/17085/2004) from Fundação para a Ciência e Tecnologia.</p>
            <p>We also wish to thank John Taylor (Natural History Museum, London) for his helpful discussion on many aspects of this paper and to Elena Krylova (P.P. Shirshov Institute of Oceanology) for information on the <tp:taxon-name>Vesicomyidae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<source> American Seashells; the marine Mollusca of the Atlantic and Pacific Coasts of North. America.</source> <publisher-name>Van Nostrand Reinhold</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, 663 pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmetzhanov</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><role>Eds</role> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Deep water cold seeps, sedimentary environments and ecosystems of the Black and Tyrrhenian Seas and the Gulf of Cadiz. Preliminary results of investigations during the TTR-15 cruise of RV Professor Logachev, June-August, 2005.</article-title> <source>IOC Technical Series</source>, <volume>72</volume>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmetzhanov</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><role>Eds</role> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Deep water depositional systems and cold seeps of the Western Mediterranean, Gulf of Cadiz and Norwegian continental margins. Preliminary results of investigations during the TTR-16 cruise of RV Professor Logachev, May-July, 2006.</article-title> <source>IOC Technical Series</source>, <volume>76</volume>: <lpage>58</lpage> pp + Annexes.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>)<article-title> On the basic form and adaptations to habitat in the Lucinacea (Eulamellibranchia).</article-title> <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B,</source> <volume>241</volume>:<fpage>421</fpage>-<lpage>484</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> The family Kelliellidae (Bivalvia: Heterodonta) from the deep Atlantic and its relationship with the family Vesicomyidae.</article-title> <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>131</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>226</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rstb.1958.0010" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1098/rstb.1958.0010</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Bivalvia of the Deep Atlantic.</article-title> <source>Malacologia</source> <volume>50</volume> (<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.2001.tb01315.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.1096-3642.2001.tb01315.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<article-title> Contributions to the knowledge of South African marine Mollusca. Part V. Lamellibranchiata.</article-title> <source>Annals of the South African Museum</source> <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>361</fpage>-<lpage>593</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Boss</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> The giant white clam from the Galapagos Rift, <italic>Calyptogena magnifica</italic> species novum.</article-title> <source>Malacologia</source> <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>-<lpage>194</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ritt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarrazin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clavier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Heterogeneous energetic pathway and carbon sources for deep eastern Mediterranean cold-seep communities.</article-title> <source>Marine Biology</source> <volume>157</volume> (<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2545</fpage>-<lpage>2565</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00227-010-1518-1" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1007/s00227-010-1518-1</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Carney</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Consideration of the oasis analogy for chemosynthetic communities at Gulf of Mexico hydrocarbon vents.</article-title> <source>Geo-Marine Letters</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howes</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDowell Capuzzo</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavanaugh</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Characterization and site description of <italic>Solemya borealis</italic> (Bivalvia: Solemyidae), another bivalve-bacteria symbiosis.</article-title> <source>Marine Biology</source> <volume>112</volume>:<fpage>601</fpage>-<lpage>613</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF00346178" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1007/BF00346178</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosel</surname><given-names>R von</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> A new species of bathymodioline mussel (Mollusca, Bivalvia, Mytilidae) from Mauritania (West Africa) with comments on the genus Bathymodiolus Kenk and Wilson, 1985.</article-title> <source>Zoosystema</source> <volume>24</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosel</surname><given-names>R von</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Taxonomy of tropical West African bivalves. VI. Remarks on Lucinidae (Mollusca: Bivalvia), with descriptions of six new genera and eight new species.</article-title> <source>Zoosystema</source> <volume>28</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>805</fpage>-<lpage>851</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosel</surname><given-names>R von</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Tropical deep-water lucinids (Mollusca: Bivalvia) from the Indo-Pacific: essentially unknown, but diverse and occasionally gigantic. In: Héros V, Cowie R, Bouchet P (Eds) Tropical Deep Sea Benthos, volume 25.</article-title> <source>Mémoires du Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle</source> <volume>196</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosel</surname><given-names>R von</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Vesicomyidae (Mollusca: Bivalvia) of the genera <italic>Vesicomya</italic>, <italic>Waisiuconcha</italic>, <italic>Isorropodon</italic> and <italic>Callogonia</italic> in the eastern Atlantic and Mediterranean.</article-title> <source>Sarsia</source> <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>333</fpage>-<lpage>366</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosel</surname><given-names>R von</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> A new genus and new species of Vesicomyidae (Mollusca, Bivalvia) from cold seeps on the Barbados accretionary prism, with comments on other species.</article-title> <source>Zoosystema</source> <volume>30</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>924</fpage>-<lpage>944</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosel</surname><given-names>R von</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Large Vesicomyidae (Mollusca: Bivalvia) from cold seeps in the Gulf of Guinea off the coasts of Gabon, Congo and northern Angola.</article-title> <source>Deep Sea Research Part II: Topical Studies in Oceanography</source> <volume>56</volume>(<issue>23</issue>): <fpage>2350</fpage>–<lpage>2379</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.dsr2.2009.04.016" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/j.dsr2.2009.04.016</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dall</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1891</year>)<article-title> On some new or interesting West American shells obtained from the dredgings of the U.S. Fish Commission steamer ‘Albatross’ in 1888, and from other sources.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the United States National Museum</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>191</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dautzenberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1906</year>)<article-title> Mollusques provenant des dragages effectués à l’ouest de l’Afrique pendant les campagnes scientifiques de S.A.S. le Prince de Monaco.</article-title> <source>Resultats des Campagnes scientifiques du Prince Albert I</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>125</lpage>, pls 1–5.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Deshayes</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1857</year>)<article-title> Note sur différents Mollusques de la Guadeloupe, Envoyés par M. Schramm.</article-title> <source>Journal de Conchyliologie</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matias</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terrinha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Interpretation of recent sedimentary and tectonic structures off SW Iberia from multibeam bathymetry, seismic reflection and experimental modelling.</article-title> <source>Geophysical Research Abstracts</source> <volume>7</volume>, 07867.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Duperron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorion</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibuet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaill</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Unexpected co-occurrence of six bacterial symbionts in the gills of the cold seep mussel <italic>Idas</italic> sp. (Bivalvia: Mytilidae).</article-title> <source>Environmental Microbiology</source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>433</fpage>-<lpage>445</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1462-2920.2007.01465.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.1462-2920.2007.01465.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> Chemoautotrophic and methanotrophic symbioses in marine invertebrates.</article-title> <source>Review Aquatic Science</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>-<lpage>436</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Mud volcanoes revealed and sampled on the Western Moroccan continental margin.</article-title> <source>Geophysical Research Letters</source> <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>-<lpage>342</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebruk</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krylova</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lein</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinogradov</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pimenov</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherkashev</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Methane seep community of the Haakon Mosby mud volcano (the Norwegian Sea): composition and trophic aspects.</article-title> <source>Sarsia</source> <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>394</fpage>-<lpage>403</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Génio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrijenhoek</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiel</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname><given-names>CTS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> New record of <italic>“Bathymodiolus” mauritanicus</italic> Cosel 2002 from the Gulf of Cadiz (NE Atlantic) mud volcanoes.</article-title> <source>Journal of Shellfish Research</source> <volume>27</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hensen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuzzo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hornibrook</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magalhães</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruckmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Sources of mud volcanoes fluids in the Gulf of Cadiz – indications for hydrothermal imprint.</article-title> <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>1232</fpage>-<lpage>1248</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Juniper</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tunnicliffe</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Southward</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Hydrothermal vents in turbidite sediments on a Northeast Pacific spreading centre: organisms and substratum at an ocean drilling site.</article-title> <source>Canadian Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>1792</fpage>-<lpage>1809</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamenev</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> North Pacific species of the genus <italic>Solemya</italic> Lamarck, 1818 (Bivalvia: Solemyidae), with notes on <italic>Acharax johnsoni</italic> (Dall, 1891).</article-title> <source>Malacologia</source> <volume>51</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>-<lpage>261</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmetzhanov</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmanov</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><role>Eds</role> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Multidisciplinary study of geological processes on the North East Atlantic and Western Mediterranean Sea Margins. Preliminary results of geological and geophysical investigations during the TTR-9 cruise of R/V Professor Logachev June-July, 1999.</article-title> <source>Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission (IOC) Technical Series</source> <volume>56</volume>, <publisher-name>UNESCO</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <lpage>102</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmetzhanov</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmanov</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><role>Eds</role> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Interdisciplinary approaches to geoscience on the North East Atlantic Margin and Mid-Atlantic Ridge. Preliminary results of investigations during the TTR-10 cruise of RV Professor Logachev. July-August, 2000.</article-title> <source>IOC Technical Series</source> <volume>60</volume>, <publisher-name>UNESCO</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <lpage>104</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmetzhanov</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmanov</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><role>Eds</role> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Geologica processes in the Mediterranean and Black Seas and North East Atlantic. Preliminary results of investigations during the TTR-11 cruise of RV Professor Logachev July-September, 2001.</article-title> <source>IOC Technical Series</source> <volume>62</volume>, <publisher-name>UNESCO</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <lpage>89</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmetzhanov</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmanov</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><role>Eds</role> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Interdisciplinary geoscience research on the Northeast Atlantic Margin, Mediterranean Sea and Mid-Atlantic Ridge. Preliminary results of investigations during the TTR-12 cruise of RV Professor Logachev June-August, 2002.</article-title> <source>IOC Technical Series</source> <volume>67</volume>, <publisher-name>UNESCO</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <lpage>112</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmetzhanov</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmanov</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><role>Eds</role> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Interdisciplinary geoscience studies of the Gulf of Cadiz and Western Mediterranean basins. Preliminary results o investigations during the TTR-14 cruise of RV Professor Logachev July-September, 2004.</article-title> <source>IOC Technical Series</source> <volume>70</volume>, <publisher-name>UNESCO</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <lpage>115</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Krylova</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Vesicomyidae from Edison Seamount (South Western Pacific: Papua New Guinea: New Ireland fore-arc basin) (Bivalvia: Glossoidea).</article-title> <source>Archiv für Molluskenkunde</source> <volume>135</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>-<lpage>263</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Krylova</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahling</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Recent bivalve molluscs of the genus <italic>Calyptogena</italic> (Vesicomyidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of Molluscan Studies</source> <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>359</fpage>-<lpage>395</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/mollus/eyl022" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1093/mollus/eyl022</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Krylova</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahling</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Vesicomyidae (Bivalvia): Current taxonomy and distribution.</article-title> <source>Plos One</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <lpage>e9957</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0009957" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0009957</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Krylova</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahling</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> <italic>Abyssogena</italic>: a new genus of the family Vesicomyidae (Bivalvia) from deep-water vents and seeps.</article-title> <source>Journal of Molluscan Studies</source> <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>132</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1948</year>)<article-title> Two new gigantic species of <italic>Solemya</italic>.</article-title> <source>Venus</source> <volume>15</volume> (<issue>1–4</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/mollus/eyp052" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1093/mollus/eyp052</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Ecology of cold seep sediments interactions of fauna with flow chemistry and microbes.</article-title> <source>Oceanography and Marine Biology: An Annual Review</source> <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>46</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1201/9781420037449.ch1" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1201/9781420037449.ch1</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Magalhães</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> Authigenic carbonates and fluid escape structures in the Gulf of Cadiz.</source> PhD thesis, <publisher-name>Universidade de Aveiro</publisher-name>, <lpage>422</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazurenko</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soloviev</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belenkaya</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Mud volcano gas hydrates in the Gulf of Cadiz.</article-title> <source>Terra Nova</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>-<lpage>329</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-3121.2002.00428.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1046/j.1365-3121.2002.00428.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Métivier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosel R</surname><given-names>von</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> <italic>Acharax alinae</italic> n. sp. Solemyidae (Mollusca: Bivalvia) géante du bassin de Lau.</article-title> <source>Académie des Sciences (Paris), Comptes Rendu de Seances (3- Sciences de la Vie)</source> <volume>316</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>237</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B44"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikkelsen</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bieler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<source> Seashells of Southern Florida - Living Marine Mollusks of the Florida Keys and Adjacent Regions: Bivalves.</source> <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey</publisher-loc>, <lpage>503</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B45"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Neulinger</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahling</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Süling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imhoff</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Presence of two phylogenetically distinct groups in the deep-sea mussel <italic>Acharax</italic> (Mollusca: Bivalvia: Solemyidae).</article-title> <source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source> <volume>312</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>-<lpage>168</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3354/meps312161" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.3354/meps312161</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B46"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Niemann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hensen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omoregie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magalhães</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elvert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boetius</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Microbial methane turnover at mud volcanoes of the Gulf of Cadiz.</article-title> <source>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</source> <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>5336</fpage>-<lpage>5355</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2006.08.010" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/j.gca.2006.08.010</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B47"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Okutani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Métivier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of three new species of vesicomyid Bivalves collected by the Submersible Nautile from the Abyssal depths off Honshu, Japan.</article-title> <source>Venus</source> <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>-<lpage>160</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B48"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Okutani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> A new species of solemyid bivalve from near submarine fumaroles in Kagoshima Bay, Japan.</article-title> <source>Venus</source> <volume>62</volume> (<issue>3–4</issue>):<fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>96</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B49"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006a</year>)<article-title> A new species of <italic>Lucinoma</italic> (Bivalvia: Lucinoidea) from the oxygen minimum zone of the Oman Margin, Arabian Sea.</article-title> <source>Journal of Conchology</source> <volume>39</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B50"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006b</year>)<article-title> New species of Thyasiridae (Bivalvia) from chemosynthetic communities in the Atlantic Ocean.</article-title> <source>Journal of Conchology</source> <volume>39</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>183</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B51"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (submitted) <source>Bacterial chemosymbiosis in the Nucinellidae (Mollusca: Bivalvia) with descriptions of two new species.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B52"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Olu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lance</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibuet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiala-Médioni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Cold seeps communities as indicators of fluid expulsion patterns through mud volcanoes seaward of the Barbados accretionary prism.</article-title> <source>Deep-Sea Research I</source> <volume>44</volume> (<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>811</fpage>-<lpage>841</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0967-0637(96)00123-9" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/S0967-0637(96)00123-9</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B53"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Olu-Le Roy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibuet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiala-Médioni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gofas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariotti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foucher</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodside</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Cold seep communities in the deep eastern Mediterranean Sea: composition, symbiosis and spatial distribution on mud volcanoes.</article-title> <source>Deep-Sea Research I</source> <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>1915</fpage>-<lpage>1936</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.dsr.2004.07.004" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/j.dsr.2004.07.004</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B54"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Olu-Le Roy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caprais</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fifis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabri</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galeron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Budzinsky</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Menach</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khripounoff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ondreas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibuet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Cold-seep assemblages on a giant pockmark off West Africa: spatial patterns and environmental control.</article-title> <source>Marine Ecology</source> <volume>28</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>115</fpage>-<lpage>130</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1439-0485.2006.00145.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.1439-0485.2006.00145.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B55"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sautkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhamanov</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magalhães</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volkonskaya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somoza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamouni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Mud volcanoes in the Gulf of Cadiz: results from the TTR-10 cruise.</article-title> <source>Marine Geology</source> <volume>195</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>-<lpage>151</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-3227(02)00685-0" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/S0025-3227(02)00685-0</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B56"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> The occurrence of <italic>Natsushima bifurcata</italic> (Polychaeta: Nautiliniellidae) in <italic>Acharax</italic> hosts from mud volcanoes in the Gulf of Cadiz (south Iberian and north Moroccan Margins).</article-title> <source>Scientia Marina</source> <volume>71</volume>(<issue>1</issue>).</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B57"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Comunidades macrobentónicas dos vulcões de lama do Golfo de Cádis// Macrofaunal assemblages from mud volcanoes of the Gulf of Cadiz.</source> <publisher-name>Departamento de Biologia, Universidade de Aveiro</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Aveiro</publisher-loc>, <lpage>348</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B58"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duperron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Distinct symbiont lineages in three thyasirid species (Bivalvia: Thyasiridae) from the eastern Atlantic and Mediterranean sea.</article-title> <source>Naturwissenchaften,</source> <volume>98</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>281</fpage>-<lpage>287</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00114-011-0766-3" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1007/s00114-011-0766-3</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B59"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duperron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaudron</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> First documented record of a living solemyid bivalve in a pockmark of the Nile Deep-sea Fan (eastern Mediterranean Sea).</article-title> <source>Marine Biodiversity Records</source> <volume>4</volume>: <lpage>e10</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S175526721100008X" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1017/S175526721100008X</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B60"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Thyasiroidea (Mollusca: Bivalvia) from the mud volcanoes of the Gulf of Cadiz (NE Atlantic).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1752</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B61"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duperron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weightman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Chemosynthetic bacteria found in Bivalvia species from mud volcanoes of the Gulf of Cadiz.</article-title> <source>FEMS Microbial Ecology</source> <volume>73</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>486</fpage>-<lpage>499</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B62"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahling</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galkin</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salyuk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greinert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foerstel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piepenburg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suess</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Depth-related structure and ecological significance of cold-seep communities - a case study from the Sea of Okhotsk.</article-title> <source>Deep Sea Research I</source> <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>1391</fpage>-<lpage>1409</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.dsr.2003.08.004" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/j.dsr.2003.08.004</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B63"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Salas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodside</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> <italic>Lucinoma kazani</italic> n. sp. (Mollusca: Bivalvia): evidence of a living benthic community associated with a cold seep in the eastern Mediterranean Sea.</article-title> <source>Deep-Sea Research Part 1</source> <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>991</fpage>-<lpage>1005</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0967-0637(02)00010-9" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/S0967-0637(02)00010-9</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B64"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Say</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1822</year>)<article-title> An account of some of the marine shells of the United States.</article-title> <source>Journal of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>, <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>, <fpage>302</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B65"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibuet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> Biogeography, biodiversity and fluid dependence of deep-sea cold-seep communities at active and passive margins.</article-title> <source>Deep-Sea Research II</source> <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>517</fpage>-<lpage>567</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0967-0645(97)00074-X" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/S0967-0645(97)00074-X</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B66"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibuet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olu-Le Roy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Cold Seep Communities on Continental Margins: Structure and Quantitative Distribution Relative to Geological and Fluid Venting Patterns.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Weffer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Billett</surname> <given-names/></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebbeln</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jorgersen</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Weering</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Ocean Margin System</source>, <publisher-name>Springer Verlag</publisher-name>, <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B67"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stadnitskaia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blinova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreulen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Weering</surname><given-names>TCE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Molecular and carbon isotopic variability of hydrocarbon gases from mud volcanoes in the Gulf of Cadiz, NE Atlantic.</article-title> <source>Marine and Petroleum Geology</source> <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>281</fpage>-<lpage>296</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B68"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stimpson,</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1851</year>)<source> A revision of the synonymy of the testaceous mollusks of New England.</source> <publisher-name>Phillips, Sampson &amp; Company</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>, <lpage>56</lpage> pp, 2 pls.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B69"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturany</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1896</year>)<article-title> Mollusken I (Prosobranchier und Opisthobranchier, Scaphopoden; Lamellibranchier) gesammelt von S. M. Schiff “Pola” 1890–94.</article-title> <source>Denkschriften der mathematisch-naturwissenschaftlichen Klasse der Kaiserlichen Akademie der Wissenschaften</source>, Wien <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>, pls 1–2.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B70"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Lucinidae (Bivalvia) - the most diverse group of chemosymbiotic molluscs.</article-title> <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>148</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>421</fpage>-<lpage>438</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.2006.00261.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.1096-3642.2006.00261.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B71"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> New lucinid bivalves from hydrocarbon seeps of the Western Atlantic (Mollusca: Bivalvia: Lucinidae).</article-title> <source>Steenstrupia</source> <volume>30</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B72"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Ancient chemosynthetic bivalves: systematics of Solemyidae from eastern and southern Australia (Mollusca: Bivalvia). In: Davie PJF, Philips JA (Eds) Proceedings of the Thirteenth International Marine Biological Workshop, The Marine Fauna and Flora of Moreton Bay, Queensland.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the Queensland Museum - Nature</source> <volume>54</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>104</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B73"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaeckel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1931</year>)<article-title> Muscheln der deutschen Tiefsee-Expedition.</article-title> <source>Wissenschaften Ergbnisse der Deutschen Tiefsee-Expedition auf der Dampfer “Valdivia” 1898–1899,</source> <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>-<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B74"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Totten</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1834</year>)<article-title> Description of some new shells, belonging to the coast of New England American.</article-title> <source>Journal of Science and Arts</source> <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>366</fpage>-<lpage>369</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B75"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tunnicliffe</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> The biology of hydrothermal vents: ecology and evolution.</article-title> <source>Oceanography Marine Biology</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>407</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B76"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Notes on mollusks of deep-sea vents and reducing sediments.</article-title> <source>American Malacological Bulletin (Special Edition )</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B77"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Rensbergen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Depreiter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pannemans</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moerkerke</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Rooij</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsset</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhmanov</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blinova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rachidi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magalhães</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henriet</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> The El Arraiche mud volcano field at the Moroccan Atlantic slope, Gulf of Cadiz.</article-title> <source>Marine Geology</source> <volume>219</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.margeo.2005.04.007" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/j.margeo.2005.04.007</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B78"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Verrill</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1898</year>)<article-title> Revision of the deep-water Mollusca of the Atlantic coast of North America, with descriptions of new genera and species.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the United States National Museum</source> <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>775</fpage>-<lpage>901</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B79"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vokes</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> Two new species of deep water bivalves from the Caribbean Sea.</article-title> <source>Veliger</source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>357</fpage>-<lpage>361</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B80"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Warén</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> New gastropods from deep-sea hydrocarbon seeps off West Africa.</article-title> <source>Deep-Sea Research II</source> <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>2326</fpage>-<lpage>2349</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.dsr2.2009.04.013" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/j.dsr2.2009.04.013</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B81"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zitellini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gràcia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matias</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terrinha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abreu</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeAlteriis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henriet</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dañobeitia</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramella</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somoza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> The quest for the Africa-Eurasia plate boundary west of the Strait of Gibraltar.</article-title> <source>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</source> <volume>208</volume> (<issue>1–4</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.dsr2.2009.04.013" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1016/j.dsr2.2009.04.013</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>