<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.111.1345</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>The identity of the Neotropical stingless bee <italic>Frieseomelitta meadewaldoi</italic> (Cockerell, 1915) (Hymenoptera, Apidae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Oliveira</surname>
                        <given-names>Favízia Freitas de</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Urban</surname>
                        <given-names>Danúncia</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Engel</surname>
                        <given-names>Michael S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Laboratório de Bionomia, Biogeografia e Sistemática de Insetos (BIOSIS), Departamento de Zoologia, Instituto de Biologia, Universidade Federal da Bahia, Rua Barão de Jeremoabo, s/n, Campus Universitário de Ondina, Salvador, CEP 40170-115, Bahia, Brazil
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Departamento de Zoologia, Universidade Federal do Paraná, Centro Politécnico, Setor de Ciências Biológicas, Caixa Postal 19020, Curitiba, CEP 81531-990, Paraná, Brazil
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Division of Entomology, Natural History Museum, and Department of Ecology &amp; Evolutionary Biology, 1501 Crestline Drive – Suite 140, University of Kansas, Lawrence, Kansas 66049-2811, USA
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Favízia Freitas de Oliveira (<email xlink:type="simple">favosgyrl@gmail.com</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Michael Ohl</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>111</issue>
            <fpage>19</fpage>
            <lpage>31</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>8</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Favízia Freitas de Oliveira, Danúncia Urban, Michael S. Engel</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new study of a surviving syntype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cockerell, 1915, was undertaken and several widely employed names for Neotropical stingless bees recognized as junior synonyms. A lectotype is designated for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and the following new synonymies established: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona francoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Moure, 1946, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona (Frieseomelitta) freiremaiai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Moure, 1963. These nomenclatural matters are here settled and the species thoroughly characterized in advance of a forthcoming phylogenetic consideration of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta</tp:taxon-name></italic> von Ihering, 1912.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Apoidea</kwd>
                <kwd>Anthophila</kwd>
                <kwd>Apidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Apinae</kwd>
                <kwd>Meliponini</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Trigona</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Frieseomelitta</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta</tp:taxon-name></italic> von Ihering, 1912 is a genus of New World stingless bees (<tp:taxon-name>Apinae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Meliponini</tp:taxon-name>), with a wide geographic range occurring from southwestern Mexico (Sinaloa) to the southeast of Brazil (São Paulo), and can be found in forests, cerrado, <!--PageBreak-->caatinga, and mountainous regions, reaching an elevation of about 1600 m (Iguala, Guerrero, México). Species are moderately aggressive and nest in cavities in living or dead trees (dry), fence posts, &amp;c. In general they apparently are not well adapted to anthropogenic environments, with few records originating in urban areas, with the exception of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta trichocerata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Moure, 1988 which is quite common in Manaus, Brazil. Species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta</tp:taxon-name></italic> are popularly known as little black girls, lacemakers, zamboque, pitch, abreu, long legs, black marmalade, white marmalade, white wings, white girls, or ties nêgo.</p>
            <p>Nineteen species are presently recognized, although no formal revision has yet been published, and at least seven undescribed species are known (Oliveira et al. in prep.). The hitherto recognized species are <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta flavicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius, 1798), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta varia</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Lepeletier de Saint Fargeau, 1836); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta longipes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Smith, 1854); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta nigra</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Cresson, 1878); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta paupera</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Provancher, 1888); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta portoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Friese, 1900); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Friese, 1900); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta lehmanni</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Friese, 1901); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta silvestrii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Friese, 1902); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Cockerell, 1915); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta parastigma</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Cockerell, 1918); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta pura</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Cockerell, 1920); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta paranigra</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Schwarz, 1940); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta francoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Moure, 1946); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta dispar</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Moure, 1950); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta freiremaiai</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Moure, 1963); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta savannensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Roubik, 1980); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta trichocerata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta languida</tp:taxon-name></italic> Moure, 1989. Herein we attempt to clarify the taxonomic status of three of these names in advance of a phylogenetic study of the genus (Oliveira et al. in prep.).</p>
            <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Smith (1854)</xref> established the species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (today <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>), for a stingless bee from “Brazil (Pará)”. Later (Smith, 1863) redescribed the species based on a series of 10 individuals presented at the International Exhibition of 1862. On pages 499–500 of his work <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Smith (1863)</xref> states, “For the purpose of examination, when describing the species in the present paper, I was supplied with ten examples of each...” and so it is presumed (taking his statement at face value) that there was originally a series upon which he based his description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in 1863.</p>
            <p>More than a half century later, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Cockerell (1915)</xref> noted the incongruence of the two descriptions published by Smith under the name <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and after examining the 1854 type for the species, concluded that the 1854 and 1863 descriptions referred to different species altogether. Cockerell (op. cit.) therefore considered the specimen redescribed as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Smith (1863)</xref> to be a separate species from the one Smith described under this name in 1854. Accordingly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Cockerell (1915)</xref> proposed the name <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> as a replacement for the species described by Smith in 1863, selecting as epithet a patronym for Geoffroy Meade-Waldo (1884–1916). However, Cockerell never did find the specimens described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Smith (1863)</xref>.</p>
            <p>From 1915 until recently, most melittologists had interpreted <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> to be a junior synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> Friese, 1900, principally by the fact that many individuals of the latter species were found among specimens from Smith’s collection. Given that the 1863 type series was apparently missing or unrecognized, there was no basis upon which to contradict this anecdotal conclusion. While the 1863 description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> could be applied in part to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic>, there are sufficient discrepancies to suspect that the specimens described by Smith in 1863 were not necessarily conspecific with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic>. One of the significant differences between Smith’s 1854 <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <!--PageBreak-->(as noted, now a valid species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and his “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>” of 1863 (clearly a species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta</tp:taxon-name></italic>) is the coloration of the face. For example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Smith (1854)</xref> notes “Head black; the clypeus, a triangular spot above, the face on each side, the scape in front, and the mandibles, yellow” and “wings testaceous” (1854: 411), while in 1863 he states, “Pale ferruginous, with the head and thorax black above; clypeus, mandibles and antennae pale ferruginous; also a narrow pale line at the inner orbits of the eyes” and “alis hyalinis” (1863: 510). The latter account aptly describes the face and wings of two other potentially conspecific species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona francoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Moure, 1946 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona freiremaiai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Moure, 1963 (e.g., Figs 4, 5, 7, 8, 10) (<italic>vide infra</italic>). All of these specimens also have identical metatibiae which are taciform in shape (e.g., <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3, 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">10, 14</xref>), rather than the more bulky form of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> and other species (e.g., <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 13</xref>). Moreover, these same features can serve to distinguish <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (a.k.a., the “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>” of 1863). Indeed, a study of Smith’s collection of material labeled by Herbert F. Schwarz as “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> = <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic>” and those bearing the label “18” mentioned by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Cockerell (1915)</xref> are identical with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> (type material of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> was studied by Oliveira 2003 and the lectotype was re-examined for the purposes of the present study, <italic>vide infra</italic>) but do not match Smith’s 1863 description of “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>” (a.k.a., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>). This led us to believe that the material examined by previous authors was not of Smith’s syntype series. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Baker (1993)</xref> noted that Smith’s series from the 1863 paper was originally broken up between London and Oxford, and that,</p>
            <p>“The second set, in another part of the type collection (UMO 2), apparently, unfortunately, not seen by Schwarz [Herbert F. Schwarz], is grouped with various vespoids in a tray with the note: ‘Honey bees and Wasps of South America. Exhibited in the International Exhibition of 1862. Presented by John Miers Esq F.R.S. 1865. See Memoir by F. Smith in Trans. Entom. Society’”</p>
            <p>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Baker 1993</xref>: 232).</p>
            <p>As noted by Baker (op. cit.) this set comprises two specimens of each species examined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Smith (1863)</xref>. For material of “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>” there are two specimens, one bearing a blue label with “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sm” in Smith’s hand, the other nothing more than a label reading “18” (as was material Cockerell had available to him). Both of these specimens are of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> and do not match Smith’s (1863) description. It can only be presumed that Smith’s original series was mixed and that he based his description on a subset of these specimens.</p>
            <p>Among material from Smith’s collection in The Natural History Museum, London, a single worker individual was discovered missing its head and bearing a blue labeled signed by Smith as “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>” (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">14</xref>). This specimen was apparently not examined by previous authors when studying Neotropical <tp:taxon-name>Meliponini</tp:taxon-name> (e.g., Cockerell, Schwarz, Moure, or Camargo as none of these authors had placed their usual identification labels with the specimen). In preserved details, this specimen matches perfectly Smith’s (1863) description (obviously those characters of the head cannot be confirmed as the head was lost at some point in the past). It was therefore suspected that this could be one of the individuals upon which Smith had based his 1863 redescription. Given that this specimen is almost certainly from Smith’s 1863 <!--PageBreak-->exhibition series and that, unlike other specimens apparently from that series, it closely matches his description, we conclude that this is material from which he based his account. No other potential syntypes are known in collections and we accordingly select herein this individual to serve as the lectotype for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <p>As alluded to earlier, two further epithets come into play. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona francoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> was described in detail by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Moure (1946)</xref>, based on a single worker from Riachuelo (Sergipe, Brazil) and collected by the famed agronomist Dr. A. Franco Filho, to whom Moure dedicated the species. Later, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Moure (1963)</xref> described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta freiremaiai</tp:taxon-name></italic>, noting however that the material could prove to be conspecific with, and thereby a junior synonym of, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona francoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Indeed, having now examined the type material for both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona francoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona freiremaiai</tp:taxon-name></italic> it is clear that the minor differences mentioned by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Moure (1963)</xref> are geographic variations of one species. In addition, both are proposed as junior synonyms of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the identity of which is established by the newly recognized holotype (<italic>supra</italic>), and which takes priority over both of Moure’s epithets. Smith’s (1863) account indicating “head and thorax black above” (p. 510) agrees perfectly with both of these putative species in which the head is yellow (or pale yellow to orange-yellow or testaceous in some older specimens) except for a black rectangle on the upper part of the face and vertex (above the upper tangent of the antennal alveoli to the vertex, extending posterior to the ocelli until the occiput), as well as the mesosoma which has a dark brown to black mesoscutum. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Smith (1863)</xref> referred to the wings as hyaline, the wing membrane tends to be very faintly infumate. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> the mesosoma is similarly yellow with a black mesoscutum but in this species the head is entirely black with yellow markings on the clypeus, supraclypeal area, paraocular area, and gena. Oliveira (2003) clarified the taxonomic status of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="material|methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The type material considered herein is deposited in the following institutions: AMNH, Division of Invertebrate Zoology (Entomology), American Museum of Natural History, New York, USA; DZUP, Coleção de Entomologia Pe. J.S. Moure Departamento de Zoologia da Universidade Federal do Paraná, Curitiba, Brazil; and NHML, Department of Entomology, The Natural History Museum, London, United Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Given the incomplete nature of some material we based the metrics on the most complete of the type material, basically that of the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona francoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and were made using an ocular micrometer (with precision of 0.001 mm) on a Leica MZ12.5 stereomicroscope. All measurements are in millimeters. Measurements used herein are as follows: length of forewing measured from apex of costal sclerite to apex wing; diameters or width of structures were obtained by taking the maximum diameter or width (e.g., head width, clypeal width, compound eye width, scape diameter, meso- and metafemoral width, meso- and metatibial width, meso- and metabasitarsal width); total body length refers to distance from apex of clypeus to posterior margin of apicalmost metasomal segment; length of head in frontal view was taken from crest of<!--PageBreak--> vertex to medioapical margin of clypeus; width of head in frontal view corresponds to maximum width including compound eyes; height of compound eye in lateral view was taken as its maximum height (length); ocellorbital distance refers to the shortest distance in laterodorsal view between lateral ocellus and upper inner margin of compound eye; interocellar distance is that between the lateral and median ocelli; upper interorbital refers to the distance between the inner margins of the upper compound eye orbits; middle interorbital refers to the distance between compound eyes along a line approximately one alveolar diameter above the upper alveolar tangent; lower interorbital refers to the distance between the inner margins of the lower compound eye orbits; antennal scape length was measured from its apex to its base excluding the radical; lengths of femora, tibiae, and basitarsi were taken along their longitudinal axis from apex to joint with preceding podite.</p>
            <p>In addition to morphometric measurements, we examined a suite of morphological characters commonly used in meliponine systematics, including, but not limited to, pilosity, body coloration, and shape of the head, legs, and mesosoma. Morphological terminology follows that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Urban (1967)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Camargo et al. (1967)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Engel (2001)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Michener (2007)</xref>, with the addition of the term “taciformes” (for metatibial shape) referring to that form resembling a baseball bat. The following abbreviations are used: DA, alveolus diameter; DE, scape diameter; DP, puncture diameter; T, metasomal tergum. All characters included in the “Diagnosis” refer to workers as this is the caste most frequently found in Nature, while queens and drones are often unknown. In addition, the characters provided are those that make it most easy to recognize the species and not all are necessarily autapomorphic (Oliveira et al. in prep.).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Genus Frieseomelitta von Ihering, 1912"><title>Genus Frieseomelitta von Ihering, 1912</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Frieseomelitta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Frieseomelitta_meadewaldoi</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>(Cockerell, 1915)</tp:taxon-authority>                        
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–5, 7</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">–12, 14</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Trigona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name>
                            <comment>Smith; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Smith 1863</xref>: 504, 510 [misidentification, <italic>non Trigona dorsalis</italic> Smith, 1854].
                            </comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name>
                            <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Cockerell 1915</xref>: 32. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nomen novum pro Trigona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Smith, 1863 <italic>non Trigona dorsalis</italic> Smith, 1854.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona francoi</tp:taxon-name>
                            <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Moure 1946</xref>: 437–438. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Moure 1963</xref>: 39. Syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Trigona (Tetragona) francoi</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Moure); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Moure 1951</xref>: 44.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Trigona(Frieseomelitta) francoi</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Moure); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Wille 1962</xref>: 179.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Trigona(Frieseomelitta) meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name><comment> Cockerell; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Wille 1962</xref>: 179.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Trigona(Frieseomelitta) freiremaiai</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Moure 1963</xref>: 39-43. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Wille 1962</xref>: 179; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Cruz-Landim 1963</xref>: 2–4 (as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Friseomelitta</tp:taxon-name></italic> [sic]); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sakagami et al. 1963</xref>: 116, 119–121, 124, <!--PageBreak-->126–128; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Kerr and Esch 1965</xref>: 532, 536; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Kerr et al. 1967</xref>: 279, 282; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Cruz-Landim 1967</xref>: 194, 254, 266, 267, 270; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Akahira and Beig 1967</xref>: 166, 169, 172, 173, 180–181, 184 (Figs 15, 16); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Michener 1990</xref>: 103. Syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta freiremaiai</tp:taxon-name>
                            <comment>(Moure); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Nogueira-Neto 1963</xref>: 115; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Abdalla 2002</xref>: 135.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Trigona(Tetragona) freiremaiai</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Moure); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Wille and Michener 1973</xref>, pp. 14, 24, 48, 59, 70.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Trigona freiremaiai</tp:taxon-name>
                            <comment>(Moure); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Costa 2002</xref>: 94.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta francoi</tp:taxon-name>
                            <comment>(Moure); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Silveira et al. 2002</xref>: 87.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta doederleini</tp:taxon-name>
                            <comment>(Friese, 1900); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Camargo and Pedro 2007</xref>: 291 [misidentification].</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Lectotype (here designated)"><title>Lectotype (here designated).</title>
                        <p>Worker (NHML, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">14</xref>): labeled “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sm” in Smith’s hand on a blue label. Locality given solely as “Brazil” by Smith (1863; <italic>vide etiam</italic> Comments, <italic>infra</italic>) in his redescription of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Smith, 1854 (in 1854 he provided “Brasil (Pará)” as the type locality for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Additional type material examined"><title>Lectotype (here designated).</title>
                        <p>Worker holotype (DZUP, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 4, 5, 7</xref>) of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona francoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Moure, 1946; labeled “Riachuelo, Sergipe, Brasil, R. Franco col.”. Holotype worker (DZUP, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 8, 10, 12</xref>) of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta</tp:taxon-name></italic>) <italic>freiremaiai</italic> Moure, 1963; labeled “Guarapari, ES, Brasil, II.1961”; and 21 paratypes, workers of the same species, labeled “Guarapari, Espírito Santo, Brasil: II.1961” [n=7], “IX.1960, M. Alvarenga col.” [n=2]; “Maracás, Bahia, Brasil: 970m, VI.1961, F.M. Oliveira col.” [n=5], and “VI.1961” [n=7]. Lectotype worker (AMNH 25290, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">13</xref>) of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> Friese, 1900; labeled “Chiriqui, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> Friese, 1910” and with a typical orange Friese “Typus” label.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Worker</tp:taxon-name></italic>: Integument predominantly pale yellow to amber-yellow except dark brown to black on frons (rectangular area), dark brown to black on mesoscutum (margined by yellow lines), dark brown to black on apical two-thirds of metatibia and metabasitarsus; metasoma largely brown except first tergum, basal half of second tergum, and entirety of apicalmost tergum yellow to amber-yellow. Wing membrane faintly infumate, darker on marginal cell and with apical 6% somewhat white. Plumose setae of dorsal surface of mesotibia with long rachis and setal branches restricted to apical one-third of rachis; plumose setae of dorsal surface of mesobasitarsus forming a broad band. Metasoma elongate; metatibia taciform, with inflated aspect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 14</xref>); forewing marginal cell scarcely open at apex; typically six hamuli on leading edge of hind wing.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Descriptive notes"><title>Descriptive notes.</title>
                        <sec sec-type="Coloration"><title>Coloration:</title>
                        <p>Head pale yellow to amber-yellow except for dark brown to black transverse rectangle on upper face extending from above upper alveolar tangent (at a distance of approximately 1 DA) to occiput, bounded laterally by paraocular yellow lines, such paraocular marks even evident on lower yellow portion of face as paler yellow markings, slightly wider below, with greatest width close to tentorial foveae (1.6 DE); genal and paraocular yellow marks join at upper border of compound eye, thereby entirely surrounding orbits; genal marks rather narrow, almost imperceptible, more clearly defined along upper border of compound eye; gena pale yellow<!--PageBreak--> to testaceous; clypeus, supraclypeal area, and paraocular area pale yellow; epistomal sulcus brown to dark brown; scape pale amber-yellow to testaceous, with a brownish spot dorsoapically occupying one-third apical length; pedicel and first flagellomere yellowish ventrally; mandibles yellow to amber-yellow, with brown apex; labrum yellow to amber-yellow. Mesosoma yellow to amber-yellow or testaceous except mesoscutum dark brown to black and bordered laterally by large yellow to amber-yellow streaks, <!--PageBreak-->such lines a little wider at corners before forming shape of an inverted “J”; tegula yellowish translucent. Wing membranes lightly infumate, darker in marginal cell, apex whitish (apical 6%); veination amber-yellow except R and Rs bordering marginal cell light brown to brown. Legs yellow to amber-yellow or testaceous except dark brown to black on apical two-thirds of metatibia and entirety of metabasitarsus, remaining tarsomeres yellow to amber-yellow. Metasoma largely reddish brown to dark brown; first<!--PageBreak--> tergum and basal half of second tergum yellow to testaceous; remaining terga dusky, with apical tergum yellow to testaceous.</p>
                        </sec>
                        <sec sec-type="Pubescence"><title>Pubescence:</title>
                        <p>Pubescence pale yellow, relatively thin and short. Face with short plumose setae (longest approximately 0.5 DE), such setae with minute rachis and compactly plumose, branches long, such setae semi-decumbent on lower face and semi-erect on frons and vertex (more distinctly evident in this area); thin erect, long, feathery setae intermingled (2 DE), those in paraocular area slightly shorter, those posterior to ocelli longer and more curved; thin, long (2 DE), erect setae between plumose setae, shorter medially in paraocular area and longer and curved posterior to ocelli; setae of scape short and sparse, the longest approximately 0.5 DE, denser along inner margin near base; pubescence of gena simple, very thin, short, and decumbent by comparison with that of face and body, erect setae posterior to ocelli somewhat more dense and with relatively long rachis (about half length) and sparse apical branches. Simpler setae of mesoscutum slightly longer than twice length of plumose setae (2.5 DE), plumose setae with relatively long rachis and poorly branched apically, slightly shorter on disc (1 DE); anterior and lateral borders with setae with shorter rachis and more abundantly branched; setae of mesoscutellum longer (2 and 3 DE for simple and plumose setae, respectively), with long rachis and relatively few branches; mesepisternum with plumose setae and simpler setae relatively thin and long (1.0–2.5 DE and 3 DE, respectively), setae with short rachis (about half length) and relatively sparse apical branching, some with a longer apical filament. Legs with pubescence yellow to pale yellow except corbicular setae, those on internal surface of metatibia dark brown, on inner surface of metabasitarsus yellowish-brown; dorsal surface of mesotibia with erect setae, some plumose, relatively long (1.5 and 1 DE, respectively), plumose setae with very long rachis and branches scarce, restricted to apical third of rachis; mesobasitarsus with a broad band of erect setae and plumose setae, relatively long (1.5 and 1 DE, respectively) and thin setae forming a prominent band in posterior half; plumose setae of posterior edge of metatibia light brown (3 DE), interspersed with longer, thicker, and fuscous setae (4 DE). First metasomal tergum glabrous; TII with very narrow band of tiny bristles along posterior edge, such bristles increasing in length and thickness on succeeding terga, as well as in density and width of band; T5 with longer setae and wider band range, especially medially, but without plumose setae (band of T3 = one-half that of T4; T4 = one-half that of T5); setae of T6 longer and denser (2 DE), intermingled with very thin plumose setae.</p>
                        </sec>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Metrics"><title>Metrics.</title>
                        <p>Total length 4.75; forewing length 5.54; head width 1.99; clypeal width 1.0; clypeal length 0.46; malar length 0.07; compound eye length 1.21; compound eye width 0.55; upper interorbital distance 1.21; maximum interorbital distance 1.26; lower interorbital distance 0.99; alveolorbital distance 0.34; interalveolar distance 0.12; ocellorbital distance 0.30; interocellar distance 0.12; scape length 0.82; scape diameter 0.12; mesofemoral length 1.46; mesofemoral width 0.29; mesotibial length 1.51; mesotibial width 0.34; mesobasitarsal length 0.84; mesobasitarsal width 0.24; metafemoral length 1.88; metafemoral width 0.27; metatibial length 2.76; metatibial width 0.76; metabasitarsal length 0.82; metabasitarsal width 0.37; maximum width of metasomal tergum II 1.34.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>BRAZIL: States of Ceará (Choró, Maranguape), Rio Grande do Norte (Martins, Mossoró, Natal, Ipanguaçu), Paraíba (Juazeirinho, Santa Luzia), Pernambuco (Cabo de Santo Agostinho, Igarassu), Bahia (Camamu, Catu, Iaçu, Igrapiúna, Itabuna, Itaparica, Lençóis, Maracás, Milagres, Mucugê), and Espírito Santo (Fundão, Guarapari, Jacaraípe, Nova Almeida, Santa Teresa, São Roque).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>There are specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Maracás (Bahia, Brazil) labeled by Moure as “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta luteola</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.” (MS name, <italic>nomen nudum</italic>) in DZUP and it is probable that there are specimens similarly labeled in other collections.</p>
                        <p>It is of historical interest to note the influence of Brazilian Emperor D. Pedro II who worked tirelessly to bring Brazil to international attention, particularly his endorsement of participation in the Third Universal Exposition of London in 1862 which brought the material studied by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Smith (1863)</xref>. It was at this exposition that various products of Brazil were exhibited, including coffee, mate, rubber, wood, precious stones, machinery, and, of course, bees and their wax and honey, selected from different provinces of Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Almeida 2000</xref>). The bees had only vernacular names associated with them and so <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Smith (1863)</xref> was unable to give more precise locality information, simply citing them all as “Brazil”, but he did list these vernacular names (most of Tupi origin) and attempted, where possible, to use them as specific epithets (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Smith 1863</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Camargo and Moure (1996</xref>: 110) it is possible that the material was collected in southeastern Brazil, perhaps even the eastern region of the State of Minas Gerais, as evidenced by the etymology of the vernacular names employed.</p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures1–7.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cockerell, 1915 (lectotype, NHML), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona francoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Moure, 1946 (holotype, DZUP), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> Friese, 1900 (lectotype, AMNH) (all are workers). <bold>1</bold> Lateral habitus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> lectotype as preserved <bold>2</bold> Dorsal view of metasoma of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> lectotype <bold>3</bold> External surface of metatibia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> lectotype <bold>4</bold> Facial view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona francoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> holotype <bold>5</bold> Lateral habitus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona francoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> holotype <bold>6</bold> Facial view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> lectotype <bold>7</bold> Dorsal oblique view of mesoscutum and mesoscutellum of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tetragona francoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> holotype.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-111-019-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 8–14.</label> 
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cockerell, 1915 (lectotype, NHML; non-type, DZUP), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> Friese, 1900 (lectotype, AMNH) (all are workers). <bold>8</bold> Facial view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona freiremaiai</tp:taxon-name></italic> holotype. <bold>9</bold> Facial view of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the State of Bahia, Brazil (non-type material). <bold>10</bold> Lateral habitus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona freiremaiai</tp:taxon-name></italic> holotype. <bold>11</bold> Lateral habitus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Frieseomelitta meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (non-type material). <bold>12</bold> Dorsal oblique view of mesoscutum and mesoscutellum of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona freiremaiai</tp:taxon-name></italic> holotype. <bold>13</bold> Metatibia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona doederleini</tp:taxon-name></italic> lectotype. <bold>14</bold> Metatibia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trigona meadewaldoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> lectotype.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-111-019-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>This paper is lovingly dedicated to our colleagues, mentors, and friends, the late Padre Dr. Jesus Santiago Moure (1912–2010) and Prof. Dr. Charles D. Michener, both of whom have dedicated their lives to the study of bees and, through their multiplicity of publications, both jointly and separately have transformed the field of melittological inquiry. Without their years of advice, consultation, and friendly discussion this work would not have been possible. We are grateful to Mr. G. Else and Ms. C. Taylor (NHML), Dr. J.G. Rozen, Jr. (AMNH), and the late Dr. J.S. Moure (DZUP) for the loans of material examined during the course of this work; to Mr. J. Hogan, Oxford, for assistance with Smith material in the Hope Entomological Collections; and to Dr. C.D. Michener and Dr. A.M. Sakakibara for nomenclatorial advice. The manuscript received valuable comments from C.D. Michener and an anonymous reviewer. This work was a small portion of that undertaken by the senior author in partial fulfillment of requirements for the PhD degree from the Departamento de Zoologia, Universidade Federal do Paraná, and was supported by the Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES, Brazil).<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdalla</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Glândulas de Dufour.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz-Landim</surname><given-names>C da</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdalla</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Glândulas Exócrinas das Abelhas. FUNPEC-RP [Fundação de Pesquisas Científicas de Ribeirão Preto]</source>, <publisher-name>Ribeirão Preto</publisher-name>, <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage> [total pages 194 pp.]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Akahira</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beig</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> Comparative study of corpora alata in Brazilian stingless bees.</article-title> <source>Papéis Avulsos de Zoologia</source> <volume>20</volume>(<issue>16</issue>): <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> O Império ligado na ciência [Caderno Mais!].</article-title> <source>Folha de São Paulo [19 November 2000]</source>: <lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<source> The Type Material of the Nominal Species of Exotic Bees Described by Frederick Smith.</source> PhD Dissertation, <publisher-name>Oxford University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>, [i]+[i]–vi+<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage> pp., +14 pls.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>JMF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moure</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Meliponini Neotropicais: O gênero <italic>Geotrigona</italic> Moure, 1943 (Apinae, Apidae, Hymenoptera), com especial referência à filogenia e biogeografia.</article-title> <source>Arquivos de Zoologia</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>JMF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedro</surname><given-names>SRM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Meliponini Lepeletier, 1836.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moure</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>GAR</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Catalogue of Bees (Hymenoptera, Apoidea) in the Neotropical Region.</source> <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Entomologia</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Curitiba</publisher-loc>, <fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>578</lpage> [total pages xiv+1058 pp.].</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>JMF de</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> Morfologia externa de <italic>Melipona</italic> (<italic>Melipona</italic>) <italic>marginata</italic> Lepeletier (Hymenoptera, Apoidea).</article-title> <source>Papéis Avulsos de Zoologia</source> <volume>20</volume>(<issue>20</issue>): <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>258</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cockerell</surname><given-names>TDA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1915</year>)<article-title> The real <italic>Trigona dorsalis</italic> Smith rediscovered (Hym.).</article-title> <source>Entomological News</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cockerell</surname><given-names>TDA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1918</year>)<article-title> Descriptions and records of bees – LXXIX.</article-title> <source>Annals and Magazine of Natural History, Series 9</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>158</fpage>–<lpage>167</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cockerell</surname><given-names>TDA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1920</year>)<article-title> Some neotropical meliponid bees.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</source> <volume>42</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>RAC da</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Glândulas hipofaríngeas.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz-Landim</surname><given-names>C da</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdalla</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Glândulas Exócrinas das Abelhas.</source> <publisher-name>FUNPEC-RP [Fundação de Pesquisas Científicas de Ribeirão Preto]</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Ribeirão Preto</publisher-loc>, <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage> [total pages 194 pp.]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cresson</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1878</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of new species of North American bees.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz-Landim</surname><given-names>C da</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<article-title> Evaluation of the wax and scent glands in the Apinae (Hymenoptera: Apidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of the New York Entomological Society</source> <volume>71</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz-Landim</surname><given-names>C da</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> Estudo comparativo de algumas glândulas das abelhas (Hymenoptera, Apoidea) e respectivas implicações evolutivas.</article-title> <source>Arquivos de Zoologia</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>290</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> A monograph of the Baltic amber bees and evolution of the Apoidea (Hymenoptera).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</source> <volume>259</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/xxxxx" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1206/0003-0090(2001)259;lt0001:AMOTBA;gt2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabricius</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1798</year>)<source> Supplementum Entomologiae Systematicae.</source> <publisher-name>Proft et Storch</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Hafniae [Copenhagen]</publisher-loc>, [iv]+<lpage>572</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Friese</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1900</year>)<article-title> Neue Arten der Bienengattungen <italic>Melipona</italic> Ill, und <italic>Trigona</italic> Jur.</article-title> <source>Természetrajzi Füzetek</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Friese</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1901</year>)<article-title> Neue Arten der Bienengattung <italic>Trigona</italic> Jur. (Hym.).</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift für Systematische Hymenopterologie und Dipterologie</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>265</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Friese</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1902</year>)<article-title> Neue Meliponiden (Hym.).</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift für Systematische Hymenopterologie und Dipterologie</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>382</fpage>–<lpage>383</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ihering</surname><given-names>H von</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>)<article-title> Zur Biologie der brasilianischen Meliponiden.</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift für Wissenschaftliche Insektenbiologie</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>)<article-title> Comunicação entre as abelhas sociais brasileiras e sua contribuição para o entendimento da sua evolução.</article-title> <source>Ciência e Cultura</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>538</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakagami</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zucchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Portugal-Araújo V</surname><given-names>de</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camargo JMF</surname><given-names>de</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> Observações sobre a arquitetura dos ninhos e comportamento de algumas espécies de abelhas sem ferrão das vizinhanças de Manaus, Amazonas (Hymenoptera, Apoidea).</article-title> <source>Atas do Simpósio Sobre a Biota Amazônica</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lepeletier de Saint Fargeau</surname><given-names>ALM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1836</year>)<source> Histoire Naturelle des Insectes – Hyménoptères [vol. 1].</source> <publisher-name>Roret</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <lpage>547</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Michener</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> Classification of the Apidae (Hymenoptera).</article-title> <source>University of Kansas Science Bulletin</source> <volume>54</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>163</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Michener</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> The Bees of the World [2nd Edition].</source> <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc>, xvi+[i]+<lpage>953</lpage> pp., +20 pls.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moure</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1946</year>)<article-title> Contribuição para o conhecimento dos Meliponinae (Hym. Apoidea).</article-title> <source>Revista de Entomologia</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moure</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1950</year>)<article-title> Notas sobre alguns Meliponinae Bolivianos (Hymenoptera, Apoidea).</article-title> <source>Dusenia</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moure</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1951</year>)<article-title> Notas sôbre Meliponinae (Hymenopt.–Apoidea).</article-title> <source>Dusenia</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moure</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<article-title> Uma nova espécie de “<italic>Trigona</italic> (<italic>Frieseomelitta</italic>)” do Norte do Distrito Tupi (Hymenoptera, Apoidea).</article-title> <source>Revista Brasileira de Biologia</source> <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moure</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> Uma nova espécie de <italic>Frieseomelitta</italic> do Oeste da Amazônia (Hymenoptera, Apoidea).</article-title> <source>Acta Biológica Paranaense</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1–4</issue>): <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moure</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Espécies novas de abelhas da região central do Estado de Minais Gerais, Brasil (Hymenoptera, Apoidea).</article-title> <source>Acta Biológica Paranaense</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>1–4</issue>): <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nogueira-Neto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<source> A Arquitetura das Células de Cria dos Meliponinae (Apoidea, Hymenoptera).</source> PhD Dissertation, <publisher-name>Universidade de São Paulo</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Ribeirão Preto</publisher-loc>, <lpage>126</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>FF de</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Notas sobre os tipos de algumas espécies do gênero <italic>Frieseomelitta</italic> Ihering (Hymenoptera, Apidae, Meliponinae), descritas por Friese.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>GAR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alves dos Santos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Apoidea: Neotropica: Homenagem aos 90 Anos de Jesus Santiago Moure.</source> <publisher-name>Editora UNESC [Universidade do Extremo Sul Catarinense]</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Criciúma</publisher-loc>, <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage> [total pages xvi+320 pp.].</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Provancher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1888</year>)<source> Additions et Corrections au Volume II de la Faune Entomologique du Canada, traitant des Hyménoptères.</source> <publisher-name>Darveau</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Québec</publisher-loc>, <lpage>477</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roubik</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> New species of <italic>Trigona</italic> and cleptobiotic <italic>Lestrimelitta</italic> from French Guiana (Hymenoptera: Apoidea).</article-title> <source>Revista de Biología Tropical</source> <volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>269</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakagami</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beig</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zucchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akahira</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<article-title> Occurrence of ovary-developed workers in queenright colonies of stingless bees.</article-title> <source>Revista Brasileira de Biologia</source> <volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1940</year>)<article-title> Additional species and records of stingless bees (Meliponidae) from British Guiana based on specimens collected by the Terry-Holden Expedition.</article-title> <source>American Museum Novitates</source> <volume>1078</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Silveira</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>GAR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>EAB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<source> Abelhas Brasileiras: Sistemática e Identificação.</source> <publisher-name>Editora IDMAR</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Belo Horizonte</publisher-loc>, <lpage>253</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1854</year>)<source> Catalogue of Hymenopterous Insects in the Collection of the British Museum. Part II. Apidae.</source> <publisher-name>Taylor and Francis</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <fpage>199</fpage>–<lpage>465</lpage> pp., +6 pls. [vii–xii].</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1863</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of Brazilian honey bees belonging to the genera <italic>Melipona</italic> and <italic>Trigona</italic>, which were exhibited, together with samples of their honey and wax, in the Brazilian Court of the International Exhibition of 1862.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the Royal Entomological Society of London</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>497</fpage>–<lpage>512</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2311.1863.tb01298.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.1365-2311.1863.tb01298.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> As espécies do gênero <italic>Thygater</italic> Holmberg, 1884 (Hymenoptera, Apoidea).</article-title> <source>Boletim da Universidade Federal do Paraná</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>309</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wille</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962</year>)<article-title> A new species of stingless bee (Meliponini) from Costa Rica.</article-title> <source>Revista de Biología Tropical</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>181</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wille</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michener</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>)<article-title> The nest architecture of stingless bees with special reference to those of Costa Rica (Hymenoptera, Apidae).</article-title> <source>Revista de Biología Tropical</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>Suplemento 1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>