<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.108.1129</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new species of Andean toad  (Bufonidae, <italic>Osornophryne</italic>)  discovered using molecular and morphological data,  with a taxonomic key for the genus</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Páez-Moscoso</surname>
                        <given-names>Diego J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:C7E6B7EF-65B3-4083-9DBF-B11E9FFE8485</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Guayasamin</surname>
                        <given-names>Juan M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:73FF62CF-DA13-46D3-95FB-E0B7208AA6E7</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Yánez-Muñoz</surname>
                        <given-names>Mario</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:4F85DEF3-9AA1-4621-8566-1FE501361DA5</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Museo de Zoología, Escuela de Ciencias Biológicas, Pontificia Universidad Católica del Ecuador, Av. 12 de Octubre y Roca, Aptdo. 17012184, Quito, Ecuador
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Centro de Investigación de la Biodiversidad y el Cambio Climático, Universidad Tecnológica Indoamérica, Av. Machala y Sabanilla, Quito, Ecuador
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>División de Herpetología, Museo Ecuatoriano de Ciencias Naturales, Rumipamba 341 y Av. de los Shyris. Quito, Ecuador
            </aff>
            <aff id="A4">
                <label>4</label>Programa de Maestría en Biología de la Conservación, Pontificia Universidad Católica del Ecuador. Av. 12 de Octubre y Roca, Aptdo. 17012184, Quito, Ecuador
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Juan M. Guayasamin (<email xlink:type="simple">jmguayasamin@gmail.com</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Franco Andreone</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>17</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>108</issue>
            <fpage>73</fpage>
            <lpage>97</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>15</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>5</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Diego J. Páez-Moscoso, Juan M. Guayasamin, Mario Yánez-Muñoz</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:9B19F989-5202-4C66-87D8-FB1B568BA049</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Combining a molecular phylogeny and morphological data, we discovered a new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Amazonian slope of the Ecuadorian Andes. Morphologically, the new taxon is distinguished from all others species in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> by having the Toes IV and V longer than Toes I–III, a short and rounded snout with a small rostral papilla, and conical pustules on flanks. The new species previously was confused with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic>. A taxonomic key is provided for all known species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            </abstract>
            <trans-abstract xml:lang="es">
                <label>Resumen</label>
                <p>Al combinar una filogenia molecular con información morfológica, se descubrió una nueva especie de <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> proveniente de la vertiente amazónica de los Andes del Ecuador. Morfológicamente, el nuevo taxón se distingue de los otras especies del género por tener los Dedos IV y V del pie más largos que los Dedos I-III, un rostro corto y redondeado con una pequeña papilla, y pústulas cónicas en los flancos <!--PageBreak-->del cuerpo. La nueva especie estaba previamente confundida con <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Se provee de una clave taxonómica para todas las especies de <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> reconocidas hasta la fecha.</p>
            </trans-abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Andes</kwd>
                <kwd>Bufonidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Ecuador</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Osornophryne</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>phylogeny</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> is endemic to the Andes of Colombia and Ecuador, where it occurs in mountain forests and paramo at elevations between 2100 and 4000 m (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Ruiz-Carranza and Hernández-Camacho 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Gluesenkamp and Guayasamin 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Mueses-Cisneros et al. 2010</xref>). Currently, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> contains 10 recognized species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne angel</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Yánez-Muñoz et al. 2010</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne antisana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Hoogmoed 1987</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne bufoniformis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Peracca 1904</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Hoogmoed 1987</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Cisneros-Heredia and Gluesenkamp 2010</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne percrassa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Ruiz-Carranza and Hernández-Camacho 1976</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne puruanta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Gluesenkamp and Guayasamin 2008</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne sumacoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Gluesenkamp 1995</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne talipes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Cannatella 1986</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne cofanorum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Mueses-Cisneros et al. 2010</xref>). The evolutionary relationships between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> and other bufonid genera remain controversial, with some authors arguing a close affinity with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atelopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Coloma 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Gluesenkamp 2001</xref>), and others supporting a topology in which <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> is sister to most other bufonids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bocxlaer et al. 2010</xref>). However, the monophyly of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> is well established by morphological and molecular characters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Ruiz-Carranza and Hernández-Camacho 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Coloma 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Gluesenkamp 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bocxlaer et al. 2010</xref>); among the most conspicuous putative morphological synapomorphies are: six presacral vertebrae, digits almost completely embedded by an extensive membrane, reduced number or lenght of phalanges in hands and feet, absence of stapes and tympanum, urostlyle laterally expanded and broadly fused with sacrum, inguinal amplexus, and direct development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Ruiz-Carranza and Hernández-Camacho 1976</xref>; this work; compare with traits in South American bufonids; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Pramuk 2006</xref>).</p>
            <p>Given the complex topography of the Andes and the opportunity for allopatric speciation in areas with similar climatic conditions, it is possible that morphologically similar populations are evolving independently. Herein, we report and describe a new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic>, previously confused with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="material|methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <sec sec-type="Morphology"><title>Morphology.</title>
                <p>We examined alcohol-preserved specimens from the herpetological collections at Museo de Zoología of the Pontificia Universidad Católica del Ecuador (QCAZ),<!--PageBreak--> Escuela Politécnica Nacional (EPN), and Museo Ecuatoriano de Ciencias Naturales (DH-MECN), all based in Quito, Ecuador. Specimens examined are listed in Appendix I. Fingers are numbered preaxially to postaxially from I–IV to facilitate comparison with previous literature dealing with anurans; however, we stress that in an evolutionary perspective anuran fingers should be numbered from II–V, consistent with the hypothesis that Digit I was lost in anurans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Shubin and Alberch 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Fabrezi and Alberch 1996</xref>). Morphological measurements were taken with digital calipers to the nearest 0.1 mm and are, as follow: (1) snout–vent length (SVL = distance from tip of snout [excluding the proboscis] to posterior margin of vent); (2) tibia length (TIB = length of flexed hind leg from knee to heel); (3) foot length (FL = distance from base of inner metatarsal tubercle to tip of Toe IV); (4) head length (HL = distance from tip of snout to articulation of jaw); (5) head width (HW = greatest width of head measured between jaw articulations); (6) interorbital distance (IOD = shortest distance between medial margins of upper eyelids); (7) upper eyelid width (EW = greatest width of eyelid measured perpendicular to medial axis of skull); (8) internarinal distance (IND = distance between internal borders of nostrils); (9) eye–nostril distance (EN = distance from anterior corner of eye to posterior border of nostril); (10) snout–eye distance (SE = distance from anterior corner of the eye to the tip of the rostrum); (11) eye diameter (ED = distance between anterior and posterior corners of eye); (12) Finger-III length (FIIIL = distance from proximal border of Finger I to distal end of Finger III); (13) Finger-IV length (distance from proximal border of Finger I to distal end of Finger IV); (14) Toe-IV length (TIVL = distance from proximal edge of Toe I to distal tip of Toe IV); (15) Toe-V length (TVL = distance from proximal border edge of Toe I to distal tip of Toe V). Sexual maturity was determinate by the presence of nuptial pads in adult males and convoluted oviducts in adult females. Techniques for clearing and double-staining specimens with Alcian Blue and Alizarin Red were those of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Taylor and Van Dyke (1985)</xref>. Illustrations were made with the aid of a Wild M3B Heerbrugg stereo dissecting microscope equipped with a camera lucida. Osteological terminology is that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Duellman and Trueb (1994)</xref>, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Fabrezi (1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">1993</xref>), and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Trueb (1973</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">1993</xref>); bufonid osteological character states are illustrated in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Pramuk (2006)</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Molecular data"><title>Molecular data.</title>
                <p>Fresh liver samples were preserved in 90% alcohol, and stored at –80°C. We used salt-precipitation protocols to extract genomic DNA from ethanol-preserved tissues (M. Fujita, unpubl. data). To amplify the mitochondrial gene 12S, we used the primers MVZ59 and tRNA-val, developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Graybeal (1997)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Goebel et al. (1999)</xref>, respectively; Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) amplification protocol was, as follows: 1 cycle of denaturation 2 min at 94°C, annealing for 30 sec at 42°C, extension for 1 min at 72°C, 5 cycles of denaturation 30 sec at 94°C, annealing for 30 sec at 42°C, extension for 1 min at 72°C, 22 cycles of denaturation 30 sec at 94°C, annealing for 30 sec at 50°C, extension for 1 min at 72°C, final extension at 72°C was conducted for 5 min. PCR products were visualized in 0.7% agarose gel, and unincorporated primers and dNTPs were removed from PCR products using ExoSap-it purification. Cycle sequencing reactions were conducted by the commercial company Macrogen Inc. Data from heavy and light stands were compared to generate a consensus sequence for each DNA fragment with Sequencer Ver. 4.8. We obtained sequences of 71 speci<!--PageBreak-->mens, including all the species in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic>, except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne talipes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and three outgroup taxa. In addition, sequences were downloaded from GenBank (NCBI). Sequences were initially aligned in Clustal X (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Larkin et al. 2007</xref>) and adjusted in Mesquite 2.71 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Maddison and Maddison 2009</xref>). Best-fit model of molecular evolution was selected in jModeltest 1.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Posada 2008</xref>) under the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC). Model parameters estimated from jModelTest were used in Bayesian analyses.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Phylogenetics"><title>Phylogenetics.</title>
                <p>Analyses were conducted using Maximum Parsimony (MP), Maximum Likelihood (ML), and Bayesian Analyses (BA). Parsimony analyses were performed in PAUP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Swofford 2009</xref>) using heuristic searches (10,000 stepwise random additions with TBR branch-swapping) and clade support was estimated via 1000 bootstraps with 10 random additions. Maximum likelihood was run in GARLI 0.951 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Zwickl 2006</xref>), which uses a stochastic genetic algorithm-like approach to find the topology, branch lengths, and substitution model parameters that maximize the log-likelihood simultaneously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Zwickl 2006</xref>). We performed a total of 50 runs to reduce the probability of inferring a suboptimal likelihood solution. Node support was assessed via 1000 bootstrap replicates. For Bayesian analyses, we implemented the model of nucleotide substitution selected as the best fit for the particular dataset according to the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) in jModeltest 1.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Posada 2008</xref>). Bayesian analysis of the mitochondrial dataset was performed in Mr Bayes 3.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Ronquist and Huelsenbeck 2003</xref>). The analysis consisted of 10 million generations and two Markov chains with default heating values. The prior used for the rate matrix was a uniform Dirichlet and no prior information on topology was incorporated. Trees were sampled every 1000 generations; stationarity was assessed by examining the standard deviation of split frequencies and by plotting the –lnL per generation using Tracer v1.4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Rambaut and Drummond 2007</xref>), and trees generated before stationary were discarded as ‘‘burn-in.” Bootstrap values <italic>p</italic> &gt; 70% are considered to indicate strong support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Hillis and Bull 1993</xref>, with their caveats). Clades with posterior probabilities <italic>p &gt;</italic> 0.95 are considered strongly supported, but we caution that relatively high posterior probabilities for short internodes (particularly those with low bootstrap values) may be over-estimates of confidence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alfaro et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Erixon et al. 2003</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results"><title>Results</title>
            <p>For most of the species and population of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osonophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> and three species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atelopus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, we obtained a total of 800 bp from the mitochondrial marker 12S rRNA (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Parameter value estimates for best-fit models for 12S gene generated by jModeltest 1.1 are TIM2 + I (0.001) + G (0.4700). The only taxon for which we could not obtain molecular information was <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne talipes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a species that, in Ecuador, is only know from a specimen collected on 02 August 1970 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Cannatella 1986</xref>). The different analyses (MP, ML, and AB) are congruent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The topology resolves most of the relationships among species in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and reveals the presence of the previously unrecognized taxon described below.<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">simpsoni</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9BFBC919-F698-4FDE-8994-9154FF9E99ED</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Osornophryne_simpsoni</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype"><title>Holotype.</title>
                    <p>QCAZ 49774 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), an adult male near San Rafael-Chontayacu (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°16'34.61"S, 78°4'21.14"W</named-content>, 2266 m.a.s.l.), Reserve Ankaku-Zona, Río Challuwayacu, Provincia de Pastaza, Ecuador, by Elicio Tapia on 21 October 2009.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratopotypes"><title>Paratopotypes:</title>
                    <p>QCAZ 48781, 49777, 45899 obtained with holotype.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes"><title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p>DH-MECN 5660 adult female, DH-MECN 5261, 5263, 5258–59, adult male obtained near Reserva Biológica Río Zuñac (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°20'57.87"S, 78°09'31.37"W</named-content>, 2250 m.a.s.l.), Parroquia Río Negro, Cantón Baños, Provincia de Tungurahua, Ecuador, by MYM, M. Urgiles y A. Laguna on 17 May 2008; QCAZ 39769 also obtained near Reserva Biológica Río Zuñac, by DJP, A. Narváez, and J. P. Reyes-Puig on 21 January 2009.</p>
                    <table-wrap position="float" orientation="portrait" id="T1">
                        <label>Table 1.</label>
                        <caption><p>Summary of specimens sequenced of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atelopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> for the gen 12S and GenBank accession numbers.</p></caption>
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species and museum no.</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locality</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latitude and Longitude</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank No.</th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atelopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 34540</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limón</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907488</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 41326</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zuruni</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907486</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 38427</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Las Tres Cruces</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907487</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne angel</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40039</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Páramo del Ángel</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°41'15"N, 77°52'46"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907459</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40036</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Páramo del Ángel</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°41'15"N, 77°52'46"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907458</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40040</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Páramo del Ángel</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°41'15"N, 77°52'46"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907493</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne antisana</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40172</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Páramo de Oyacachi</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°10'34"S, 78°0.6'50"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907453</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40173</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Páramo de Oyacachi</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°10'34"S, 78°0.6'50"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907485</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40174</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Páramo de Oyacachi</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°10'34"S, 78°0.6'50"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907484</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DH-MECN 838</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salvefaccha</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°13'54"S, 78°0.1'1"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907490</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DH-MECN 811</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salvefaccha</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°13'54"S, 78°0.1'1"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907489</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 46204</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Llanganates</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°15'57"S, 78°26'45"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907450</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 46212</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Llanganates</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°15'57"S, 78°26'45"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907449</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 48035</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Llanganates</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°15'57"S, 78°26'45"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907448</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 48223</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Llanganates</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°15'57"S, 78°26'45"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907445</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 48220</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Llanganates</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°15'57"S, 78°26'45"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907446</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 48034</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Llanganates</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°15'57"S, 78°26'45"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907447</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne bufoniformis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40123</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Santa Bárbara</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°38'29"N, 77°31'18.5"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907431</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40121</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Santa Bárbara</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°38'29"N, 77°31'18.5"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907432</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40003</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Santa Bárbara</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°38'29.5"N, 77°31'18.5"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907430</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 45082</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huaca</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°40'15"N, 77°46'11"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907460</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 45083</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huaca</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°40'15"N, 77°46'11"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907461</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 45084</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huaca</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°40'15"N, 77°46'11"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907462</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DH-MECN 1815</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Playón de San Francisco</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°37'43"N, 77°54'35"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907455</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DH-MECN 1806</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Playón de San Francisco</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°37'43"N, 77°54'35"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907457</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DH-MECN 1807</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Playón de San Francisco</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°37'43"N, 77°54'35"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907456</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DH-MECN 1808</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Playón de San Francisco</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°37'42.6"N, 77°54'35"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907454</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne cf. bufoniformis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 9316</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vía Tulcán-Maldonado</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°47'31"N, 77°54'25"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF375498</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne cofanorum</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DH-MECN 1591</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Bonita</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">00°29'19"N, 77°35'11"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907440</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DH-MECN 1579</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Bonita</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">00°29'19"N, 77°35'11"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907439</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DH-MECN 1629</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Bonita</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">00°29'19"N, 77°35'11"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907441</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40138</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poblado de Oyacachi</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°10'34"S,, 78°0'50"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907463</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40143</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poblado de Oyacachi</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°10'34"S,, 78°0'50"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907464</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40147</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poblado de Oyacachi</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°10'34"S,, 78°0'50"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907465</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 43370</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volcán Sumaco</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°34'11"S, 77°35'39"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907474</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 4576</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volcán Sumaco</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°34'11"S, 77°35'39"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907491</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40106</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cordillera de los Guacamayos</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°37'26.5"S, 77°50'27"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907468</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40102</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cordillera de los Guacamayos</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°37'26.5"S, 77°50'27"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907492</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 43554</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cordillera de los Guacamayos</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°37'26.5"S, 77°50'27"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907467</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 17295</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volcán Reventador</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°6'43"S, 77°40'44"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907471</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 17294</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volcán Reventador</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°6'43"S, 77°40'44"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907473</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 17293</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volcán Reventador</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°6'43"S, 77°40'44"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907472</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 12240</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Río Angel</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°37'26.5"S, 77°50'27"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907469</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 12241</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Río Angel</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°37'26.5"S, 77°50'27"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907470</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 2735</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jondachi (Río Angel)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°37'26.5"S, 77°50'27"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907466</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 46662</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Santa Bárbara</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°33'51"N, 77°31'38"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907475</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 40028</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chilma</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°51'50"N, 78°4'1"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907436</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 43652</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cuellaje</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°27'30"N, 78°32'43"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907444</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 43498</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cuellaje</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°27'30"N, 78°32'43"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907443</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 43653</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cuellaje</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°27'30"N, 78°32'43"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907442</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne puruanta</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 13271</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laguna de San Marcos</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°7'36"N, 78°15'22"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907451</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 13320</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laguna de San Marcos</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°7'36"N, 78°15'22"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907452</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 11471</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laguna de Puruanta</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">00°12’ N, 77°57’ W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AF375499.1</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 49779</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Llanganates</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°16'35"S, 78°4'21"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907482</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 49777</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Llanganates</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°16'35"S, 78°4'21"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907477</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 49781</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Llanganates</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°16'35"S, 78°4'21"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907483</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 49776</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Llanganates</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°16'35"S, 78°4'21"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907476</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 39774</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Río Zuñac</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°20'58"S, 78°09'31"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907478</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> DH-MECN 5262</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Río Zuñac</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°20'58"S, 78°09'31"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907480</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 39778</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rio Zuñac</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°20'58"S, 78°09'31"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907479</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 39773</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rio Zuñac</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°20'58"S, 78°09'31"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907481</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne sumacoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 41243</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volcán Sumaco</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°34'11"S, 77°35'39"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907434</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 41250</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volcán Sumaco</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°34'11"S, 77°35'39"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907433</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 41246</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volcán Sumaco</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°34'11"S, 77°35'39"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907437</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 41249</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volcán Sumaco</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°34'11"S, 77°35'39"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907438</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 43379</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Volcán Sumaco</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°34'11"S, 77°35'39"W</named-content></td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JF907435</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from all other species in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> (except for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne cofanorum</tp:taxon-name></italic>) by having Toes IV and V longer than Toes I–III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Morphologically, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo;</tp:taxon-name></italic> both species have Toes IV and V longer than Toes I–III, pustular dorsal skin, and dark brown dorsal coloration. However, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> lacks the conspicuos proboscis present in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo;</tp:taxon-name></italic> males of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from males of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic> by having ventral skin with conical pustules (non-conic pustules in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic>), and light brown to orange conical pustules on the flanks (dark brown to black non-conical pustules in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic>); the venter of female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic> is mostly whitish to yellowish with brown marks, whereas that of female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> is orange-brown. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne cofanorum</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> by having its vertebrae and urostlyle coosified with the overlying skin (not co-osified in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and vertebral neural spines that are visible dorsally (not visible in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>); also, males of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne cofanorum</tp:taxon-name></italic> have yellow pustules on the tip of the snout, upper eyelid, limbs, and dorsolateral pustular clusters (absent in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>). Finally, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> is distinguished from its sister species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, by having a rounded snout in lateral view (protruding in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>), brown dorsum with some lighter patches (dark brown dorsum with dark ochre-brown warts in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>), orange-brown venter (white in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne occidetalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>), and by inhabiting in the Amazonian slopes of the Andes (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is found on the Pacific slopes of the Andes).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Species Description"><title>Species Description.</title>
                    <p>Ten adult males and one adult female. Females of medium size (SVL = 33.0 mm, <italic>n</italic> = 1); males small (SVL = 17.6–26.1 mm; mean = 21.1 ±2.40, <italic>n =</italic> 10; <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Head length 77.2–95.1% head width; male head width 34.9–40.8% SVL; female head width 37.3% SVL; width of head greater at level of posterior margin of mouth; snout short, rounded, with rostral papilla in dorsal and lateral views; nostrils slightly swollen; each nostril oblique, oval, directed laterally; internarial area concave in males and slightly concave in female; interorbital region with skin co-osified with underlying bone, which has few low tubercles; occipital region mostly flat, but with few bony tubercles and cranial crests in males and females; upper eyelids finely tuber<!--PageBreak-->culate in females, with conical tubercles in males; interorbital region wider than the upper eyelid (upper eyelid 73.0–87.5% of interorbital distance in males, <italic>n</italic> = 9; 64.4% in female); outer edge of the eyelid delineated by a continuous row of warts, which are more conical in males than in female; canthus rostralis straight; loreal region slightly concave, with small warts in males and female; pale brown lips; eyes with oval horizontally pupil; infraorbital and postorbital regions with some prominent tubercles of variable size in males and females. Skin of dorsum highly tuberculate, with discontinuous row of conical tubercles starting at level of posterolateral edge of cranium and ending at level of sacrum in males and females; in males, ventral skin with several small pustules and few conical tubercles on gular region and toward the flanks, pustules much denser on chest and abdomen and less conical; in females, ventral skin smooth, with small, non-conical isolated pustules, pustules more numerous on abdomen.</p>
                    <p>Forelimb long, slender, finely granular, with several larger tubercles extending along inner and outer edges of fingers in males; in females, tubercles smaller than in males. Hand of moderate length, representing 25.0–30.4% (<italic>n</italic> = 10) of SVL in males and 28.5% in female; extensive webbing between fingers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>); lengths of fingers in order of increasing length : I &lt; II &lt; IV &lt; III; palms with numerous tubercles; subarticular tubercles not distinguishable; palmar tubercle rounded, thenar tubercle almost undistinguishable.<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p>Hind limbs long and slender; well-defined pustules present on inner and outer edges of fingers in males, females with less pronounced pustules than those in males; tibia and foot, respectively, 32.8–36.9% and 34.9–42.5% of male SVL, and 33.9% and 41.9% of female SVL; webbing between Toes I–III more extensive that webbing between Toes IV–V (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>); lengths of Toes: I &lt; II &lt; III &lt; V &lt; IV; Toe V much longer than Toe III, soles with numerous tubercles; subarticular tubercles indistinguishable; inner metatarsal tubercle oval. Choanae slightly rounded; adult males lacking vocal sacs; vocal slits absent; nuptial pads on proximal surfaces of Toes I and II, not pigmented; cloacal opening medial to thighs.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p>Maximum likelihood phylogeny of the species in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> inferred from the mitochondrial gene 12S (lnL = –1384,3649).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-108-073-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in life (male holotype, QCAZ 49774).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-108-073-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 3.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in alcohol. <bold>A–C</bold> Dorsal, ventral and lateral views of holotype, adult male, QCAZ 49774, SVL 20.1 mm <bold>D–F</bold> Dorsal, ventral and lateral views of adult female, DH-MECN 5260, SVL 33.0 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-108-073-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 4.</label>
                        <caption><p>Foot (<bold>A</bold>) and hand (<bold>B</bold>) of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (holotype, adult male, QCAZ 49774).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-108-073-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                 <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Coloration in alcohol"><title>Coloration in alcohol.</title>
                    <p>Dorsum, head, forearms, and hind limbs brown to dark brown, with some orange patches; tubercles on upper eyelid, proboscis, and flanks pale yellow. Throat pale yellow; venter cream with brown tubercles.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Coloration in life"><title>Coloration in life.</title>
                    <p>Dorsum, head, forearms, and hind limbs dark brown to light brown with some lighter patches; tubercles on upper eyelid, proboscis and flanks orange to yellow. Throat cream yellow, with small dark marks; venter orange-brown.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Osteology"><title>Osteology.</title>
                    <p>The following osteological description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> is based on a cleared-and-double stained adult male (QCAZ 45899, SVL = 19.5 mm). The osteological description of females was not possible because only one female is known.</p>
                    <p>Cranium. <italic>Shape and proportions</italic>. The skull is widest posterior to the orbit at the level of the articulation of the maxilla with the quadratojugal. The braincase is broad; at the level of the midorbit, the width of the braincase is about 41.2% of the greatest width of the skull and 26.2% of the medial skull length.</p>
                    <sec sec-type="Neurocranium"><title>Neurocranium.</title>
                    <p>The neurocranium is formed by five bones—the sphenethmoid, and the paired prootics and exoccipitals. Anteriorly, the neurocranium is completely ossified. A minute septomaxilla is embedded in the anterior nasal capsule cartilage. In dorsal aspect, the cartilaginous planum antorbitale has a perpendicular orientation in relation to the longitudinal axis of the skull. In lateral and ventral views, a broad cartilaginous separation between bony sphenethmoid and prootic is evident. The frontoparietal fontanelle is partially exposed medially between the frontoparietals. Distally, the otic capsules are cartilaginous. Medially, the exoccipitals are slightly separated from one another. The dorsal surface of each prootic is smooth. The epiotic eminences are prominent.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Auditory apparatus"><title>Auditory apparatus.</title>
                    <p>The stapes and tympanic annulus are absent. The operculum is oval and cartilaginous.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Dermal investing bones"><title>Dermal investing bones.</title>
                    <p>Dorsal investing bones are well developed. The nasals are separated from one another and cover most of the nasal capsules dorsally. The maxillary process of the nasal overlaps the pars fascialis of the maxilla to form a bony anterior margin of the orbit. The frontoparietals are well developed and have a narrow separation between one another along its longitudinal axis. The posteriormedial margin of each frontoparietal contacts the exoccipital, but is not fused to it. Posterolateraly, each frontoparietal bears a bony extension that reaches the epiotic eminence. Each frontoparietal has a lamina perpendicularis that is narrow anteriorly and greatly expanded posteriorly <!--PageBreak-->(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>). The dorsal surface of each frontoparietal bears small, bony tubercles that are visible externally; the tubercles seem to be co-ossified with the overlying skin.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Ventral investing and palatal bones"><title>Ventral investing and palatal bones.</title>
                    <p>The parasphenoid has the shape of an inverted T. The broad cultriform process extends anteriorly to about the mid-level of the orbit, where it is narrowly separated from the posterior border of the sphenethmoid. The cultriform process reaches its maximum width at a level that is coincident with the posterior margin of the optic fenestra. The parasphenoid alae are robust, investing the cartilaginous floor of the otic capsule anterior to the exoccipitals; the length of each ala is 61.8% the length of the cultriform process. A broadly acuminate posteromedial process of the parasphenoid terminates just anterior to the margin of the foramen magnum. The vomers are small, arcuate, broadly separated bones that support the medial margins of the choanae; the bones are unornamented, edentate, and lack dentigerous processe; the prechoanal ramus of the vomer is especially short. The neopalatine is short and narrow; medially, it reaches the anterolateral margin of the sphenethmoid; medially, the neopalatine does not contact the maxilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Maxillary arcade"><title>Maxillary arcade.</title>
                    <p>The premaxillae and maxillae lack teeth. The arcade is complete and has a tenuous articulation with the short quadratojugals. The pars palatinae of the premaxillae are broad. The premaxilla bears two palatine processes, a narrow longer medial and a broad lateral process. There is a simple, juxtaposed articulation between the anterior end of the maxilla and the premaxilla. The pars facialis of the maxilla is well-developed anteriorly, covering the the posterior region of the olfactory capsule; also, the pars facialis has a well-developed preorbital process, which covers most of the planum antorbitale (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B, C</xref>).</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Suspensory apparatus"><title>Suspensory apparatus.</title>
                    <p>The tridiate pterygoid bears a slightly curved anterior ramus that is orientated anterolaterally toward the maxilla, with which it articulates. The pterygoid is in close proximity to the maxilla and the narrow space between them is filled by the pterygoid cartilage. The medial and posterior rami of the pterygoid are about equal in length; however, the medial ramus is more robust than the posterior. The lateral end of the medial ramus overlaps the lateral edge of the prootic. The squamosal has the shape of an inverted L; the zygomatic ramus is almost absent, whereas the otic ramus is long and almost reaches the posterior end of the skull. The otic ramus overlaps the lateral margin of the crista parotica slightly. The ventral ramus invests the lateral surface of the palatoquadrate, and articulates with the quadratojugal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A, C</xref>); along its anterior margin, the ventral ramus has a conspicuos flange, which extends along the upper border of the otic ramus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>).</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Hyoid"><title>Hyoid.</title>
                    <p>The width of the cartilaginous hyoid corpus is narrower than its medial length (width 63.1% of length). The anterolateral and posterolateral processes of the hyoid are absent. The bony posteromedial processes are slightly expanded proximally; each process has a bony flange along the posteromedial margin. The hypoglossal sinus is broadly U-shaped. The hyalia are simple and lack any processes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5D</xref>).</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Postcranium. Vertebral column"><title>Postcranium. Vertebral column</title>
                    <p>There are six prepresacral vertebrae. Presacrals I and II are not fused and are notably shorter than Presacrals III–VI. The vertebral profile in decreasing order of overall width of bony parts is: Sacrum &gt; III &gt; IV &gt; V &gt; VI &gt; II &gt; I. Presacral I, or the atlas, lacks transverse processes. All presacrals are non-imbricate. The transverse processes of Presacral II have a anterolateral orientation, Presacrals III–V have a slightly posterolateral orientation, and Presacral VI is approximately perpendicular to the longitudinal axis of the body. The bony sacral diapophyses are broadly expanded; posteriorly, the sacrum is broadly fused with the urostyle, which is greatly expanded laterally. The urostyle bears a well-developed dorsal crest throughout most of its length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Pectoral girdle"><title>Pectoral girdle.</title>
                    <p>The clavicles have a slight orientation, with the medial tips distinctly separated from one another and located at about the same level of the anterolateral end of the clavicle, which articulates with the pars acromialis of the scapula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). The coracoid is notably stout, with the sternal end having a moderate expansion and the sternal end being heavily expanded (sternal end 45% of glenoid end); the inner edge of coracoid has an angle of about 45˚, wheras the external edge is straight (no angle). The pectoral fenestra is has a tringular shape, in which the base is anteriorly convex. The scapula is moderately long with a prominent pars acromialis <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->that is separated from the pars glenoidalis; the leading and posterior edges of the scapula are slightly concave. The suprascapula is mostly cartilaginous, but it is mineralized at both ends, with the ossified cleithrum apparent as a slender bone along the leading edge of the suprascapular blade and with a proximal end that is wider than its distal end. The sternum is small and completely cartilaginous; it contacts the epicoracoid cartilage, which is extensive, and the posterior margin of the coracoid. The omosternum is absent.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Pelvic girdle"><title>Pelvic girdle.</title>
                    <p>The long, slightly concave, and slender ilial shafts bear small dorsal crests, which extend from the anterior third to the posterior end of the shafts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). The ilial prominence is broad and low; the pubes is highly mineralized.</p>
                    </sec>
                    <sec sec-type="Manus and pes"><title>Manus and pes.</title>
                    <p>The phalangeal formulae for the hand and foot are standard—i.e., 2-2-3-3 and 2-2-3-4-3, respectively; however, the distal phalange of Finger I, Toe I, and Toe III are greatly reduced and formed mostly by cartilage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). Relative length of fingers, in increasing order, is: I-II-IV-III, and of the foot is: I-II-III-V-IV. The carpus is composed of a radiale, ulnare, Element Y, Carpal 2, and a large postaxial assumed to represent a fusion of Carpals 3–5. Element Y is about 3 times the size of Carpal 2, and the prepollex is an elongated cartilage. The terminal phalanges are acuminate, except Finger III that is slightly T-shaped. The tarsus is composed of two tarsal elements, presumably Tarsal 1 and Tarsal 2 + 3. The prehallux is presented by a proximal mineralized cartilage element associated with a small bony element.</p>
                    </sec>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific name <italic>simpsoni</italic> is a patronym for Dr. Nigel Simpson in recognition for his continual efforts in protecting the Andean cloud forests of Ecuador. Dr. Simpson is a collaborator of two of the most important conservation NGOs in Ecuador, EcoMinga Foundation (www.ecominga.net) and Jocotoco Foundation (www.fjocotoco.org). As the common name of the species, we suggest “Simpson’s Plumb Toad.” In Spanish, we suggest the name “Osornosapo de Simpson.<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->”</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution and conservation"><title>Distribution and conservation.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornoprhyne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> is only known from the type locality and surrounding areas, Reserva Zuñac (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°20'58"S, 78°09'31"W</named-content>) and Reserve Ankaku-Zona (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°16'35"S, 78°4'21"W</named-content>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>). These localities are included in the Bosque de Niebla Montano (Montane Cloud Forest) according to the classification proposed by Valencia et al.(1999). Vegetation is dominated by Clusia spp. trees. All individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> have been found on leaves of bromeliads and ferns during the night. Simpatric anurans include <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pristimantis altamis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pristimantis bicantus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pristimantis imcomptus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pristimantis galdi</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Following the IUCN (2001) criteria, we consider <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> as Data Deficient; however, it is likely that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a restricted distribution, as observed in other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> species.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion.</title>
                    <p>It has become increasingly evident that lineage independence is not always accompanied by morphological change when ecological conditions remain similar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Wiens 2004</xref>). Therefore, combining different sources of data in the process of species discovery increases the probabilities of revealing evolutionary species (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Simpson 1961</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Wiley 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Padial et al. 2009</xref>). The discovery of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> represents a good example of such approach. The phylogeny presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> shows some interesting issues that will need further research. For example, given the current gene sampling, there is no genetic differentiation between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne angel</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne bufoniformis;</tp:taxon-name></italic> similarly, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne antisana</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne puruanta</tp:taxon-name></italic> are not reciprocally monophyletic, although they have conspicuous morphological differences (e.g., body size). Last, within <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic>, there are two genetically distinctive populations that might represent evolutionary species.</p>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 5.</label>
                        <caption><p>Skull and hyoid of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., adult male, QCAZ 45899. <bold>A</bold> Dorsal view of skull <bold>B</bold> Ventral view of skull <bold>C</bold> Lateral view of skull <bold>D</bold> Ventral view of hyoid.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-108-073-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 6.</label>
                        <caption><p>Vertebral column of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in dorsal view; adult male, QCAZ 45899.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-108-073-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 7.</label>
                        <caption><p>Pectoral girdle of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in ventral view; adult male, QCAZ 45899.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-108-073-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 8.</label>
                        <caption><p>Osteology of hand and foot of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in ventral view; adult male, QCAZ 45899.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-108-073-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Table 2.</label> 
                        <caption><p>Morphometrics of adult males and female of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osonophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p></caption>
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Museum number </th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SVL</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HL</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HW</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">FL</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIB</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IOD</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">EW</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IND</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IND</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">FIIIL</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">FIVL</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LM</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">LF</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TL</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">EN</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED</th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DH-MECN 5260</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 49774</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 45899</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 49777</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 49781</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 39774</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">QCAZ 39769</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DH-MECN  5261</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DH-MECN  5259</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DH-MECN  5258</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DH-MECN  5263</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
             </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Key to the species of Osornophryne"><title>Key to the species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic></title>
            <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toe V longer than Toes I–III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toe V shorter than Toes I–III</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vertebrae and urostyle co-ossified with overlying skin; in life, males with yellow pustules on upper eyelid and tip of snout</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne cofanorum</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vertebrae and urostyle not coossified with overlying skin; males lacking yellow pustules on tip of snout</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head acuminate, with a long proboscis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>); dorsal skin lacking conical tubercles in most populations (except population from Volcan Sumaco); dorsum dark brown to black, sometimes with grayish-yellow dorsolateral stripes</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Head with short and round snout, with small papillae at tip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>); dorsal skin with conical tubercles; dorsum lacking dorsolateral stripes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsum covered with numerous round pustules of different sizes (lacking space among pustules)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsum with sparsely distributed pustules (space among pustules clearly evident)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female dorsal skin highly tuberculate, with prominent dorsolateral ridges; flanks with large rounded pustules; males and females with prominent occipital ridges; in males, head acuminated to subacuminated in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne angel</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female dorsal skin highly tuberculate, with faintly defined dorsolateral ridges; flanks with scattered and small pustules; males and females with low (or lacking) occipital ridges; in males, head rounded or truncated in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne bufoniformis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsolateral, occipital, and pelvic ridges separated by smooth skin</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsolateral, occipital, and pelvic ridges separated by flat pustules</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Males and females large (in males, SVL &gt; 23.5 mm; in females, SVL &gt; 40 mm); males and females with a continuous dorsolateral ridges, and acuminate snout in dorsal view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Males and females small (in males, SVL &lt; 19.0 mm; in females, SVL &lt; 30 mm). Males and females with discontinuous dorsalateral ridges</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne antisana</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Males and females with prominent dorsolateral, occipital, and pelvic ridges</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne talipes</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females with comparatively lower dorsolateral, occipital, and pelvic ridges (males unknown)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne puruanta</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females with yellow, orange, or white venter in life</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females with blue to silver venter in life; males with a yellow to orange papillae at tip of snout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne sumacoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females with yellow to orange venter in life; males and females lacking dorsolateral ridges</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne percrassa</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females with yellow to white venter; males and females with clearly defined dorsolateral ridges</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 9.</label>
                <caption><p>Distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (white circles) in Ecuador.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-108-073-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 10.</label>
                <caption><p>Head shape in dorsal and lateral views of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> males. Illustrated species are: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne angel</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 40048; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne antisana</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 48209; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne bufoniformis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 45084; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne cofanorum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, DH-MECN 6248; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 40106; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 49774; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 43529; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne sumacoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 41246; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne talipes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ICN 12256. Not drawn at scale.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-108-073-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 11.</label>
                <caption><p>Head shape in dorsal and lateral views of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne</tp:taxon-name></italic> females. Illustrated species are: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne angel</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 43560; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne antisana</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 48221; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne bufoniformis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 40122; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne cofanorum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, DH-MECN 6194; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 26047; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne simpsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>, DH-MECN 5260; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 43498; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne percrassa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ICN 319; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne puruanta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 11471; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne sumacoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, QCAZ 41244; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne talipes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, EPN 2823. Not drawn at scale.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-108-073-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>This article was greatly improved by comments from Linda Trueb, Franco Andreone and Andrew Gluesenkamp. Initial field work has possible thanks to the project “Evaluación de la Herpetofauna de las Reservas Biológicas de la Fundación Ecominga. Cuenca Alta del Río Pastaza. Ecuador”, executed by the Museo Ecuatoriano de Ciencias Naturales and funded by Fundación Jocotoco and Fundación Ecominga. Research was supported by the projects “Inventario y Caracterización Genética y Morfológica de la Diversidad de Anfibios, Aves y Reptiles de los Andes del Ecuador” and “Diversidad Críptica de los Géneros <italic>Pristimantis, Osornophryne</italic> e <italic>Hypsiboas,</italic>” granted by the Secretaría Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología del Ecuador (PIC-08-0000470) and the Pontificia Universidad Católica del Ecuador, respectively. Universidad Tecnológica Indoamérica supported the final phase of this investigation. For access to collection specimens, we thank the Museo Ecuatoriano de Ciencias Naturales, Museo de Zoología of the Pontificia Universidad Católica del Ecuador, and the Museo de Zoología de la Escuela Politécnica Nacional. Research was conducted under collection permit No. 021–08 IC-FAU-DNBAPVS/MA, issued by Ministerio del Ambiente del Ecuador. Fieldwork at Reserva Zuñac was possible thanks to the collaboration of Lou Jost, Francisco Sornoza M., Rocío and Javier Robayo. MYM thanks Miguél Urgiles, Juan P. Reyes Puig and Andrés Laguna for assistance during field work, and Mauro Yánez C., Joaquín Yánez C., and Alejandra Bejarano for their continuous support. Special thanks go to Elicio Tapia, who found many of the specimens herein reported, Luis A. Coloma and Eduardo Toral for the photographs shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, and Diego Paucar, who rendered most of the figures shown in this article (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Alfaro</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutzoni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Bayes or bootstrap? A simulation study comparing the performance of Bayesian Markov chain Monte Carlo sampling and bootstrapping in assessing phylogenetic confidence.</article-title> <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source> <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>266</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msg028" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1093/molbev/msg028</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocxlaer</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loader</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roelants</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biju</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menegon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Gradual adaptation toward a range-expansion phenotype initiated the global radiation of toads.</article-title> <source>Science</source> <volume>327</volume>:<fpage>679</fpage>-<lpage>682</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1181707" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1126/science.1181707</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cannatella</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> A new genus of bufonid (Anura) from South America, and phylogenetic relationships of the neotropical genera.</article-title> <source>Herpetologica</source> <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>-<lpage>205</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cisneros-Heredia</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gleusenkamp</surname><given-names>AGG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> A new Andean toad of the genus <italic>Osornophryne</italic> (Amphibia: Anura: Bufonidae) from northwestern Ecuador, with taxonomic remarks on the genus.</article-title> <source>Avances en Ciencias e Ingenierías</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>B64</fpage>–<lpage>B73</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coloma</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<source> Morphology, systematics, and phylogenetic relationships among frogsof the genus Atelopus (Anura: Bufonidae).</source> Unpublished PhD dissertation, <publisher-name>The University of Kansas</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Lawrence</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Duellman</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trueb</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<source> Biology of Amphibians.</source> <publisher-name>The Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Erixon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Svennblad</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oxelman,</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Reliability of Bayesian posterior probabilities and bootstrap frequencies in phylogenetics.</article-title> <source>Systems Biology</source> <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>665</fpage>-<lpage>673</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10635150390235485" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1080/10635150390235485</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabrezi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> El carpo de los anuros.</article-title> <source>Alytes</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabrezi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> The anuran tarsus.</article-title> <source>Alytes</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabrezi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alberch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> The carpal elements of anurans.</article-title> <source>Herpetologica</source> <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>-<lpage>204</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gluesenkamp</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> A new species of <italic>Osornophryne</italic> (Anura: Bufonidae) from Volcán Sumaco, Ecuador with notes on other members of the genus.</article-title> <source>Herpetologica</source> <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>268</fpage>-<lpage>279</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gluesenkamp</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<source> Development mode and adult morphology in bufonid frogs: A comparative analysis of correlated traits.</source> PhD thesis, <publisher-name>Texas University</publisher-name>, Austin.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gluesenkamp</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guayasamin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> A new species of <italic>Osornophryne</italic> (Anura: Bufonidae) from the Andean highlands of northern Ecuador.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1828</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Goebel</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atz</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> PCR primers and amplification methods for 12S ribosomal DNA, the control region, cytochrome oxidase I, and cytochrome b in bufonids and other frogs, and an overview of PCR primers which have amplified DNA in amphibians successfully.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>-<lpage>199</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/mpev.1998.0538" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1006/mpev.1998.0538</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Graybeal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Phylogenetic relationships of bufonid frogs and test of alternate macroevolutionary hypotheses characterizing their radiation.</article-title> <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>119</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>-<lpage>338</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.1997.tb00139.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.1096-3642.1997.tb00139.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> An empirical test of bootstrapping as a method for assessing confidence in phylogenetic analysis.</article-title> <source>Systematic Biology</source> <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>182</fpage>-<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoogmoed</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> New <italic>Osornophryne</italic> (Amphibia: Anura: Bufonidae) from the Pacific slopes of the Andes in Ecuador.</article-title> <source>Zoologische MEdedelingen</source> <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>242</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackshields</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chenna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGettigan</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McWilliam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valentin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0.</article-title> <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>2947</fpage>-<lpage>2948</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btm404" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btm404</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Mesquite: a modeular system for evolutionary analysis ver 2.71.</source> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mesquiteproject.org" xlink:type="simple">http://mesquiteproject.org</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mueses-Cisneros</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yánez-Muñoz</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guayasamin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Una nueva especie de sapo del género <italic>Osornophryne</italic> (Anura: Bufonidae) de las estribaciones amazónicas de los Andes de Ecuador.</article-title> <source>Papéis Avulsos de Zoologia</source> <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>279</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Padial</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castroviejo-Fisher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Köhler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilà</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaparro</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De la Riva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Deciphering the products of evolution at the species level: the need for an integrative taxonomy.</article-title> <source>Zoologica Scripta</source> <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>431</fpage>-<lpage>447</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1463-6409.2008.00381.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.1463-6409.2008.00381.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Peracca</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1904</year>)<article-title> Rettili ed amfibii in viaggio del Dr. Enrico Festa nell" Ecuador e regioni vicine.</article-title> <source>Bolletino dei Musei di Zoologia ed Anatomia Comparata della Universitá di Torino</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msn083" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1093/molbev/msn083</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> jModelTest: Phylogenetic Model Averaging.</article-title> <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source> <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1253</fpage>-<lpage>1256</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pramuk</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of South American <italic>Bufo</italic> (Anura: Bufonidae) inferred from combined evidence.</article-title> <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>146</volume>:<fpage>407</fpage>-<lpage>452</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.2006.00212.x" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1111/j.1096-3642.2006.00212.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> Tracer v1.4.</source> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer" xlink:type="simple">http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> MrBayes 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference under mixed models.</article-title> <source>Bioinformatics</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1572</fpage>-<lpage>1574</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btg180" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btg180</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Carranza</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernández-Camacho</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>)<article-title> <italic>Osornophryne</italic> género nuevo de anfibios bufónidos de Colombia y Ecuador.</article-title> <source>Caldasia</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>148</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Shubin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alberch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> A morphogenetic approach on the origin and basic organization of the tetrapod limb.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hecht</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prance</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Evolutionary Biology</source>. <publisher-name>Plenum Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>)<source> Principles of Animal Taxonomy.</source> <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Swofford</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Phylogenetic Analysis Using Parsimony (*and Other Methods) ver 4.0a109.</source> <publisher-name>Sinauer Associates</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Sunderland, Massachusetts</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dyke</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Revised procedures for staining and clearing small fishes and other vertebrates for bone and cartilage study.</article-title> <source>Cybium</source> <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>119</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Trueb</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>)<article-title> Bones, frogs, and evolution.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vial</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Evolutionary Biology of the Anurans.</source> <publisher-name>University of Missouri Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Columbia</publisher-loc>, <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Trueb</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Patterns of cranial diversity among the Lissamphibia.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanken</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>The Skull: Patterns of Structural and Systematic Diversity, Vol. 2.</source> <publisher-name>Chicago University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>, <fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiens</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Speciation and ecology revisited: phylogenetic niche conservatism and the origin of species.</article-title> <source>Evolution</source> <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>197</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiley</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>)<article-title> The evolutionary species concept reconsidered.</article-title> <source>Systematic Zoology</source> <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/2412809" xlink:type="simple">doi:10.2307/2412809</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yánez-Muñoz</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altamirano-Benavides</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cisneros-Heredia</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gluesenkamp</surname><given-names>AGG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Nueva especie de sapo andino del género <italic>Osornophryne</italic> (Amphibia: Bufonidae) del norte de Ecuador, con notas sobre la diversidad del género en Colombia.</article-title> <source>Avances en Ciencias e Ingenierías</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>B46</fpage>–<lpage>B53</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zwickl</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> Genetic algorithm approaches for the phylogenetic analysis of large biological sequence datasets under the maximum likelihood criterion.</source> PhD thesis, <publisher-name>Texas University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
        </ref-list>
    <app-group>
        	<app>
            <title>Appendix I: Examined Specimens.</title>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne angel:</tp:taxon-name></italic> Carchi: El Voladero (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°41'15"N, 77°52'46"W</named-content>), DH-MECN 4617, 4606, 4629–30, 4626, 6079, QCAZ 40030–31, 40040, 40043–49.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne antisana</tp:taxon-name></italic>: Napo: Oyacachi (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°10'34"S, 78°0.6'50"W</named-content>, 3913 m) QCAZ 40172, 40174; Salvefaccha (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°13'54"S, 78°0.1'01"W</named-content>, 3900 m) EPN 8937. Tungurahua: Llanganates (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">1°15'57"S, 78°26'45"W</named-content>, 3600 m), QCAZ 515, 46282, 48231, 46207, 46204–5, 48230, 48487, 48233–36, 48222, 48215, 48217, 48213, 46212.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne bufoniformis</tp:taxon-name></italic>: Carchi: Huaca (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°40'15"N, 77°46'11"W</named-content>, 3780 m) QCAZ 45082–4, 45080–81, 43351; El Chamizo QCAZ 14597–98; Tulcán-Maldonado (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°47'31"N, 77°54'25"W</named-content>, 3817 m) QCAZ 735, 9316–17. Sucumbios: El Playón de San Francisco (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">00°36'44"N, 77°40'13"W</named-content>, 3400–4100 m), DH-MECN 6067–70, 6073, 6079, 6082; La Bonita (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">00°29'19"N, 77°35'11.4"W</named-content>, 2614 m) QCAZ 46640–43; Santa Bárbara (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°38'29.47"N, 77°31'18.55"W</named-content>, 2700 m), QCAZ 40003, 40122, 14080–81, 40118–19.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne cofanorum</tp:taxon-name></italic>: Sucumbios: La Bonita (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°29'19"N, 77°35'11"W</named-content>, 2614 m), DH-MECN 6192, 6194, 6205, 6214, 6219, 6232, 6237, 6243, 6250, 6296–97, 6300, 6303–04, 6315, 6325, 6328, 6334, 6337, 6339.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne guacamayo</tp:taxon-name></italic>: Napo: Cordillera de los Guacamayos (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°37'26.5"S, 77°50'27.09"W</named-content>, 2238 m), QCAZ 3266, 4889, 9894, 12245, 12249, 13260, 12240, 13259, 26047, 26049, 39081, 33197, 10457, 40106, 40111, 10465, 12241, EPN 6822, 6821, 7438, 7806; Oyacachi (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°15'25"S, 77°57'53"W</named-content>, 2253 m), QCAZ 40158, 40169, 40138, 40143, 40160, 40148, 40137; Volcán Sumaco (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°34'11"S, 77°35'39"W</named-content>, 2479 m), QCAZ 41211, 41206, 41210, 41194, 41207, 41229, 41196, 41223, 41203, 41190, 43378, 43370, 43377, 43551–54, 43557, 43550, 43557–59. Sucumbios: Santa Bárbara (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°33'51.4"N, 77°32'50"W</named-content>, 2388 m), QCAZ 46661.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne occidentalis:</tp:taxon-name></italic> Carchi: Chilma Bajo (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°51'50"N, 78°4'01"W</named-content>, 2237 m), QCAZ 40028. Imbabura: Rosario (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°27'29"N, 78°32'50"W</named-content>, 2296 m) QCAZ 36894, 43498, 43649, 43647, 10141, 43652, 43529, 43650, 43646, 43651, 43653. Pichincha: Guarumos (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">00°02'S, 78°39'W</named-content>, 2550–2600 m) EPN 1239.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne puruanta</tp:taxon-name></italic>: Imbabura: Laguna de Puruanta (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">00°12'N, 77°57'W</named-content>, 3000–3500 m) QCAZ 11471, 7685. Pichincha: Laguna de San Marcos (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°7'36"N, 78°15'22"W</named-content>, 3834 m), EPN7081–83, QCAZ 13271.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Osornophryne sumacoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>: Napo: Volcán Sumaco (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°34'11"S, 77°35'39"W</named-content>, 2479 m), QCAZ 41247–50, 41243–54, 41233–34, 43379, 4574.</p>
            </app>
        </app-group>
    </back>
</article>