<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.238.3884</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Two new species of Tornidae (Caenogastropoda, Rissooidea) from Espírito Santo, Brazil</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Simone</surname>
                        <given-names>Luiz Ricardo L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:E66B5424-8F32-4710-B332-F35B9C8B84B0</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de São Paulo. Cx. Postal 42494; 04299-970 São Paulo, SP. Brazil
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Luiz Ricardo L. Simone (<email xlink:type="simple">lrsimone@usp.br</email>, <email xlink:type="simple"> lrlsimone@gmail.com</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: E. Neubert</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>6</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>238</issue>
            <fpage>77</fpage>
            <lpage>85</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>22</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>2</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Luiz Ricardo L. Simone</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:DD490835-3158-46A5-97B1-464D3A1F2761</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Two new species of shallow water <tp:taxon-name>Tornidae</tp:taxon-name> are found in Espírito Santo state, Brazil, formally described herein. They belong to a complex group of tiny gastropods, in such the taxonomy is very confused. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus mohicanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> is characterized by three well-developed spiral, equidistant carinas, working as base of three series of tall, aligned periostracal rods. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcinia itanhuna</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> has as single sculpture a series of pustules in periphery, but the periostracum bears three series of peripheral fringes with irregular rods. The new species are compared with the allies, showing a close relation with Caribbean fauna, but possessing worthy differences. These similarities have raised misidentifications.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Tornidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Caenogastropoda</kwd>
                <kwd>biodiversity</kwd>
                <kwd>coastal waters</kwd>
                <kwd>Espírito Santo</kwd>
                <kwd>Brazil</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The <tp:taxon-name>Tornidae</tp:taxon-name> Sacco, 1896 has also been called <tp:taxon-name>Vitrinellidae</tp:taxon-name> Bush, 1897. They normally are tiny (~2 mm), discoid gastropods living in coastal shallow waters, usually associated with other organisms, such as algae, worm galleries, etc.</p>
            <p>Possibly because of the minute size, the tornids are normally absent in faunal inventories. In collections, the few samples are normally poorly identified, and the draft identification, at least in Brazilian samples, is normally south expansions of North Atlantic or Caribbean species, resulting exceedingly wide distributed species. The <!--PageBreak-->same has reflected in the pertinent literature. This wide distribution contrasts with the minute size and the paucispiral protoconch, both normally indicating short or no planktonic phase, and low dispersion. On the other hand, this supposedly wide distribution does not resist to a close look, in such interesting and important differences appear confronting distant collected samples. This paper is just another example. It deals with two species so far identified as species described from <tp:taxon-name>Florida</tp:taxon-name> and North <tp:taxon-name>Carolina</tp:taxon-name>, which has been extended to Caribbean. However, some significant details have demonstrated that the Brazilian samples actually belong to different, undescribed species.</p>
            <p>The western Atlantic tornid fauna had an important improvement with a recent revision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Rubio et al. 2011</xref>), allowing a better analysis of samples. The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pilsbry &amp; Olsson, 1945 (type species, OD, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vitrinella panamensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> C.B. Adams, 1852, from Caribbean) has a worldwide, tropical distribution. It is mainly characterized by usually carina-bearing shell, normally with secondary sculpture in intervals of carinas, and a wide, opened umbilicus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Pilsbry and Olsson 1945</xref>: 266; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Rubio et al. 2011</xref>: 83). The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mörch, 1875 (type species, M, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Solarium inornatum</tp:taxon-name></italic> d’Orbigny, 1842, from Caribbean), is restricted to Pacific and Atlantic coasts of Americas. It is mainly characterized by serrate peripheral keel, deep umbilicus, and spiral fringes with periostracal filaments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Rubio et al. 2011</xref>: 125). This paper deals with the formal descriptions of two species belonging to these genera, recently collected in sediment sorting by local researchers, as well as confrontation with type specimens.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The studied samples are only empty shells in all kinds of preservation levels, since specimens with periostracum to eroded shells. They are photographed in multi-focus dissecting microscope and in SEM (Laboratório de Microscopia Eletrônica do Museu de Zoologia da USP).</p>
            <p>Abbreviations of institutions are: MNRJ: Museu Nacional da Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro; MZSP, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de São Paulo; USNM, National Museum of Natual History, Smithsonian Institution.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics">
            <title>Systematics</title>
            <sec sec-type="Genus Cyclostremiscus Pilsbry &amp; Olsson, 1945">
                <title>Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pilsbry &amp; Olsson, 1945</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cyclostremiscus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">mohicanus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FF9F3D9C-8BF9-4CAB-A236-8C143BA62A6F</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cyclostremiscus_mohicanus</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–15</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Types">
                        <title>Types.</title>
                        <p>Holotype MZSP 106551 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–5</xref>). Paratypes: 106552, 16 shells from type locality.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality">
                        <title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p>BRAZIL. <bold>Espírito Santo</bold>; São Mateus, Guriri, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">18°47'S, 32°39'W</named-content>, 3 m depth.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Shell of about 2.5 mm; almost planispiral. Three carina-like spiral threads somewhat equidistant; superior surface smooth or with scanty spiral cords. Periphery smooth except threads. Peri-umbilical area with string spiral cords. Periostracum with aligned series of tall rods on spiral threads.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><bold>Shell</bold>. Up to ~2.5 mm, discoid; height ~52% of maximum width (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3, 10, 12</xref>). Color pure white, weakly translucent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2, 5, 6</xref>). Protoconch of 2 whorls, weakly-turbiform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 4, 10, 11, 15</xref>); whorls of rounded profile, suture shallow; surface glossy, smooth; occupying ~10% of shell size; located almost central, weakly dislocated towards right. Transition protoconch-teleoconch unclear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 15</xref>). Spire weakly elevated, with ~45% of shell width; ~15% of shell height. Teleoconch up to 2.5 whorls, uniformly growing weakly planispiral, bearing three somewhat equidistant carinas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 9, 10, 11, 12</xref>); peripheral carina as tallest, profile blunt, ~100°, located in middle level of last whorl, inflating ~15% shell width; inferior carina similar to peripheral carina, located midway between this and peri-umbilical slope (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 10, 12, 13</xref>); superior carina with ~half size as peripheral carina, located midway between this and adjacent suture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 6, 8, 9, 11</xref>); between carinas somewhat planar surface, being weakly elevated in carina’s base. Sculpture superior to peripheral carina absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 11, 14</xref>) to series of narrow, low, obsolete spiral cords (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 6, 8</xref>), varying from zero (surface smooth, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 14</xref>) to ~10 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 8</xref>); interspaces between spiral cords ~1/4 their width; sculpture inferior to peripheral carina absent (smooth). Umbilicum widely opened; maximum diameter ~30% shell width; flanking by strong, somewhat planar slope; sculptured from 1 to 5 spiral cords, with interspaces ~3 times their width (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 5, 7, 12, 13</xref>). Aperture weakly prosocline (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 4, 9, 11, 13</xref>); rounded, weakly pentangular, i.e., bearing somewhat equidistant blunt angles produced by three carinas and umbilical slope (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 10, 12</xref>); with ~35% shell width, ~70% of shell height. Callus practically absent, weakly covering adjacent whorl in apertural implantation.</p>
                        <p>Periostracum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–5</xref>). Opaque, transparent, color pale beige. Series of tall rods aligned on three carinas; rods of peripheral carina augmenting ~10% shell width (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2</xref>), about twice taller than wide, tip rounded, slightly broader than base; rods of superior carina similar to those of peripheral carina, with ~80% of their size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3, 4</xref>); rods of inferior carina also similar to those of peripheral carina, with ~30% their height and ~60% their width (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3, 5</xref>). Each rod blade-like, flexible, located close to each other from same carina, forming tall flexible ridge on each carina. Periostracum ridge on three carinas suddenly finishing at apertural level. On aperture, region between ridge of superior carina and insertion of outer lip in adjacent preceding whorl a small region with ridge of peripheral ridge reabsorbed, forming anal notch with ~1/5 of aperture size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2, 5</xref>).</p>
                        <p><bold>Measurements</bold> (in mm). Holotype: 2.8 by 0.9; paratype 106552 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 10</xref>): 1.7 by 0.8.</p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 1–15.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus mohicanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. types <bold>1</bold> holotype MZSP 106551 (W 2.8 mm), apical view <bold>2</bold> same, umbilical view <bold>3</bold> same, apertural view <bold>4</bold> same, apertural-slightly apical view <bold>5</bold>, same, apertural-slightly umbilical view <bold>6</bold> paratype MZSP 106552 #1, apical view (W 1.8 mm) <bold>7</bold> same, umbilical view <bold>8</bold> #2, apical view (W 1.7 mm) <bold>9</bold> #1, apertural-slightly apical view <bold>10</bold> same, apertural view <bold>11</bold> #3, SEM, apertural-slightly apical view (W 1.7 mm) <bold>12</bold> same, apertural view <bold>13</bold> same, apertural-slightly umbilical view <bold>14</bold> #4, SEM, apical view (W 1.5 mm) <bold>15</bold> same, detail of apical region, scale 0.1 mm.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-238-077-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Only known from type locality.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Habitat">
                        <title>Habitat</title>
                        <p>. Sandy bottoms, 3 m depth (no living specimens).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Types.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion">
                        <title>Discussion.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus mohicanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus beauii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fischer, 1857) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Rosenberg et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Rubio et al. 2011</xref>) from Florida and Caribbean. It differs by the smoother superior surface, lacking so developed spiral cords, the contrary happens in the umbilicum, in such that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus mohicanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a series of spiral cords, while <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus beauii</tp:taxon-name></italic><!--PageBreak--> has only growth lines; the size is also different, as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus mohicanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has about 3 mm, while <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus beauii</tp:taxon-name></italic> reaches 9-10 mm. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus mohicanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> also resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus pentagonus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Gabb, 1873), also from Caribbean, it differs by the more developed spiral sculpture in the superior shell surface, by the peri-umbilical spiral sculpture, in being slightly taller (height/width tax= ~52% against ~48% of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus pentagonus</tp:taxon-name></italic>), and in having the peripheral carina slightly more elevated. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus pentagonus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been referred as occurring in south Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Rios 2009</xref>: 59, in Porto Belo, Santa Catarina; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Rubio et al. 2011</xref>: 91); as that material was not found, this record is here considered doubtful, but possibly they are of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus mohicanus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Another important difference between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus mohicanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus pentagonus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the protoconch, it has ~2 whorls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 15</xref>), while that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus pentagonus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is ~0.5 whorl longer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Rubio et al. 2011</xref>, fig. 46F). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus mohicanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is also somewhat similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus trilix</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Bursh, 1885), sharing the size and the carinas shape; however, it differs from that species in lacking the microtubercles on the protoconch, in having spiral sculpture in surface between suture and superior carina, and in being taller (height/width tax= ~52% against ~42% of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus trilix</tp:taxon-name></italic>).</p>
                        <p>The periostracum bearing expansions are relatively common in living and fresh-died specimens of tornids. However, a periostracum with the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus mohicanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> arrangement appears to be novelty. Nothing like that has been found in other congeneric species. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus mohicanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> clearly belongs to the “group 1” as defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Rubio et al. (2011</xref>: 84), which encompasses carinate species of the genus, with 2 or 3 peripheral carinas. Possibly all carinas of those species are base of periostracal expansions like those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclostremiscus mohicanus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Genus Episcynia Mörch, 1875">
                <title>Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mörch, 1875</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Episcynia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">itanhura</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:154F48BF-4FB0-44B1-B83A-62C1650CB74E</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Episcynia_itanhura</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 16–27</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Episcinia inornata</tp:taxon-name><comment>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Rios 1994</xref>: 59 (fig. 221), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">2009</xref>: 101 (fig. 245) (non d’Orbigny, 1842).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Episcinia inornata</tp:taxon-name><comment> form <italic>“multicarinata”</italic>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Rubio et al. 2011</xref>: 126 (fig. 68D) (non Dall, 1889).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Types">
                        <title>Types. </title>
                        <p>Holotype MZSP 106553 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 16-18</xref>). Paratypes: 106556, 18 shells, MNRJ, 3 shells, USNM, 3 shells, all from type locality.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality">
                        <title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p>BRAZIL. <bold>Espírito Santo</bold>; São Mateus, Guriri, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">18°47'S, 32°39'W</named-content>, 3 m depth.</p>
                        <p><bold><italic>Diagnosis</italic>.</bold> Shell relatively trochoid. Periostracum with 3 series of peripheral fringes constituted of irregular rods. Surface smooth except for peripheral line of pustules. Peripheral carina wanting (profile rounded).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><bold>Shell</bold>. Up to ~2.5 mm, discoid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 18, 24</xref>) to trochiform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 20, 25</xref>); height ~57-68% of maximum width (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 18, 20, 24, 25</xref>). Color white, <!--PageBreak-->weakly translucent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 16–20</xref>). Protoconch of 1 whorl, ~90 µm, weakly-turbiform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 26, 27</xref>); whorl of rounded profile, suture shallow; surface glossy, smooth; occupying ~7% of shell size; located almost central, weakly dislocated towards right (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 17</xref>). Transition protoconch-teleoconch clear, orthocline (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 26, 27</xref>). Spire dome-shaped to elevated, with ~66% of shell width; ~60–64% of shell height. Te<!--PageBreak-->leoconch up to 4 whorls, uniformly growing inferiorly; last whorl with rounded profile, lacking peripheral carina. Sculpture practically absent, except for growth lines looking undulations and aligned set of small pustules located just superiorly to suture and in middle level of past whorl periphery; each pustule rounded, separated from neighboring pustules by space equivalent to half its width; 2 to 4 equidistant, very weak spiral cords present in ~50% of specimens located in superior region of each whorl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 20, 25</xref>); inferior region of body whorl only with growth lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 19, 22</xref>). Umbilicum widely opened; maximum diameter ~30% shell width; flanking by strong, somewhat planar slope, beating only growth lines; weak angulation marking periphery of umbilicum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 19, 23, 24, 25</xref>). Aperture slightly prosocline (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 21, 22, 23</xref>); elliptical (longer axis vertical) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 24, 25</xref>); with ~36% shell width, ~40–43% of shell height. Callus practically absent, weakly covering adjacent whorl in apertural implantation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 21, 23</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Periostracum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 16–18</xref>). Opaque, transparent, color yellowish beige (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 16–18</xref>). Three series of rods running on periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 18</xref>); central fringe running on pustule lines; other 2 fringes running above and below central fringe, distance between fringes equivalent to ~1/3 of whorl height; periostracum rods located on fringes not uniformly distributed and sized; longer rods extending ~10% shell width, weakly coiled, distantly separated from neighbor rods.</p>
                        <p><bold>Measurements</bold> (in mm). Holotype (Fig. 18): 2.0 by 1.1; paratypes MZSP 106556 (Fig. 20)#1: 2.2 by 1.3; (Fig. 24)#5: 2.6 by 1.5; (Fig. 25)#4: 2.5 by 1.6.</p>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 16–27.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia itanhura</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. types <bold>16</bold> holotype MZSP 106553, umbilical view (W 2.0 mm) <bold>17</bold> same, apical view <bold>18</bold> same, apertural view <bold>19</bold> paratype MZSP 106556#1, umbilical view (W 2.2 mm) <bold>20</bold> same, apertural view <bold>21</bold> #2, SEM, umbilical-slightly apertural view (W 2.5 mm) <bold>22</bold> #3, SEM, umbilical view (W 2.1 mm) <bold>23</bold> #4, SEM, apertural-slightly umbilical view (W 2.5 mm) <bold>24</bold> #5, SEM, apertural view (W 2.6 mm) <bold>25</bold> #4, SEM, apertural view <bold>26</bold> #6, SEM, apical view (W 1.0 mm) <bold>27</bold> #6, detail of protoconch (scale 50µm).</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-238-077-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Brazil, from Bahia to São Paulo.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Habitat">
                        <title>Habitat.</title>
                        <p>Sandy bottoms, ~3 m depth (no living specimens collected).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Types. Additional material: MZSP 106571, 90 shells from type locality. BRAZIL. <bold>Bahia</bold>; Salvador, Itapoã beach, MZSP 53439, 1 shell (C.M. Cunha col.). <bold>Rio de Janeiro</bold>; Cabo Frio, MZSP 57159, 2 shells (17/ii/1970). <bold>São Paulo</bold>; off Ubatuba, MZSP 88431, 1 shell (Veliger II, sta. PI-15; 21/i/1986); <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">23°33'978"S, 45°09'821"W</named-content>, 12.3 m depth, MZSP 42087, 1 shell (Biota sta. 145i; 16/iv/2002). N.B. These samples are not part of the type material because of low quality of the shell preservation.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific epithet is derived from the Paritintin word Itanhura’mbi – chain used as necklace (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Betts 1981</xref>), an allusion to the peripheral ornamentation of the shell.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion">
                        <title>Discussion.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia itanhura</tp:taxon-name></italic> is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia inornata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (d’Orbigny, 1842), from Florida and Caribbean, differing in lacking so developed peripheral carina, the profile of each whorl is rounded while that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia inornata</tp:taxon-name></italic> is bluntly pointed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Rubio et al. 2011</xref>, Figs 68B, 69); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia itanhura</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a more developed axial undulation, almost sculpture (e.g., <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 20, 25</xref>), this is rare in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia inornata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, in such the surface is smoother and glossy. The size of the protoconch of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia inornata</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been referred as 190 µm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Rubio et al. 2011</xref>), while that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia itanhura</tp:taxon-name></italic> is about half that size (~90 µm, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 26, 27</xref>). The periostracum rods are organized in 3 fringes in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia itanhura</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 18</xref>), while a single pair is found in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia inornata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Andrews 1971</xref>: 68; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Abbott 1974</xref>: 86). The 3 fringes are also found in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia multicarinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Dall 1889</xref>), from North Carolina <!--PageBreak-->to north Caribbean, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia itanhura</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs in having periostracum rods more sparsely and less uniformly developed, by the deeper suture, and by the straighter profile of spire. The differences between Caribbean and Brazilian specimens have been pointed in literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Rubio et al. 2011</xref>, fig. 68D), however, the differences obviously did not influenced the specific separation. Nevertheless, some doubt still remains in relation to the specimen figures in that paper (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Rubio et al. 2011</xref>), because that illustrated specimen has whorls with almost squared profile, possibly it belong to another undescribed specimen. No specimen with such features has been examined herein. Additionally, there is some uncertainties respect to the possible synonymy between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia inornata</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia multicarinata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Dall 1889</xref>), described from North Carolina. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Dall (1889</xref>: 392-393) clearly stated a specimen with four to five carinas per whorl. This feature is not found in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia inornata</tp:taxon-name></italic> or allied species; this can demonstrate a valid entity. Moreover, Dall still described a more richness of sculpture, a lack of periostracal fringe in peripheral carina, and color yellow, whose can be extra indicative of specific differentiation. Despite further studies are necessary to clarify the question, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia itanhura</tp:taxon-name></italic> cannot be confused with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Episcynia multicarinata</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>A special thanks to the collectors of the specimens, Franklin N. Santos and Joel Braga, and for the donation of the samples. To Lara Guimarães for helping in SEM examination. To Frederico Rubio and Eike Neubert for additional comments on the paper.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbott</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<source> American Seashells, second edition. Van Nostrand Reinhold Company. New York, 663 pp., 240pls.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Altena</surname> <given-names>COvR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1966</year>)<article-title> Vitrinellidae (marine Mollusca Gastropoda) from Holocene deposits in Surinam (Dutch Guiana).</article-title> <source>Zoologische Mededelingen </source> <volume>41</volume> (<issue>16</issue>): <fpage>233</fpage>-<lpage>241</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<source> Sea shells of the Texas coast. University of Texas Press. Austin, 298 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Betts</surname> <given-names>LV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<source> Dicionário Paritintin-Portugues. Sociedade Internacional de Lingüística. Cuiabá, 231 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dall</surname> <given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1889</year>)<source> Reports on the results of dredgings, under the supervision of Alexander Agassiz, in the Gulf of Mexico (1877–78) and in the Caribbean Sea (1879–80), by the U. S. Coast Survey Steamer ‘Blake’. Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology 18: 1–492, pls. 10–40.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pilsbry</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsson</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1945</year>)<article-title> Vitrinellidae and similar gastropods of the Panamic Province. Part I.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia </source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>-<lpage>278</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rios</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<source> Seashells of Brazil. Second edition. Fundação Universidade do Rio Grande. Rio Grande, 368 pp., 113 pls.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rios</surname> <given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Compendium of Brazilian seashells. Universidade Federal do Rio Grande. Rio Grande, 668 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moretzsohn</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>García</surname> <given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Gastropoda (Mollusca) of the Gulf of Mexico.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Felder</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camp</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Gulf of Mexico – Origins, Waters, and Biota.</issue-title> <source>Biodiversity. Texas A&amp;M Press, College Station. Texas</source>: <fpage>579</fpage>-<lpage>699</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubio</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Garcés</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rolán</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> The family Tornidae (Gastropoda, Rissooidea) in the Caribbean and neighboring areas.</article-title> <source>Iberus </source> <volume>29</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>230</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>