<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>

        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>

        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.57.310</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    Descriptions of two new species in the genus 
                        Macrostylis Sars, 1864 (Isopoda,  Asellota, Macrostylidae) from the Weddell Sea (Southern Ocean), with a synonymisation of the genus 
                        Desmostylis Brandt, 1992 with 
                        Macrostylis
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
	
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Riehl</surname>
                        <given-names>Torben</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <aff>
                        Biozentrum Grindel &amp; Zoologisches Museum, Martin-Luther-King-Platz 3, 20146 Hamburg
                    </aff>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:1ED7340B-1448-43BE-8006-C4EE32EE4A65</uri>
                </contrib>
                
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Brandt</surname>
                        <given-names>Angelika</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <aff>
                        Biozentrum Grindel &amp; ogisches Museum, Martin-Luther-King-Platz 3, 20146 Hamburg
                    </aff>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:0FDF2B93-7FEB-42BE-B19F-C1F11F698F09</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>

            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Torben Riehl (<email xlink:type="simple">t.riehl@gmx.de</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Saskia Brix</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>

            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>21</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>57</issue>
            <fpage>9</fpage>
            <lpage>49</lpage>

            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>31</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2009</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>27</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
            </history>

            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Torben Riehl, Angelika Brandt</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:02A04749-3A3A-4443-AA62-9FB15F2C5586</self-uri>

            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Descriptions of <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. and <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. are presented with notes on intraspecific variability and sexual dimorphism. <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. showes differences to <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. in the length of the antenna 2, the shape of the pleotelson and length of uropods.</p>
                <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 1992 (formerly including the two species <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis obscurus</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 1992 and <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2002) is synonymised with the genus <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name>. Based on type material additional remarks and additions to the original descriptions are provided for both species. Results lead to following nomenclatorial changes: <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis obscurus</tp:taxon-name> (Brandt, 1992), comb. n. and <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> (Brandt, 2002), comb. n. A setal nomenclature is proposed and the diagnosis for the family is revised.</p>
            </abstract>
	
            <kwd-group>
		            
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Antarctic</kwd>
                <kwd>deep sea</kwd>
                <kwd>Macrostylis uniformis sp. n.</kwd>
                <kwd>Macrostylis antennamagna sp. n.</kwd>
                <kwd>ANDEEP</kwd>
                <kwd>Janiroidea</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>macrobenthos</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>During recent ANDEEP I–III cruises (ANtarctic benthic DEEP-sea biodiversity: colonization history and recent community patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Brandt et al. 2004</xref>a)), isopods have been found to be an important component of the Southern-Ocean deep sea (in terms of both richness and abundance). Most of the collected isopods belonged to the suborder Asellota Latreille, 1802 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Brandt et al. 2004b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Brandt et al. 2007a</xref>). Among these, the family <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916 showed a remarkable species richness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Brandt et al. 2004</xref>, 2007, Kaiser et al. 2007).</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name> have been suggested to be a specialized endobenthic component of deep-sea macrofauna (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Harrison 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Hessler and Strömberg 1989</xref>). They have been regularly reported from deep-sea samples (e.g. Menzies 1962, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Wolff 1962</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Menzies and George 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Brandt 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Wilson 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Vey and Brix 2009</xref>).</p>
            <p>This taxon consists of two genera: <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name> Sars, 1864 and <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 1992. Species of <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name> have been reported from the Antarctic shelf (<tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2002; 238 m) and deep sea (<tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis obscurus</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 1992; 4335 m). Species of <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name> have been reported from all major marine realms, from near-shore and deeper sublittoral habitats (e.g. <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis spinifera</tp:taxon-name> Sars, 1864 from 27–1761 m) to hadal regions (e.g. <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis mariana</tp:taxon-name> Mezhov, 1993; 10223–10730 m, e.g. deepest isopod record), and thus <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name> has the widest depth range amongst all isopod families (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Tab. 2</xref>).</p>
            <p>To date, 78 valid macrostylid species are known worldwide of which ten occur in the Southern Ocean (Tab. 2). During the ANDEEP cruises at least 33 species of <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name> have been collected, of which 23 where unlike any previously described species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Vey and Brix 2009</xref>). In the current paper, two of these previously unknown species, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis unifomis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. and <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. are described. Based on type material, additions to the original description of <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis obscurus</tp:taxon-name> is presented and close examination of characters led to a rejection of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name>. It has been found synonymous with <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Specimens used for species descriptions were collected at four stations in the northern and south-eastern Weddell Sea during the ANDEEP II–III expeditions with RV Polarstern. These cruises took part in Austral summer 2001/2002 and 2004/2005. An epibenthic sledge was used for sampling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Brenke 2005</xref> and references therein). On board samples were immediately transferred into 96% pre-cooled ethanol and stored at -20° for at least 48 h. Samples were sorted into major groups on board. Sorting of isopods to family level has been continued in the laboratories of the Zoological Museum, Hamburg.</p>
            <p>For habitus drawings and dissections of limbs, specimens were transferred into glycerine. Habitus were photographed in deionized water or glycerine. For identifications and pencil habitus sketches a Leica MZ12.5 with a camera lucida was used (max. 100 ×). Specimens were stained in high-concentration water solution of methylene green or stained glycerine (glycerol with methylene green). Limbs and habitus of small specimens were drawn using a Leica DM 2500 with camera lucida (max. 800 × with phase contrast). For digital photographs a Keyence VHX-500FD digital microscope with two lenses (VH Z20R &amp; VH Z100R) was applied. Limbs were fixed on temporal or permanent slides. Temporal slides were made using stained glycerine. Permanent slides were made using Hydro-Matrix. Pencil drawings were scanned as grayscale PDF. Line drawings were made from pencil drawings and stack photos using Adobe Illustrator and WACOM Intuos digitizer boards following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Coleman (2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">2009</xref>).</p>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <p>Ratios were calculated from measurements made from the line drawings. Measurements were made following the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Hessler (1970)</xref>. They were taken using the distance measurement and cumulative distance measurement tools imbedded in Adobe Acrobat Professional. All appendages´ article-length ratios are given in proximal to distal order, excluding setae. Body lengths are given in anterior-posterior order excluding appendages. Ratios were rounded to first position after decimal point. Only one or two specimens were precisely measured for each description. Thus, a certain number provided here guarantees only to be within an unknown range of variation.</p>
            <p>Terminology is based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Hessler (1970)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Wilson (1989)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Larsen (2003)</xref> with several additions and modifications. Setal nomenclature follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Hessler (1970)</xref> and is updated after <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Larsen (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Garm (2004)</xref>. See also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. Type material examined is listed in Table 1.</p>
            <p>Abbreviations. AMNH - American Museum of Natural History, New York City; NHM- Natural History Museum, London, UK; NMNH - National Museum of Natural History, Washington, D.C.; ZMB - Museum für Naturkunde, Berlin, Germany; ZMH - Zoological Museum Hamburg, University of Hamburg, Germany; ZMUC - Zoologisk Museum, University of Copenhagen, Denmark</p>

            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
	
                <caption><p>1–13 Specialized setae, all articulating infracuticularly, except when mentioned otherwise; 1 Sensilla, pappose seta, shaft densely covered with fringe-like appearing setules; on pereopod 1–3 dactyli 2 broom seta, pedestal pappose seta 3 sensilla, distally pappose seta, densely covered with fringe-like appearing setules, showing a gradual transition from denticles to setules; on distal margins of maxilliped palp and on pereopods 4 tuft seta, a pedestal pappose seta, setule bases closely together, continuous transition to shaft cuticle; only known from distal articulation margin of 5. article in antenna 2 5, 7 simple setae, short 5 on general cuticle and pereopodal basis 6–8, 12 different setal types, on lateral margin of pleopod cavity and operculum 6 plumose seta with few short setules on distal half 8 spine-like unequally bifid seta 12 small pappose seta, with short setules 9 “feather-like” plumose seta like at pleopod 3 apex 10–11 pappose setae, on operculum distal apex and pleopod 2 distal apex 13 simple tubular seta with big apical pore and associated small simple seta, on antenna 1 articles and antenna 2 flagellar articles.</p></caption>
	
                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>

            <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 2.</label>
	
                <caption><p>14–24 Most common pereopodal setae, occurring e.g. on dorsal and ventral margins of all pereopodal articles; 14–16 unequally bifid setae 15, 17, 18–21, 23 serrate setae 22 simple seta, very long and slender 24 bifurcate seta. Lumen indicated by dotted lines where visible in light microscopy. Scale bar = 0.1 mm.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>

            <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Table 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Type material examined for comparison. <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longiremis</tp:taxon-name> (Meinert, 1890) is labelled as <tp:taxon-name>Vana longiremis</tp:taxon-name> Meinert, 1890. <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis obscurus</tp:taxon-name> (Brandt, 1992) and <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> (Brandt, 2002) are labelled as the genus <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name>.</p></caption>
                <table>
	                   <tbody>
	                      <tr>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scientific Name</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Museum no</th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type status</th>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis abyssalis</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40284</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis abyssalis</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40285</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis abyssicola</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-5037</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syntypes</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis abyssicola</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-5038</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syntypes</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis abyssicola</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-5046</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syntypes</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis angolensis</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40280</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis angolensis</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40281</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis bifurcatus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12126</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis bifurcatus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12268</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis bipunctatus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12056</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis bipunctatus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12057</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis bipunctatus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12262</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis bipunctatus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12277</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis bipunctatus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12265</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis caribbicus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12072</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis cerritus</tp:taxon-name> Vey &amp; Brix, 2009</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-41431</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis cerritus</tp:taxon-name> Vey &amp; Brix, 2009</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-41432</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis cerritus</tp:taxon-name> Vey &amp; Brix, 2009</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-41433</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis cerritus</tp:taxon-name> Vey &amp; Brix, 2009</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-41434</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis dellacrocei</tp:taxon-name> Aydogan, Wägele &amp; Park 2001</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMB 27338</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holo- and Paratypes</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis elongata</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU6348</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis galatheae</tp:taxon-name> Wolff, 1956</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU6509</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syntypes</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> (Brandt, 2002) comb. n.</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-39915</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> (Brandt, 2002) comb. n.</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-39916</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis hadalis</tp:taxon-name> Wolff, 1956</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-6647</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis hadalis</tp:taxon-name> Wolff, 1956</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-6648</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macroistylis hirsuticaudis</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12122</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macroistylis hirsuticaudis</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12122A</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macroistylis hirsuticaudis</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12123</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratypes</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longifera</tp:taxon-name> George &amp; Menzies, 1972</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USNM 121743</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-type</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longifera</tp:taxon-name> George &amp; Menzies, 1972</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USNM 121746</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longifera</tp:taxon-name> George &amp; Menzies, 1972</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USNM 121745</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longifera</tp:taxon-name> George &amp; Menzies, 1972</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">USNM 121747</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longipedis</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40278</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longipedis</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40279</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longipes</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-7126</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longispinis</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40286</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longiremis</tp:taxon-name> (Meinert, 1890)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-7131</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syntype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longiremis</tp:taxon-name> (Meinert, 1890)</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-9596</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syntype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis magnifica</tp:taxon-name> Wolff, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-7189</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis meteorae</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40282</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis meteorae</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40283</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis minutus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12059</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis minutus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12060</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis minutus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12203</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratypes</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis minutus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12202</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratypes</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis obscurus</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 1992 comb. n.</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM (NH) 1990:39:1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis robusta</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40277</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis robusta</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40695</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis robusta</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40696</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis robusta</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMH K-40697</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis sarsi</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 1992</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BM (NH) 1990:40:1</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis setifer</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12058</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis subinermis</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-8301</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syntype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis subinermis</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-8302</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syntype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis subinermis</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-8303</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syntypes</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis subinermis</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-8304</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syntypes</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis subinermis</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-8305</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syntypes</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis subinermis</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZMUC CRU-8306</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syntype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis trucatex</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12065</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis vemae</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12074</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Holotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis vemae</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12075</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allotype</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis vemae</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12076</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratypes</td>
                        </tr>
				
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis vemae</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMNH 12204</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paratypes</td>
                        </tr>
			
                    </tbody>
		
                </table>
            </table-wrap>

        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <p>Asellota Latreille, 1802</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916</p>
            
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="family">Desmosomidae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Sars, 1899</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylini</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Hansen 1916 p. 74</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Wolff 1956 p. 99</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
								
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylinae</tp:taxon-name> <comment>Birstein, 1973</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
								
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Gurjanova 1933, p. 411</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Menzies 1962a, p. 28</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">1962b, p. 127</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Wolff 1962</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Menzies and George 1972, p. 79–81</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Wägele 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Brandt 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Birstein 1970</xref>, Kussakin 1999, p. 336; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Mezhov 1988, p. 983–994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">1992, p. 69</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Composition"><title>Composition.</title>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name> Sars, 1864</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type genus"><title>Type genus.</title>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name> Sars, 1864</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Cephalothorax free, about as broad as long. Body elongated. Eyes absent. Antenna 1 small, number of articles variable (1–9). Antenna 2 short or only moderately long, with articles 1–3 together about as long as articles 4 and 5 respectively, squama absent. Mandible with pars molaris reduced, subacute triangular and setiferous on apex; palp absent; lacinia mobilis ambilateral. Maxilliped with long and narrow basis; subtriangular epipod subequal in length to basis; palp articles 1–3 expanded and articles 4–5 minute.</p>
                    <p>Pereonites 1–3 constituting separate subquadrangular section with tightly articulated segments but tergite borders visible: fossosome. Pereonites 4–7 articulated moveably, constricted anteriorly. Pereopods 1–4 fossorial; pereopods 1–3 dactylus with 2 (anterior and posterior) subterminally inserting claws and posterior to both claws with elongated expansion, proximodorsally to claws with 2–3 sensillae, exceeding the distal tip in length. Pereopod 3 most robust, strongly setiferous, ischium extended dorsally, with row of long setae, with 1–2 apical setae strongly pronounced (spine-like, thickened, bent), merus distally extended; orientation of propodus twisted 180° along proximo-distal axis compared to pereopods 1–2, hence, propodus and dactylus bent in dorsal direction instead of ventral. Pereopod 4 shortest, bent laterally at mero-carpal articulation, directed in lateral or laterodorsal position. Posterior pereopod articles elongate subcylindrical. Pereopodal coxae inserted lateroventrally.</p>
                    <p>Coxae 1–3 inserted at anteriolateral margins of pereonites, coxae 4 inserted medially, coxae 5–7 inserted under posterolateral protrusions.</p>
                    <p>Sternite of pleonite 1 distinguishable; pleopodal articulations merged together at anterior margin of branchial cavity; anus subterminally, separated from branchial cavity in longitudinal ventrocaudal excavation stretching from branchial cavity to pleotelson apex. Female operculum oblong, distally with long pappose setae covering anal chamber. Uropods with 1-, 2- or many articles, elongated, terminally articulated, uniramous. Pleotelson with a pair of statocysts.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>G.O. Sars, 1864</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Sars 1864, p.13</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">1899, p. 120</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Beddard 1886b, p. 173</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Hansen 1916, p. 75</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Barnard 1920, p. 411</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Wolff 1956, p. 99–106</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">1962, p. 91–93</xref>; Menzies 1962, p. 127–133; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Birstein 1963a, p. 95–106</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Mezhov 1988, p. 60–69</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Brandt 1992, p. 74–78</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Vey &amp; Brix 2009, p. 358</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Vana</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Meinert 1890, p. 195</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Brandt 1992, p.70, Figs 11–13</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Composition"><title>Composition.</title>
                        <p>See Table 2.</p>

                        <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
	
                            <label>Table 2.</label>
		
                            <caption>
			<p>Composition and distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name> Hansen, 1916.</p></caption>
	
		
                            <table>
			
                                <tbody>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Taxon</th>
                                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Locality</th>
                                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depth (m)</th>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name> G. O. Sars, 1864</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">abyssalis Brandt, 2004</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S Atlantic, Angola Basin</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5389</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">abyssicola Hansen, 1916</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Atlantic, Davis Strait</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">698–3921</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">affinis Birstein, 1963</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Pacific</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4690–5554</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">amplinexa Mezhov, 1989b</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2385–4221</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">angolensis Brandt, 2004</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE Atlantic, Angola Basin</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5395</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">angulata Mezhov, 1999</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE Atlantic</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5420–6051</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">antennamagna sp. n.</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern Ocean, NW Weddell Sea</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4698–4760</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">belyaevi Mezhov, 1989a</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Pacific</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8540–8780</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">bifurcatus Menzies, 1962</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE Atlantic</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4588–4960</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">bipunctatus Menzies, 1962</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW Atlantic</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3954–5024</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">birsteini Mezhov, 1993</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S Pacific</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1200</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">capito Mezhov, 1989b</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2218–4737</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">caribbicus Menzies, 1962</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W Atlantic, Caribbean, Columbia</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2875–941</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">carinifera carinifera Mezhov, 1988</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3074–4458</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">carinifera dilatata Mezhov, 1988</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2540</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cerritus Vey &amp; Brix, 2009</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern Ocean, Weddell Sea</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2149</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">compactus Birstein, 1963</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W Pacific, Bougainville Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6920–7954</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">confinis Mezhov, 2003</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3617</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">curticornis Birstein, 1963</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Pacific</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5680–6670</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">dellacrocei Aydogan, Wägele &amp; Park, 2000</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE Pacific, Atacama Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7800</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">diatona Mezhov, 2004</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6433</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">elongata Hansen, 1916</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Atlantic, Iceland</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1591</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">emarginata Mezhov, 2000</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Atlantic</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5420</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">expolita Mezhov, 2003b</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Indian Ocean, Arabian Sea</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2478–2519</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">foveata Mezhov, 2000</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W Atlantic, Puerto Rico Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5060–6650</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">fragosa Mezhov, 2004</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5410</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">galatheae Wolff, 1956</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W Pacific, Philippine Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8440–10000</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gerdesi (Brandt, 2002) comb. n.</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern Ocean, Maud Rise</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">gestuosa Mezhov, 1993</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W Pacific</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5526</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">grandis Birstein, 1970</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Pacific, Kurile-Kamchatka Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7265–7295</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hadalis Wolff, 1956</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W Pacific, Banda Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7270</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">hirsuticaudis Menzies, 1962</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE Atlantic</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2997</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lacunosa Mezhov, 2003b</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4706–4737</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">latifrons Beddard, 1886</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Pacific</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3749</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">latiuscula Mezhov; 2003b</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4730–4808</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">longifera Menzies &amp; George, 1972</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E Pacific, Peru-Chile Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4823–6134</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">longipedis Brandt, 2004</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S Atlantic, Angola Basin</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5389</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">longipes Hansen, 1916</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Atlantic, Iceland</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">325–1412</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">longiremis (Meinert, 1890)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Atlantic, Skagerrak</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149–228</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">longispinis Brandt, 2004</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S Atlantic, Angola Basin</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5415</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">longissima Mezhov, 1981</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Central Pacific</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6043–6051</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">longiuscula Mezhov, 1981</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Central Pacific</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4400</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">longula Birstein, 1970</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Pacific</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5005–5045</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">magnifica Wolff, 1962</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Atlantic, Davis Strait</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3521</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mariana Mezhov, 1993</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W Pacific</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10223–10730</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">medioxima Mezhov, 2003b</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4458</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">meteorae Brandt, 2004</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S Atlantic, Angola Basin</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5387–5390</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">minuscularia Mezhov, 2003b</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3617</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">minutus Menzies, 1962</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W Atlantic, Puerto Rico Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5163–5494</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">obscurus (Brandt, 1992) comb. n.</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern Ocean, Weddell Sea</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4335</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ovata Birstein, 1970</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Pacific, Kurile-Kamchatka Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6435–6710</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pectorosa Mezhov, 2004</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2807</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">polaris Malyutina &amp; Kussakin, 1996</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arctic Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">325–400</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">porrecta Mezhov, 1988</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6433</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">profundissima Birstein, 1970</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Pacific, Kurile-Kamchatka Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8185–9530</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">prolixa Mezhov, 2003a</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4458</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pumicosa Mezhov, 2004</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2917</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">quadratura Birstein, 1970</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Pacific, Kurile-Kamchatka Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3175–3250</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">rectangulata Mezhov, 1989b</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5220</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">reticulata Birstein, 1963</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Pacific</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5502</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">robusta Brandt, 2004</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S Atlantic, Angola Basin</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5497–5398</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">sarsi Brandt, 1992b</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern Ocean, Weddell Sea</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4335</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">sensitiva Birstein, 1970</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Pacific, Kurile-Kamchatka Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5005–5100</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">setifer Menzies, 1962</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W Atlantic, Puerto-Rico Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5477–5494</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">setulosa Mezhov, 1992</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern Ocean, Scotia Sea</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">757–2705</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">spiniceps Barnard, 1920</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S Atlantic, South Africa</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1280</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">spinifera Sars, 1864</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Atlantic, Norwegian Sea</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27–1710</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">squalida Mezhov, 2000</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Atlantic, Romanche Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6380–6430</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">strigosa Mezhov, 1999</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE Atlantic</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5420</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">subinermis Hansen, 1916</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N Atlantic, Norwegian Sea</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">830–3474</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">truncatex Menzies, 1962</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Atlantic</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3950–3963</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tumulosa Mezhov, 1989</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W Pacific, Izu-Bonin Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8900</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">uniformis sp. n.</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern Ocean, Weddell Sea</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4651–4975</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">urceolata Mezhov, 1989b</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2596</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">vemae Menzies, 1962</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W Atlantic, Puerto-Rico Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5410–5684</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">vigorata Mezhov, 1999</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE Atlantic</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2655–2667</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">vinogradovae Mezhov, 1992</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern Ocean, Weddell Sea</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2705–4335</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">viriosa Mezhov, 1999</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE Atlantic</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4050</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">vitjazi Birstein, 1963</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W Pacific, Bougainville Trench</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6920–7954</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">wolffi Mezhov, 1988</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indian Ocean</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2385–3717</td>
                                    </tr>
				
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">zenkevitchi Birstein, 1963</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Pacific</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4690–6135</td>
                                    </tr>
			
                                </tbody>
		
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>

                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species.</title>
                        <p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis spinifera</tp:taxon-name> Sars, 1864</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>As of the family.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>Some characters are absent or poorly illustrated in original descriptions and could not be analysed thoroughly during this study. Therefore these have not been included in the family diagnosis (e.g. presence of exopod of pleopod 5, setation patterns and setal substructures).</p>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                        <p>Following the original description (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Brandt 1992</xref>), <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name> can be separated from <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name> by the following characters: absence of dorsal triangular expansion on the pereopod 3 ischium, lack of dactylus on pereopod 4 and of claws on pereopods 5–7. However, after comparisons of different species of <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name>, and re-examination of the holotype of <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis obscurus</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 1992 these characters have been found not to be delimitating <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name> from <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name>. Shape and extension of pereopod 3 ischium varies greatly between species of <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name>. For example <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis galatheae</tp:taxon-name> Wolff, 1956 (p. 101, Fig. 17) has a strong and acute extension and no extension is present in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis abyssalis</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2004 (p. 28, Fig. 15), very similar to <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis obscurus</tp:taxon-name>. However, another described species of <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 2002 shows a strongly fossorial pereopod 3 bearing a prominent dorsal extension on the ischium. Thus, the condition of this character in <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name> lies within the interspecific range of variation in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name>. Therefore, this character is not usable to maintain the genus <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                        <p>The absence of a pereopod 4 dactylus was another generic character of <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name>. However, the dactyli in <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis obscurus</tp:taxon-name> are not absent but have been overseen in the original description and they were distorted in the pereopod illustrated of the holotype. The value of differences in setal counts or occurrence of types of setae on pereopod 3 ischium for discriminating between two genera is not known. The genus <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> was erected on basis of a juvenile specimen. Using ontogenetically variable characters of a juvenile type specimen to erect a new genus is problematic.</p>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                        <p>Dactylar setae fit the definition of claws (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Wilson 1989</xref>): terminal/subterminal modified setae on pereopodal dactyli with pronounced sclerotisation and a sharp tip. This definition was to the authors’ knowledge not narrowed since then. Taking into account the incomplete documentation of dactylar claws in the literature on the one hand, and insufficient knowledge about plasticity of setae and their substructures on the other, a differentiation of genera exclusively based on such characters seems problematic. Due to the above listed reasons we consider the genus <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name> synonymous with <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:taxon-treatment>
                        <tp:nomenclature>
                            <tp:taxon-name>
                                <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                                <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">uniformis</tp:taxon-name-part>
		                            <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5105DA6E-E793-42B6-A5D7-A4D9F8C5933A</object-id>
                            </tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                            <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref>
                            <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>
                        </tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                            <p>Holotype. Preparatory female, 4.6 mm long, ZMH (K-42172). South-eastern Weddell Sea southwest of Maud Rise; station ANTXXII-3 59-5 (ANDEEP III; 67°29.81’S; 000°00.23’W); 4651 m depth. Paratypes. 1 paratype, ovigerous female, damaged, ZMH (K-42173) from type locality; 1 paratype female without oostegites fixed for SEM, 3.5 mm, ZMH (K-32174) northern Weddell Sea, station 137 (ANDEEP II; 63°45.00’S; 033°47.81’W), 4975 m depth. For further material examined for comparison see: Table 1.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                            <p>Cephalothorax almost semicircular, little longer than wide with no transverse ridge on frons; antenna 1 minute, incl. aesthetascs not reaching article 4 of antenna 2; mandible with blunt pars incisiva, left lacinia mobilis spiniform, integrated into spine row; dorsal extension of ischium of pereopod 3 positioned much more distally, on apex with 2 conspicious setae, 1 bent robust and spiniform unequally bifid seta proximally, and another more straight and less robust unequally bifid seta distally; posterolateral corners of posterior pereonites rounded; pleotelson compact, not constricted anteriorly of uropod articulations; uropod endopod of half the length of protopod.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description of holotype female"><title>Description of holotype female.</title>
                            <p>Body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>) elongate, 5.3 times longer than wide; maximal body width in pereonite 3 1.2 times maximal width of pleotelson; pereonites 1–5 about the same width, gradually narrowing from pereonite 6 towards pleotelson. Surface of tergites, sternites and operculum bearing comb-like structures, which can be worn off due to abrasion to a smooth surface in exposed areas (e.g. cephalothorax, pereonite 3); posterolateral setae only in pereonite 7, otherwise lacking or broken off; no sockets found in SEM (probably due to dirt on cuticle). Cephalothorax free, almost semicircular with maximal width at posterolateral margin, length 1.1 times maximal width and 0.2 times total body length; 0.9 times width of pereonite 1; no transverse ridge on frons.</p>

                            <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 3.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Holotype ♀, ZMH (K-42172)) digital stack photograph of female holotype; 1 lateroventral view; stained with methylene green H2O solution; colours inverted, greyscale; scale bar = 0.5 mm 2 dorsal view; stained with methylene green H2O solution; colours inverted, greyscale; scale bar = 0.5 mm.</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
	
                                <label>Figure 4.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Holotype ♀, ZMH (K-42172)) A habitus (dorsal view, pereopods and left uropod omitted) B habitus (lateral view), uropods omitted C pleotelson (ventral view).</p></caption>
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>
            
                            <p>Fossosome 1.1 times longer than wide, laterally slightly convex, median length: pereonite 1 about 1.4 times longer than pereonite 2, as long as pereonite 3; lateral length: pereonite 1 1.3 times as long as pereonite 2 and 0.5 times as long as pereonite 3; pereonite with prominent anteroventral spine and pereonite 3 with very small posteroventral spine. Pereonites 4–5 of same length and width, 1.6 times wider than long; pereonite 4 laterally convex, maximal width amid segment. Pereonites 5–7 posterolateral corners tapering, with tiny simple apical setae; pereonites with short posterior ventral spines. Pereonite 6 0.8 times pereonite 4 length, 1.7 times wider than long. Pereonite 7 0.7 pereonite 4 length, 1.9 times wider than long; Pleotelson 1.5 times longer than wide, length about 0.2 times total body length, as long as fossosome and as long as pereonites 5 and 6 together; laterally convex, slightly narrowing towards uropodal articulations with no constriction; apex bluntly rounded with several long setae; compared to rest of body with strongest sculpturation of cuticle; cuticle not translucent, dorsal organ not visible; slot-like apertures in dorsal cuticle not present; pleopodal chamber maximal opening width 0.6 times maximal pleotelson width; longitudinal excavation minimal width about 0.3 times max pleotelson width.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <p>Antenna 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>) of 5 articles, 0.25 times fossosome median length; 2,6 times longer than wide; articles gradually decreasing in size and length-width ratio towards distal end, relative length ratios: 1:0.5:0.3:0.2:0.1; article 1 length 1.4 times of width, 50% of total antenna 1 length, article 5 as long as wide, less than 0.1 times total antenna 1 length; articles 4 and 5 with 1 aesthetasc each; articles 1 and 2 with distal broom setae; simple setae on distal margins of articles 2 and 3, 1 seta on article 5.</p>
                            <p>Antenna 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>) basal five articles reaching the posterior end of cephalothorax; flagellum reaching the anterior margin of pereopod 2 basis when directed posteriorly; article 1 broadest, 1.4 times wider than long, article 2 1.2 times longer than wide and article 3 1.4 times longer than wide, article 4 little narrower than articles 1–3, 4 times longer than wide, article 5 longest 1.1 times article 4, 4.5 times longer than wide; several broom setae distally on basal articles, most on article 5; seven flagellar articles, width about 0.5 times article 5 width.</p>
                            <p>Mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>) gradually narrowing towards pars incisiva; pars incisiva blunt and rounded, without teeth; left lacinia mobilis spine-like, with subtriangular basis in dorsal and medial view and 1 small spine on apex, little shorter than adjacent spine row; right lacinia mobilis tiny with several short spine-like projections; spine row of 5–7 fanned spines, more in left mandible, partially serrated at tips and along proximal margin, especially more proximal ones; pars molaris shorter than adjacent spines of spine row, apex oriented proximally.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->

                            <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 5.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp.n. (Holotype ♀, ZMH (K-42172)) antenna 1; antenna 2 (flagella broken off); left mandible (dorsal and medial view); right mandible (dorsal view); right maxilliped (dorsal view, some setae omitted); right maxilliped (enlarged endite and palp), right maxilla 1 (with inner endite illustrated separately), right maxilla 2.</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>
            
                            <p>Maxilla 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>) inner endite shorter and more slender than outer one, terminally spatulate; dense accumulation of simple setae around distal apex, along a dorsal ridge as well as along medial and lateral margins with setae; outer endite broad, narrowing in the most distal quarter, with numerous setae of different lengths on lateral and medial margins, numerous setae of different lengths around distomedial corner 12 robust setae, some two-sided serrate, on distal margin.</p>
                            <p>Maxilla 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>) inner and outer endites of similar width, equally projecting distally; medial endite thinner and shorter; along proximedial margin of inner endite more than 15 long simple setae of less than half the length of inner endite, an accumulation of about 10 small and intermediate simple setae distolaterally, on distal margin 7 strong setae, some heavily denticulate, medial endite with few simple setae along lateral and medial margins, distally with 3 simple setae of different lengths, longest seta less than half as long as the medial endite; outer endite with simple setae around lateral margin, distally with four robust setae of different lengths the most lateral one longest and one-sided denticulate.</p>
                            <p>Maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>) epipod 3.6 times longer than wide, distally narrowing to multiple small tips, with tiny setae or setules, laterally concave, reaching midlength of palp article 3; endite medially thickening, proximomedially with two coupling hooks, distally with heavily sclerotized and denticulate tooth-like setae and fine dense setae; row of setae along rounded distolateral margin, lateral margins of basis and palp articles 1–3 with rows of thin setae; article 2 largest and longest, 3.5 times longer than article 1 and 2.3 times longer than article 3; articles 4 and 5 distomedially and distolaterally with medially scaled and distally pappose sensillae: 3 medially and 1 laterally on article 2, 5 medially and 2 laterally on article 3, 3 medially and 1 laterally on article 4, article <!--PageBreak-->5 with 6 such setae terminally and subterminally; basis including endite 0.9 times epipod length.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->

                            <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 6.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (♀) pereopods 1–3 (PI–III; 0.3 mm scale) of preparatory female (holotype, ZMH (K-42172); left side) and ovigerous female (paratype, ZMH (K-42173, right side); with dactylus of pereopod 3 enlarged (0.1 mm scale).</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>
            
                            <p>Anterior pereopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>) slightly increasing in length, pereopod 1 0.9 times length of pereopods 2 and 3 respectively; all articles covered with tiny setules of varying density of coverage.</p>
                            <p>Pereopod 1 relative length ratios: 1:0.6:0.4:0.4:0.3:0.2, basis with at least 3 broom setae and 1 short simple seta dorsally and 2 broom setae and row of 5 short setae ventrally, 3.6 times longer than wide; ischium 2.4 times longer than wide, with row of 4 long and slender setae distally, 1 seta on the opposite side, 1 short distally pappose sensilla ventrally, 1 short seta proximodorsally; merus compact, 1.4 times longer than wide, posteriorly on dorsal extension with row of 4 simple setae of different length and 1 bifurcate setae, along ventral margin 4 distally pappose setae and on distoventral extension 1 stout bifurcate seta; carpus 2.3 times longer than wide, distodorsally with row of 2 simple setae and 1 bifurcate seta most distally, 1 broom seta on distoventral margin, ventral margin with four distally fringed setae; propodus 3.4 times longer than wide, dorsally with 1 short setae, ventral side with 3 short sensillae, caudally with 1 long and slender seta; dactylus 3 times longer than wide, about 0.7 times carpus length, with 1 sensilla on dorsal and ventral side respectively.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <p>Pereopod 2 1.1 times longer than pereopod 1; setation comparable to pereopod 1 with slight variations in length and numbers; relative length ratios: 1:0.7:0.5:0.6:0.4:0.3, basis 3.1 times longer than wide; ischium 2.6 times longer than wide; merus 1.8 times longer than wide, with row of 5 distally serrate setae; on the anterior side of distodorsal extension with 1 robust unequally bifid seta; carpus 2.8 times longer than wide, distodorsally with row of 5 long setae, first 4 of this setae distally serrate, most distal one bifurcate, 1 broom seta; propodus 4.5 times longer than wide, 1 broom seta and terminally expanded to subtriangular lobe dorsally with two notches at apex; dactylus 5 times longer than wide, anterior and posterior claw of about the same length, slender posterior extension clasping, reaching beyond claws.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <p>Pereopod 3 1.1 times longer than pereopod 2, with bigger dorsal and ventral extensions and generally longer and more robust setae, relative length ratios: 1:0.7:0.7:0.8:0.3:0.3, basis damaged in holotype, 3.3 times longer than wide in paratype, with at least 2 broom setae and 3 short setae on ventral side, with 2 small setae on dorsal margin; ischium 1.8 times longer than wide, dorsal extension with concave flanks, with 3 serrate setae proximally and 2 distally of apex, on apex with 2 pronounced unequally bifid setae; proximal seta very robust and bent proximally; 1 seta bent towards proximal hollow of ischium articulation; merus about 2 times longer than wide with distodorsal and distoventral extensions, with row of 7 serrate setae dorsally, the most distal seta bifurcate and robust, along ventral margin with 7 distally pappose, fringed setae; carpus 3 times longer than wide, distodorsally with row of 7 serrate setae, most distal seta bifurcate, with 1 broom seta and 6 distally pappose, fringed setae ventrally; propodus 4.3 times longer than wide, distodorsally with 2 sensillae and 1 broom seta ventrally; dactylus long and slender, 6 times longer than wide, as long as carpus, with 1 proximal, 2 medial and 3 subterminal sensillae, claws as in pereopod 2.</p>
                            <p>Posterior pereopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>; pereopods 6–7 of paratype missing) length ratios: 1:1.4:1.9:1.7.</p>

                            <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 7.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Holotype ♀, ZMH (K-42172)) pereopods 4–7 (PIV–VII; 0.3 mm scale); pereopod 4 dactylus enlarged (0.1 mm scale).</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <p>Pereopod 4 about 0.6 times the length of pereopod 1, relative length ratios: 1:0.5:0.4:0.3:0.2:0.1, basis 3.7 times longer than wide with at least 4 broom and 2 short simple setae; ischium 2.9 times longer than wide, distodorsally with row of 3 setae and 1 tiny seta distoventrally; merus 1.9 times longer than wide, distodorsally expanded and with 4 setae of very different lengths, first 3 longer than carpus, serrate, the most distal one smaller, 2 distally pappose, fringed setae on ventral margin; carpus 2.2 times longer than wide, anterior-posteriorly flattened, and 3 times broader than propodus, dorsally extended with row of 4 long serrated, bifurcate setae reaching beyond dactylus tip, distodorsally with broom seta, on ventral margin with 4 distally pappose, fringed setae; propodus distally projecting into a subtriangular lobe, 3.5 times longer than wide, distoventrally with 1 long bifurcate and terminally fringed seta projecting beyond dactylus tip, 1 broom seta distally on dorsal side; dactylus of half propodus length, twice as long as wide, 1 short terminal claw, 1 subterminal claw of 0.5 times dactylus length, with 1 long thin seta subterminally and 2 sensillae.</p>
                            <p>Pereopod 5 0.9 times pereopod 1 length, relative length ratios: 1:0.6:0.5:0.5:0.4:0.2, basis broad, 2.9 times longer than wide with at least 3 broom setae dorsally, 2 broom setae and 3 small setae ventrally, 1 large simple seta distoventrally; ischium 2.3 times longer than wide, on dorsal and ventral side with 2 simple setae respectively; merus about 1.8 times longer than wide, distodorsally extending with 1 bifurcate and 1 long seta, with 2 tiny and 2 long setae on ventral side, longer seta longer than merus; carpus 2.6 times longer than wide,  wide, ventrally with 1 stout bifurcate seta, articulation to propodus surrounded by 5 bifurcate setae, 1 broom seta and ventrally with 3 long and slender simple setae, longest seta exceeding propodus in length; propodus 5 times longer than wide, with 1 short bifurcate seta ventrally, distally with 2 setae on ventral side, the longest more than 2 times dactylus length, 1 broom seta dorsally; dactylus 2 times longer than wide, half propodus length, with 2 setae ventrally of more than 2 times dactylus length, with 2 short claws, 0.7 times dactylus length; at least 2 thin subterminal sensillae.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <p>Pereopod 6 1.2 times pereopod 1 length, relative length ratios: 1:0.6:0.4:0.7:0.7:0.4, basis 4.3 times longer than wide, dorsally with 3 short setae and 3 broom setae, ventrally with 4 broom setae and 4 short setae; ischium 2.7 times longer than wide, dorsally slightly projecting with row of 7 long setae, ventrally with 2 setae and distoventrally with a group of 3 simple setae of different lengths; merus short and broad, 1.8 times longer than wide, distodorsally extending with 6 setae, the longest exceeding carpus, some denticulate or bifurcate, with row of 6 setae on ventral side; carpus slender, 4.4 times longer than wide, dorsally with row of 3 short setae and 1 broom seta, 2 simple setae ventrally, distally 4 robust, bifurcate and one-sided serrate setae and 2 slender setae, longer than propodus; propodus 7.6 times longer than wide, along ventral margin with 2 groups of 1 short bifurcate and 1 slender seta each; dactylus 6 times longer than wide, with 2 small sensillae on anterior side, with 2 very long simple setae along ventral margin, with terminal claw as long as dactylus and 1 subterminal claw, 1.7 times longer than dactylus.</p>
                            <p>Pereopod 7 1.1 times longer than pereopod 1, relative length ratios: 1:0.6:0.4:0.8:0.9:0.4, basis 4.1 times longer than wide, dorsally with 9 simple setae as well as 2 broom setae, ventrally with 4 broom setae and 6 simple setae of different lengths as well as 1 broom seta; ischium 3.2 times longer than wide, dorsally with row of 6 long simple setae, ventrally with 5 simple setae; merus 2 times longer than wide, distodorsally extending with 6 long setae, on the ventral margin with 1 simple and 1 serrate seta; carpus slender, 5.7 times longer than wide, dorsally with 2 bifurcate setae and a broom seta distally, a group of serrate setae on ventral margin, mero-carpal articulation surrounded by 6 short, robust, bifurcate and one-sided serrate setae; propodus slender, 9 times longer than wide, 4 setae ventrally, the two proximal ones serrate and very long; dactylus 3.8 times longer than wide, with 1 intermediate and 1 long seta of 2 times dactylus length on ventral side, with 2 claws of different lengths and 1 sensilla on apex.</p>
                            <p>Pleopods 2–4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). Presence of pleopod 5 could not be clarified for both specimens. Relative length ratios: 1:0.8:0.6; operculum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>) 0.7 times pleotelson length. Operculum covered ventrally with small setules and setae, along proximolateral margins with plumose setae with few short setules, distally with at least 8 pappose setae, several setae broken off and substructures not reconstructable. Pleopod 3 protopod constituting half of total length, rhomboid shape, endopod as wide as protopod, not considerably narrowing distally, with 3 distally plumose setae of 0.4 times pleopod 3 length, exopod 0.7 times total length, proximally about 0.7 times maximal width of endopod, distally narrowing, with 1 pronounced seta subterminally, row of numerous simple setae laterally. Pleopod 4 endopod long oval, 0.8 times total length; protopod as long as wide; exopod thin and long, 0.6 times total length and 7.7 times longer than wide, distal seta broken off and missing.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->

                            <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 8.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Holotype ♀, ZMH (K-42172)) operculum (Op; ventral view); pleopods 3–4 (PlIII–PlIV, ventral view); uropod (Urp).</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <p>Uropod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>) of 2 articles, about half pleotelson length, protopod 5.5 times longer than wide, endopod 0.5 times protopod length, protopod with at least 1 broom seta distally, and endopod with at least 4 broom setae distally next to 3 very long and 3 short simple setae.</p>
                            <p>Male unknown.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Intraspecific variations in pereopods"><title>Intraspecific variations in pereopods.</title>
                            <p>(Numerals in brackets and italics are variations in the ovigerous female, paratype).Pereopod 1 ischium 2.4 (3.2) times longer than wide, with row of 4 (3) setae distally. propodus 3.4 (2.8) times longer than wide; dactylus 3 (3.7) times longer than wide. Pereopod 2 basis 3.1 (3.7) times longer than wide; ischium 2.6 (3.2) times longer than wide; merus with row of 5 (6) setae; carpus distodorsally with row of 5 (6) long setae; propodus 4.5 (4) times longer than wide; dactylus 5 (5.5) times longer than wide.</p>
                            <p>Pereopod 3 ischium with 3 (4) setae proximally; merus with row of 7 (9) setae dorsally, along ventral margin with 7 (8) setae; carpus distodorsally with row of 7 (8) serrate setae, with 6 (7) setae ventrally. Pereopod 4 basis 3.7 (4.3) times longer than wide; ischium 2.9 (2.4) times longer than wide; merus 1.9 (2.4) times longer than wide; carpus 2.2 (2.8) times longer than wide; propodus 3.5 (3) times longer than wide. Pereopod 5 basis 2.9 (5) times longer than wide; ischium 2.3 (3) times longer than wide; carpus 2.6 (3.1) times longer than wide, propodus 5 (4.4) times longer than wide.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                            <p>“Uniformis” is derived from the latin word for “uniform” as this species’ female on the first view resembles a most common macrostylid appearance and is hard to distinguish from other species.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                            <p>Only known from the type locations: Southern Ocean, northern and south-eastern Weddell Sea, 4651–4975m depth.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                            <p>Analysis of two specimens from different station reveals little variation. Differences in body shape and limb segments are usually too subtle to be detected in visual inspection. Variation in setal count tends to be allometric in the pereopods (compare <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Hessler 1970</xref> for <tp:taxon-name>Desmosomatidae</tp:taxon-name>). Variation was observed in pereopod 3 in setal counts on ischium, merus and carpus, but none in length-width ratios. Setal variation also occurs in pereopod 1 ischium as well as pereopod 2 merus and carpus. In all cases, the number of setae is increased by one or two per row in the female paratype. In pereopods 1, 2 and 5 length-width ratios of all articles are increased or identical in the ovigerous female except for the propodus. The strong variation in pereopod 4 has to be treated carefully, as the articles are flattened and in the appendage contortions along the proximo-distal axis limit comparability between both specimens.</p>
                            <p>In the shape of the cephalothorax and lateral pleonite borders as well as the pleotelson apex <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. closely resembles that of <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis hadalis</tp:taxon-name> Wolff, 1956, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis zenkevitchi</tp:taxon-name> Birstein, 1963 and <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longifera</tp:taxon-name> Menzies &amp; George, 1972. <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. also shares the small subtriangular lacinia mobilis and the minute pars molaris with <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis hadalis</tp:taxon-name>. They can be separated by bicusp and acute pars incisiva in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis hadalis</tp:taxon-name> (blunt and rounded in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.) and the smaller relative length of the antenna 2 compared to the antenna 1 in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis hadalis</tp:taxon-name>. <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis zenkevitchi</tp:taxon-name> has more acute posterolateral corners of the posterior pereonites than found in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. The mandible of <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis zenkenvitchi</tp:taxon-name> has incisors with 3 blunt teeth and a strong lacinia mobilis (incisor without teeth, blunt and rounded, lacinia mobilis spine like and integrated into spine row in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.). From <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longifera</tp:taxon-name> it can be distinguished by the pronounced posterolateral setae in pereonites 3–7 (no or tiny posterolateral setae in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.) and in the stretched posterolateral protrusions of the posterior pereonites in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longifera</tp:taxon-name> (protrusions subtle in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.). The paratype female has damage on the pereon and exact measurements could not be taken. Nevertheless, length and width data from the anterior subsection indicate a high similarity in length and the ovigerous female being less wide in these pereonites.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <p>No male specimen of this species could be identified and the male identity therefore remains unknown.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                    </tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:taxon-treatment>
                        <tp:nomenclature>
                            <tp:taxon-name>
                                <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                                <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">antennamagna</tp:taxon-name-part>
		                            <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:5B09C3B7-6291-458D-BC5E-975BCBD39D80</object-id>
                            </tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                            <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9</xref>
                            <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18</xref>
                        </tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                            <p>Holotype. Adult male, 3.4 mm, ZMH (K-42168), Southern Ocean, North-western Weddell-Enderby Abyssal Plain, south of the South Orkney Islands, station 110-8 (ANDEEP III), 64°59.20’S; 043°002.05’W, 4698 m depth. Paratypes. 1 preparatory female, 4.7 mm, ZMH (K-42169) and 1 adult male ZMH (K-42169) from type locality; 1 male , 3.1 mm, ZMH (K-42171); 1 male fixed for SEM, 2.8 mm, ZMH (K-42172) Southern Ocean, northern Weddell Sea abyssal plain, south of the Endurance ridge, station 138-6 (ANDEEP II), 64°1.67’S; 39°7.68’W, 4760 m depth. For further material examined for comparison see Table 1.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                            <p>Cephalothorax semicircular, antenna 2 long, basal 5 articles pronounced, flagellum reaching to the posterior end of pereonite 3 when bent backwards, little shorter in female; mandible flat, dorsoventrally constricted proximally to laciniae; pars incisiva without pronounced or sharp teeth but bump-like structures; dominant setae on pereopods of bifurcate type; setation pattern on male pleopod 1 mostly not symmetrical, distolateral lobes of pleopod 1 projecting less distally than medial lobes, bent laterally (~90°) and ventrally, medial lobes rounded, each with 7 setae.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description holotype male"><title>Description holotype male.</title>
                            <p>Body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>) elongate, 5.3 times longer than wide; maximal body width in pereonites 2 and 3, maximal pereonite width 1.5 times maximal width of pleotelson; pereonites 1–3 about the same width, from pereonite 3 towards pleotelson slightly but gradually narrowing, pereonite 7 0.8 times as wide as pereonite 3. Surface of body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref>) bearing comb-like structures which can be worn off in exposed areas, e.g. posterolateral protrusions, cephalothorax or dorsal surface of pereonite 3; numerous small simple setae and setules on general cuticle; pereonites 3–7 unsymmetrical with respect to number and length of 1–2 posterolateral setae. Cephalothorax almost semicircular, length 0.7 times maximal width posteriorly to antenna 2 articulation and less than 0.2 times total body length; width 0.9 times pereonite 1 width; transverse ridge on frons not recognized. Fossosome 0.2 times total body length; as long as wide, laterally slightly convex; median legth: 1:1:1.3; frontal spine in sternite of pereonite 1, dorsoventral constrictions close to the segment borders of pereonites 2–3. Posterior pereonites anteriorly strongly constricted; anterior margins overlapped by preceding tergite; relative medial lengths of pereonites 4–7: 1:1.2:1.4:1.2; laterally concave. Posterolateral parts of tergites slightly tapered backwards; pereonites 5–7 with ventral spines directed posteriorly. Pleotelson 0.2 times body length; about 1.7 times longer than wide, laterally concave, narrowing towards a constriction anterior to uropodal articulations; caudal apex concave surrounded by setules; compared to rest of body, most prominent sculpturation of cuticle, shingle-like appearance; cuticle slightly translucent, statocysts visible; slot-like apertures in dorsal cuticle; breathing cavity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15</xref>) maximal opening width 0.7 times maximal pleotelson width, narrowest width of longitudinal excavation 0.2 times maximal pleotelson width.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->

                            <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 9.</label>
	
                                <caption><p>Top: <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Holotype ♂, ZMH (K-42168)) digital stack photograph; stained with methylene green H2O solution, greyscale; below: <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (♀) digital stack photograph of pleotelson with operculum, ventrocaudal excavation and anus (ventral view).</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 10.</label>
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Holotype ♂, ZMH (K-42168)) A lateral view, pereopod 3 broken off, uropods omitted B dorsal view anterior C dorsal view, AII and pereopods omitted, anterior part flexed.</p></caption>
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <p>Antenna 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 10</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>) with 5 articles, small, barely reaching halfway to posterior margin of cephalothorax when directed backwards; length 2.6 times article 1 width; all articles about as long as wide, gradually decreasing in size towards distally; fifth article 0.1 times total length; at least 4 aesthetascs on each of articles 4 and 5, some broken off; broom setae around distal margin of article 2; some distally fringed sensillae on distal margins of articles 1–3; with 1 seta distally on article 5, next to aesthetascs.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <p>Antenna 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>) relatively long and broad, peduncle reaching to the posterior end of pereonite 2 and flagellum reaching to the posterior end of pereonite 3; each of articles 1–3 1.4 times longer than wide; article 4 longest, length 0.3 times total length, as wide as articles 1–3; article 5 0.8 times article 4 length, about 0.4 times article 4 width; flagellum of 7 articles; all 5 basal articles with 1–several distal broom setae (not shown in illustration) and some simple setae; tubular setae with large apical pores distally on flagellar articles 1–4 ans 7, articles 1–3 with 3 setae each, articles 4 and 7 with 2; article 7 with long simple distal setae, 3 times longer than article.</p>
                            <p>Mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig 11</xref>) flat, dorsoventrally constricted proximally to lacinia; pars incisiva without teeth, but bump-like structures, left mandible with 1 terminal, 1 ventral and 2 dorsal cusps, right mandible with a centered lobe-like cusp; left lacinia mobilis longer and more robust than right lacinia mobilis, with 4 strong blunt teeth, 1.5 times longer than following spines of spine row; right lacinia mobilis twice as long as following spines of spine row, with 6 teeth, more acute than in left lacinia mobilis, dorsoventrally arranged, with ventral teeth projecting most distally; spine row of about 8 spines with multiple cusps, partially serrated; Maxilla 1 and 2: see description of female paratype.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->

                            <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 11.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Holotype ♂, ZMH (K-42168)) left antenna 1; left antenna 2; right antenna 2 enlarged last flagella article; left mandible (dorsal and medial view); right mandible (dorsal and medial view); left maxilliped (dorsal view, some setae omitted); left maxilliped (enlarged endite).</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <p>Maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11</xref>) epipod oblong-subtriangular, distally narrowing to multiple small tips, distolaterally concave, without any setae or setules, reaching distal end of palp article 2; endite with 2 coupling hooks, densely covered with fine but rather long simple setae, medially broadening, more proximally and dorsally forming lobe-like protrusion with 4 setae on lateral blunt apex, together constituting a sheath in which the epipod rests; lateral margins of basis, and palp articles 1–2 with row of small setae, basis and epipod subequal in length; palp article 2 3 times longer than article 1, articles 2–4 distomedially and distolaterally with medially scaled and distally pappose (fringed) sensillae, article 5 with the same setae terminally and subterminally.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <p>Anterior pereopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12</xref>) length ratios: 1:1.1:1.1, all articles covered with tiny setules of varying density of coverage.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->

                            <fig id="F12" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 12.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Holotype ♂, ZMH (K-42168)) pereopods 1–3 (PI–III; 0.3 mm scale) with dactyli enlarged (0.1 mm scale).</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g012.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <p>Pereopod 1 relative length ratios: 1:0.5:0.4:0.3:0.4:0.2, basis 3.8 times longer than wide, with 4 broom setae and 1 short simple seta on dorsal side, 3 short simple setae and 1 broom seta ventrally,; ischium 2.3 times longer than wide, with 2 setae distodorsally and 1 small seta distoventrally; merus almost 1.4 times longer than wide, with distodorsal extension bearing 4 unequally long setae; carpus 2.4 times longer than wide, distodorsally with 1 bifurcate seta and 1 broom seta, 3 setae ventrally; propodus 3.5 times longer than wide, dorsally with 2 short setae, ventral side with 3 sensillae, terminally expanded to a subtriangular lobe; dactylus 4.6 times longer than wide, 0.7 times the length of carpus, with 7 sensillae of different lengths.</p>
                            <p>Pereopod 2 relative length ratios: 1:0.6:0.3:0.5:0.2:0.2, basis with 3 broom setae dorsally and row of short setae ventrally, 4.2 times longer than wide; ischium 3.1 times longer than wide, with 1 small seta bent backwards proximodorsally, row of 4 long simple setae distodorsally and 1 small seta distoventrally; merus 1.5 times longer than wide with distodorsal extension bearing row of 4 long simple setae; carpus 2.6 times longer than wide, distodorsally with row of 4 long setae, most distal one bifurcate, with 4 unequal simple setae ventrally; propodus 3 times longer than wide, dorsally with 2<!--PageBreak--> simple setae, with 1 broom seta dorsally, terminally expanded to a subtriangular lobe; dactylus 5.2 times longer than wide, subterminally with 3 sensillae.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <p>Pereopod 3, relative length ratios: 1:0.6:0.8:0.7:0.3:0.3, basis 2.9 times longer than wide with at least 3 broom setae, row of short setae on ventral side; ischium 1.8 times longer than wide, dorsal extension strongly expanded, sub-triangular, with 7 robust setae, apical 2 setae bifurcate, about as long as maximum ischium width, proximal 2 and distal 3 setae simple, but slightly increasing towards apex, proximodorsally 1 short seta, bent and directed towards proximal hollow of ischium articulation; merus twice as long as wide with weak distoventral extension and strong distodorsal extension bearing 6 bifurcate setae of similar length, 1.4 times maximal merus width, furcation not observed in most proximal seta of row, 4 simple setae ventrally; carpus 2.8 times longer than wide, distodorsally with 5 bifurcate setae and 1 broom seta, with 4 simple setae ventrally; propodus of 0.4 times carpus length, 3.6 times longer than wide, distoventrally with 1 simple and 1 broom seta, distodorsally with sensilla; dactylus 5.5 times longer than wide, 1.1 times carpus length, with 4 sensillae of different lengths arranged in 2 pairs on opposite sides.</p>
                            <p>Posterior pereopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13</xref>) length ratios: 1:1.7:2.3:1.9.</p>

                            <fig id="F13" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 13.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Holotype ♂, ZMH (K-42168)) pereopods 4–7 (PIV–VII); pereopod 4 dactylus enlarged.</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g013.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <p>Pereopod 4 0.6 times pereopod 2 length, relative length ratios: 1:0.4:0.3:0.3:0.2:0.1, basis 3.9 times longer than wide, with at least 4 broom setae; ischium twice as long as wide, with 2 short and 2 long setae; merus about 1.8 times longer than wide, row of 3 setae of same length as merus, most distal seta bifurcate, with 1 simple seta distally on opposite side of the article; carpus 3 times longer than wide, 1.3 times longer than merus, setation similar to merus but most proximal seta of row with bifurcation, and 1 very long bifurcate seta, almost reaching distal tip of propodus; with 1 very long bifurcate seta reaching the tip of the most distally reaching seta of propodus, projecting beyond all setae of dactylus; propodus distally projecting into a subtriangular lobe, 2.3 times longer than wide, distally with 1 long simple seta and 1 robust and acute seta; dactylus very small, twice as long as wide, about 0.4 times<!--PageBreak--> propodus length, with 1 terminal bifurcate claw of 1.3 times dactylus length and 1 subterminal claw of 0.5 times dactylus length, with 1 thin terminal seta of intermediate length.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <p>Pereopod 5 as long as pereopod 2, relative length ratios: 1:0.6:0.4:0.6:0.5:0.2, basis 4.1 times longer than wide with at least 6 broom setae dorsally, 2 rows with 5 small, acute and distally directed setae respectively, arranged dorsally and ventrally, with 1 large simple seta distoventrally; ischium 2.3 times longer than wide, with 2 setae dorsally, 2 groups of 3 closely together articulating setae, 1 group medioventrally and 1 group distoventrally; merus 1.8 times longer than wide, distodorsally extending with 1 simple and 1 very long bifurcate seta of 1.1 times merus length, with 3 setae ventrally; carpus 2.5 times longer than wide, ventrally with 3 setae and distoventrally with 3 setae, the strongest of which is bifurcate; propodus 3 times longer than wide, distodorsally projecting into an acute subtriangular lobe, with 2 simple setae distodorsally and 2 on the opposite side, 3 setae ventrally, articulating closely together; dactylus small, 3.7 times longer than wide, of half propodus length, 2 claws, terminal claw of 0.4 times dactylus length, subterminal claw of 0.3 times the length of dactylus, with 1 thin subterminal seta ventrally.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <p>Pereopod 6 1.3 times pereopod 2 length, relative length ratios: 1:0.6:0.4:1:0.7:0.2, basis 3.9 times longer than wide, setation as in pereopod 5 except no setae dorsally; ischium 2.4 times longer than wide, with 5 setae dorsally, 9 setae in 3 groups ventrally; merus about 2.3 times longer than wide, distodorsally extending with 4 unequal setae, the longest little longer than the article and bifurcate, 2 groups of setae ventrally; carpus elongated, as long as basis, 7.7 times longer than wide, dorsally with 1 seta and 1 broom seta, with 1 simple and 1 bifurcate seta distodorsally, ventrally with 3 robust bifurcate setae and distoventrally with a group of 3 bifurcate setae of varying lengths; propodus slender, 6.8 times longer than wide, distodorsally projecting into an acute subtriangular lobe, 2 bifurcate setae ventrally and 2 distoventrally, the longest one 1.5 times longer than dactylus; dactylus 5 times longer than wide, 0.3 times propodus length, with a terminal claw of 1.4 times dactylus length and a subterminal claw less than half as long.</p>
                            <p>Pereopod 7 1.1 times longer than pereopod 2, relative length ratios and setation similar to pereopod 6 except basis without broom setae, but dorsally with row of more than 25 simple setae of twice the length of basis width and a ventral row of at least 5 simple setae.</p>
                            <p>Pleopods 1–4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14</xref>) relative length ratios: 1:0.9:0.6:0.4. Operculum of 0.7 times pleotelson length, opening width of distoventral excavation about 0.2 pleotelson width. Pleopod 1 elongate, proximal width about 0.4 times length, width at distolateral lobes 0.3 times length, laterally convex with minimal width about 0.1 times length, setation pattern mostly not symmetrical, distolateral lobes not projecting as wide distally as medial lobes, bent laterally and ventrally, medial lobes rounded, with 7 simple setae of different lengths and strengths arranged symmetrically. Pleopod 2 elongate, proximal width 0.3 times length, maximal width (including stylet) 0.4 times length, stylet almost 0.5 times total length of protopod, laterally with row of at least 11 pappose setae, and 9 long distal pappose setae, medially some simple setae. Pleopod 3 protopod of rhomboid shape, 0.4 times total length, endopod not considerably narrowing, with 3 plumose setae and 2 pairs of 2 short setae distally, exopod 0.9 times total endopod length, distally narrowing, with 1 seta subterminally, row of numerous long simple setae surrounding the exopod laterally incl. distal apex and getting shorter medially. Pleopod 4 protopod and exopod broken off and missing; with several very small setae on apex margin and 1 pronounced seta subterminally.</p>

                            <fig id="F14" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 14.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Holotype ♂, ZMH (K-42168)) pleopods 1 (ventral view); left pleopods 2–4 (PlII–PlIV, ventral view); setules omitted in 2 of 3 distal plumose setae of pleopod 3 endopod (all pleopods’ scale = 0.1 mm); pleotelson and uropods (ventral view, scale = 0.5 mm, pleopod 1 not planar but obscured projecting into plain of view).</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g014.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <p>Uropod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14</xref>) of two articles, 0.8 times pleotelson length, protopod 7.9 times longer than wide, endopod small and slender, less than 0.2 times the length of protopod.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description paratype female"><title>Description paratype female.</title>
                            <p>Body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15</xref>) elongate, 4.5 times longer than wide; maximal body width in pereonite 4, 1.6 times wider than pleotelson; pereonites 2–4 about the same width, 1.1 times pereonite 1 width, small ventral spine posteriorly on pereonite 3. Cephalothorax (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16</xref>) almost semicircular with maximal width at posterolateral corners, length 0.8 times width; slightly longer than 0.1 times total body length; transverse ridge on frons not very prominent, of curved shape. Anterior pereonal division (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16</xref>) 0.2 times total body length; 1.1 times longer than wide. Posterior pereonites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16</xref>) relative medial segment lengths: 1:1.4:1.1:1.2; relative segment widths of pereonites 4–7: 1:0.9:0.8:0.8, pereonite 7 0.8 the width of pereonite 1. Pleotelson (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16</xref>) 0.2 times body length; about 1.7 times longer than wide; caudal apex slightly concave; breathing cavity maximal opening width 0.7 times pleotelson width, longitudinal excavation 0.2 times maximal pleotelson width.</p>

                            <fig id="F15" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 15.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Paratype ♀, ZMH (K-42169)) habitus: A dorsal view, flattened B lateral view C dorsal view of pereonites 4–7, bent.</p></caption>
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g015.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <p>Antenna 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16</xref>) of 5 articles, 3.4 times longer than article 1 width; articles 1 and 5 as long as wide, fifth article 0.1 times total length, articles 2–4 2 times longer than wide, gradually decreasing in size; 1 aesthetasc on article 5, 0.6 times the length of antenna 1.</p>
                            <p>Antenna 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16</xref>) relatively slender compared to male antenna 2; articles 1–3 as long as wide; article 4 half as wide as articles 1–3; article 5 0.6 times article 4 length and of same width.</p>
                            <p>Maxilla 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16</xref>) inner endite shorter and more slender than outer endite, terminally narrowing, around distal apex, dorsally and along lateral margin with numerous long and some very small simple setae; outer endite 1.4 times longer than inner one, narrowing distolaterally, with at least 11 simple setae on lateral margin, with 4 combs of 2–4 simple setae on medial margin, numerous simple setae of different lengths distomedially and 12 robust distal setae, some two-sided denticulate on distal margin.</p>
                            <p>Maxilla 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16</xref>) inner endite broadest, outer endite of intermediate width, medial endite longest, outer endite 0.8 times middle-endite length, inner endite 0.9 times middle-endite length; margin of inner endite with 12 long simple basomedial setae of more than half the length of endite, numerous small simple setae ventrally and laterally, distal margin with 8 robust setae: 5 simple and 3 denticulate; medial endite with 1 lateral row of simple setae, distally with 4 long simple setae; outer endite with small simple setae along both margins, distally with 4 stiff simple setae of different lengths, the longest of which is of more than half the length of the outer endite. Measurements of article lengths ratios and length-width ratios of articles are listed in Table 3.</p>

                            <fig id="F16" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 16.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Paratype ♀, ZMH (K-42169)) antenna 1 broken in 2 pieces; antenna 2, maxilla 1 (dorsal view); maxilla 2 (dorsal view).</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g016.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
	
                                <label>Table 3.</label>
		
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. paratype; preparatory female ZMH (K-42169); relative length ratios of articles of pereopods 1–7 (PI–VII) (basis to dactylus, excluding setae); length-width ratios (L/W) of pereopodal articles; basis damaged in pereopod 2; pereopod 7 broken off and missing.</p></caption>
		
                                <table>
                                    <tbody>
                                        <tr>
                                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Article length ratios</th>
                                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">L/W basis</th>
                                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">L/W ischium</th>
                                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">L/W merus</th>
                                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">L/W carpus</th>
                                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">L/W propodus</th>
                                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">L/W dactylus</th>
                                        </tr>
				
                                        <tr>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>I</sub></td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 : 0.5 : 0.4 : 0.4 : 0.3 : 0.3</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td>
                                        </tr>
				
                                        <tr>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>II</sub></td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">???</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">???</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td>
                                        </tr>
				
                                        <tr>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>III</sub></td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 : 0.6 : 0.6 : 0.5 : 0.3 : 0.2</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td>
                                        </tr>
				
                                        <tr>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>IV</sub></td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 : 0.4 : 0.4 : 0.3 : 0.2 : 0.1</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                        </tr>
				
                                        <tr>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>V</sub></td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 : 0.5 : 0.4 : 0.5 : 0.4 : 0.2</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                        </tr>
				
                                        <tr>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">P<sub>VI</sub></td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 : 0.6 : 0.5 : 0.5 : 0.4 : 0.2</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td>
                                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td>
                                        </tr>
                                    </tbody>
                                </table>
                            </table-wrap>

                            <p>Anterior pereopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17</xref>) increasing in length, relative length ratios, omitting basis: 1:1.2:1.3, with basis longest article. Shapes and setation as in holotype. Pereopod 2 basis damaged. Except: pereopod 3 relative length ratios and setation different from holotype: basis relatively elongated; ischium only 2.2 times longer than wide, dorsal expansion less prominent than in holotype; propodus 0.5 times the length of carpus; dactylus long and slender, 0.9 times carpus length; lengths and robustness of setae as well as the number of setae per row increased in merus and carpus.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->

                            <fig id="F17" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 17.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Paratype ♀, ZMH (K-42169)) pereopods 1–3 (	PI–PIII), pereopod 2 basis broken off.</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g017.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <p>Posterior pereopods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 18</xref>). Pereopod 4 shortest, length ratios: 1:1.6:2.0; pereopod 7 missing. Pereopod 4 0.7 times pereopod 1 length; dactylus 0.6 times propodus length. Pereopod 5 1.1 times longer than pereopod 1; all articles elongated compared to holotype, especially carpus and propodus. Pereopod 6 1.4 times longer than pereopod 1; with more setae in carpus and propodus.</p>

                            <fig id="F18" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 18.</label>
	
                                <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (Paratype ♀, ZMH (K-42169)) pereopods 4–6 (PIV–PVI), pereopod 7 missing (scale = 0.3 mm); operculum (ventral view, scale = 0.2 mm).</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g018.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                            <p>Operculum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18</xref>) length/width ratio 1.6, densely covered with small setules, with 4 setae alternating along medial line of fusion, numerous setae ventrolaterally along proximal margin, distally with 15 pappose setae. Pleopod 3 and 4 as in male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14</xref>). Uropods broken off and missing in analysed specimens.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Sexual dimorphism"><title>Sexual dimorphism.</title>
                            <p>The male specimen is more slender than the female, its pleotelson is less narrowing posteriorly. The antenna 1 is relatively smaller but wider than in female and with more aesthetascs. The antenna 2 is little larger in the male, almost 0.4 times the length of the total body, 0.3 in female. Pereopods are dimorphic by means of article length ratios while pereopod length in relation to body length and setation are identical in both sexes.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                            <p>“Antennamagna” is derived from the Latin word for “big antenna” as the second antennae are conspicuously large in both sexes.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                            <p><tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. can be delimited from all other species by the large antenna 2, the three-lobed pars incisiva, the roundish appearance of the cephalothorax without a transverse ridge on frons and the shape of male pleopod 1. <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is most similar to <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis urceolata</tp:taxon-name> Mezhov, 1989 which is the only known species of this genus with comparably prominent antenna 2. Both species also share the general appearance in dorsal view and have high similarities in following characters: mandibles, male pleopod 1 and ventral spines. <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. can be distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis urceolata</tp:taxon-name> by the transverse ridge on frons lacking, antenna 1 being stouter, lacinia mobilis being smaller, the male pleopod 1 being wider and stouter, the smaller relative length of the pleotelson, and the “bifurcate” caudal tip of the pleotelson. <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> (Brandt, 2002), <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis carinifera</tp:taxon-name> Mezhov, 1988, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis grandis</tp:taxon-name> Birstein, 1970, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis hirsuticaudis</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longiremis</tp:taxon-name> (Meinert, 1890), <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis minuscularia</tp:taxon-name> Mezhov, 2003, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis sarsi</tp:taxon-name> Brandt, 1992, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis sensitiva</tp:taxon-name> Birstein, 1970, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis ovata</tp:taxon-name> Birstein, 1970, and <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis vinogradovae</tp:taxon-name> Mezhov, 1992 have a comparably long antenna 2. However, these species show distinct characters clearly delimitating them from <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. of which only the most obvious are listed below: antenna 1 of <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> has nine articles, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis carinifera</tp:taxon-name> bears a posterior ventral spine on pereonite 4 and a much more stout pleopod 2, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis grandis</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis ovata</tp:taxon-name> have a much wider habitus in dorsal view, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis hirsuticaudis</tp:taxon-name> has an uniquely shaped pleotelson with an almost straight posterior end, the habitus of <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis longiremis</tp:taxon-name> is constantly narrowing towards posteriorly and the cephalothorax bears spines in posterolateral corners, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis minuscularia</tp:taxon-name> has a comparably long but thinner antenna 2 and antenna 1 differs in article length ratios and size, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis sarsi</tp:taxon-name> shows a stouter habitus and more slender antenna 2, the latter is also true for <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis sensitiva</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis vinogradovae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                            <p>Antenna 2 can be found even bigger in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis spinifera</tp:taxon-name> Sars, 1864, <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis polaris</tp:taxon-name> Malyutina &amp; Kussakin, 1996 and <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis porrecta</tp:taxon-name> Mezhov, 1988. However, in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis spinifera</tp:taxon-name> shape and size ratios of male and female pleopods 1 and 2 differ from <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. and in the other two species antenna 2 has more slender peducular articles and antenna 1 is bigger compared to <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <p>The slender habitus with almost parallel sides in dorsal view shown by <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is common in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name>. The “bifurcated” caudal end is also present in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis bifurcatus</tp:taxon-name> Menzies, 1962, although much stronger developed there. The pleopods 5 have not been found in both sexes. It is unclear, though, whether these have been broken off during dissection or if they are generally reduced in this species. The analysis of five specimens from two stations has revealed little individual variation. Variations in setal counts are probably allometric (compare <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Hessler 1970</xref> for <tp:taxon-name>Desmosomatidae</tp:taxon-name>).</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                    </tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:taxon-treatment>
                        <tp:nomenclature>
                            <tp:taxon-name>
                                <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                                <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">obscurus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            </tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-authority>(Brandt, 1992)</tp:taxon-authority>
                            <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                            <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19</xref>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                                <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis obscurus</tp:taxon-name> <comment>Brandt, 1992, p. 69–74, Fig. 11–13</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        </tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Addition to original description"><title>Additions to original description.</title>
                            <p>Pereopod 4 relative article length ratios: 1:0.5:0.5:0.4:0.3:0.1, basis 2.3 times longer than wide, with at least 5 broom setae, 1 short simple seta distodorsally; ischium 1.8 times longer than wide, with 1 short simple seta distodorsally; merus almost 1.8 times longer than wide, distodorsally with 1 stout bifurcate seta, distoventrally 2 acute simple setae, 1 reaching beyond propodal articulation; carpus 1.6 times longer than wide, distodorsally with 1 bifurcate seta, 1 broom seta distoventrally next to 1 long simple seta exceeding dactylus in length; propodus twice as long as wide, dorsally expanding into a distal lobe, with 1 long bifurcate seta distoventrally, exceeding dactylar claw, and 1 short and simple seta ventrally; dactylus small, twice as long as wide, about half propodus length and width, with 1 terminal stout and acute claw, 1.5 times article length, and 1 subterminal bifurcate claw, shorter than article, 2 setae terminally and 1 thin and long simple seta subterminally, twice as long as article.</p>
                            <p>Pereopod 5 propodus 3.3 times longer than wide, with 2 long simple setae distoventrally, thinner seta more than twice as long as dactylus, the stouter one almost reaching the tip of dactylus, 1 simple seta ventrally; dactylus 5 times longer than wide, half propodus length, with 3 simple, acute claws, terminal claw longer than dactylus, subterminal claw stout, robust and shorter than dactylus, second subterminal claw slender and more than twice as long as dactylus.</p>
                            <p>Pereopod 6 propodus expanding into a distal lobe, with 1 long bifurcate seta, reaching beyond tip of dactylus, with 1 very long and simple seta and 1 broom seta; dactylus 4.3 times longer than wide, with 1 terminal long and acute claw, 1.5 times dactylus length, and 1 subterminal claw, longer than article, with 2 thin and unequally long simple setae subterminally.</p>
                            <!--PageBreak-->

                            <fig id="F19" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                                <label>Figure 19.</label>
	
                                <caption><p>Top: <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> (Brandt, 2002) comb. n., holotype female (ZMH (K-39915)); lateral view on left side; specimen damaged: pereonite 7 broken off, pereopods, antennae 1–2 and mouthparts dissected; ventral spines on pereonites 1–3 and 5–7 (for measurements see original description); below: <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis obscurus</tp:taxon-name> (Brandt, 1992) comb. n. holotype female manca, (BNHM 1990:39); left and right pereopods 4; dactyli of pereopods 5 and 6.</p></caption>
	
                                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/310/supp/ZooKeys-057-009-g019.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                            </fig>

                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                    </tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:taxon-treatment>
                        <tp:nomenclature>
                            <tp:taxon-name>
                                <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                                <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">gerdesi</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                            </tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-authority>(Brandt, 2002)</tp:taxon-authority>
                            <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                            <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19</xref>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                                <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> <comment>Brandt, 2002, p. 616–626, Fig. 1–4.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        </tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Addition to original description"><title>Additions to original description.</title>
                            <p>Ventral spine in pereonite 1, directed onteriorly; ventral spines in pereonites 2–3 and 5–7, directed posteriorly. Pereonites 4–6 slightly constricted towards anterior margin.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                        <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                            <p>Re-examination revealed spines on all sternites not illustrated before, except from pereonite 4. In the latter a ventral constriction is present close to the posterior margin. In <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> comb. n. long sensory terminal setae on dactyli and additionally long sensory setae on propodi of posterior pereopods are considered to be apomorphies for <tp:taxon-name>Desmostylis</tp:taxon-name>. The value of these characters to discriminate between genera is discussed above. However, a dactylus is present in pereopod 4 and in contrast to the <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis obscurus</tp:taxon-name> comb. n. holotype, pereopod 3 ischium is triangularly expanded in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis gerdesi</tp:taxon-name> comb. n. As a consequence of the character discussion listed above this species is transferred the genus <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                        </tp:treatment-sec>
                    </tp:taxon-treatment>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Pereopodal measures are variable within a species. Not only can differences be found between the sexes (see below) but also within a sex. Certain variability does not necessarily occur in all pereopods at the same time and to the same extend. In <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., for example, we have found the pereopod 3 to be almost similar with regard to length-width ratios in an ovigerous and a non-ovigerous female specimen. Here, only the number of setae per row was slightly different. Contrastingly, pereopod 5 shows rather strong variation. While the pereopod 5 in general and most of its articles were longer in the ovigerous female, ischium and merus had the same length compared to the preparatory female. Besides propodus and dactylus, all articles had the same width or were narrower in the ovigerous female compared to the preparatory one. These measures could be interpreted as allometry but may also be variable within a stage.</p>
            <p>In <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis antennamagna</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. we observed differences in posterolateral setation of cephalon and pereomeres with regard to robustness, length and substructures. These differences occurred between male and female as well as between left and right side of the same pereomere of one specimen. This indicates that such setal features are intraspecifically variable. To clarify if this is general variability or sexual dimorphism, higher numbers of specimens need to be analysed.</p>
            <p>Sexual dimorphisms have been reported for a wide range of taxa. Not much is known about dimorphism in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name>. Here, species have been described based on one sex only. Sexual dimorphism is probably the reason why correct allocation of a complementary male or female is often impossible based solely on morphological characters. This is the case for example in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Knowledge about general patterns of dimorphism in closely related species could provide an aid for allocation in new species. However, we found distinct differences between males and females in macrostylids. A general pattern of sexual dimorphism can be found in the copulatory organs and a few additional characters: the male antenna 1 bears more aesthetascs and is sometimes broader than in the female (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Hansen 1916</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Menzies and George 1972</xref>). Furthermore, in the antenna 2 articles are sometimes broader in males than in females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Mezhov 2003a</xref>, b).</p>
            <p>To date no cases of more extreme sexual dimorphism, as for example reported for the paramunnid genus <tp:taxon-name>Abyssaranea</tp:taxon-name> Wilson &amp; Hessler, 1974, have been described in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name>. It is possible that no example has been discovered so far but it also may be that in strongly dimorphic species males and females have been defined as distinct species. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Wilson and Hessler (1974)</xref> mentioned the possible value of the dimorphic degree as being a significant character on generic level. A comprehensive comparison of gender differences has been reported for <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis dellacrocei</tp:taxon-name> Aydogan, Wägele &amp; Park, 2000. In the original description a juvenile male was compared to the preparatory female holotype. Differences found exceed the above mentioned general pattern for <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name> by far. The differences that occurred between sexes (i.e. lack of sternal projection in pereonite 1, the relatively smaller pereonite 7, the smaller aesthetasc and terminal article in the antenna 1, the reduced sizes of pars molaris and spine row in the mandible, the reduced sizes in right and left lacinia mobilis, reduced number of setae on pereopod 7), though, are most likely allometric characters at an early ontogenetic stage in the juvenile male specimen. Therefore, these characters cannot be used to infer sexual dimorphism in this species or to gain insights into general patterns of sexual dimorphism in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <p>On this background we assume sexual dimorphism likely to be common in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name> and to vary from species to species. Both sexes have so far only been described in species with low degree of sexual dimorphism, where allocation was straight forward. It is likely that in some cases only one gender per species has been collected, particularly where sample size is low. It may also be likely that strong sexual dimorphism leads to allocation of male and female specimens into separate species. This could e.g. be the case in <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylis uniformis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. To allocate specimens safely it is necessary to know characters that are less affected by sexual dimorphism. For the identification of such characters, analyses of higher numbers of specimens from one sampling site are needed. Patterns could be not only generalized to allocate species where lower numbers of specimens are available but probably also be used to infer subtaxa (i.e. genera) within <tp:taxon-name>Macrostylidae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <label>Acknowledgements</label>
            <p>We are very grateful to the German Science Foundation for financial support (DFG Br 1121/26) and to Marina Malyutina and an anonymous reviewer for their corrections and comments leading to an improved manuscript. This is ANDEEP publication # 137. ANDEEP was financially also supported by CeDAMar (Census of the Diversity of Abyssal Marine life). For helpful comments on the manuscript we would like to thank Dr. Stefanie Kaiser. Chester J. Sands kindly corrected the English. Helpful discussions with Drs Saskia Brix, Marina Malyutina, Karin Meißner, Ralph Peters and George D.F. Wilson are appreciated. We also appreciate the help of Marylin Schotte, T. Chad Walter and the IZ staff at NMNH and of Christine LeBeau at AMNH.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>            
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aydogan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wägele</surname><given-names>J-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> New deep-sea isopods (Crustacea. Isopoda. Asellota) from the Atacama-Trench.</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen-Museum für Naturkunde in Berlin</source> <volume>76</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>194</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1920</year>)<article-title> Contribution to the Crustacean fauna of South Africa No. 6: Further Additions to the list of marine Isopoda.</article-title> <source>Annals of the South African Museum</source> <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>428</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Beddard</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1886a</year>)<article-title> Report on the Isopoda collected by HMS Challenger during the years 1873–1876.</article-title> <source>Challenger Reports</source> <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>156</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Beddard</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1886b</year>)<article-title> Report on the Isopoda collected by HMS Challenger during the years 1873–76. Part 2.</article-title> <source>Report of the Voyage of HMS Challenger</source> <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>178</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Birstein</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963a</year>) <source>Deep water isopods (Crustacea. Isopoda) of the north-western part of the Pacific Ocean.</source> <publisher-name>Akademiya Nauk SSSR</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Moscow</publisher-loc>, <lpage>213</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Birstein</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963b</year>)<article-title> Isopods from the ultra-abyssal zone of the Bougainville Trench.</article-title> <source>Zoologicheskii Zhurnal</source> <volume>42</volume> (<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>814</fpage>-<lpage>834</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Birstein</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> New Crustacea Isopoda from the Kurile-Kamchatka Trench area. Fauna of the Kurile-Kamchatka Trench and its environment, VG Bogorov (ed.</article-title> <source>)</source> <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>308</fpage>-<lpage>356</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> Morphology and ultrastructure of the sensory spine, a presumed mechanoreceptor of Sphaeroma hookeri (Crustacea, Isopoda), and remarks on similar spines in other peracarids.</article-title> <source>Journal of Morphology</source> <volume>198</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>229</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> New Asellota from the Antarctic deep sea (Crustacea, Isopoda, Asellota), with descriptions of two new genera.</article-title> <source>Zoologica Scripta</source> <volume>21</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Desmostylis gerdesi, a new species (Isopoda: Malacostraca) from Kapp Norvegia, Weddell Sea, Antarctica.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Biological Society of Washington</source> <volume>115</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>616</fpage>-<lpage>627</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> New deep-sea species of Macrostylidae (Asellota: Isopoda: Malacostraca) from the Angola Basin off Namibia, South West Africa.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>448</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Broyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gooday</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilbig,</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>MRA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004a</year>)<article-title> Introduction to ANDEEP (ANtarctic benthic DEEP-sea biodiversity: colonization history and recent community patterns)—a tribute to Howard L. Sanders.</article-title> <source>Deep-Sea Research Part II</source> <volume>51</volume> (<issue>14–16</issue>):<fpage>1457</fpage>-<lpage>1465</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brökeland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brix</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malyutina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004b</year>)<article-title> Diversity of Southern Ocean deep-sea Isopoda (Crustacea, Malacostraca)—a comparison with shelf data.</article-title> <source>Deep-Sea Research Part II</source> <volume>51</volume> (<issue>14–16</issue>):<fpage>1753</fpage>-<lpage>1768</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brix</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brökeland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malyutina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007a</year>)<article-title> Deep-sea isopod biodiversity, distribution and endemism in the Atlantic sector of the Southern Ocean—results from the ANDEEP I–III expeditions.</article-title> <source>Deep-Sea Research II</source> <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>1760</fpage>-<lpage>1775</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gooday</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandao</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brix</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brökeland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cedhagen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelius</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Mesel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillan</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilbig</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janussen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malyutina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pawlowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raupach</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanreusel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007b</year>)<article-title> First insights into the biodiversity and biogeography of the Southern Ocean deep sea.</article-title> <source>Nature</source> <volume>447</volume>:<fpage>307</fpage>-<lpage>311</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> An epibenthic sledge for operations on marine soft bottom and bedrock.</article-title> <source>Marine Technology Society Journal</source> <volume>39</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> “ Digital inking”: how to make perfect line drawings on computers.</article-title> <source>Organisms Diversity &amp; Evolution</source> <volume>3</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>303</fpage>-<lpage>304</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Drawing setae the digital way.</article-title> <source>Zoosystematics and Evolution</source> <volume>85</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>305</fpage>-<lpage>310</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellingsen</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebbe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Diversity and species distribution of polychaetes, isopods and bivalves in the Atlantic sector of the deep Southern Ocean.</article-title> <source>Polar Biology</source>, <volume>30</volume>(<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>1265</fpage>–<lpage>1273</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Garm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Revising the definition of the crustacean seta and setal classification systems based on examinations of the mouthpart setae of seven species of decapods.</article-title> <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>142</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>233</fpage>-<lpage>252</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>        
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurjanova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1933</year>)<article-title> Die marinen Isopoden der Arktis.</article-title> <source>Fauna Arctica</source> <volume>6</volume> (<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>391</fpage>-<lpage>470</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1916</year>)<article-title> Crustacea Malacostraca: The order Isopoda.</article-title> <source>Danish Ingolf Expedition</source> <volume>3</volume> (<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Are Deep-Sea Asellote Isopods Infaunal or Epifaunal?</article-title> <source>Crustaceana</source>: <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>319</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref> 
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hessler</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> The Desmosomatidae (Isopoda, Asellota) of the Gay Head-Bermuda Transect.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography</source> <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>185</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hessler</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strömberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Behavior of janiroidean isopods (Asellota), with special reference to deep sea genera.</article-title> <source>Sarsia</source> <volume>74</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Proposed new standardized anatomical terminology for the Tanaidacea (Peracarida).</article-title> <source>Journal of Crustacean Biology</source> <volume>23</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>644</fpage>-<lpage>661</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Latreille</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1802</year>) <article-title>Histoire Naturelle des Crustaces et des Insectes.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>de Buffon</surname><given-names>GLL</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Histoire Naturelle, nouvelle edition, accompagnee des notes.</source> <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <fpage>1802</fpage>–<lpage>1805</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Malyutina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kussakin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Addition to the Polar Sea bathyal and abyssal Isopoda (Crustacea). Part 1. Anthuridea, Valvifera, Asellota (Ischnomesidae, Macrostylidae, Nannoniscidae).</article-title> <source>Zoosystematica Rossica</source> <volume>4</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinert</surname><given-names>FVA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1890</year>)<article-title> Crustacea malacostraca. Det Videnskabelige Udbytte af Kanonbaaden.</article-title> <source>‘Hauchs’ Togter</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>-<lpage>230</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Menzies</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962a</year>) <source>Abyssal Crustacea</source>, <publisher-name>Columbia University Press New York</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York and London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>233</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Menzies</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962b</year>)<article-title> The isopods of abyssal depths in the Atlantic Ocean.</article-title> <source>Vema Research Series</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>206</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Menzies</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Isopod Crustacea of the Peru-Chile Trench.</article-title> <source>Anton Bruun Report</source> <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>124</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezhov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Isopoda.</article-title> In: <source>Benthos of the Submarine mountains Marcus-Necker and adjacent Pacific regions.</source> <publisher-name>Academy of Sciences of the U.S.S.R. P.P. Shirshov Institute of Oceanology</publisher-name>: <fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezhov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> The first findings of Macrostylidae (Isopoda, Asellota) in the Indian Ocean.</article-title> <source>Zoologicheskii Zhurnal</source> <volume>67</volume> (<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>983</fpage>-<lpage>994</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezhov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989a</year>)<article-title> Additions to the fauna of Macrostylids in the Indian Ocean (Isopoda, Asellota, Macrostylidae).</article-title> <source>Zoologicheskii Zhurnal</source> <volume>68</volume> (<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>60</fpage>-<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezhov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989b</year>)<article-title> Two new species of Macrostylis (Isopoda, Macrostylidae) from the trenches of the Pacific Ocean and comments on the morphology of M. galatheae.</article-title> <source>Zoologicheskii Zhurnal</source> <volume>68</volume> (<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>           
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezhov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Two new species of the genus Macrostylis G.O.Sars, 1864 (Crustacea Isopoda Asellota Macrostylidae) from the Antarctic.</article-title> <source>Arthropoda Selecta</source> <volume>1</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>87</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezhov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Three new species of Macrostylis G.O. Sars, 1864 (Crustacea Isopoda Asellota Macrostylidae) from the Pacific Ocean.</article-title> <source>Arthropoda Selecta</source> <volume>2</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezhov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Four new species of the genus Macrostylis (Crustacea, Isopoda, Macrostylidae) from the Atlantic Ocean abyssal zone.</article-title> <source>Zoologicheskii Zhurnal</source> <volume>78</volume> (<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1417</fpage>-<lpage>1423</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezhov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Addition to the fauna of isopod crustacean genus Macrostylis G.O. Sars, 1864 (Crustacea: Isopoda: Macrostylidae) of the Atlantic and Arctic oceans, with descriptions of three new Atlantic species.</article-title> <source>Arthropoda Selecta</source> <volume>9</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>83</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezhov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003a</year>)<article-title> New abyssal species of the genus Macrostylis G.O. Sars, 1864 (Crustacea: Isopoda: Macrostylidae) from the northwestern part of the Indian Ocean.</article-title> <source>Arthropoda Selecta</source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezhov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003b</year>)<article-title> Three new species of the genus Macrostylis G.O. Sars, 1864 (Crustacea: Isopoda: Macrostylidae) from the Indian Ocean.</article-title> <source>Arthropoda Selecta</source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>100</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sars</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1864</year>) <article-title>Om en anomal Gruppe af Isopoder.</article-title> <source>Forhandhlinger Videnskapsselskapet I Kristiania</source>, <publisher-name>Anar 1863</publisher-name>, <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>221</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B44"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sars</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1897</year>) <article-title>Isopoda. Part VII, VIII. Desmosomidae, Munnopsidae. An account of the Crustacea of Norway with short descriptions and figures of all the species</article-title>, <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B45"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sars</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1899</year>) <source>An Account of the Crustacea of Norway Vol. II.</source>, <publisher-name>Bergen Museum</publisher-name>, x + <lpage>270</lpage> pp + 107 pl.</mixed-citation></ref>     
            <ref id="B46"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brix</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Macrostylis cerritus sp. nov., a new species of Macrostylidae (Isopoda: Asellota from the Southern Ocean.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2096</volume>:<fpage>356</fpage>-<lpage>370</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>   
            <ref id="B47"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wägele</surname><given-names>J-W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Evolution und phylogenetisches System der Isopoda.</article-title> <source>Zoologica</source> <volume>140</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>262</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B48"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GDF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> A systematic revision of the deep-sea subfamily Lipomerinae of the isopod crustacean family Munnopsidae.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography</source> <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B49"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GDF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hessler</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<article-title> Some unusual Paraselloidea (Isopoda, Asellota) from the deep benthos of the Atlantic.</article-title> <source>Crustaceana</source> <volume>27</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B50"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GDF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Local and regional species diversity of benthic Isopoda (Crustacea) in the deep Gulf of Mexico.</article-title> <source>Deep-Sea Research Part II</source> <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>2634</fpage>-<lpage>2649</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B51"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1956</year>)<article-title> Isopoda from depths exceeding 6000 meters.</article-title> <source>Galathea Report</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>157</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>            
            <ref id="B52"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1962</year>)<article-title> The systematics and biology of bathyal and abyssal Isopoda Asellota.</article-title> <source>Galathea Report</source> <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>320</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>