<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.81.1122</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    <bold>Volatile compounds released by disturbed and undisturbed adults of</bold> Anchomenus dorsalis
                     <bold>(Coleoptera, Carabidae, Platynini) and structure of the pygidial gland</bold>
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Bonacci</surname>
                        <given-names>Teresa</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Brandmayr</surname> 
                        <given-names>Pietro</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Zetto</surname>
                        <given-names>Tullia</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Perrotta</surname>
                        <given-names>Ida Daniela</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Guarino</surname>
                        <given-names>Salvatore</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Peri</surname> 
                        <given-names>Ezio</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Colazza</surname>
                        <given-names>Stefano</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>Department of Ecology, Università degli Studi della Calabria – via P. Bucci s.n., 87036, Rende (CS), Ital</label></aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>Department of Demetra Ed. 5, Università degli Studi di Palermo - Viale delle Scienze, 90128, Italy</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Teresa Bonacci (<email xlink:type="simple">t.bonacci@unical.it</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Terry Erwin</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>18</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>81</issue>
            <fpage>13</fpage>
            <lpage>25</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>20</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Teresa Bonacci, Pietro Brandmayr, Tullia Zetto, Ida Daniela Perrotta, Salvatore Guarino, Ezio Peri, Stefano Colazza</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Volatile compounds produced by adults of <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> under undisturbed and disturbed conditions were investigated with an all-glass aeration apparatus. GC-MS analysis of the crude extracts from undisturbed and disturbed adults highlighted four major volatile compounds, undecane, heneicosane, <italic>Z</italic>-9 tricosene and tricosane, of which significantly more undecane was released by disturbed adults compared to undisturbed beetles. The pygidial glands of adults of <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> were investigated using light and Transmission Electron Microscopy (TEM). Each gland showed dense aggregates of secretory cells organized into visually distinct lobes; a long collecting canal that drains the secretion towards the reservoir, a bean-shaped double lobed muscular reservoir in which secretion is stored and a short duct (efferent duct) through which the secretion is discharged. The function of the pygidial glands and the possible role played by undecane as a defensive allomone and/or chemical signalling molecule are discussed.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>undecane</kwd>
                <kwd>GC/MS</kwd>
                <kwd>chemical defences</kwd>
                <kwd>gland morphology</kwd>
                <kwd>predation avoidance mechanisms</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Carabid beetles are known to produce a large variety of defensive substances, and their chemical nature has been elucidated in more than 500 species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Schildknecht et al. 1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Eisner et al. 1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Eisner 1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Eisner et al. 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Moore and Wallbank 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Moore 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Forsyth 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Kanehisa 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Scott et al. 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Dazzini-Valcurone and Pavan 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Will et al. 2000</xref>). The defensive compounds are produced by a pair of glands that open at the tip of the abdomen, known as the “pygidial glands” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Eisner 1958</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Eisner and Aneshansley 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Eisner et al. 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">2000</xref>). The defensive substances are normally sprayed in the form of large droplets, but in the bombardier beetles the spray mechanism involves a two-chamber system by which benzoquinones are forced against attackers by way of an exothermic reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Schildknecht et al. 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Eisner et al. 2001</xref>). Previous chemical analytical studies on the defensive secretions of several <tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name> species revealed that these substances are blends, mainly characterized by polar organic compounds such as acids, phenols, aldehydes and quinones plus minor non-polar compounds such as ketones, esters and hydrocarbons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Dettner 1987</xref>). These chemicals are ejected or discharged mainly when a disturbance stimulus occurs, such as the attack of a predator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Schildknecht et al. 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Forsyth 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Thiele 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Rossini et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Eisner et al. 2001</xref>). In this case, one or both glands can be discharged almost immediately and the secretion aimed towards the disturbance source (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Forsyth 1972</xref>). To date, defensive compounds produced by these insects have been analyzed using whole body or droplet extracts but the differences in the quality and amounts of volatiles emitted from the undisturbed and disturbed carabid adults have been not yet been thoroughly investigated.</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> (Pontoppidan, 1763) is a gregarious platynine carabid inhabiting muddy soils and fields across Europe. It is often found in association with species of <tp:taxon-name>Brachinus</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Juliano 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Zaballos 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Lindroth 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bonacci et al. 2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Mazzei et al. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Zetto Brandmayr et al. 2006</xref>) and, like <tp:taxon-name>Brachinus</tp:taxon-name>, it has a bright bicoloured (green-blue and red-brown) coat body that contrasts with the background. These species usually aggregate under heavy stones in open lands with sparse vegetation, such as pasturelands, croplands or in humid, sun exposed soils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bonacci et al. 2004b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Mazzei et al. 2005</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Zetto Brandmayr et al. (2006)</xref> described a peculiar “rubbing behavior” of <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> towards <tp:taxon-name>Brachinus sclopeta</tp:taxon-name> (Fabricius, 1792) observed in laboratory conditionsand in natural aggregations, where the individuals (conspecifics and no-conpecifics)live in strinct contact and in peaceful coexistence. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Thiele (1977)</xref> defines the carabid aggregations as positive intraspecific relationships and as “indications of a type of social behavior”, in which the members of the species are mutually beneficial. Aggregation in ground beetles seems to occur in only very few species and specially between conspicuous and chemically protected species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Thiele 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bonacci et al. 2004b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Zetto Brandmayr et al. 2006</xref>). Laboratory investigations carried out by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bonacci et al. (2008)</xref> showed that <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Brachinus sclopeta</tp:taxon-name> (which in natural habitats live gregariously), use aposematic colours and warning odours versus natural enemies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bonacci et al. 2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2006</xref>). The authors supposed that the combination of visual<!--PageBreak--> and olfactory signals, common in many insect groups (especially aposematic coloured insects, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Rothschild and Moore 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Moore et al. 1990</xref>), can produce a multimodal warning display that, acting along many sensory channels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Rowe and Guilford 1999</xref>), increases the antipredatory strategies.</p>
            <p>When disturbed, the ground beetles <tp:taxon-name>Brachinus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> releases a strong odour (perceived even by humans) (Bonacci, personal observation), and quickly retreat (with dispersal movement that produce a great confusion in the observer) into deeper soil crevices (like the <italic>dilution effect</italic>). Under laboratory conditions, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bonacci et al. (2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">2008</xref>) demonstrated that <tp:taxon-name>Brachinus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Brachinus sclopeta</tp:taxon-name> are attacked less by predators, such as <tp:taxon-name>Ocypus olens</tp:taxon-name> (O. Muller, 1764) (<tp:taxon-name>Staphylinidae</tp:taxon-name>), <tp:taxon-name>Crocidura leucodon</tp:taxon-name> (Hermann, 1780) (<tp:taxon-name>Insectivora</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Soricidae</tp:taxon-name>) and <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis sicula</tp:taxon-name> (Rafinesque, 1810) (<tp:taxon-name>Reptilia</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Lacertidae</tp:taxon-name>) than other carabids used as preys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Juliano 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Zaballos 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Lindroth 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bonacci et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Zetto Brandmayr et al. 2006</xref>). Based on these behavioural studies and observations, experiments were conducted to characterize and quantify the volatile compounds produced by <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> upon disturbance. The putative organs producing such defensive compounds, the pygidial glands, were also investigated using light and electronic microscopy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods"><title>Materials and methods</title>
            <sec sec-type="Insects"><title>Insects</title>
                <p>Adults of <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> were collected by hand from different inter-specific aggregations (each composed by 100–130 individuals) of <tp:taxon-name>Brachinus sclopeta</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> found under stones or straw bales in Calabria (Crati Valley, province of Cosenza, 39°35'56"N; 16°15'48"E; elevation: 60 m a.s.l.). Following field collections, monospecific groups were placed in separate plastic cages (30 × 22 × 20 cm) with 4 cm of clay soil in a climatic chamber at 22 °C, photoperiod L/D of 18/6, and fed on veal meat and earthworm pieces (<tp:taxon-name>Lumbricus terrestris</tp:taxon-name> (Linnaeus, 1758)).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Air collection of adult volatiles"><title>Air collection of adult volatiles</title>
                <p>The collection of volatiles from <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> adults was conducted using a horizontal all-glass apparatus 1 l in volume. Humidified and charcoal filtered air was drawn through the apparatus at 0.5 l min-1 by a peristaltic pump for 2 h in a conditioned room at temperature of 22 ± 2 °C. The volatiles produced by experimental groups of 20 individuals of <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> adults of both sexes were trapped in glass collectors (6 mm ID) loaded with 600 mg of porapak Q, and held in place by glass wool plugs. Two experimental individual groups were considered: disturbed and undisturbed. Adults were considered undisturbed when they were gently transferred into the glass apparatus and disturbed <!--PageBreak-->when, before the start of the aeration, the glass chamber containing the adults was vigorously shaken for 10 seconds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Gómez et al. 2005</xref>). Preliminary observations showed that during this time the <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> adults released the odour. Five replicates were carried out for each groups: “disturbed” and “undisturbed”. We proceeded in order to avoid any pseudo-replication and each individual was tested once. At the end of the aeration period, collectors were eluted with hexane (400 µl) and the extracts stored at -15 °C until used for GC-MS analysis. Blank aerations were also carried out with the empty apparatus using the same procedure.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Chemical Analyses"><title>Chemical Analyses</title>
                <p>GC–MS analyses were performed using a Hewlett-Packard 5890 GC system interfaced with an HP 5973 quadrupole mass spectrometer detector. As a stationary phase an HP5–MS capillary column (5% diphenyl-95% dimethylpolysiloxane 30 m - 0.2 mm, 0.25 μm film thickness, J&amp;W Scientific, USA) was used. Injector and detector temperatures were 250 °C and 270 °C respectively. Helium was used as the carrier gas. The GC oven temperature program was 60 °C for 5 min, than increased by 10 °C/min to 280 °C. Electron impact ionization spectra were obtained at 70 eV, recording mass spectra from 42 to 550 uma. Compound analysis and identification was carried out using a commercial NIST 2005 mass spectra library search and by comparison with standard analytical grade compounds purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (U.S.A.). Quantitative analysis was carried out for 4 compound identified by GC-MS analysis: undecane, heneicosane, <italic>(Z)</italic>-9 - tricosene and tricosane.</p>
                <p>For this analysis the elutes were diluted in 1 ml of hexane using a volumetric flask. Six point calibration curves, using analytical standards undecane, heneicosane, <italic>(Z)</italic>-9 - tricosene and tricosane, in the 0.2–100 ng μl-1 range, were used in order to evaluate the chromatographic response. The mean amount ± SE of each of these compounds was calculated dividing the amount of the compound obtained per replicate per the number of individuals used in each replicate.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Gland anatomy"><title>Gland anatomy</title>
                <p>For anatomical study by optical microscopy, adult beetles were killed at -15 °C and their abdomens were treated with 10% potassium hydroxide for 4 days before examination of the chitinous structures. The glands were mounted on clean glass slides and observed by optical microscopy equipped with Nomarsky interference contrast and photographed with a Coolpix 4500 camera (Nikon).</p>
                <p>For light and transmission electron microscopy (TEM), samples were fixed in 3% glutaraldehyde solution in 0.1 M phosphate buffer (pH. 7.4) for 2 h at 4 °C and post fixed with 3% osmium tetroxide for 2 h. The specimens were then washed in phosphate buffer, dehydrated through graded acetone solutions and embedded in Araldite<!--PageBreak--> (Fluka, Buchs, Switzerland). Semithin sections (1 μm) were obtained with a Leica Ultracut UCT ultramicrotome by using glass knives, mounted on clean glass slide and stained with 1% toluidine blue. They were then photographed with the Zeiss Axioskop microscope. For transmission electron microscopy, ultrathin sections (600–900 Ǻ) were prepared using a diamond knife and collected on copper grids (G 300 Cu), contrasted using both lead citrate and uranyl acetate and then examined with a “Zeiss EM 900” electron microscope (TEM). Gland structure terminology follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Forsyth (1972)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Eisner et al. (2001)</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Statistical Analysis"><title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p>The quantitative analysis to determine differences in the amount of undecane, heneicosane, <italic>(Z)</italic>-9 - tricosene and tricosane recovered from <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> adults were compared by t-test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Sokal and Rohlf 1995</xref>). The statistical analysis was performed using Statistica for Windows 6.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Stat Soft Italia 1997</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results"><title>Results</title>
            <sec sec-type="Chemical analysis of adult volatiles"><title>Chemical analysis of adult volatiles</title>
                <p>GC-MS analysis of volatile collections showed that disturbed and undisturbed adults of <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> released the same four major volatile compounds: undecane, heneicosane, <italic>(Z)</italic>-9 - tricosene and tricosane (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). A significant difference between disturbed and undisturbed adults was observed only in the released amount of undecane. An amount of 22.37 ± 8.48 ng (Mean ± SE) were collected from each disturbed adult vs. 0.94 ± 0.29 ng collected from a undisturbed adult (t = 2,52; df = 8; <italic>p</italic> = 0.035). Other chemicals (heneicosane, <italic>(Z)</italic>-9 - tricosene and tricosane) tend to be released more when <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> individuals are disturbed but their amount is not statistically significant (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Table 1.</label>
                    <caption><p>Volatile compounds from <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> adults obtained from air collections carried out for 2 hours at 0.5 l min-1. <bold>RT</bold>: retention time at the GC-MS analysis; <bold>df</bold>: degree of freedom.</p></caption>
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compound</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">R.T. (min.)</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="2">Amount (ng) /adult (mean ± SE)</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic>- value</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disturbed</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Undisturbed</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Undecane</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.82</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.37 ± 8.48</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 ± 0.29</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.52</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heneicosane</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.92</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 ± 0.96</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 ± 0.31</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<italic>Z</italic> )- 9 - Tricosene</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.96</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19 ± 2.10</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 ± 0.70</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tricosane</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.98</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 ± 0.86</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 ± 0.28</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Figure 1.</label>
                    <caption><p>Gas chromatograms of volatile compounds collected from disturbed (up) and undisturbed (down) adults of <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name>. <bold>1</bold> undecane <bold>2</bold> heneicosane <bold>3</bold> (<italic>Z</italic>)-9 - tricosene <bold>4</bold> tricosane. On the x axis is reported the retention time (minutes). As a stationary phase an HP5–MS capillary column was used. The GC oven temperature program was 60 °C for 5 min, than increased by 10 °C/min to 280 °C.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-081-013-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Gland structure"><title>Gland structure</title>
                <p>The pygidial glands of <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> are cuticular invaginations of the body wall that open outside immediately behind the eighth abdominal tergite. Each gland consists of a aggregate of secretory cells, an collecting canal, a reservoir and an efferent duct through which the secretion is discharged. The efferent duct open near the abdominal tip to the sides of anus. Each lobe is essentially a ball of cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2 A</xref>) aligned radially around a central collecting lumen (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Forsyth 1970</xref>) that carry the secretion towards collecting canal. The overall structure of the secretory lobe and collecting canal resemble a cluster of grapes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2 A</xref>). Each cluster of cells converges to form a long efferent duct that drains the chemical product into a bean-shaped sac (reservoir) in which it is stored (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2 C</xref>). The reservoirs extend forward, one along each side of the hindgut. This reservoir or “storage sac” (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Rossini et al. 1997</xref>) in <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> has a smooth constriction at about one third from its hind end, where both the collecting canal as well the efferent duct (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Forsyth 1970</xref>) converge (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2 C and D</xref>). The collecting canal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Forsyth 1970</xref>) is a cylindrical tube twice the length of the body of the carabid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2 B and D</xref>), its lumen occupying about one third of the diameter. It carries the secretion from the secretory lobes to the reservoir and shows a continuous and regular spiral ridge along the whole length of its outer surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2 D</xref>). Each efferent canal (treated with potassium hydroxide) show evident apical ramifications (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2 E</xref>) extending towards the center of the secretory lobe. These structures, as observed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Eisner et al. 2001</xref> in <tp:taxon-name>Crepidogaster</tp:taxon-name> Boheman, 1848 genus and defined by these authors also microtubules (intracellular organelle sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Rossini et al. 1997</xref>), are grouped into convergent clusters, to form tiny individual “floret” that carry the secretion from the secretory lumen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2 E</xref>) to the main collecting canal. The tubules and florets are cuticular and could be isolated readily by potassium hydroxide treatment of the glands.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Figure 2.</label>
                    <caption><p>Light microscope: <bold>A</bold> Dorsal aspects of pygidial gland; <bold>ed</bold>, efferent duct; <bold>r</bold>, reservoir; <bold>cc</bold>, collecting canal; <bold>sl</bold>, secretory lobe (Scale bar = 0.5 mm) (not treated with potassium hydroxide) <bold>B</bold> collecting canal (Scale bar = 0.125 mm) <bold>C</bold> reservoir with smooth constriction at about one third from its hind end (Scale bar = 0.125 mm) <bold>D</bold> insertion of collecting canal (black arrow) and efferent duct (white arrow) in the reservoir (Scale bar = 0.05 mm) <bold>E</bold> collecting canal with apical ramifications (white arrows) (Scale bar = 0.05 mm) <bold>F</bold> “floret” (sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Eisner et al. 2001</xref>) (Scale bar = 0.015 mm) (treated with potassium hydroxide).</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-081-013-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Examined by TEM, the wall of the collecting canal is lined by epidermal part (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3 A</xref>) that consist of cells connected to each other by micro-canals projecting into the collecting canal lumen. The lumen of collecting canal contain a heterogeneous secretion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3 A</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Figure 3.</label>
                    <caption><p>Transmission electron microscope (TEM): <bold>A</bold>, collecting canal with lumen (<bold>lu</bold>); the black arrows show interstitial spaces (<bold>is</bold>) <bold>B</bold> secretory lobe with secretory lumen (<bold>sl</bold>) <bold>C</bold> vesicle (<bold>v</bold>) with microvilli (<bold>mv</bold>) <bold>D</bold> microvilli structure (<bold>mv</bold>) at highest enlargement (the white arrows show the thin lamina) and <bold>E</bold> Inner wall of the reservoir with chitinous basal lamina (<bold>la</bold>) (black arrows) and massive muscle layer around.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-081-013-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <p><!--PageBreak-->Each secretory lobe consist of secretory cells arranged radially around the central lumen. Each secretory cell has an secretory vesicle which is almost as long as the cell itself (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3 B</xref>) with a coated membrane and bear many microvilli projecting into the cavity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3 C</xref>). Between the secretory cells are evident (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3 B</xref>) the vesicular ducts that carry the secretion in the collecting lumen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3 B</xref>). Each microvillus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3 D</xref>) is formed by three structures: one with a typical spiral shape and other two structures, similar in shape and size. All the structures are enveloped by a thin lamina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3 D</xref>). The inner wall of the reservoir is composed of a thick chitinous layer (basal lamina) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3 E</xref>). A thick muscle layer was found surrounding the reservoir. Likely, the muscles play an important role for the expulsion of the secretory products through the efferent duct. This is composed of muscle bundles that pass spirally around it.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion and conclusions"><title>Discussion and conclusions</title>
            <p>The chemical analyses of disturbed and undisturbed <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> adults showed that undecane was produced significantly in larger amounts in disturbed individuals. This suggests that this compound (which can be perceived even by humans) could play a prominent role in the chemical defence of the species. The role of undecane as a defensive substance has been widely reported in the Insecta: <tp:taxon-name>Acanthomyops claviger</tp:taxon-name> (Roger, 1862) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Regnier and Wilson 1968</xref>), <tp:taxon-name>Formica polyctena</tp:taxon-name> Foerster, 1850 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Löfqvist and Bergström 1980</xref>), <tp:taxon-name>Paratrechina longicornis</tp:taxon-name> (Latreille, 1802) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Morgan et al. 2005</xref>) and in <tp:taxon-name>Oxytelinae</tp:taxon-name> rove beetles (<tp:taxon-name>Bledius spectabilis</tp:taxon-name> Kraatz, 1857, <tp:taxon-name>Platystethus arenarius</tp:taxon-name> (Fourcroy, 1785), and <tp:taxon-name>Oxytelus piceus</tp:taxon-name> L.) (Dettner and Schwinger 1982). Although in other carabids, hydrocarbons are generally produced in lesser amounts than polar compounds such as acids, phenols, aldehydes or quinones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Dettner 1987</xref>), but the occurrence of undecane in pygidial glands has been described in <tp:taxon-name>Pterostichini</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Abaris aenea</tp:taxon-name> Dejean, 1831, <tp:taxon-name>Pseudabarys</tp:taxon-name> Chaudoir, 1873, sp), <tp:taxon-name>Loxandrini</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Loxandrus</tp:taxon-name> LeConte, 1852, spp), <tp:taxon-name>Morionini</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Morion simplex</tp:taxon-name> Dejean, 1831, <tp:taxon-name>Moriosomus seticollis</tp:taxon-name> Straneo, 1985), <tp:taxon-name>Catapieseini</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Catapiesis</tp:taxon-name> Solier, 1835, spp), <tp:taxon-name>Perigonini</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Diploharpus laevissimus</tp:taxon-name> Chaudoir, 1850) and <tp:taxon-name>Odacanthini</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Colliuris pensylvanica</tp:taxon-name> Linnaeus, 1758) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Will et al. 2000</xref>). Furthermore, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Peschke and Eisner (1987)</xref> reported that hydrocarbons produced by carabid species are potentially defensive.</p>
            <p>Undecane is an optimal chemical signalling molecule, its molecular weight and polarity combining moderate olfactory efficiency with a sufficiently high vapour pressure to broadcast in the centimetre range when present in microgram quantities or less (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Regnier and Wilson 1968</xref>). As with a number of carabids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Eisner 1958</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Eisner et al. 1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Will et al. 2000</xref>), a defensive spray constituted mainly of undecane appears to be an effective deterrent of predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bonacci et al. 2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">2008</xref>). Moreover, the efficacy of these chemicals is improved in that carabid species that are able to direct their ejections directly against the head or the eyes of the predator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Eisner 1958</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Peschke and Eisner 1987</xref>).</p>
            <p>The laboratory observations of the pygidial glands of <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> show that they resemble those of other <tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name> in their structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Forsyth 1970</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">1972</xref>), and the form<!--PageBreak--> of the reservoir, clearly double lobed, resembles the apparatus of <tp:taxon-name>Anthia</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Harpalines</tp:taxon-name> described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Forsyth (1972)</xref>. The secretory “florets” show a very small lumen, compared to other tribes of carabid beetles, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Forsyth 1972</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Rossini et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Eisner et al. 2001</xref>), but very little investigations have been done on <tp:taxon-name>Platynine</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Agoninae</tp:taxon-name>) ground beetles. The inner wall of reservoir of pygidial glands in <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> shows a thin coat of chitinous tissue which probably preserves the cells by the toxic mixture of chemicals and requires that this secretion must be efficiently isolated from the rest of the body. Another feature of the glands of <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> is the extreme length of the collecting canal. This tube seems to be much longer than necessary for the transfer of chemical secretion. Very long collecting canals were found by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Forsyth (1970)</xref> in <tp:taxon-name>Pterostichus madidus</tp:taxon-name> (Fabricius) and the author proposed that this feature serves to abridge the back-pressure from the reservoir.</p>
            <p>As mentioned above, the defense glands in carabid beetles produce chemical compounds primarily to provide protection against putative predators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Thiele 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Will et al. 2000</xref>). Nevertheless, in <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name>, volatile compounds ejected after disturbance could have a double function: repellent function to predators and chemical signalling <!--PageBreak-->function for conspecifics. In fact, previous studies showed that the defensive compounds released by a number of disturbed <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> individuals is not only a repellent towards natural enemies, but also elicited dispersal behavior in conspecifics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bonacci et al. 2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">2008</xref>). Such an intra-specific dispersal function is supported by the gregarious nature of this species; gregariousness and high population density allowing rapid intra-specific communication is generally thought to be necessary for evolution of chemical signalling molecule (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Nault and Phelan 1984</xref>). It is reasonable to believe that in <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name>, undecane emission (characterized by strong smell, which can be perceived even by humans) by the pygidial glands causes dispersal movement of individuals inside the aggregation (authors’ personal observations). If the assumption of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Blum (1985)</xref> is correct (deterrence against predators and intraspecific alarm function of the same compounds being coupled), the chemicals of this carabids evoke an alarm reaction in conspecifics and avoidance behaviour in natural enemies, as showed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bonacci et al. (2004a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">2008</xref>). Usually <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> occurs in dense aggregations of many individuals with other carabids belonging to the genus <tp:taxon-name>Brachinus</tp:taxon-name>. It can be expected that in species occurring in such masses an adequate defense mechanism has evolved towards potential predators. <tp:taxon-name>Brachinus sclopeta</tp:taxon-name> producing several defensive chemicals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Zetto Brandmayr et al. 2006</xref>) and <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name> producing a putative chemical signalling molecule, undecane, from the pygidial glands. Assemblages of mixed species that share common predators may experience benefits that are similar to or exceed those of monospecific groups. These benefits may be particularly pronounced if individuals of one species can recognize the alarm signals produced by individuals of other species in the assemblage (in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Mathis and Smith 1993</xref>).</p>
            <p>In summary, undecane and the pygidial glands appear to play a role in the defence mechanism of <tp:taxon-name>Anchomenus dorsalis</tp:taxon-name>. Further studies will carry on to investigate if undecane emission is able to elicit dispersal and retreating movements both in co-specific and inter-specific groups.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonacci</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aloise</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandmayr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zetto Brandmayr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004a</year>)<article-title> Risposte comportamentali di <italic>Crocidura leucodon</italic> (Hermann, 1780) (Insectivora, Soricidae) ai meccanismi antipredatori di alcuni Artropodi.</article-title> <source>Hystrix, Italian Journal of Mammalogy (Nova Series, Pavia, Italy)</source> <volume>15</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>73</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonacci</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zetto Brandmayr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandmayr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004b</year>)<article-title> Aposematic aggregtion of carabid beetles (Coleoptera Carabidae): preliminary data</article-title>. <source>Redia</source> <volume>LXXXVII</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonacci</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massolo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandmayr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zetto Brandmayr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Predatory behaviour on ground beetles (Coleoptera: Carabidae) by <italic>Ocypus olens</italic> (Müller) (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae) under laboratory conditions.</article-title> <source>Entomological News</source> <volume>117</volume> (<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>545</fpage>-<lpage>551</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonacci</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aloise</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandmayr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zetto Brandmayr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capula</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Testing the predatory behaviour of <italic>Podarcis sicula</italic> (Reptilia: Lacertidae) towards aposematic and non-aposematic preys.</article-title> <source>Amphibia-Reptilia</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>449</fpage>-<lpage>453</lpage>.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Alarm pheromones</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerkut</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Comprehensive Insect Physiology, Biochemistry and Pharmacology</source>. <publisher-name>Pergamon Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>, <fpage>194</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dazzini Valcurone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Glandole pigidiali e secrezioni difensive dei Carabidae (Insecta Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Publicazioni dell’Istituto di Entomologia dell’Università di Pavia,</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dettner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname> Schwinger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<article-title> Defensive secretions of three oxytelinae rove beetles (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of Chemical Ecology,</source> <volume>8</volume> (<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1411</fpage>-<lpage>1420</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dettner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Chemosystematics and evolution of beetle chemical defense.</article-title> <source>Annual Review of Entomology</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>)<article-title> The protective role of the spray mechanism of the bombardier beetle, <italic>Brachynus ballistarius</italic> Lec.</article-title> <source>Journal of Insect Physiology</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>-<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinwald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<article-title> Defense Mecanisms of Arthropods. XI. The Structure, Function, and Phenolic Secretions of the Glands of a Chordeumoid Millipede and a Carabid Beetle.</article-title> <source>Psyche</source> <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>94</fpage>-<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> Chemical defense against predation in arthropods</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sondheimer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simeone</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Chemical Ecology</source>. <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>280</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aneshansley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tschinkel</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silbergleid</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinwald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>)<article-title> Chemistry of defensive secretions of Bombardier Beetles (Brachinini, Metriini, Ozaenini, Paussini).</article-title> <source>Journal of Insect Physiology</source> <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1383</fpage>-<lpage>1386</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aneshansley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<article-title> Spray aiming in bombardier beetles: jet deflection by the Coanda effect.</article-title> <source>Science</source> <volume>215</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attygalle</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aneshansley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinwald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Chemical defense of a primitive Australian bombardier beetle: <italic>Mystropomus regularis</italic>.</article-title> <source>Chemoecology</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aneshansley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Spray aiming in the bombardier beetle: photographic evidence.</article-title> <source>Proceeding of National Academy of Science, USA</source> <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>9705</fpage>-<lpage>9709</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aneshansley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attygalle</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alsop</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinwald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Spray mechanism of the most primitive bombardier beetle (<italic>Metrius contractus</italic>).</article-title> <source>The Journal of Experimental Biology</source> <volume>203</volume>:<fpage>1265</fpage>-<lpage>1275</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aneshansley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yack</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attygalle</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Spray mechanism of crepidogastrine bombardier beetles (Carabidae; Crepidogastrini).</article-title> <source>Chemoecology</source> <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>219</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Forsyth</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> The ultrastructure of the pygidial defence glands of the <italic>Pterostichus madidus</italic> F.</article-title> <source>Journal of Morphology</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>397</fpage>–<lpage>416</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Forsyth</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> The structure of the pygidial defence glands of Carabidae (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Transactions of the Zoological Society of London</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>-<lpage>309</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrera</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macias-Samano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liedo</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz-Lopez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Badii</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Volatile compounds released by disturbed females of <italic>Cephalonomia stephanoderis</italic> (Hymenoptera: Bethylidae): a parasitoid of coffee berry borer <italic>Hypotenemus hampei</italic> (Coleoptera: Scolytidae).</article-title> <source>Florida Entomologist</source> <volume>88</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>180</fpage>-<lpage>187</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Juliano</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Habitat associations, resources, and predators of an assemblage of <italic>Brachinus</italic> (Coleoptera: Carabidae) from southeastern Arizona.</article-title> <source>Canadian Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>1683</fpage>-<lpage>1691</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Secretion of defensive substance by carabidae and Brachinidae</article-title>. <source>Bulletin Resesearch Institute Bioresources</source>, <publisher-name>Okayama Univ.</publisher-name> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. [in Japanese]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindroth</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<source> The Carabidae (Coleoptera) of Fennoscandia and Denmark Fauna. Entomologica Scandinavica, 15, part 2</source>. <publisher-name>Scandinavian Science Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Copenhagen</publisher-loc>, <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>497</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Löfqvist</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergström</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Volatile communication substances in Dufour’s gland of virgin females and old queens of the ant <italic>Formica polyctena</italic>.</article-title> <source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source> <volume>6</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>320</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonacci</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zetto Brandmayr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandmayr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Capacità di aggregazione di Coleotteri geoadefagi, in ambiente ipolitico di suoli argillosi del bioclima mediterraneo arido</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of XV Congress of the Italian Society of Ecology</source>. <publisher-loc>Torino, Italy</publisher-loc>. 12–14 September 2005. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RJF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Intraspecific and cross-superorder responses to chemical alarm signals by brook stickleback.</article-title> <source>Ecology,</source> <volume>74</volume> (<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2395</fpage>-<lpage>2404</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> Chemical defense in carabids and its bearing on phylogeny. Carabids beetles: their evolution, natural history, and classification</article-title>. In <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>The Ilague</source>, <publisher-name>Junk</publisher-name>, <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallbank</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> Chemical composition of the defensive secretion in carabid beetles and its importance as a taxonomic character.</article-title> <source>Proceeding of Royal Entomological Society of London B</source> <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vance Brown</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> Methylalkylpyrazines in aposematic insects, their hostplants and mimics.</article-title> <source>Chemoecology</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Billen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Chemical secretions of the “crazy ant” <italic>Paratrechina longicornis</italic> (Hymenopetra: Formicidae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology</source> <volume>46</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>304</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nault</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Alarm pheromones and sociality in pre-social insects. Chemical ecology of Insects</article-title>. In <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardè</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>United Kingdom</publisher-loc>, <fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>256</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Peschke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Defensive secretion of the tenebrionid beetle, <italic>Blaps mucronata</italic>: Physical and chemical determinants of effectiveness.</article-title> <source>Journal of Comparative Physiology A</source> <volume>161</volume>:<fpage>377</fpage>-<lpage>388</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Regnier</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> The alarm-defense system of the ant <italic>Acanthomyops claviger</italic>.</article-title> <source>Journal of Insect Physiology</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>955</fpage>-<lpage>970</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attygalle</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>González</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smedley</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinwald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Defensive production of acid formic (80%) by a carabid beetle (<italic>Galerita lecontei</italic>).</article-title> <source>Proceeding of National Academy of Science, USA</source> <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>6792</fpage>-<lpage>6797</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Pyrazines as alerting signals in toxic plants and insects</article-title>. In:  <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Laberie</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabres</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lachaise</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Insects-Plants</source>.  <publisher-loc>Dordrecht,  Holland</publisher-loc>, <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guilford</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> The evolution of multimodal warning displays.</article-title> <source>Evolutionary Ecology</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>655</fpage>-<lpage>671</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schildknecht</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holoubek</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<article-title> Defensive substances of the Arthropods, their isolation and identification.</article-title> <source>Angewandte Chemie International Edition</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schildknecht</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maschwitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maschwitz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> Die Explosionschemie der Bombardierkäfer (Coleoptera, Carabidae) III. Mitteilung: Isolierung und Charakterisierung der Explosionskatalysatoren</article-title>. <source>Zeitschrift für Naturforschung</source>. <volume>23b</volume>: <fpage>1213</fpage>–<lpage>1218</lpage>.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hepburn</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crewe</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>)<article-title> Pygidial defensive secretions of some carabid beetles.</article-title> <source>Insect Biochemistry</source> <volume>5</volume> (<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>805</fpage>-<lpage>811</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokal</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohlf</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<source> Biometry. 3rd ed</source>. <publisher-name>W.H. Freeman</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <lpage>887</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stat Soft Italia</surname></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<source> Statistica per Windows. User’s Manual</source>. <publisher-name>Statsoft Italia</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Vigonza</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>)<source> Carabid beetles in their environments. A study on habitat selection by adaptations in physiology and behavior</source>. <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg, New York</publisher-loc>, <lpage>369</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Will</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attygalle</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herath</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> New defensive chemical data for ground beetles (Coleoptera: Carabidae): interpretations in a phylogenetic framework.</article-title> <source>Biological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>459</fpage>-<lpage>481</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B44"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaballos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Paralelismo fenológico en <italic>Brachinus variventris</italic> Schaufuss, 1862 y <italic>Anchomenus dorsalis</italic> (Pontoppidan, 1963). (Coleoptera Carabidae)</article-title>. <source>Actas do II Congresso Ibérico de Entomologia</source>, <publisher-loc>Lisboa, Ispagna</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B45"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zetto Brandmayr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonacci</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massolo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandmayr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> What is going on between aposematic carabid beetles? The case of <italic>Anchomenus dorsalis</italic> (Pontoppidan 1763) and <italic>Brachinus sclopeta</italic> (Fabricius 1792) (Coleoptera Carabidae).</article-title> <source>Ethology Ecology and Evolution</source> <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>335</fpage>-<lpage>348</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>