<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.114.1310</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>New species of the genus <italic>Cyamops</italic> Melander  from New Zealand  (Diptera, Periscelididae, Stenomicrinae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Mathis</surname>
                        <given-names>Wayne N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:343B52CC-CFFB-4DC1-AE3A-EC76D0C4B94A</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Sueyoshi</surname>
                        <given-names>Masahiro </given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:B69E84BD-3895-4E5C-890B-ED14DF1A749F</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Entomology, PO Box 37012, MRC 169; Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C. 20013-7012, USA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Forest Zoology Group, Kyushu Research Center, Forestry and Forest Products Research Institute, 4-11-16 Kurokami, Kumamoto, 860-0862 Japan
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Wayne N. Mathis (<email xlink:type="simple">mathisw@si.edu</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Torsten Dikow</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>30</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>114</issue>
            <fpage>29</fpage>
            <lpage>40</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>28</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Wayne N. Mathis, Masahiro Sueyoshi</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:C03FC644-0ED2-4695-8527-B1BAD631CDC0</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Two new species of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Periscelididae</tp:taxon-name>), the first from New Zealand, are described. The two newly described species are: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops alessandrae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops crosbyi</tp:taxon-name></italic>. A key to the genera of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Stenomicrinae</tp:taxon-name> and to the species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Australasian/Oceanian Region and detailed illustrations of structures of the male terminalia are provided.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Diptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Periscelididae (Stenomicrinae)</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>New Zealand</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Melander 1913</xref> includes 30 valid species: two from the Afrotropical Region; 12 from the Australasian/Oceanian Region; three from the Nearctic Region, seven from the Neotropical Region, five from the Oriental Region, and one from <!--PageBreak-->the Palearctic Region (Mathis and Rung 2011). Previously none was known from New Zealand. The purpose of this paper is to describe two new species from New Zealand that were recently discovered. These discoveries were made while conducting general research on acalypterates of this island nation.</p>
            <p>To facilitate identification of these species, we have included a key to the genera of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Stenomicrinae</tp:taxon-name> and to the species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Australasian/Oceanian Region (modified from the key produced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Baptista and Mathis 2000</xref>). We have also produced detailed illustrations of structures of the male terminalia of the new species.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods|materials"><title>Methods and materials</title>
            <p>The descriptive terminology, with the exceptions noted in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Baptista and Mathis (1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2000</xref>), is that published in the Manual of Nearctic <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name> (McAlpine 1981). The format for the species’ description adheres to (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Baptista and Mathis (1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2000</xref>). Because specimens are small, less than 3.00 mm in length, study and illustration of the male terminalia requires use of a compound microscope. For most of the structures of the male terminalia, we follow the terminology adopted by other workers in <tp:taxon-name>Periscelididae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Baptista and Mathis 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Sueyoshi and Mathis 2004</xref>). The species’ descriptions are composite and not based solely on holotypes.</p>
            <p>Three venational ratios used in the descriptions of new species are based on the largest, smallest, and one other specimen and is defined as: (1) Wing ratio: straight line distance between wing base and apex/greatest straight line distance from anterior margin to posterior margin. (2) 1st costal ratio: the straight line distance between the apices of R1 and R2+3 (costal section II)/distance between the apices of R2+3 and R4+5 (costal section III). (3) 2nd costal ratio: straight line distance between the apices of R2+3 and R4+5 (costal section IV)/distance between the apices of R4+5 and M (costal section III).</p>
            <p>Most specimens examined as part of this study are deposited in the New Zealand Arthropod Collection (NZAC, Auckland, New Zealand). A few specimens have been deposited in the Smithsonian Institution (USNM) and California Department of Food and Agriculture (CDFA).</p>
            <p>Dissections of male and female genitalia and descriptions were performed using the method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Clausen and Cook (1971)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Grimaldi (1987)</xref>. Microforceps were used to remove abdomens, which were macerated in a hot sodium hydroxide solution. Cleared terminalia were rinsed in distilled water and 70% ethanol and then transferred to glycerin for observation. For long-term storage, abdomens were placed in an attached plastic microvial filled with glycerin and attached to the pin supporting the remainder of the insect from which it was removed.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics"><title>Systematics</title>
            <sec sec-type="Key to genera of the subfamily Stenomicrinae"><title>Key to genera of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Stenomicrinae</tp:taxon-name></title>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frons with 1 pair of interfrontal setae; eyes bare. Katepisternum with 2 subequal setae. Hindfemur bearing anterodorsal, preapical seta</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Planinasus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cresson 1914</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frons lacking interfrontal setae; eyes microsetulose, sometimes sparsely. Katepisternum bearing 1 prominent seta. Hindfemur lacking anterodorsal, preapical seta</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fronto-orbital setae reclinate or occasionally mesoclinate, lacking a proclinate seta; medial vertical seta present but with proclinate orientation; face in profile angulate, dorsal surface flattened. Supra-alar seta lacking; lateral scutellar setae 1 pair, apical. Crossvein bm-cu absent, making cells bm and dm confluent; vein CuA2 weak or lacking; cell cu<italic>p</italic> lacking</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Stenomicra</tp:taxon-name></italic> Coquillett 1900</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fronto-orbital setae comprising 1 proclinate and 1 reclinate setae; medial vertical seta absent; face in profile shallowly and vertically arched, lacking a flattened, dorsal area. Supra-alar seta present, well developed; lateral scutellar setae variable but usually 2. Crossvein bm-cu well developed, cell bm distinct from dm; vein CuA2 present, well developed; cell cu<italic>p</italic> present</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                </sec>
                <sec sec-type="Description of species"><title/>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <label>Genus</label>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cyamops</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cyamops</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Melander, 1913</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Melander 1913</xref>: 291. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops nebulosus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Melander, by original designation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Sturtevant 1954</xref>: 557–559 [revision]. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Hennig 1958</xref>: 633 [generic characters, relationships], 1969: 610–613 [discussion]. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Sabrosky 1958</xref>: 169–171 [revision], 1965: 820 [Nearctic catalog]. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Khoo 1985</xref>: 527–536 [revision, Australian species]. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Khoo and Sabrosky 1989</xref>: 551 [Australasian/Oceanian catalog]. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Baptista and Mathis 1994</xref>: 1–25 [revision, New World species], <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2000</xref>: 481–506 [review]. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Grimaldi 2009</xref>: 23–27 [revision, Fiji].</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Adult: Small flies, body length 1.65–3.30 mm, with slender habitus.</p>
                        <p><italic>Head:</italic> Typically dark brown in ground color; fronto-orbits below the insertion of fronto-orbital setae, parafacial and genal region usually with silvery white microtomentum; occipital region shiny, sparsely microtomentose; lower face usually strongly microtomentose below genal region; median plate of clypeus shiny brown; head usually broader than thorax; postcranium strongly concave; eye bearing interfacetal setulae, shape of eye in profile more or less diagonal, lower anterior facets enlarged and encroaching on facial region more in males than in females (males and females of two species from Oceanic Region have the face with almost the same width); eyes closer together at lower edge of frons than at top of head; frons slightly longer than wide; ocel<!--PageBreak-->lar tubercle small, situated near vertex; mesofrons somewhat depressed, concave; antennal form as for other <tp:taxon-name>Periscelididae</tp:taxon-name>; arista 3-segmented (see D.K. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">McAlpine 1983</xref>), branched, in some species with basal bifurcate rays; face in profile nearly straight to distinctly angulate, ventral portion (below narrowest gap between eyes) more broadly developed, sometimes shallowly carinate medially, carina narrow to broad, but always broader in females; lower epistomal margin of midface extended around oral opening to form a narrow peristomal area; clypeus a large inverted U, somewhat retracted in males but easily visible in females; palpus short, compressed, with silver luster when viewed under certain angles. Chaetotaxy: Lateral vertical seta slightly to strongly divergent, curved outward; medial vertical and postocellar setae lacking; 2 pairs of fronto-orbital setae, inner pair reclinate, sometimes oriented outward, outer pair proclinate, in most cases pointed inward; inner fronto-orbital seta usually about 3/4 length of outer, rarely shorter; fronto-orbits typically bearing small setulae below setae; true vibrissa apparently absent, but uppermost pair of facial setae developed as porrect, anaclinate “pseudovibrissae,” followed by a row of peristomal setulae and setae at margin of gena; pseudovibrissae sometimes placed externally to row of peristomal setae.</p>
                        <p><italic>Thorax:</italic> Shiny, brown to dark brown, sparsely whitish microtomentose, microtomentum more dense at lower portion of katepisternum; calypter brown; postscutellum developed; greater ampulla convex; prosternum bare. Chaetotaxy: Acrostichal setulae in 2 more or less regular rows, slightly diverging behind, being strongly reduced in some species; dorsocentral setae 0+1 or 0+2, 1st seta, when present smaller, 1 row of dorsocentral setulae in front of setae; some setulae also present between acrostichal and dorsocentral rows in some species; supra-alar seta 1, preceded by small setulae, which can be sometimes strongly reduced; scutellum typically with 1 or 2 pairs of setae, basal pair, when present, smaller, notopleural setae 1+1, 1st seta usually longer; katepisternal seta 1, located dorsally (sometimes a 2nd, smaller and weaker seta is present); anepisternum bare or with 1 seta and few setulae along posterior margin. Wing: Costal vein without true costal breaks, but with a weakness before end of vein R1; costal vein extended to vein M; crossvein bm-cu either present, delimiting discal cell from cell bm (species in Afrotropical, Australian, Nearctic, Neotropical, Oriental, and Palearctic Regions), or absent (some Oceanian species); anal vein sometimes strongly reduced in length; anal cell present, well delimited. Legs: Posteroventral setulae of forefemur sometimes differentiated as a row of distal small, spine-like setulae; mid tibia bearing an apicoventral spine.</p>
                        <p><italic>Abdomen of Male:</italic> Sparsely microtomentose, brown to dark brown; 6th tergite somewhat narrowed, asymmetrical, extended more on right side near 6th sternite; 7th tergite narrow, asymmetrical, fused to 6th and 7th sternites on left side; 7th right spiracle, sometimes also the left, in 7th tergite; surstyli articulated with epandrium, asymmetrical (left usually longer), connected with hypandrium posteriorly by a weak membrane; cerci small, weakly sclerotized to completely membranous, bearing some setae on posterior half; hypandrium asymmetrical, expanded posteriorly on each side into convex, bowl-shaped structures, sometimes bearing a ventral projection on left side, visible near base of 6th sternite (“hypandrial projection”); parameres apparently<!--PageBreak--> absent (a single, setulose postgonite in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops nebulosus</tp:taxon-name></italic>);gonopods present; aedeagal apodeme long, free or joined posteriorly with hypandrium; aedeagus completely sclerotized; ejaculatory apodeme developed, variously shaped.</p>
                        <p><italic>Abdomen of Female:</italic> Syntergosternite 6 a complete ring (tergite and sternite fused), with spiracle within sclerotization; tergite and sternite 7 either fused (Nearctic, Neotropical, Oceanian species), forming a syntergosternal ring enclosing spiracle, or separate (Australian), with spiracle in sternite; segment 8 with tergite and sternite separate, sternite either free (Nearctic and Neotropical species) or partially fused with 7th (Australian species); 2–4 spherical to oblong spermathecae (2 in Australasian/Oceanian species, 3 in Nearctic species, and 4 in Neotropical species).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion.</title>
                        <p>The Australasian/Oceanian fauna demonstrates variation in characters that are constant in American and Afrotropical species, i.e., sexual dimorphism in the shape of the face (absent in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops micronesicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and an undescribed species from Ponape) and presence of crossvein bm-cu. All species, however, have a single pair of dorsocentral setae, and the anepisternum lacks setae along the posterior margin.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to Australasian/Oceanian Species of Cyamops"><title>Key to Australasian/Oceanian Species of Cyamops</title>
                        <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basal aristal rays bifurcate</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basal aristal rays not bifurcate</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midface flat throughout; face of male wide, not constricted medially</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Midface bearing a vertical carina (male) or a wide elevated portion (female); face of male narrow, constricted medially</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Femora brown; male with left surstylus broadly curved (Fiji)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops femobrunneus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Grimaldi, 2009</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Femora yellow or apically brown, male left surstylus virtually straight</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral facial triangle yellow medially and laterally (New Zealand)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops alessandrae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventral facial triangle white laterally and whitish yellow medially</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pedicel and basal flagellomere yellow (Fiji)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops fiji</tp:taxon-name></italic> Baptista and Mathis, 2000</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pedicel and basal flagellomere bicolored, black dorsally, yellow ventrally (New Zealand)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops crosbyi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pseudovibrissa placed externally to the row of peristomal setae; basal scutellar seta about 3/4 or more length of apical seta (Micronesia)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">“Ponape” species complex</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pseudovibrissa aligned with other peristomal setae; basal scutellar seta about 1/2 length of apical seta</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesofacial plate without setae; foretibia and tarsus mostly brown to dark-brown; ocellar tubercle shiny; vertex shiny (Yap)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops micronesicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Baptista &amp; Mathis</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesofacial plate setose between upper peristomal setae; foretibia and tarsus mostly yellow; ocellar tubercle dull microtomentose; vertex dull microtomentose (Ponape)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops</tp:taxon-name></italic> “species 3”</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1st costal ratio 2.3 or more</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1st costal ratio 1.0–1.8</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comb present on ventral margin of midcoxa (Australia)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops pectinatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khoo, 1985</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comb lacking on ventral margin of midcoxa</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peristomal setae on mesofacial plate (Australia)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops claudiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khoo, 1985</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peristomal setae on genal suture</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basal scutellar seta at most 1/3 length of apical seta; tibia and tarsus of foreleg mostly brown to dark-brown (New Guinea)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops papuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Baptista &amp; Mathis</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basal scutellar seta about 3/4 or more length of apical seta; tibia and tarsus of foreleg mostly yellow to yellowish brown</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing hyaline (Australia)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops truncatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khoo, 1985</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing with a conspicuous brown pattern (Australia)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops dayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khoo, 1985</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forefemora with a ctenidium (Fiji)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops femoctenidius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Grimaldi, 2009</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forefemora lacking a ctenidium</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5th sternite of male abdomen divided medially (American Samoa)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops samoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Baptista &amp; Mathis, 2000</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5th sternite of male abdomen entire</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Legs mostly yellowish; midfemur yellow; wing hyaline (Australia)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops australicus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hennig, 1969</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Legs mostly yellowish brown to black; midfemur brown apically; wing with a conspicuous brown pattern (Australia)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops delta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Khoo, 1985</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cyamops</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">alessandrae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8AA31D3E-BFD0-4D99-8827-683E5036FD3C</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cyamops_alessandrae</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Mathis and Sueyoshi</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–4</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Adult body length 1.90–2.60 mm; wing length 2.10–3.00 mm; wing width 0.70–1.10 mm.</p>
                        <p>Head: Ocellar tubercle polished; shiny spot on vertex large and distinct, extended from ocellus 2/3 distance to eye margin; depressed region of frons deep, velvet. Pedicel brownish on dorsal half, otherwise yellow; basal aristal rays minutely bifurcate apically; basal flagellomere yellow, infuscate dorsally. Face constricted medially by the anteroventral margin of the eyes, expanded into a ventral triangular region below level of pseudovibrissae and bearing a vertical, midfacial, yellow carina, facial triangle microtomentose, yellow to whitish yellow, bordered dorsolaterally with yellow stripe, facial setulae in yellow stripe, some specimens with blackish yellow on ventrolateral margin; gena when viewed anteriorly conspicuously silvery white microtomentose, in lateral view more yellowish tan; labellum and palpus pale yellow; face produced, very shallowly angulate. Chaetotaxy: Inner fronto-orbital setae slightly divergent, slightly<!--PageBreak--> smaller than lateral vertical seta; arista bearing 6–7 dorsal, 3 ventral rays; pseudovibrissae oriented dorsally; peristomal setae 6–7.</p>
                        <p>Thorax: Halter brown yellow to yellow; scutellum triangular, posteroapical angle rounded, orientation of scutellum moderately more elevated than scutum, disk a little <!--PageBreak-->convex; postpronotum sparsely microtomentose, subshiny to dull. Chaetotaxy: Dorsocentral setae 0+2, length of anterior seta subequal to posterior seta; mesonotal setulae moderately well-developed; scutellar setae 2, basal seta 1/2 length of apical seta. Wing: Hyaline, slightly fuscous; cells bm and dm separated by crossvein bm-cu; 1st costal ratio 2.6–2.9; 2nd costal ratio 2.2–2.7; wing ratio 0.35–0.36; crossvein bm-cu present. Legs mostly yellow; femora mostly yellow, gradually becoming blackish on apical 1/3; tibiae yellowish, blackish basally and especially apically; apical and subapical tarsomere of each leg blackish brown, 3rd tarsomere brown, basal 2 yellowish.</p>
                        <p>Male abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–4</xref>): 6th tergite about same width as dorsal portion of 7th tergite, both sclerites almost without setae; 4th and 5th sternites with well-developed lateral setae and a row of setae along posterior margin; 5th sternite twice as wide as long; 6th and7th sternite asymmetrically bilobed, left lobe much larger than medial lobe. Male terminalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2–4</xref>): right surstylus in posterior view paddle-like with extended portion angulate ventromedially, lateral margin irregularly rounded, bearing setulae ventrally, basal stem narrowed, broadly stem-like; left surstylus elongate, somewhat digitiform, narrower than right surstylus, basal portion vertical, thereafter oriented ventromedially, apex moderately pointed, in lateral view elongate, almost parallel sided, pointed apically.</p>
                        <p>Female: Head: Ventral midfacial triangle black with silvery white microtomentum; gena densely microtomentose, silver except on facial carina where microtomentum is thin; basal flagellomere infuscate dorsally.</p>
                        <p>Thorax: Legs with femora and tibiae mostly brown.</p>
                        <p>Abdomen: 7th tergite and sternite separate; 7th tergite about 3/4 length of 6th tergite; 2 subequal, spherical spermathecae; sclerotized portion of spermathecal duct about 1/5 length of spermatheca.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>The holotype male is labeled “NEW ZEALAND [North Island:] WO Whangamarino Peat Bog [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">37°20.9'S, 175°06.8'E</named-content>], malaise [sic] trap[,] 22 Nov-20 Dec 2006[,] C. H. Watts/Site 2: Manuka/Baumea/Empodisma/N.Z. Arthropod Collection, NZAC Private Bag 92170 AUCKLAND New Zealand [yellow]/HOLOTYPE ♂ <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops alessandrae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mathis and Sueyoshi NZAC [red].” The holotype is double mounted (glued to a paper point), is in fair condition (head partially collapsed), and is deposited in the NZAC. Twelve paratypes (8♂, 4♀; NZAC, USNM) bear the same locality label data as the holotype. Other paratypes are as follows:</p>
                        <p>NEW ZEALAND. North Island. WO: Kawhia, Taharoa (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">38°09'S, 174°44'E</named-content>; Malaise trap), 22 Nov-20 Dec 2006, C. H. Watts (1♀; NZAC); Kopuatai Peat Bog (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">37°24.1'S, 175°34.1'E</named-content>; Site 1: Sporodanthus &amp; Site 2: Sporodanthus-Empodisma; Malaise trap), 22 Nov-20 Dec 2006, C. H. Watts (5♂, 4♀; NZAC).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The species epithet, <italic>alessandrae</italic>, is a genitive Latin patronym to honor and recognize the numerous contributions of Dr. Alessandra Rung to the study of <tp:taxon-name>Periscelididae</tp:taxon-name> and to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops</tp:taxon-name></italic> specifically.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 1–4.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops alessandrae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (New Zealand. North Island. WO: Whangamarino Peat Bog). <bold>1</bold> 6th and 7th abdominal segments and postabdomen in ventral view <bold>2</bold> epandrium, proctiger, and surstyli, posterior view <bold>3</bold> same, anterior view <bold>4</bold> same, left lateral view. Epandrium, surstyli, aedeagus, and hypandrium are masked by black tone in Fig. 1. All setae on the epandrium are abbreviated in Fig. 2 and 3. Abbreviations: ep, epandrium; s, surstylus; 6–7S: 6th and 7th abdominal sternites. Scale bar: 1 = 0.20 mm, 2–4 = 0.12 mm.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-114-029-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cyamops</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">crosbyi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B8FE6378-7DB8-4359-82FD-5704324BB908</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cyamops_crosbyi</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Mathis and Sueyoshi</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 5–12</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Adult body length 2.20–2.55 mm; wing length 2.30–2.75 mm; wing width 0.85–1.00 mm.</p>
                        <p>Head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>): Ocellar tubercle sparsely microtomentose, subshiny; shiny spot immediately anterior of lateral vertical seta small, about the size of an ocellus; depressed region of frons densely microtomentose, appearing velvety black; fronto-orbits microtomentose, silvery white. Antenna bicolored, dorsal portion brownish black to black, ventral portion yellow; basal aristal rays minutely bifurcate apically; basal flagellomere yellow, infuscate dorsally. Face constricted medially by the anteroventral margin of the eyes, expanding into a triangular region ventrally below the level of the pseudovibrissae and bearing a verticomedial ridge facial region, face yellow in ground color, strongly microtomentose; labellum and palpus pale yellow; face produced and slightly angulate. Chaetotaxy: Inner fronto-orbital setae slightly divergent, slightly smaller than outer vertical seta; arista bearing 9 dorsal, 3 ventral rays, 6 basal rays bifurcate; pseudovibrissae oriented dorsally; peristomal setae 7.</p>
                        <p>Thorax: Halter brown; scutellum trapezoidal, orientation of scutellum moderately more elevated than scutum, disk a little convex; postpronotum polished. Chaetotaxy: Dorsocentral setae 0+2, anterior seta greatly reduced in length, at most 1/8 length of posterior seta; mesonotal setulae moderately well-developed; scutellar setae 2, basal seta 1/3 length of apical seta. Wing: Hyaline, slightly fuscous; cells bm and dm separated; 1st costal ratio 2.7–3.0; 2nd costal ratio 2.1–2.4; wing ratio 0.35–0.37; crossvein bm-cu present. Legs mostly yellow; femora mostly yellow, gradually becoming blackish on apical 1/3; tibiae yellowish, blackish basally and especially apically; apical and subapical tarsomere of each leg blackish brown, 3rd tarsomere brown, basal 2 yellowish.</p>
                        <p>Male abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 6–12</xref>): 6th tergite about same width as dorsal portion of 7th tergite, both sclerites almost without setae; 4th and 5th sternites with well-developed lateral setae and a row of setae along posterior margin; 5th sternite twice as wide as long; 6th and 7th sternite asymmetrically bilobed, left lobe much larger than medial lobe. Male terminalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–12</xref>): right surstylus with extended portion irregularly angulate, in posterior view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>) subtriangular, with obtuse angles, basal stem parallel sided basally; left surstylus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–9</xref>) moderately broad basally, apical half narrow, ventromedial extension, somewhat digitiform, apex pointed, in lateral view elongate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 9</xref>), almost parallel sided, truncate apically; hypandrium and gonites in ventral as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>; aedeagus complex, as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 11–12</xref>.</p>
                        <p>Female: Head: Ventral midfacial triangle black with sparse silvery white microtomentum; gena densely microtomentose, silver except on facial carina where microtomentum is thin; basal flagellomere infuscate dorsally.</p>
                        <p>Thorax: Legs with femora and tibiae mostly brown.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Abdomen: 7th tergite and sternite separate; 7th tergite about 3/4 length of 6th tergite; 2 subequal, spherical spermathecae; sclerotized portion of spermathecal duct about 1/5 length of spermatheca.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>The holotype male is labeled “NEW ZEALAND.N.Isl. AK: Cascade (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">36°53.2'S, 174°31.2'E</named-content>; 60 m), 2 Jan 2994[,] Wayne N. Mathis/HOLOTYPE ♂ <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops crosbyi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mathis &amp; Sueyoshi NZAC [red].” The holotype is double mounted (minuten in a block of plastic), is in excellent condition, and is deposited in the NZAC. Twenty-four paratypes (23♂, 1♀; NZAC, USNM) bear the same locality label data as the holotype.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined"><title>Other material examined.</title>
                        <p>NEW ZEALAND. AK: Henderson Valley, Scenic Reserve (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">36°53.8'S, 174°35.7'E</named-content>; Candia Road entrance. On plants by stream), 14 Jan 2007, S. E. Thorpe (1♀; NZAC).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The species epithet, <italic>crosbyi</italic>, is a genitive Latin patronym to honor and recognize the numerous contributions of Dr. Trevor K. Crosby to the study of <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name> from New Zealand, the family <tp:taxon-name>Simuliidae</tp:taxon-name> in particular.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 5–12.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyamops crosbyi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (New Zealand. North Island. AK: Cascade). <bold>5</bold> head, left lateral view <bold>6</bold> male 4–7th abdominal segments and postabdomen, ventral view <bold>7</bold> epandrium, proctiger, and surstyli, posterior view. 8, same, anterior view <bold>9</bold> same, left lateral view <bold>10</bold> hypandrim and gonites in ventral view <bold>11</bold> phallus, left lateral view <bold>12</bold> same, posterior view. Epandrium, surstyli, aedeagus, and hypandrium are masked by black tone in Fig. 6. All setae are abbreviated in Fig. 7. Abbreviations: ep, epandrium; s, surstylus; 4–7S, 4–7T:, 4–7th abdominal sternites and tergites. Scale bar: 5 = 0.50 mm, 6 = 0.40 mm, 7–10 = 0.25 mm, 11–12 = 0.05 mm.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-114-029-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>We gratefully acknowledge the assistance and cooperation of many organizations and individuals who contributed to the field work and production of this paper. To Trevor K. Crosby (NZAC, New Zealand Arthropod Collection, Landcare Research, Entomology Division, Auckland, New Zealand) and his institution, who loaned specimens, we express our sincere thanks. We also thank Irina Brake and Alessandra C. Rung for reviewing a draft of this paper and the late Hollis B. Williams for generally facilitating the research for this paper.</p>
            <p>Field work on New Zealand was facilitated through a grant from the Mr. Helmut Hollmann, benefactor for research on shore flies. We gratefully acknowledge his generous assistance. British Airways largely provided travel to and from New Zealand. We are very grateful to them for generously supporting this research, especially the fieldwork on New Zealand.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Clausen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<article-title> A revision of the Nearctic species of the tribe Parydrini (Diptera: Ephydridae).</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the American Entomological Society</source> <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Baptista</surname><given-names>ARP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> A revision of New World <italic>Cyamops</italic> Melander (Diptera: Periscelididae).</article-title> <source>Smithsonian Contributions to Zoology</source> <volume>563</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Baptista</surname><given-names>ARP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Notes on the genus <italic>Cyamops</italic> Melander (Diptera: Periscelididae), including description of ten new species.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington</source> <volume>102</volume>:<fpage>481</fpage>-<lpage>506</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimaldi</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Phylogenetics and taxonomy of <italic>Zygothrica</italic>.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History</source> <volume>186</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>-<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimaldi</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title>The Asteioinea of Fiji (Insecta: Diptera: Periscelididae, Asteiidae, Xenasteiidae).</article-title> <source>American Museum Novitates</source> <volume>3671</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hennig</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>)<article-title> Die Familien der Diptera Schizophora und ihre phylogenetischen Verwandtschaftsbeziehungen.</article-title> <source>Beiträge zur Entomologie</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>5/6</issue>): <fpage>505</fpage>–<lpage>688</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hennig</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>)<article-title> Neue Gattungen und Arten der Acalyptratae.</article-title> <source>Canadian Entomologist</source> <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>589</fpage>-<lpage>633</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoo</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> The Australian species of <italic>Cyamops</italic> Melander (Diptera: Periscelididae).</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>527</fpage>-<lpage>536</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoo</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabrosky</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<source> 75. Family Stenomicridae. In: Evenhuis, NL (Ed) Catalog of the Diptera of the Australasian and Oceanian Regions.</source> <publisher-name>B. P. Bishop Museum special publication 86 and E. J. Brill</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Honolulu and Leiden</publisher-loc>, <lpage>551</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>in press</year>)<source> World catalog and conspectus on the family Periscelididae (Diptera: Schizophora). Myia 12</source>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McAlpine</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> A new subfamily of Aulacigastridae (Diptera: Schizophora), with a discussion of aulacigastrid classification.</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McAlpine</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<article-title> Morphology and terminology-adults.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McAlpine</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> et al. (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Manual of Nearctic Diptera. Volume 1. Research Branch Agriculture Canada, Monograph no. 27</source>, <publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc>, <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Melander</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1913</year>)<article-title> A synopsis of the dipterous groups Agromyzinae, Milichiinae, Ochthiphilinae and Geomyzinae.</article-title> <source>Journal of the New York Entomological Society</source> <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>283</fpage>-<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabrosky</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>)<article-title> New species and notes on North American acalyptrate Diptera.</article-title> <source>Entomological News</source> <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>-<lpage>176</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabrosky</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>)<article-title> Family Anthomyzidae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> et al. (<role>Eds</role>) <source>A catalog of the Diptera of America north of Mexico, USDA handbook 276</source>, <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>, <fpage>810</fpage>–<lpage>820</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturtevant</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1954</year>)<article-title> Nearctic flies of the family Periscelidae (Diptera) and certain Anthomyzidae referred to the family.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the United States National Museum</source> <volume>103</volume> (<issue>3332</issue>):<fpage>551</fpage>-<lpage>561</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sueyoshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> A new species of <italic>Cyamops</italic> Melander, 1913 (Diptera: Periscelididae) from Japan and a review of the Japanese Periscelididae.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington</source> <volume>106</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>