<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.150.1877</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    <italic>Sphaerosyllis levantina</italic> sp. n. (Annelida) from the eastern Mediterranean, with notes on character variation in 
                    <italic>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</italic> Claparède, 1863
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Faulwetter</surname>
                        <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:9BF02566-AF30-47EB-840E-DFC841B6FF84</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Chatzigeorgiou</surname>
                        <given-names>Georgios</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:E3A716D4-9C20-4DD0-A231-EAA04168F17D</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Galil</surname>
                        <given-names>Bella S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:06EF9833-A3C5-48FA-BBA8-1881AC51E361</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Nicolaidou</surname>
                        <given-names>Artemis</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:9FA2A4EE-7E52-4111-A9B6-CDB99E7C909E</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Arvanitidis</surname>
                        <given-names>Christos</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:737F149F-C30C-42EB-A690-5E693AD95427</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Zoology-Marine Biology, Faculty of Biology, National and Kapodestrian University of Athens, Panepistimiopolis, 15784, Athens, Greece
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Department of Biology, University of Crete, 71409 Heraklion, Crete, Greece
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>National Institute of Oceanography, Israel Oceanographic &amp; Limnological Research, POB 8030, Haifa 31080, Israel
            </aff>
            <aff id="A4">
                <label>4</label>Institute of Marine Biology and Genetics, Hellenic Centre for Marine Research, 71003 Heraklion, Crete, Greece
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Sarah Faulwetter (<email xlink:type="simple">sarifa@hcmr.gr</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: C. Glasby</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>28</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>150</issue>
            <fpage>347</fpage>
            <lpage>380</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>18</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Sarah Faulwetter, Georgios Chatzigeorgiou, Bella S. Galil, Artemis Nicolaidou, Christos Arvanitidis</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:18BC77D8-3A1A-433F-AAC2-47534DF3FC48</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Examination of polychaete specimens from Haifa Bay (Israel, eastern Mediterranean Sea) revealed several individuals exhibiting morphological characteristics similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> Claparède, 1863. A detailed morphometrical analysis of the Israeli specimens in comparison to specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Musco, Çinar and Giangrande, 2005 supported the description of the former as a new species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> Individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> formed a very heterogeneous group with strong character variations in the analysis and the presumed cosmopolitan distribution of the species is discussed based on literature records.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Polychaetes</kwd>
                <kwd>Syllidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Exogoninae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Sphaerosyllis</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>Mediterranean</kwd>
                <kwd>Cybertaxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>Scratchpads</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The polychaete genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Claparède, 1863 (<tp:taxon-name>Annelida</tp:taxon-name>) is one of the most species-rich genera of the syllid subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Exogoninae</tp:taxon-name>. At present, ca. 48 species are considered valid within <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic> after the recent split of the group into the three genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Prosphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Erinaceusyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">San Martín 2005</xref>). Up to date, 18 species of the genus have been recorded from the Mediterranean Sea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Musco and Giangrande 2005</xref>), one of them described but yet unnamed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">San Martín 2003</xref>), another one in the process of description (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Del Pilar-Ruso and San Martín in press</xref>). In the framework of a project focusing on the soft bottom benthos of Haifa Bay (Israel, eastern Mediterranean Sea), a number of individuals of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic> were found to exhibit morphological features which did not entirely correspond to any description of known <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic> species, namely falcigers with a strong serration and with a subdistal spine present in all chaetigers. A subdistal spine on the blades of at least some falcigers has been described for the type species of the genus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Claparède 1863</xref>, and for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Musco, Çinar and Giangrande, 2005. Re-examination of material of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> revealed that some individuals –contrary to descriptions available in the literature– possess a subdistal spine not only on the blades of the falcigers in anterior but also in posterior chaetigers. Consequently, this characteristic could not be used to unambiguously distinguish the Israeli material from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic>. In order to clarify the relationship between the three very similar species possessing falcigers with a subdistal spine, a morphometric analysis has been performed, a method allowing not only to discriminate statistically significant groupings but also to identify taxonomically important characters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Costa-Paiva and Paiva 2007</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="material|methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <sec sec-type="Specimen collection and processing"><title>Specimen collection and processing</title>
                <p>Specimens were collected on 11 Oct. 2009 in Haifa Bay, (Israel, Eastern Mediterranean Sea) from fine to medium sands in shallow waters (10 m). Sediment samples were taken with a Van-Veen grab (KAHLSICO, model WA265/SS214) 32×35 cm, volume 20 l, penetration 20 cm. The sediment was preserved in buffered formalin 10% for 3–7 days, then sieved through a 250 µm mesh sieve and subsequently stored in 70% ethanol. Specimens were examined under an Olympus SZx12 stereomicroscope and an Olympus BX50 microscope. Illustrations in pencil were made by means of a drawing tube, subsequently scanned, imported into a graphic program (GIMP), re-drawn<!--PageBreak--> and saved as a vector graphic. Three specimens selected for obtaining Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM) images were dehydrated, critical point dried (Bal-Tec CPD 030), sputter-coated with gold (Bal-Tec SCD 050) and examined under a JEOL JSM-6390LV at the Department of Biology, University of Crete. Specimens are deposited in the invertebrate collection of the Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History, Washington D.C., USA (USNM) and in the Tel Aviv University Zoological Museum, Israel (TAU).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Morphometric analyses"><title>Morphometric analyses</title>
                <p>A total of 30 individuals belonging to three species (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic>: 3 individuals; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic>: 21 individuals; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.: 6 individuals) were analysed. Twenty-five variables were measured: I. body length, to account for size-dependencies of other characters; II. number of chaetigers; III. length of blade of dorsalmost falciger of a) anterior, b) midbody, c) posterior chaetigers; IV. length of blade of ventralmost falciger of a) anterior, b) midbody, c) posterior chaetigers; V. ratio of length of blades of dorsalmost to ventralmost falciger in a) anterior, b) midbody, c) posterior chaetigers; VI. ratio of length of blades of falcigers in anterior to posterior chaetigers for a) dorsalmost; b) ventralmost falciger; VII. Ratio of length of dorsalmost falciger to body length in in a) anterior, b) midbody, c) posterior chaetigers; VIII. Ratio of length of ventralmost falciger to body length in in a) anterior, b) midbody, c) posterior chaetigers; IX. maximum length of serration of falcigerous blades in a) anterior, b) midbody, c) posterior chaetigers (smooth, finely serrated, strongly serrated); X. presence of a subdistal spine in dorsalmost falcigerous blades of in a) anterior, b) midbody, c) posterior chaetigers.</p>
                <p>Body length was measured excluding antennae, anal cirri and palps. Falciger blade lengths were measured from point of insertion into shaft to distal tip. Falciger blade lengths could not always be measured on the same chaetiger in all animals if blades were broken. Instead, measurements were made in predefined body regions (anterior: first 1–5 chaetigers; posterior: last 5–7 chaetigers; midbody: in between). Three individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> were excluded from the multivariate statistical analysis due to missing values for some characters.</p>
                <p>Summary statistics (mean, minimum, maximum, standard deviation, coefficient of variation and range of values) were calculated for each species (measurements and calculations available in online supplementary material:</p>
                <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/measured-values-sphaerosyllis-specimens" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/measured-values-sphaerosyllis-specimens</ext-link></p>
                <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/summary-statistics-sphaerosyllis-hystrix" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/summary-statistics-sphaerosyllis-hystrix</ext-link></p>
                <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/summary-statistics-sphaerosyllis-boeroi" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/summary-statistics-sphaerosyllis-boeroi</ext-link></p>
                <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/summary-statistics-sphaerosyllis-levantina" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/summary-statistics-sphaerosyllis-levantina</ext-link>)</p>
                <p>To take the different data types (numerical, categorical, binary) into account, Gower’s similarity coefficient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Gower 1971</xref>) was chosen to calculate a similarity matrix. <!--PageBreak-->Multidimensional Scaling (MDS) was subsequently employed to display the similarities of the different individuals. To test for significance of differences between species a PERMANOVA (Permutational Multivariate Analysis of Variance) was performed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Anderson 2001</xref>). A Principal Component Analysis (PCA) was used to determine variability of characters and to identify characters for the species differentiation. To determine the importance of the characters discriminating the species, the Principal Component Scores were correlated (Spearman’s correlation coefficient) with the measured character values of each individual.</p>
                <p>Multivariate statistical analyses were performed with PRIMER V6, correlation of the Principal Component Scores were calculated with the R package (R package version 2.10; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.R-project.org</ext-link>).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Electronic publication"><title>Electronic publication</title>
                <p>The description of the new taxon was prepared in a Virtual Research Environment (Scratchpads) allowing for rapid and simultaneous publication of the results in print as well as electronically in a semantically enhanced form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Blagoderov et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Penev et al. 2010</xref>). This publication and all supplementary data (measurements, results of statistical analyses, images) can be accessed on the Polychaete Scratchpads (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org</ext-link>).</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results"><title>Results</title>
            <sec sec-type="Taxonomic results"><title>Taxonomic results</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">levantina</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9CEE8F90-9596-49F6-AA22-BB79C0E816D9</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Sphaerosyllis_levantina</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Holotype (USNM 1160540) ALA-IL-7, Haifa Bay, 10.5 m depth. Label: “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic>, Haifa Bay, coll. B. Galil 11.10.09 [Holotype]”. Paratypes USNM 1160541–1160573: 33 individuals, TAU-AN 25006: 10 individuals; Haifa Bay, Israel, Eastern Mediterranean Sea, Station ALA-IL-7, coll. 11.10.2009, depth 10.5 m; Labels: “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic>, Haifa Bay, coll. B. Galil 11.10.09 [Paratype X]” (where X=1–43). All material preserved in 96% Ethanol.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comparative material examined"><title>Comparative material examined</title>
                        <p><bold>.</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Musco, Çinar, and Giangrande, 2005 (Southern Evoikos Gulf, Aegean Sea, Greece: 3 specimens [Label: Tribe <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic>]). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Southern Evoikos Gulf, Aegean Sea, Greece: 1 specimen [Label: Tribe <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic>]; Northern Evoikos Gulf, Aegean Sea, Greece: 7 specimens [Label: DI9a 7.3.91 <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic>, checked S.Martín], all deposited the in <!--PageBreak-->Hellenic Centre for Marine Research, Anavyssos, Greece; Chalkida, Aegean Sea, Greece: 1 specimen [Label: 56 – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic>, κατώτερη µεσοπαραλιακή Χαλκίδας, Στενά Ευρίπου, Ξενοδοχείο Λούσι, St. 18, 25.9.97 0-0.5m, Άτοµα: 1, Διδακτορικού Mίλτου] (= lower intertidal zone, Chalkida, Eviros Straight, Hotel Lousi, coll. M.S. Kitsos), Chalkida, Aegean Sea, Greece: 1 specimen [Label: 26 – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic>, κατώτερη µεσοπαραλιακή Χαλκίδας, Στενά Ευρίπου, Ξενοδοχείο Παλίρροια, St. 1a, 24.9.97 0-0.5m, Άτοµα: 1, Διδακτορικού Mίλτου] (= lower intertidal zone, Chalkida, Eviros Straight, Hotel Palirroia, coll. M.S. Kitsos), Chalkida, Aegean Sea, Greece: 6 specimens [Label: 33 – S<italic>phaerosyllis hystrix</italic>, κατώτερη µεσοπαραλιακή Χαλκίδας, Στενά Ευρίπου, Ξενοδοχείο Παλίρροια, St. 1α, 24.9.97 0-0.5m, Άτοµα: 6, Διδακτορικού Mίλτου] (= lower intertidal zone, Chalkida, Eviros Straight, Hotel Palirroia, coll. M.S. Kitsos), Chalkida, Aegean Sea, Greece: 4 specimens [Label: 80 – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic>, κατώτερη µεσοπαραλιακή Χαλκίδας, Στενά Ευρίπου, Ξενοδοχείο Παλίρροια, St. 1α, 24.9.97 0-0.5m, Άτοµα: 6, Διδακτορικού Mίλτου] (= lower intertidal zone, Chalkida, Eviros Straight, Hotel Palirroia, coll. M.S. Kitsos), Thessaloniki, Aegean Sea, Greece, 1 specimen [Label: 66 – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic>, κατώτερη µεσοπαραλιακή Λιµάνι Θεσσαλονίκης, 2γ, 6.10.97 0-0.5m, Άτοµα: 1, Διδακτορικού Mίλτου]) (= lower intertidal zone, Port of Thessaloniki, coll. M.S. Kitsos), all deposited the in Zoological Museum of the Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Greece.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality"><title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p>Eastern Mediterranean Sea, Levantine Basin, Israel, Haifa Bay (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">32°54.533N, 35°04.071E</named-content>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, entire animal, with 25 chaetigers, length 1.9 mm with palps but without anal cirri; width at sixth chaetiger 250 µm without parapodia, 300 µm with parapodia. Body small, slender, widest at level of proventricle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Dorsal papillation on anterior chaetigers irregular, after proventricle in four longitudinal rows: two mid-dorsal rows with two papillae per segment, lateral rows with three papillae near dorsal cirri (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Ventrum without visible papillation. Prostomium wider than long with 4 coalescent lensed eyes in trapezoidal arrangement. Anterior eyespots absent. Antennae pyriform with bulbous bases and elongated tips, median antenna <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->40 µm long, lateral ones 33 µm, longer than prostomium and palps together. Median antenna inserted between anterior pair of eyes, lateral ones attached on anterior margin of prostomium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Palps directed ventrally, fused along their length, with a dorsal notch and few small papillae. Peristomium indistinct, dorsal fold partly covering prostomium. One pair of tentacular cirri, shaped like antennae but shorter (23 µm). Second chaetiger without dorsal cirri but with large papilla instead. Dorsal cirri similar in shape and length to tentacular cirri, anteriorly as long as parapodial lobes (23 µm), posteriorly slightly longer (28 µm). Ventral cirri conical, half as long as parapodial lobe, originating at bases of parapodia. Parapodial lobes triangular, with small papilla on each side of distal end. Parapodial glands with fibrillar material and with conical opening; from fourth chaetiger. Anterior parapodia with 4–5, rarely with 6 falcigers per fascicle; blades slender, unidentate with small subdistal spine and strong serration on 1–2 dorsalmost falcigers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2b–d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3a</xref>). Dorso-ventral gradation in length of blades, dorsal ones maximally 14 µm, ventral ones 10 µm. Posteriorly, dorsal blades of similar length (13 µm), but stouter and more curved with robust subdistal spine and strong serration as long as subdistal spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2e, f</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b, c</xref>). Dorsalmost falciger posteriorly thicker than remaining ones in fascicle. Blades of ventral falcigers similar throughout body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2g</xref>). All shafts with fine serration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). Dorsal simple chaeta from chaetiger 1, subdistally serrated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2h</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4a</xref>). Ventral simple chaeta on posterior chaetigers, sigmoid, smooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref>). Anteriorly two aciculae per parapodium, one distally bent at right angle, acuminate tip curved upwards, the other straight and blunt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref>); posteriorly only one acicula of the former type per parapodium. Pharynx occupying three chaetigers. Width more than ¾ of width of proventricle. Pharyngeal tooth located on anterior margin, surrounded by a crown of soft papillae. Proventricle in chaetigers 3–4 (120 µm long) with 15–17 muscle cell rows. Pygidium papillated, with two cirriform anal cirri twice as long as dorsal cirri (60 µm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 1.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. holotype, dorsal view</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-150-327-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 2.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. SEM images of <bold>a</bold> anterior end and midbody, dorsal view <bold>b–c</bold> compound chaetae, anterior chaetigers <bold>d</bold> dorsalmost compound chaetae, anterior chaetiger <bold>e</bold> compound and dorsal simple chaetae, midbody <bold>f</bold> dorsalmost compound chaeta, posterior chaetiger <bold>g</bold> ventralmost compound chaetae, posterior chaetiger <bold>h</bold> dorsal simple chaeta</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-150-327-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 3.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Dorsal (left) and ventral (right) falciger of <bold>a</bold> anterior <bold>b</bold> midbody <bold>c</bold> posterior chaetiger</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-150-327-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 4.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>a</bold> dorsal <bold>b</bold> ventral simple chaeta <bold>c</bold> aciculae, anterior chaetiger</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-150-327-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Derived from the type locality (Levantine Basin), levantina being a neo-Latin adjective meaning “pertaining to the region where the sun raises”; feminine declination in accordance with the genus name (Syllis was a river nymph in the greek mythology and thus female).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution"><title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Israeli Coast (Levantine Basin, Eastern Mediterranean Sea).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Habitat"><title>Habitat.</title>
                        <p>Fine to medium sands.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Taxonomic remarks"><title>Taxonomic remarks.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis minima</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hartmann-Schröder, 1960 in having blades of falcigers with strong serration throughout the body. However, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis minima</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a stronger dorso-ventral gradation of the blades of falcigers (dorsal ones twice as long as ventral ones) than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (dorsal ones 1.5 times longer than ventral ones) and the ventral cirrus is longer than the parapodial lobe in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis minima</tp:taxon-name></italic>, whereas is is half as long as the parapodial lobe in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Day, 1953, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis taylori</tp:taxon-name></italic> Perkins, 1981, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis sandrae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Álvarez and San Martín, 2009 are similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in the shape and serration of the blades of the falcigers, but <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> has all antennae positioned in line (median one posteriorly of lateral ones in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis taylori</tp:taxon-name></italic> shows no dorso-ventral gradation of the falciger blade length (dorsal blade 1.5 times longer than ventral one in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.) and<!--PageBreak--> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis sandrae</tp:taxon-name></italic> has smooth falcigerous blades posteriorly and parapodial glands with hyaline material (strongly serrated blades throughout the body and parapodial glands with fibrillar material in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.). All the above species differ from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by lacking a subdistal spine on the blades of the falcigers. The only <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic> species known to possess this spine are <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> Claparède, 1863, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis parabulbosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> San Martín and López, 2002 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Musco, Çinar &amp; Giangrande, 2005. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis parabulbosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> clearly differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by having minute dorsal cirri and antennae, by the presence of a subdistal spine only on blades of the posterior falcigers and by smooth blades of posterior falcigers. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in having much longer blades of the falcigers which show a more pronounced dorso-ventral gradation (dorsal blades 2.6 times longer than ventral ones in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 1.5 times longer in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.) than those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, see also tables in online supplementary material), by having a subdistal spine on blades of all falcigers (only on dorsalmost ones in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.) and by the dorsalmost falcigers being serrated only proximally. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic>, according to the literature, has a subdistal spine only on the blades of the anterior dorsalmost falcigers. However, in the examined material of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Aegean Sea 8 out of 21 specimens also possessed a subdistal spine in posterior falcigers. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> can nevertheless be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by having smooth or finely serrated posterior falcigers (serration less than half the length of the subdistal spine), even when the spine is present (serration almost as long as subdistal spine in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2f</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Furthermore, the blades of the dorsalmost falcigers show an anteroposterior gradation in length in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> (anteriorly 1.5 times longer than posteriorly), whereas they are of similar length throughout the body in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, see also tables in online supplementary material). Finally, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a very narrow pharynx (almost half the width of proventricle), whereas the pharynx of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is wider than ¾ of the width <!--PageBreak-->of the proventricle. An identification key to the Mediterranean <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic> species is provided at the end of this manuscript.</p>
                        <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 5.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Dorsal (left) and ventral (right) falciger of <bold>a</bold> anterior <bold>b</bold> midbody <bold>c</bold> posterior chaetiger</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-150-327-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 6.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Dorsal (left) and ventral (right) falciger of <bold>a</bold> anterior <bold>b</bold> midbody <bold>c</bold> posterior chaetiger</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-150-327-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Ben-Eliahu (1977)</xref> discusses two different morphological forms of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> occurring in her samples from Israel. Based on her description and illustrations, the animal identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Westheide 1974</xref> could potentially belong to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. because of the similar characters of falcigers andpapillation. However, the description does not report the characteristic subdistal spine on the blades of the posterior falcigers. In addition, Westheide’s (1974) description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Galápagos Islands differs from both Ben-Eliahu’s specimen and the present material by the absence of parapodial glands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Westheide 1974</xref>), a character considered as variable and thus of no taxonomic value by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Ben-Eliahu (1977)</xref> but recently accepted as a taxonomically stable character (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Riser 1991</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Multivariate morphometrical analysis"><title>Multivariate morphometrical analysis</title>
                <p>The results of the Principal Component Analysis show that the first principal component (PC1) account for 77.4% of the variability, the second (PC2) for 16.4% and the remaining 3 PCs for 5.1% (eigenvector values available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/morphometric-analysis-pca-eigenvectors" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/morphometric-analysis-pca-eigenvectors</ext-link>). The Spearman’s correlation of the Principal Component scores with the measured character values of the individuals revealed that the length of the dorsalmost falcigerous blades in all<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> body parts (anterior, midbody, posterior), as well as the ratio of the anterior to posterior ventralmost falcigerous blade are the most important characters discriminating between the three species (ρ-values &gt;0.8 / &lt;-0.8 at p &lt; 0.005) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/spearmans-correlation-principal-component-scores-vs-measurements" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/spearmans-correlation-principal-component-scores-vs-measurements</ext-link>).</p>
                <p>The PCA plot of the first two components show a discrimination of species into three groups, with individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. having the lowest PC1 scores, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> the highest scores. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> show similar PC2 scores, whereas <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> shows lower scores, and, except for one small-sized individual, forms a distinct group apart from the remaining species. Individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. likewise form a close group, however, a couple of individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> cannot be distinguished from this cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). The MDS diagram gives similar results, with individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. forming distinct groups, whereas individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> are spread as a heterogeneous group, with some of them being plotted close to individuals of either <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> or <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 7.</label>
                    <caption><p>PCA plot.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-150-327-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 8.</label>
                    <caption><p>MDS plot.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-150-327-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <p>The PERMANOVA analysis results in a <italic>p</italic>-value of 0.001 as calculated by 999 permutations, thus the null-hypothesis (no differences between the groups) cannot be sustained. Subsequent analyses of the differences between species through pairwise tests reveals significant differences between species (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> / <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic>: <italic>p</italic> = 0.003, 713 permutations; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> / <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. nov: <italic>p</italic> = 0.001, 995 permutations; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> / <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.: <italic>p</italic> = 0.015, 84 permutations).</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic> –like many of the small-sized <tp:taxon-name>Exogoninae</tp:taxon-name> genera– has a difficult and often confused taxonomy and biogeography. Among the potential causes contributing to the current confusion the following could be cited: a) lack of detail in older (before ca. 1970) species descriptions; b) difficulties of observing certain characters in fixed material (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Riser 1991</xref>); c) descriptions of new species without examination of comparative material; d) ongoing discussions on the taxonomic value of characters such as the presence or absence of dorsal cirri on the second chaetiger (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Fauvel 1923</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">San Martín 2005</xref>), presence and type of parapodial glands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Westheide 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Ben-Eliahu 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Riser 1991</xref>) and variations in chaetal structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Riser 1991</xref>). These factors have lead to the assignment of individuals with very different character sets to the same species name and thus to wide-spread distribution records of some species. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> (type locality Normandy, France) is included among those species with an alleged cosmopolitan distribution, since it has been recorded from most European coasts including the Mediterranean Sea, the north-western coasts of America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Berkeley and Berkeley 1948</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Hartman 1968</xref>), the Galápagos Islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Westheide 1974</xref>), China (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Men et al. 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Ding and Westheide 2008</xref>), Australia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Hartmann-Schröder 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">1985</xref>) and the Western Atlantic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Hartman and Fauchald 1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Temperini 1981</xref>), among others. However, recent studies suggest that the North American records of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis pirifera</tp:taxon-name></italic> Claparède, 1868 are in fact <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis californiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hartman, 1966 and that the two European species are not represented in the American Pacific fauna (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Kudenov and Harris 1995</xref>). Similarly, some specimens from the Mediterranean Sea previously identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> had been re-examined and found to exhibit significant morphological differences to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic>, leading to the establishment of a new species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Musco et al. 2005</xref>). In the light of an ever-increasing number of molecular analyses revealing cryptic species complexes in morphologically indistinguishable polychaete species with an assumed cosmopolitan distribution (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Westheide and Hass-Cordes 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Westheide and Schmidt 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Barroso et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Bleidorn et al. 2006</xref>) it is likely that the various specimens recorded under the name <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> may in fact form a complex of similar species, especially since many descriptions differ substantially from each other (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Ben-Eliahu 1977</xref>).</p>
            <p>The morphometric analysis conducted in this study support the hypothesis of several morphologically very similar species co-existing in the Mediterranean. The individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> form distinct groups in the PCA and MDS plots, however the individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> show a much wider spread, marginally overlapping with the other two species when only the meristic characters are taken into account. This is explained through a high character variability in the examined individuals, especially concerning the presence of a subdistal spine on the blades of the posterior falcigers and the length of the falciger blades. The presence of a subdistal spine on all dorsal falcigerous blades is invariable in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., wheras individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> with otherwise very similar chaetal structures might or might not possess such spine. Another feature that seems to be highly variable in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the length of the falciger blades in relation to body size. In fact, individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. with short falciger blades are located at the lower end of the size spectrum of all measured blades, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> with almost spiniger-like blades at the higher end, whereas the blade lengths of the examined individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> form a smooth transition between the other two species.</p>
            <p>However, when tested by strict statistical criteria, the hypothesis of different co-existing species is significantly supported, and based on their meristic characters the species show significant differences. The results of the current study suggest that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> may well constitute a species complex. Given the difficult taxonomic status of the genus, similar results might be expected for other species as well, and consequently, distributions of several <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic> species might be in fact questionable or unknown.</p>
            <sec sec-type="Key to the Mediterranean Sphaerosyllis species"><title>Key to the Mediterranean <tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name> species:</title>
                <p>The three species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis claparedei</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ehlers, 1864, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis papillifera</tp:taxon-name></italic> Naville, 1933 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis ovigera</tp:taxon-name></italic> Langerhans, 1879 are poorly known. All have been described as having dorsal cirri on the second chaetiger, however, other species, such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic>, were also originally described or illustrated with dorsal cirri on the second chaetiger whereas they are in fact absent. Since the three aforementioned species are exclusively known from their<!--PageBreak--> original description (or partly reproductions of these) and have never been re-described based on new material, they are tentatively included in the key below, but their identity remains questionable.</p>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal cirri on chaetiger 2 present</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal cirri on chaetiger 2 absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Papillae on dorsum absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis claparedei</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ehlers, 1864</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Papillae on dorsum present</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parapodial glands absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis papillifera</tp:taxon-name></italic> Naville, 1933</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parapodial glands with fibrillar material</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis ovigera</tp:taxon-name></italic> Langerhans, 1879</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parapodial glands present</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parapodial glands absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parapodial glands with fibrillar material</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parapodial glands with granular material</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All antennae in line</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis capensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Day, 1953</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median antenna inserted more posteriorly than lateral ones</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal cirri shorter than parapodial lobes, at least in anterior chaetigers</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal cirri longer than parapodial lobes</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blades of falcigers strongly serrated, short (&lt;10µm); shafts with strong spines</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis thomasi</tp:taxon-name></italic> San Martín, 1984</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blades of falcigers with serration only anteriorly and dorsalmost; blades with slight dorso-ventral gradation but always longer than 10µm; shafts smooth</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis parabulbosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> San Martín and López, 2002</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blades of falcigers without marked dorso-ventral gradation in length</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis taylori</tp:taxon-name></italic> San Martín, 1984</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blades of dorsalmost falcigers at least 1.5 times the length of ventral ones</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blades of posterior dorsal compound falcigers smooth to finely serrated</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> Claparède, 1863</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blades of posterior dorsal compound falcigers strongly serrated (spinules of almost same length as the subdistal spine)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blades of anterior dorsal compound falcigers at least twice as long as ventral ones; anteroposterior gradation of blade length; blades of both dorsal and ventral compound chaetae with a subdistal spine</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Musco, Çinar and Giangrande, 2005</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blades of anterior dorsal compound falcigers less than twice as long as ventral ones; no anteroposterior gradation of blade length; blades of only dorsal compound chaetae with a subdistal spine</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis levantina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blades of dorsalmost falcigers long (&gt;30µm), at least twice as long as ventral ones</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis magnidentata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Perkins, 1981</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blades of falcigers short (&lt;15µm), with only slight dorso-ventral gradation</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal cirri clearly longer than parapodial lobes</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. [San Martín, 2003]</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal cirri as long as or shorter than parapodial lobe</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennae bulbous with small tip, shorter than prostomium; dorsal simple chaetae smooth; anterior parapodia with two aciculae, one straight, one with tip bent at right angle</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. Del-Pilar-Ruso &amp; San Martín, in press</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennae pyriform, as long as prostomium, dorsal simple chaetae serrated, all parapodia with one acicula</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis glandulata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Perkins, 1981</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All aciculae straight</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tip of some aciculae bent at right angle</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsal cirri with conspicious papilla, giving cirri a bifid appearance</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis gravinae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Somaschini and San Martín, 1994</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doral cirri without papilla</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis bulbosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Southern, 1914</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All antennae in line</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis austriaca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Banse, 1959</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median antenna inserted more posteriorly than lateral ones</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior parapodia with two aciculae, one straight, one with tip bent at right angle; pharyngeal glands on chaetiger 1 present</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis pirifera</tp:taxon-name></italic> Claparède, 1868</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All parapodia with one acicula only; pharyngeal glands on chaetiger 1 absent </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis piriferopsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Perkins, 1981</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowlegements</title>
            <p>The authors kindly acknowledge assistance from the following colleagues: Dr Nomiki Simboura (HCMR, Anavyssos) and Dr Miltiadis Kitsos (Aristotelian University of Thessaloniki) for loans of comparative material of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis hystrix</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphaerosyllis boeroi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, Dr Guillermo San Martín (Universidad Autónoma de Madrid) for the provision of some of the literature resources, Mrs Alexandra Siakouli (University of Crete) for taking SEM pictures, Dr Vincent Smith, Simon Rycroft, Ben Scott (NHM, London) and Dr Lyubomir Penev (Pensoft Publishers, Bulgaria) for support with the electronic Scratchpads publication. The two reviewers (Dr Guillermo San Martín, Dr Luigi Musco) are thanked for their suggestions to improve the manuscript. Financial support was provided by the ViBRANT project (FP7, EU).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> A new method for non-parametric multivariate analysis of variance.</article-title> <source>Austral Ecology </source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>-<lpage>46</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1442-9993.2001.01070.pp.x" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1111/j.1442-9993.2001.01070.pp.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Álvarez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>San Martín</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> A new species of <italic>Sphaerosyllis</italic> (Annelida: Polychaeta: Syllidae) from Cuba, with a list of syllids from the Guanahacabibes Biosphere Reserve (Cuba).</article-title> <source>Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the UK </source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>1427</fpage>-<lpage>1435</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0025315409000654" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1017/S0025315409000654</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>﻿Banse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>)<article-title> Über die Polychaeten-Besiedlung einiger submariner Höhlen. Ergebnisse der Österreichischen Tyrrheni- Expedition 1952, Teil XII.</article-title> <source>Pubblicazioni della Stazione Zoologica di Napoli </source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>-<lpage>469</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barroso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klautau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solé-Cava</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paiva</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> <italic>Eurythoe complanata</italic> (Polychaeta: Amphinomidae), the “cosmopolitan” fireworm, consists of at least three cryptic species.</article-title> <source>Marine Biology </source> <volume>157</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00227-009-1296-9" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1007/s00227-009-1296-9</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Eliahu</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>)<article-title> Polychaete cryptofauna from rims of similar intertidal vermetid reefs on the Mediterranean coast of Israel and in the Gulf of Elat: Exogoninae and Autolytinae (Polychaeta Errantia: Syllidae).</article-title> <source>Israel Journal of Zoology </source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Berkeley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berkeley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1948</year>)<source> Canadian Pacific Fauna.</source> <publisher-name>Fisheries Research Board of Canada</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc>, <lpage>100</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blagoderov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brake</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgiev</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penev</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryrcroft</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agosti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catapano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Streamlining taxonomic publication: a working example with Scratchpads and ZooKeys.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys </source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.50.539" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.3897/zookeys.50.539</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bleidorn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartolomaeus</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> Mitochondrial sequence data expose the putative cosmopolitan polychaete <italic>Scoloplos armiger</italic> (Annelida, Orbiniidae) as a species complex. BMC Evolutionary Biology 6: 47. </source><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-6-47" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1186/1471-2148-6-47</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Claparède</surname><given-names>É</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1863</year>)<source> Beobachtungen über Anatomie und Entwicklungsgeschichte wirbelloser Thiere an der Küste von Normandie angestellt. Wilhelm Engelmann Verlag, Leipzig, 172pp. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biodiversitylibrary.org/item/40310" xlink:type="simple">http://biodiversitylibrary.org/item/40310</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Claparède</surname><given-names>É</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1868</year>)<source> Les annélides chétopodes du Golfe de Naples. Mémoires de la Société de physique et d’histoire naturelle de Genève 20: 313–584. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biodiversitylibrary.org/item/18576" xlink:type="simple">http://biodiversitylibrary.org/item/18576</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa-Paiva</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paiva</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> A morphometric analyis of <italic>Eunice</italic> Cuvier (Annelida, Polychaeta) species.</article-title> <source>Revista Brasileira de Zoologia </source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>-<lpage>358</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S0101-81752007000200013" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1590/S0101-81752007000200013</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1953</year>)<article-title> The Polychaete fauna of South Africa. Part 2. Errant species from Cape shores and estuaries.</article-title> <source>Annals of the Natal Museum </source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>397</fpage>-<lpage>441</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Del-Pilar-Ruso</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>San Martín</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>in press</year>)<source> Description of a new species of <italic>Sphaerosyllis</italic> Claparède, 1863 (Polychaeta: Syllidae: Exogoninae) from the Alicante coast (W Mediterranean) and first report for the Mediterranean Sea and the Iberian Peninsula of two other species of Syllidae. Mediterranean Marine Science.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z-hu</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westheide</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Interstitial Exogoninae from the Chinese coast (Polychaeta, Syllidae).</article-title> <source>Senckenbergiana Biologica </source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1864</year>)<source> Die Borstenwürmer (Annelida Chaetopoda) nach systematischen und anatomischen Untersuchungen dargestellt. Wilhelm Engelmann Verlag, Leipzig, 748 pp. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biodiversitylibrary.org/item/18348" xlink:type="simple">http://biodiversitylibrary.org/item/18348</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fauvel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1923</year>)<source> Polychètes errantes. Faune de France, Paris, 488 pp. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.faunedefrance.org/bibliotheque/docs/P.FAUVEL(FdeFr05)Polychetes-errantes.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.faunedefrance.org/bibliotheque/docs/P.FAUVEL(FdeFr05)Polychetes-errantes.pdf</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gower</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<source> A General Coefficient of Similarity and Some of Its Properties. Biometrics 27: 857–874. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/pss/2528823" xlink:type="simple">http://www.jstor.org/pss/2528823</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1966</year>)<article-title> Quantitive survey of the benthos of San Pedro Basin, southern California. Part II. Final results and conclusions.</article-title> <source>Allan Hancock Pacific Expeditions </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>455</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<source> Atlas of the errantiate polychaetous annelids from California.</source> <publisher-name>Allan Hancock Foundation</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Los Angeles</publisher-loc>, <lpage>828</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fauchald</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<source> Deep-water benthic polychaetous annelids off New England to Bermuda and other North Atlantic areas. Part II. Allan Hancock Monographs in Marine Biology 6: 1–327. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/10088/3458" xlink:type="simple">http://hdl.handle.net/10088/3458</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann-Schröder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1960</year>)<article-title> Polychaeten aus dem Roten Meer.</article-title> <source>Kieler Meeresforschungen </source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>125</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann-Schröder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Die Polychaeten der antiborealen Südküste Australiens (zwischen Albany im Westen und Ceduna im Osten). Teil 10.</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen aus dem Hamburgischen Zoologischen Museum und Institut </source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann-Schröder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Die Polychaeten der antiborealen Südküste Australiens (zwischen Port Lincoln im Westen und Port Augusta im Osten). Teil 11.</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen aus dem Hamburgischen Zoologischen Museum und Institut </source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kudenov</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<source> Family Syllidae Grube, 1850. In: Blake et al. (Eds) Taxonomic Atlas of the Bentic Fauna of the Santa Maria Basin and Western Santa Barbara Channel. The Annelida Part 2 - Polychaeta: Phyllodocida (Syllidae and Scale-Bearing Families), Amphinomida and Eunicida. Santa Barbara Museum of Natural History, Santa Barbara, 1–97.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Langerhans</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1879</year>)<article-title> Die Wurmfauna von Madeira.</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift für wissenschaftliche Zoologie </source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>-<lpage>592</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Men</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z-hu</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B-L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> A preliminary study on small syllides from the Huanghai Sea (Yellow Sea).</article-title> <source>Journal of Oceanography of Huanghai and Bohai Seas </source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Musco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giangrande</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Mediterranean Syllidae (Annelida: Polychaeta) revisited: biogeography, diversity and species fidelity to environmental features.</article-title> <source>Marine Ecology Progress Series </source> <volume>304</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>-<lpage>153</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3354/meps304143" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.3354/meps304143</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Musco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Çinar</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giangrande</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> A new species of <italic>Sphaerosyllis</italic> (Polychaeta, Syllidae, Exogoninae) from the coasts of Italy and Cyprus (eastern Mediterranean Sea).</article-title> <source>Italian Journal of Zoology </source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>-<lpage>166</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/11250000509356666" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1080/11250000509356666</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>﻿Naville</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1933</year>)<article-title> Quelques formes epitoques d’annelides polychetes nouvelles ou peu connues pechees a la lumiere dans la baie de Banyuls.</article-title> <source>Annales des sciences naturelles </source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>171</fpage>-<lpage>208</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Penev</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agosti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgiev</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catapano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blagoderov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brake</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryrcroft</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sautter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chavan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remsen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoev</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Semantic tagging of and semantic enhancements to systematics papers: ZooKeys working examples.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys </source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.50.538" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.3897/zookeys.50.538</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<source> Syllidae, principally from Florida, with descriptions of a new genus and twenty-one new species. Proceedings of the Biological Society of Washington 93: 1080–1172. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biostor.org/reference/73932" xlink:type="simple">http://biostor.org/reference/73932</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Riser</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<source> An evaluation of taxonomic characters in the genus <italic>Sphaerosyllis</italic> (Polychaeta: Syllidae). Ophelia supplement: 209–218.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>San Martín</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<source> Estudio biogeográfico, faunistico y sistemático de los poliquetos de la familia Silidos (Syllidae: Polychaeta) en Baleares. PhD Thesis, Madrid, Spain: Universidad Complutense de Madrid.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>San Martín</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<source> Annelida, Polychaeta II: Syllidae. In: Ramos MA et al. (Eds) Fauna Ibérica, vol. 21.</source> <publisher-name>Museo Nacional de Ciencias Naturales. CSIC</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Madrid</publisher-loc>, <lpage>554</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>San Martín</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Exogoninae (Polychaeta: Syllidae) from Australia with the description of a new genus and twenty-two new species.</article-title> <source>Records of the Australian Museum </source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>152</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3853/j.0067-1975.57.2005.1438" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.3853/j.0067-1975.57.2005.1438</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>San Martín</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>López</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> New species of <italic>Autolytus</italic> Grube, 1850, <italic>Paraprocerastea</italic> San Martín &amp; Alós, 1989, and <italic>Sphaerosyllis</italic> Claparède 1863 (Syllidae, Polychaeta) from the Iberian Peninsula.</article-title> <source>Sarsia </source> <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>-<lpage>143</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/003648202320205210" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1080/003648202320205210</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Somaschini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>San Martín</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Description of two new species of <italic>Sphaerosyllis</italic> (Polychaeta: Syllidae: Exogoninae) and first report of <italic>Sphaerosyllis glandulata</italic> for the Mediterranean Sea.</article-title> <source>Cahiers de Biologie Marine </source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>-<lpage>367</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Southern</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1914</year>)<source> Clare Island Survey. Archiannelida and Polychaeta. Proceedings of the Royal Irish Academy 31: 1–160. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biodiversitylibrary.org/page/34773787" xlink:type="simple">http://biodiversitylibrary.org/page/34773787</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Temperini</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<source> “Sistemática e Distribuição dos Poliquetos Errantes da Plataforma Continental Brasileira entre as Latitudes de 23°05'S&quot; e 30°00'S&quot;.MSc Thesis, São Paulo, Brazil: Universidade de São Paulo.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Westheide</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<article-title> Interstitielle Fauna von Galapagos. XI. Pisionidae, Hesionidae, Pilargidae, Syllidae (Polychaeta).</article-title> <source>Mikrofauna des Meeresbodens </source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>146</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Westheide</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hass-Cordes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Molecular taxonomy: description of a cryptic <italic>Petitia</italic> species (Polychaeta: Syllidae) from the Island of Mahé (Seychelles, Indian Ocean) using RAPD markers and ITS2 sequences.</article-title> <source>Journal of Zoological Systematics and Evolutionary Research </source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>-<lpage>111</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1439-0469.2001.00166.x" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1046/j.1439-0469.2001.00166.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Westheide</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Cosmopolitan versus cryptic meiofaunal polychaete species: an approach to a molecular taxonomy.</article-title> <source>Helgoland Marine Research </source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10152-002-0114-2" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1007/s10152-002-0114-2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
        <sec sec-type="Supplementary material"><title>Supplementary material</title>
            <p>The Scratchpads version of this publication is available at:</p>
            <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/node/35" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/node/35</ext-link></p>
            <p>Character matrices for specimens used in the morphological analysis are available at:</p>
            <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/measured-values-sphaerosyllis-specimens" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/measured-values-sphaerosyllis-specimens</ext-link></p>
            <p>Summary statistics for the species are available at:</p>
            <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/summary-statistics-sphaerosyllis-hystrix" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/summary-statistics-sphaerosyllis-hystrix</ext-link></p>
            <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/summary-statistics-sphaerosyllis-boeroi" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/summary-statistics-sphaerosyllis-boeroi</ext-link></p>
            <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/summary-statistics-sphaerosyllis-levantina" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/summary-statistics-sphaerosyllis-levantina</ext-link></p>
            <p>Results of the morphometric analysis are available at:</p>
            <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/morphometric-analysis-pca-eigenvectors" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/morphometric-analysis-pca-eigenvectors</ext-link></p>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/spearmans-correlation-principal-component-scores-vs-measurements" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/content/spearmans-correlation-principal-component-scores-vs-measurements</ext-link></p>
            <p>Illustrations and graphs of the statistical analysis are available at:</p>
            <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/category/image-galleries/sphaerosyllis" xlink:type="simple">http://polychaetes.marbigen.org/category/image-galleries/sphaerosyllis</ext-link></p>
        </sec>
    </back>
</article>