<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.229.3919</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Revision of the freshwater genus 
                    <italic>Atyaephyra</italic> (Crustacea, Decapoda, Atyidae) based on morphological and molecular data
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Christodoulou</surname>
                        <given-names>Magdalini</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:9C51EB19-3625-4BD3-9049-33B709EDEFEF</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Antoniou</surname>
                        <given-names>Aglaia</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:A9891030-7E7F-41EF-8970-BA949B002BA7</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Antonios Magoulas</surname>
                        <given-names></given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:17EED3B5-B7F5-4665-B97E-A0C729258224</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname> Athanasios Koukouras</surname>
                        <given-names></given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:BEF5A889-9F46-4212-92CC-52FFBA25E250</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Zoology, School of Biology, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, 54124 Thessaloniki, Macedonia, Greece
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Institute of Marine Biology and Genetics, Hellenic Centre for Marine Research, Gournes Pediados, 71003, Heraklion, Crete, Greece
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Magdalini Christodoulou (<email xlink:type="simple">magchris@bio.auth.gr</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Niel Bruce</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>19</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>229</issue>
            <fpage>53</fpage>
            <lpage>110</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>30</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>12</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Magdalini Christodoulou, Aglaia Antoniou, Antonios Magoulas,  Athanasios Koukouras</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:5F529BC5-C0D6-4F36-B9C7-D19BC139BEA4</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> de Brito Capello, 1867 was described from the Mediterranean region almost 200 years ago. Since then, the genus has been recorded from various freshwater habitats in Europe, North Africa and the Middle East. Despite its long history, the taxonomic status of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species remains confusing and uncertain. Consequently numerous specimens from the known range of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> were analysed using morphological characters and mitochondrial COI sequences in an attempt to clarify the taxonomy of this genus. The present study recognises seven <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species, more than twice as many as previously recorded (three), four of which are considered as new. The new species are described, additional information to the original descriptions are provided for the remaining three taxa, while neotypes of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> Millet, 1831 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Karaman, 1972 are designated to stabilize their taxonomy. Non-overlapping distinguishing morphological characters are used to discriminate the examined material into five species, e.g., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bouvier, 1913, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> In <!--PageBreak-->addition, the genetic analysis supports the existence of multiple phylogenetic clades in the broader Mediterranean area and distinguishes two new cryptic species, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> The geographic distribution of these species is confirmed and their phylogenetic relationships are described.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Atyidae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Atyaephyra</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>cryptic species</kwd>
                <kwd>COI</kwd>
                <kwd>freshwater shrimp</kwd>
                <kwd>molecular data</kwd>
                <kwd>morphology</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Atyidae is one of the most diverse shrimp families comprising at least 469 valid species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">De Grave and Fransen 2011</xref>) being found in freshwater habitats world-wide with the exception of Antarctica. However, this high number of species is probably an underestimate of the family’s species richness. The latter becomes evident given the current indication of numerous, yet undescribed species, many of which being characterized as cryptic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Cook et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">Page and Hughes 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">Page et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Cook et al. 2008</xref>) and pending further research to be confirmed or not as such. Currently, 43 atyid genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">De Grave and Fransen 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">Richard et al. 2012</xref>) have been established, five of which (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> de Brito Capello, 1867, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dugastella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bouvier, 1912, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Gallocaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sket and Zakšek, 2009, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Typhlatya</tp:taxon-name></italic> Creaser, 1936, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Troglocaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dormitzer, 1853) are found in the broader Mediterranean region.</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the most widespread atyid taxon in the Mediterranean region with its native range spanning from the Middle East to North Africa, a large part of Southern Europe and to some Mediterranean islands (Corsica, Sardinia, Sicily) (d’ <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">Udekem d’ Acoz 1999</xref>). Furthermore, it has been introduced into North and Central Europe through river canals opened in France (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Dhur and Massard 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">Moog et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Grabowski et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">Straka and Špaček 2009</xref>).</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> was first reported in the Mediterranean region almost 200 years ago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Rafinesque 1814</xref>) and like most of old taxa has a very confused taxonomic history. The oldest species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and only one until recently, was first described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Rafinesque (1814)</xref> as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Symethus fluviatilis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, based on material most likely collected from Simeto River in Sicily (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Holthuis 1993</xref>). In 1831, Millet after studying material from the rivers of the Maine and Loire area (France) thought he found a different species which he described and named <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hippolyte desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Joly (1843)</xref> stated that Millet erroneously placed the new species in the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hippolyte</tp:taxon-name></italic> Leach, 1814 and transferred it to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caridina</tp:taxon-name></italic> H. Milne Edwards, 1837. A few years later, de <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Brito Capello (1867)</xref> described a new genus and a species named <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> from material collected from the surroundings of Coimbra (Portugal) most probably from the River Mondego that crosses the city or from one of its tributaries. Ortman (1890) assigned the species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caridina desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> to a new genus named <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hemicaridina</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However some years later, he realized that the species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hemicaridina desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> were actually the same and thus proposed a new name combination of this species and established <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>.<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <p>In the beginning of the 20th century, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref> described two varieties of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>: (a) a westernvariety named <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii var. occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bouvier, 1913, distributed in North Africa up to Tunisia, and the entire area of Southern Europe, up to and including Macedonia; (b) an eastern one, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii var. orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bouvier, 1913, found in Syria. Fifty years later, these two forms were elevated to subspecies level by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Holthuis (1961)</xref> and since <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii var. occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> contained the name-bearing type of the species it was re-named to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>. A third subspecies, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Karaman (1972)</xref> from Doirani Lake which is situated at the borders between Greece and Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia (F.Y.R.O.M.). Finally, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Al-Adhub (1987)</xref> described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii mesopotamica</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Shatt Al-Arab River and Hammar Lake (Iraq) thus increasing the number of subspecies to four.</p>
            <p>Subsequent studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Gorgin 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Anastasiadou et al. 2004</xref>) questioned the validity of these four subspecies based on the observed overlapping in the key characters used to separate them. However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Anastasiadou et al. (2004)</xref> stated that given the wide distribution of this species and the degree of isolation of its populations it is likely that a detailed examination of other morphological features could reveal real differences among the various populations of this species.</p>
            <p>Recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. (2006)</xref> re-described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> Millet, 1831 after studying specimens from Garrone River (France) and 2 years later they (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Anastasiadou et al. 2008</xref>) re-validated and re-described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> de Brito Cappelo, 1867 based on specimens from São Barnabé River (Odelouca River, Algarve, Portugal).</p>
            <p>After examining two mitochondrial genes (COI, 16S) from specimens collected mainly from the western Mediterranean area, Garcia Muñoz et al. (2009) proposed the existence of two species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, distributed in West Europe and North Africa and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Karaman, 1972 distributed in Greek freshwaters which was elevated from the subspecies to the species level. Furthermore, the authors argued about the existence of a third genetically distinguished group, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra mesopotamica</tp:taxon-name></italic> Al-Adhub, 1987 (or <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bouvier, 1913), without confirming its status as a distinct species. In addition, they synonomised <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic>, as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Anastasiadou et al. (2008)</xref>, with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> was characterized as cryptic since previous studies failed to detect any distinguishing morphological characters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Anastasiadou et al. 2004</xref>) that would enable its discrimination from the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> complex (Garcia Muñoz et al. 2009).</p>
            <p>A comprehensive revision of synonyms of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic>, at species level, has been provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">De Grave and Fransen(2011)</xref> while a list of synonyms at genus level is given by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Holthuis (1993)</xref>.</p>
            <p>This eventful taxonomic history, and the high intra- and inter-specific morphological variability observed among the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> taxa make the recognition of discrete species intricate. Also, the wide distribution of the genus and the apparent isolation between populations may support the existence of new non-described species. Therefore the lack of any study including material covering all the known distribution of the genus provoked the present current multidisciplinary study.</p>
            <p>In an attempt to recognize and delimit species within <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic>, samples covering the known distribution of the genus were analysed, using morphological and <!--PageBreak-->molecular methods to evaluate the consensus of groupings as inferred by both datasets. In the last decade molecular data have been widely used in conjunction with decapod morphology, and have been instrumental in discriminating cryptic or sibling species (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Macpherson and Machordom 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Jesse et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">2011</xref>).</p>
            <p>This study specifically aims to: (a) test the status of the species already recognized based on morphological and molecular data; (b) describe new species based on morphological and molecular data; (c) provide knowledge on the current geographic distribution of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species; (d) describe the phylogenetic relationships of new and previously described species based on COI gene.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <sec sec-type="Abbreviations used">
                <title>Abbreviations used</title>
                <p>MMNH: Macedonian Museum of Natural History, Skopje, F.Y.R.O.M.; ZMAUTH: Zoological Museum of the Department of Biology, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Greece; MNHN: Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris, France; NHM: Natural History Museum, London, England; NMW: Naturhistorisches Museum Wien, Austria; OUMNH: Oxford University Museum of Natural History, England; SMF: Senckenberg Research Institute and Natural History Museum, Frankfurt, Germany and NHMC: Natural History Museum of Crete, Greece; CL: carapace length (measured from the posterior margin of the orbit to the posterior margin of the carapace); stn: station; ovig: ovigerous.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Morphological analyses">
                <title>Morphological analyses</title>
                <p>Specimens were collected with a hand dredge over the period 2000–2012 from numerous river catchments in Greece, while additional material from the rest of the Mediterranean region was either offered or loaned by researchers and Museum collections. Samples were loaned or offered from the following museums: NHM, NMW, MNHN, MMNH, ZMAUTH, OUMNH and SMF. In total 1,082 adult individuals (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.: 4, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>: 431, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.: 194, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>: 111, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>: 106, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.: 92, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.: 2; furthermore 112 and 30 additional individuals were examined pending their assignment to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> respectively) were examined from 122 different stations (49 river basins, 20 countries) spanning throughout the known distribution of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Middle East to North Africa and Europe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Part of this examined material has been included in the studies of Kinzelbach and Koster (1987) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Anastasiadou et al. (2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2008</xref>). A total of 135 morphological characters including 68 somatometric distances were analysed (see Appendix: Table 1). Morphometric measurements were taken using a Carl Zeiss standard trinocular microscope or an Olympus VM stereoscope both with<!--PageBreak--> ocular micrometer. Only adult individuals were taken into account in order to exclude deviations in the features which appear in the juvenile individuals. A threshold of CL ≥ 5 mm was set for all the specimens examined except for those belonging to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> for which the threshold was set to CL ≥ 3.8 mm. The threshold corresponds to the smaller ovigerous individual found. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is of smaller size and thus the threshold must be lower than in the other species. Drawings were made based on photos taken which were subsequently digitized and processed with CorelDRAW® Graphics Suite X5.</p>
                <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 1.</label>
                    <caption><p>Map showing the sampling localities of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> and the geographic distribution of the genus in Europe, Middle East and North Africa. Numbers 1–122, next to a solid symbol, indicate the different rivers, lakes or barrages from where samples were collected. Letters a–d, next to an open symbol, represent localities reported in the published sources of sequences. The symbols correspond to different <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. Question marks indicate station’s unsure placement inside <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (the clarification of their position will have to await the sequencing) while the general distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> shown is only speculation.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Electronic publication">
                <title>Electronic publication</title>
                <p>All data (e.g. taxon descriptions, figures, characters measured) underlying this publication can also be accessed on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> Scratchpad (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://atyaephyra.myspecies.info/">http://atyaephyra.myspecies.info/</ext-link> ). Scratchpads (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scratchpads.eu">http://scratchpads.eu</ext-link> ) is a Virtual Research Environment, that enable taxonomists to collaborate in the production of websites documenting the diversity of life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Blagoderov et al. 2010</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Molecular analyses">
                <title>Molecular analyses. DNA extraction, amplification and sequencing</title>
                <p>Genomic DNA was extracted exclusively from abdominal tissue using ammonium acetate protocol (provided by Poulakakis N, NHMC, University of Crete, Greece). Abdominal tissue was dissolved in 600μl extraction buffer (0.05M Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 1mM EDTA pH 8.0, 0.15M NaCl, 0.3% sodium dodecyl sulfate, and 0.6μg/μl proteinase K) and incubated in a shaking waterbath at 56°C overnight. Following the incubation, 340μl of 4M ammonium acetate were added to each sample and incubated at room temperature for 60 min. Samples were mixed several times during this period by inversion. The solution was centrifuged at 18,000g for 20 min and supernatant was transferred to 2.0ml centrifuge tubes and 1ml of absolute ethanol was added to each sample. The tubes were inverted several times and centrifuged at 18,000g for 30 min. Following the removal of ethanol samples were dried overnight. DNA pellet was diluted by adding 50μl ddH<sub>2</sub>O and incubated at 4°C overnight. A fragment of the 5' region of mitochondrial (mtDNA) cytochrome c oxidase subunit I (COI) gene was amplified using the polymerase chain reaction (PCR). Two pairs of primers were used for each DNA extract, following the technique of nested PCR. Different combinations of primers were used as first pair: (a) LCO-1490 (5'-GGTCAACAAATCATAAAGATATTGG-3'; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Folmer et al. 1994</xref>) and HCO-2198 (5'-TAAACTTCAGGGTGACCAAAAAATCA-3'; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Folmer et al. 1994</xref>); (b) LCO-1490 and C1-N-2191 (5'-CCCGGTAAAATTAAAATATAAACTTC-3'; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">Simon et al. 1994</xref>); (c) Pals-COI-F1 (5'-GAGCTGAACTAGGTCAACC-3', designed on <tp:taxon-name>Palaemoninae</tp:taxon-name> sequences) and HCO-2198 specifying a ~700 bp to ~600 bp fragment of the COI gene. Thermocycling was performed with an initial denaturation step of two min at 94°C; followed by 35 cycles of one min at 94°C, one min at 42–52°C (depending on the primer pair used), and one min at 72°C, with a final extension of 72°C for 10 min. Then, the primary PCR product was directly used for another amplification reaction, without further purification, using two different combinations of primers as second pair: (a) the newly designed Pals-COI-F1 and Pals-COI-R1 (5'-AGTATAGTAATAGCTCCAGC-3', designed on <tp:taxon-name>Palaemoninae</tp:taxon-name> sequences) and (b) C1-J-1718, (5'-GGAGGATTTGGAAATTGATTAGTTCC-3'; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">Simon et al. 1994</xref>) and Pals-COI-R1 which amplified a ~450 bp and ~330 bp fragment respectively. The thermal profile for the secondary amplification reaction was the same as that of the primary amplification reaction. All amplification reactions were carried out in a final volume of 20μl. Each reaction contained 1.0μl template DNA, 0.15μM of each primer, 0.15mM dNTPs, 1.5mM or 3mM MgCl2 (depending on the primer pair used), 1X PCR reaction buffer, and 0.5U Taq (Gennaxon).</p>
                <p>In some cases after the nested PCR a re-amplification was made using a modified Band-stab PCR protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Bjourson and Cooper 1992</xref>). The re-amplification reaction was carried out in a final volume of 50μl containing: 0.1μM of each primer, 0.08mM dNTPs, 1mM MgCl2, 1X PCR reaction buffer, and 1.25U Taq (Gennaxon). After an initial denaturation step of two min at 94°C, 25 cycles of one min at 94°C, one min at<!--PageBreak--> 45°C, and one min at 72°C were performed, followed by a final extension of five min at 72°C. The amplified fragments were then purified using ethanol and sodium acetate precipitation method and sequenced using Big Dye Terminator Cycle Sequencing 3.1 (Applied Biosystems) standard protocol on an ABI 3730 Genetic Analyzer (Applied Biosystems). All individuals were sequenced either with the forward or the reverse COI primer or with both (Pals-COI-F1, Pals-COI-R1).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Alignment and genetic divergence">
                <title>Alignment and genetic divergence</title>
                <p>Thirty-seven new COI sequences were generated (GenBank accession numbers JX289898–JX289919, JX289921–JX289933, JX289935–JX289936; <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Our dataset was supplemented with eight COI sequences of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the study of Garcia Muñoz et al. (2009), one from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Franjević et al. (2010)</xref>, one from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">Zakšek et al. (2007)</xref> and four from Page et al. (unpublished data). Furthermore, three COI sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Page et al. 2005a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">Zakšek et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Garcia Muñoz et al. 2009</xref>) from another two atyid genera, were included as outgroups (i.e. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dugastella valentina</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Ferrer Galdiano 1924</xref>) from Spain, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dugastella marocana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bouvier, 1912 from Morocco, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paratya curvirostris</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Heller, 1862) from New Zealand,accession numbers provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The choice of the taxa used as outgroup was based on their close relationship with the genus under study since they all belong to the same atyid group (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Paratya</tp:taxon-name></italic> group) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">Von Rintelen et al. 2012</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
								<label>Table 1.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens and COI sequences accession numbers listed by area and species. The sex and the CL are given for each specimen sequenced in parenthesis (first column). Museum accession numbers are given in parentheses (second column). GenBank accession numbers of published sequences, used in this study, are provided with their corresponding studies indicated by the letters a–e [a: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Garcia Muñoz et al. 2009</xref>, b: Page et al. (unpub sequences), c: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Franjević et al. 2010</xref>, d: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">Zakšek et al. 2007</xref>, e: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Page et al. 2005a</xref>].</p></caption>
                <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specimen</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sampling site</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Station number in Fig. 1</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank accession no. COI</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leb1 (♀, CL: 6.6 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tunisia, Lebna Barrage, 21.3.2010, coll. S. Dhaouadi-Hassen</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289898</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Met1 (♀, CL: 6.8 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tunisia, Ben Metir Barrage, 22.2.1974 (NHM 1515–1540.22.2.74)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289899</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moul1 (♀, CL: 6.1 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morocco, Moulouya River, 11.4.2011, coll. M. Melhaoui</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289900</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Krum2 (♀, CL: 6.9 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morocco, Krumane River, 22.7.1952, coll. J. Phillipson (NHM 1953.12.2.12–15)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289901</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bord2 (♀, CL: 5.7 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Portugal, Bordeira River, 5.3.1985, coll. J. Paula (NHM 1986.261)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289902</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sint1 (♀, CL: 7.0 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Portugal, Tagus Basin, Colares River, 1880 (NHM 1880.36)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289903</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mon1 (♀, CL: 7.2 mm)&lt;br/&gt; Mon2 (♀, CL: 6.8 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Portugal, Mondego Basin, Ceira River, 24.5.2010, coll. V. Ferreira</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289904&lt;br/&gt; JX289905</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vet1 (♀, CL: 8.0 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain, Guadalquivir Basin, Guadiamar River, 8.5.2006, coll. C. Lejeusne</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289906</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mu1 (♀, CL: 6.9 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain, Segura Basin, Mundo River, 27.9.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289907</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vb1 (♀, CL: 6.1 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain, Guadiana Basin, Vado Blanco River, 3.10.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289908</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta1 (♀, CL: 7.8 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain, Tagus Basin, Tajuna River, 7.8.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289909</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Er1 (♀, CL: 8.2 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain, Ebro Basin, Erro River, 25.5.2007, coll. J. Oscoz</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289910</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fl1 (♂, CL: 5.3 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain, Catalan Basin, Fluvia River, 4.2.2005, coll. M.L. Zettler</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289911</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gar2 (♀, CL: 6.0 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France, Garrone River, 25.8.2004, coll. R. Liasko and S. Combes</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289912</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sart1 (♀, CL: 7.0 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France, Loire Basin, Sarthe River, 20.9.2000, coll. P. Noél</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289913</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">May2 (♀, CL: 5.6 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France, Loire Basin, Mayenne River, 20.9.2000, coll. P. Noél </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289914</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hav1 (♀, CL: 6.3 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany, Elbe Basin, Havel River, 26.8.2005, coll. M.L. Zettler </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289915</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dan1 (♀, CL: 7.4 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Austria, Danube River, 8.10.1998, coll. Zipek and Melcher (NMW 18315)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289916</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sim3 (♀, CL: 6.5 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sicily, Simeto River, 1.9.1978, coll. C. Froglia </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289917</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Riz1 (♂, CL: 5.8 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corsica, Rizzanese River, 13.8.2003, coll. M.L. Zettler </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289918</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Br1 (♀, CL: 7.9 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corsica, Bravone River, 16.8.2003, coll. M.L. Zettler</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289919</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tunisia, Medjerda River</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ594343</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morocco, Zegzel River</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ594340</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain, Guadalquivir River</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ594339</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain, Ebro River</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ594342</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">France, Loire Basin, Mayenne River</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ594341</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sicily, Frattina River</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ594344</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corsica, Liamone River</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ594345</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guad1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain, Guadalhorce River, coll. C.N. Sánchez </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">b1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX853921</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cog1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sardinia, Coghinas River, coll. M. Jowers</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">b2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX853920</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dour1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Portugal, Douro River, coll. M. Fidalgo</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">b3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289920</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drag1 (♂, CL: 5.1 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slovenia, Dragonja River, Aug.1971</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289921</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ach1 (♀ ovig., CL: 5.9 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece, Acherontas River, 15.4.2012, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou (NHM 2012.1493)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289922</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lour1 (♀, CL: 7.6 mm)&lt;br/&gt; Lour2 (♀ ovig., CL: 7.0 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece, Louros River, 15.4.2012, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289923&lt;br/&gt; JX289924</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Croatia, Krka River</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">c1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DQ320047</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>  sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lour3 (♀, CL: 7.4 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece, Louros River, 15.4.2012, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289925</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lef2 (♂, CL: 5.7 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece, Lefkada Island, Vardas River, 2.10.1932, coll. Beier (NHMW 466)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289926</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doir2 (♀, CL: 5.0 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece–F.Y.R.O.M., Doirani Lake, 26.10.1994, coll. S. Jovanovich</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289927</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece, Lisimakhia River</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ594346</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myl1(♀, CL: 5.2 mm)&lt;br/&gt; Myl2 (♀, CL: 5.3 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece, Strymonas Basin, Mylopotamos Springs, 23.5.2011, coll. M. Christodoulou and M.S. Kitsos</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289928&lt;br/&gt; JX289929</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece, Nestos River</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">d1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DQ641570</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kar2 (♀, CL: 4.5 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey, Orontes Basin, Karasu River, 22.9.1982, coll. R.K. Kinzelbach (SMF 12174)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289930</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Or2 (♀, CL: 5.0 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syria, Orontes River, 30/31.3.1979, coll. R.K. Kinzelbach (SMF 12050)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289931</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Euph2 (♀, CL: 4.7 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syria, Euphrates River, 17.8.1978, coll. R.K. Kinzelbach (SMF 12188)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289932</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shat2 (♀, CL: 5.3 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iraq, Euphrates–Tigris Basin, Shatt Al-Arab River, 2011, coll. M.D. Naser</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289933</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AlH1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iraq, Euphrates–Tigris Basin, Al-Huaizah Marshes, coll. M.D. Naser</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">b4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289934</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="4"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nah1 (♀, CL: 6.2 mm)&lt;br/&gt; Nah2(♀, CL: 7.1 mm)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syria: Nahr Al-Kabir River, 5.3.1979, coll. R.K. Kinzelbach (SMF 43020-1)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JX289935&lt;br/&gt; JX289936</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="4">Outgroups</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Dugastella valentina</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">d2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DQ641569</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Dugastella marocana</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morocco</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a9</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FJ594347</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Paratya curvirostris</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">New Zealand (North Island), Marawara Stream </td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">e1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AY661487</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>COI sequences were aligned using FSA (Fast Statistical Alignment) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Bradley et al. 2009</xref>) and translated into amino acids prior to analysis, to ensure that no gaps or stop codons were present in the alignment. The number of distinct haplotypes was estimated with the software Arlequin version 3.5.1.3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Excoffier and Lischer 2010</xref>). jModelTest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">Posada 2008</xref>) was used to determine the model of DNA sequence evolution that best fit the data using AIC and BIC criteria. Sequence divergences were estimated with the software MEGA version 5.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">Tamura et al. 2011</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Phylogenetic analyses">
                <title>Phylogenetic analyses</title>
                <p>Phylogenetic inference analyses were conducted using Neighbor Joining (NJ), Maximum Likelihood (ML), and Bayesian Inference (BI) methods. The nucleotide substitution model selected by jModeltest [Tamura-Nei, 1993 (TrN) + gamma (G)] was applied to the data matrix in all analyses. A NJ tree was produced with the software MEGA where branch support was assessed with 1,000 bootstrap replicates. ML estimates were made using PhyML online web server (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Guindon et al. 2010</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.atgc-montpellier.fr/phyml/">http://www.atgc-montpellier.fr/phyml/</ext-link> ). Nearest neighbor interchanges (NNIs) and subtree pruning and regrafting (SPR) topological moves were used to explore the space of tree topologies. Approximate likelihood-ratio test (aLRT) based on a non-parametric Shimodaira-Hasegawa-like (SH-like) procedure was employed to estimate branch support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Guindon et al. 2010</xref>). BI analysis was performed in BEAST version 1.7.2. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Drummond et al. 2012</xref>) assuming an uncorrelated lognormal relaxed-clock model, setting the tree prior to Yule process, run for 100,000,000 generations (10% was discarded as burn-in period). Finally, TreeAnnotator was used to find the Maximum Clade Credibility tree. In order to show the geographic distribution of the distinct haplotypes, in all the analyses, not only the unique haplotypes were used, but all the sequences acquired.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <sec sec-type="Phylogenetic analyses">
                <title>Phylogenetic analyses</title>
                <p>Out of the 51 <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> COI sequences 35 distinct haplotypes were distinguished. Shared haplotypes were observed among individuals in close geographical proximity. Of the 600 nucleotide sites examined, 237 were variable of which 197 were parsimony informative (14% in the first, 2% in second, and 84% in third codon position). The nucleotide substitution model that best fits our data according to both AIC and BIC criteria is Tamura and Nei (1993) + gamma (G) based on which <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> sequence divergence ranged from 0% to 25.7%.</p>
                <p>All employed methods yielded consistent tree topologies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The monophyly of the genus is highly supported in all methodologies (BI posterior probability: 1.0, ML SH-like value: 96, NJ bootstrap value: 95).</p>
                <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 2.</label>
                    <caption><p>Bayesian inference phylogenetic tree of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> based on COI dataset. Numbers on nodes indicate Bayesian Inference posterior probabilities, Maximum Likelihood SH-like branch support and Neighbor Joining bootstrap respectively. Only values above 0.75 and 75% are shown. Colours correspond to those used in Figure 1.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <p>In all phylogenetic analyses four main and well-supported phylogroups were identified, corresponding to different groups of species designated by morphology (presented in the next section) and/or well defined geographic regions throughout the Mediterranean region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The first phylogroup comprises specimens from the Middle East which were classified to the nominal species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> by morphology. Specimens from the topotypical populations of the subspecies <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Orontes River, Syria) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii mesopotamica</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Shatt Al-Arab River, Iraq) were also included. However, present data do not allow for within clade fine scale resolution. The mean genetic distances between the Middle East phylogroup (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and the other groups/subgroups were very high ranging from 18.7% to 24.5% while the average intraspecific distance was 5.8% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
								<label>Table 2.</label>
                <caption><p>Nucleotide mean distances (% Tamura-Nei 1993 + G model) of cytochrome c oxidase I (COI) within (first column) and among the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. The range of pairwise distances is given in parenthesis.</p></caption>
                <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within species</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic></th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic></th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016&lt;br/&gt; (0.000–0.048)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001&lt;br/&gt; (0.000–0.003)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083&lt;br/&gt; (0.059–0.116)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000&lt;br/&gt; (0.000)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.239&lt;br/&gt; (0.206–0.271)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.238&lt;br/&gt; (0.233–0.251)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024&lt;br/&gt; (0.024)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.236&lt;br/&gt; (0.204–0.261)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.232&lt;br/&gt; (0.215–0.241)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167&lt;br/&gt; (0.163–0.176)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003&lt;br/&gt; (0.000–0.005)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.233&lt;br/&gt; (0.201–0.273)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.219&lt;br/&gt; (0.205–0.234)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.182&lt;br/&gt; (0.166–0.194)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.119&lt;br/&gt; (0.117–0.119)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058&lt;br/&gt; (0.009–0.102)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222&lt;br/&gt; (0.192–0.287)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.238&lt;br/&gt; (0.216–0.256)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.187&lt;br/&gt; (0.169–0.200)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.226&lt;br/&gt; (0.190–0.244)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.245&lt;br/&gt; (0.219–0.270)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000&lt;br/&gt; (0.000)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230&lt;br/&gt; (0.208–0.260)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222&lt;br/&gt; (0.215–0.232)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.257&lt;br/&gt; (0.237–0.278)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.232&lt;br/&gt; (0.215–0.242)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.254&lt;br/&gt; (0.243–0.267)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.197&lt;br/&gt; (0.172–0.221)</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>The second phylogroup which is strongly supported by both BI and ML methodologies while in NJ yielded lower bootstrap values (BI posterior probability: 0.99, ML SH-like value: 94, NJ bootstrap value: 65) includes sequences exclusively from Gre<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->ek populations. The Greek phylogroup is further subdivided into three well supported groups. The first subgroup corresponds to the nominal species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, found in West-central Greece. It is worth noticing that specimens from the type locality (Doirani Lake) of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> are also included. The remaining Greek specimens are grouped in two well defined subgroups, one distributed in North-east Greece while the other is located in West Greece (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The mean genetic divergence among the three subgroups ranges from 11.9% to 18.2%, while the mean genetic distances within subgroups varied from 0% to 2.4% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
                <p>The third phylogroup contains specimens from the Syrian River Nahr Al-Kabir and it is strongly supported in all methodologies (BI posterior probability: 0.99, ML SH-like value: 100, NJ bootstrap value: 100). The mean genetic distances between the Syrian subgroup and the other groups/subgroups were very high ranging from 19.7% to 25.7% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
                <p>The fourth phylogroup which is well supported by BI, ML and NJ (BI posterior probability: 0.97, ML SH-like value: 99, NJ bootstrap value: 100) includes specimens originating from West-central Europe, North Africa and the Balkans. Within this phylogroup, specimens from Croatia, Slovenia and Greece form a distinct highly supported subgroup (BI posterior probability: 0.99, ML SH-like value: 100, NJ bootstrap value: 99). The remaining specimens within the phylogroup i.e. specimens from West-central Europe and North Africa, although classified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (nominal species) by morphology (discussed in the next section) do not constitute a well supported subgroup <!--PageBreak-->except in NJ analysis where it is relatively well supported (NJ bootstrap value: 89). Sequences from the topotypical populations of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Mayenne and Sarthe River), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> described by de Brito Capello (Ceira River, tributary of Mondego River) were included in this subgroup as well as a sequence acquired from river Bordeira (Portugal) which is near to São Barnabé River from where <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> was re-described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Anastasiadou et al. (2008)</xref>. The genetic distances between these two subgroups are quite large, ranging from 5.9% to 11.6% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). The lowest values (5.9–6.8%) were observed between the specimens of the Balkan subgroup and those of South Iberian Peninsula and North Africa (Morocco), located in the distant end of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> distribution. On the contrary higher values (7.5–10.2%) were observed between the nearest to the Balkan subgroup populations (e.g. Danube River) as well as between the topotypical populations of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Mayenne and Sarthe River) and the Balkan populations. Furthermore, no haplotypes were shared between these two subgroupings.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Morphological analysis">
                <title>Morphological analysis. Account of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species</title>
              <p>The present study recognises five well defined by morphology species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic>: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Millet, 1831), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Karaman, 1972, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bouvier, 1913 and two new species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Neotypes are designated for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> in an attempt to stabilize their taxonomy. In addition, two cryptic species are defined by the molecular analysis. Descriptions are provided for all these species.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <sec sec-type="Family Atyidae de Haan, 1849 (in de Haan, 1833–1850)">
                <title>Family <tp:taxon-name>Atyidae</tp:taxon-name> de Haan, 1849 (in de Haan, 1833–1850)</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <label>Genus</label>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atyaephyra</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>de Brito Capello, 1867</tp:taxon-authority>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                        <title>Type species:</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> de Brito Capello, 1867: 6–7, Pl. 1, Figs 1A–E [type locality: Coimbra, Portugal]; by monotypy.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Carapace with supraorbital and antennal tooth. Rostrum long and armed up to the tip. Eyes well developed, pigmented. Exopods present only on the two first pairs of pereiopods, carpus of first and second pair of pereiopods with a distal excavation. Uropod diaeresis with a single spine (rarely two). Appendix masculina of male second pleopod long, sub-cylindrical and armed with numerous spiniform setae. Eggs small to medium, size 0.40–0.75 × 0.25–0.5 mm.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">desmarestii</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atyaephyra_desmarestii</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>(Millet, 1831)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Symethus fluviatilis</tp:taxon-name><comment> Rafinesque, 1814: 23–24 [suppressed under the plenary powers for the purposes of the Principle of Priority but not for those of the Principle of Homonymy in Opinion 522 in 1958].</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Acilius fluviatilis</tp:taxon-name><comment>. –<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Rafinesque 1815</xref>: 221.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hippolyte Desmarestii</tp:taxon-name><comment> Millet, 1831: 55–57, Pl. 1, Figs 1A–B [type locality: Mayenne River, Sarthe River, Loir River, Thouet River, Layon River (France)]. –<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">H. Milne Edwards 1837</xref>: 376; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">Taramelli 1864</xref>: 363–369.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Caridina Desmarestii</tp:taxon-name><comment>. –<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Joly 1843</xref>: 34–86, Figs 1–78; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Heller 1863</xref>: 238, Pl. 8, Fig. 3; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">Pelseneer 1886</xref>: 211–216; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Bolivar 1892</xref>: 131.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra Rosiana</tp:taxon-name><comment> de Brito Capello, 1867: 6–7, Pl. 1, Figs 1A–E. [type locality: Coimbra, Portugal].</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hemicardina desmarestii</tp:taxon-name><comment>. –<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Ortmann 1890</xref>: 464–465.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaëphyra Desmaresti</tp:taxon-name><comment>. –<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Ortmann 1895</xref>: 401; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Bouvier 1925</xref>: 84–89, Figs 164–174, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaëphyra Desmaresti</tp:taxon-name><comment> var. <italic>occidentalis</italic> Bouvier, 1913: 65–74, Figs 2E–H, 2J–L, 3E–J, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii desmarestii</tp:taxon-name><comment>. –<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Holthuis 1961</xref>: 5–10, Figs 2A, 3A, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name><comment>. –<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Anastasiadou et al. 2004</xref>: 5–13, partim; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>: 1195–1207, Figs 1–5; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Garcia Muñoz et al. 2009</xref>: 32–42; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">Von Rintelen et al. 2012</xref>: 82–96, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name><comment>. –<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Anastasiadou et al. 2008</xref>: 191–205, Figs 1–5.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>Type material.</bold> Neotype: 1 ovig. ♀ (CL 7.1 mm), MNHN-IU-2009-2270 (ex MNHN-Na480), Maine-et-Loire, France [here designated].</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Non-type material">
                        <title>Non-type material.</title>
                        <p><bold>Tunisia:</bold> 8 ♀♀ (1 ovig.) (CL 5.4–7.4 mm), Barrage Lebna (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 1), 21.3.2010, coll. S. Dhaouadi-Hassen; 2 ♀♀ (CL 6.0–6.8 mm), NHM 1515–1540.22.2.74, Ain Draham, Barrage Ben Metir (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 2), 22.2.1974. <bold>Algeria:</bold> 1 ♂ (CL 5.1 mm), NHM 1955.5.3.15–18, Algiers, Seybouse River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 3), 3.5.1955; 11 ♀♀ (6 ovig.) (CL 5.0–8.0 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.2 mm), NHM 1949.5.2.1–12, Beni Abbes, Saoura River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 4), 2.5.1949, coll. H. Munro Fox. <bold>Morocco:</bold> 4 ♀♀ (1 ovig.) (CL 5.5–6.5 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.0 mm), Moulouya River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 5), 11.4.2011, coll. M. Melhaoui; 1 ♀ (CL 6.9 mm) and 4 ♂♂ (CL 5.2–5.6 mm), NHM 1953.12.2.12–15, Krumane River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 6), 22.7.1952, coll. J. Phillipson. <bold>Portugal:</bold> 21 ♀♀ (12 ovig.) (CL 5.8–7.3 mm) and 11 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–5.7 mm), Algarve, São Barnabé River (Odelouca River) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 7), 23.7.1988, coll. C. d' Udekem d' Acoz; 7 ♀♀ (6 ovig.) (CL 6.2–7.7 mm) and 5 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–5.2 mm), NHM 1971.105, Portimao, Odelouca River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 8), 1970; 18 ♀♀ (4 ovig.) (CL 5.5–8.0 mm) and 3 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–5.1 mm), NHM 1986.261, Bordeira River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 9), 5.3.1985, coll. J. Paula; 5 ♀♀ (4 ovig.) (CL 7.0–8.1 mm) NHM 1880.36, Sintra, Colares River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 10), 1880; 15 ♀♀ (3 ovig.) (CL <!--PageBreak-->5.8–7.9 mm) and 5 ♂♂ (CL 5.3–6.1 mm), Coimbra, Ceira River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 11), 24.5.2010, coll. V. Ferreira. <bold>Spain:</bold> 2 ♀ (CL 6.5–8.0 mm), Veta la Arena, Guadiamar River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 12), 8.5.2006, coll. C. Lejeusne; 5 ♀♀ (CL 6.1–6.7 mm) and 17 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–6.5 mm), Cadiz, Guadalete River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 13), 2000, coll. A. Rodriguez; 3 ♀♀ (CL 5.1–6.3 mm), Segura River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 14), 28.9.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 10 ♀♀ (1 ovig.) (CL 6.1–7.5 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.5 mm), Mundo River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 15), 18/27.9.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 2 ♀♀ (CL 6.6–7.7 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.5 mm), Villalva de la Sierra, Jucar River, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">40°07.99'N, 02°08.38'W</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 16), 16.8.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 7 ♀♀ (CL 5.1–6.4 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.3 mm), Ossa de Montiel, Vado Blanco River, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">38°54.60'N, 02°48.03'W</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 17), 3.10.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 3 ♀♀ (CL 5.7–6.5 mm), El Torno, Bullaque River, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">39°14.36'N, 04°15.57'W</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 18), 11.10.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 2 ♀♀ (CL 7.2–7.7 mm), Canavera, Guadiella River, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">40°25.36'N, 02°28.95'W</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 19), 14.8.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 3 ♀♀ (CL 6.2–8.0 mm), Abanades, Tajuna River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 20), 7.8.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 3 ♀♀ (1 ovig.) (CL 6.3–7.2 mm) and 6 ♂♂ (CL 5.5–6.5 mm), Henares River, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 21), 1.8.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 1 ovig. ♀ (CL 7.4 mm), Naharros, Canamares River, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">41°09.10'N, 02°55.14'W</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 22), 30.7.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 2 ovig. ♀♀ (CL 7.3–7.8 mm), Puebla de Valles, Jarama River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 23), 31.7.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 1 ♀ (CL 5.9 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.1 mm) La Guardia, Cedron River, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">39°48.26'N, 03°20.33'W</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 24), 6.9.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 1 ♀ (CL 5.2 mm), Escalona, Alberche River, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">40°09.45'N, 04°25.04'W</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 25), 27.8.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 1 ♀ (CL 5.1 mm) and 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.3–5.7 mm), Tietar River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 26), 28.8.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 9 ♀♀ (1 ovig.) (CL 5.1 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.0 mm), Tagus River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 27), 14.8.2001 and 5.9.2001, coll. J.L. Moreno Alcaraz; 1 ♂ (CL 5.5 mm), Calanda, Guadalope River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 28), 25.5.2004, coll. J. Oscoz; 1 ♀ (CL 7.2 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.1 mm), Escatron, Martin River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 29), 24.5.2001, coll. J. Oscoz; 1 ♀ (CL 5.6 mm) and 3 ♂♂ (CL 5.3–5.6 mm), Murillo de Gallego, Gallego River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 30), 7.8.2007, coll. J. Oscoz; 1 ovig. ♀ (CL 6.5 mm), Gurrea de Gallego, Soton River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 31), 14.6.2006, coll. J. Oscoz; 1 ♂ (CL 6.2 mm), Lumbier, Irati River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 32), 8.7.2005, coll. J. Oscoz; 2 ovig. ♀♀ (CL 6.9–7.5 mm) and 4 ♂♂ (CL 5.2–5.8 mm), Aspurz, Salazar River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 33), 3.7.2007, coll. J. Oscoz; 1 ovig. ♀ (CL 6.5 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.2 mm), Ripodas, Areta River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 34), 3.7.2007, coll. J. Oscoz; 5 ♀♀ (4 ovig.) (CL 5.0–7.5 mm) and 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.6 mm), Castejon, Alfaro, Tudela, Ebro River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 35), 11/12.7.2007, coll. J. Oscoz; 6 ♀♀ (5 ovig.) (CL 7.0–8.6 mm), San Adrian, Ega River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 36), 27.6.2007, coll. J. Oscoz; 1 ovig. ♀ (CL 7.3 mm) and 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.2–5.5 mm), Marcilla, Aragon River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 37), 28.6.2007, coll. J. Oscoz; 2 (1 ovig.) ♀♀ (CL 8.2–8.5 mm) and 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.6–6.5 mm), Urroz, Erro River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 38), 25.5.2007, coll. J. Oscoz; 1 ovig. ♀ (CL 7.5 mm) and 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.8–6.0 mm), Mendigorria, Salado River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 39), 14.6.2007, coll. J. Oscoz; 1 ovig. ♀ (CL 7.6 mm), Puentelarreina, Arga River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 40), 20.6.2007, coll. J. Oscoz; 1 ♀ (CL 7.2 mm), Iraneta, Arakil River<!--PageBreak--> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 41), 20.6.2007, coll. J. Oscoz; 1 ♀ (CL 7.4 mm), Palazuelos, Jerea River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 42), 1.6.2004, coll. J. Oscoz; 3 ovig. ♀♀ (CL 7.3–8.0 mm) and 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.3–5.5 mm), NHM 1955.10.5.2–6 and NHM 1957.8.12.69–75, Barcelona, Llobregat River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 43), 5.10.1955 and 12.8.1955; 8 ♂♂ (CL 5.2–6.1 mm), Bascara, Fluvia River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 44), 4.2.2005, coll. M.L. Zettler; 3 ♀♀ (CL 5.6–6.6 mm), NHM 1955.10.5.8–10, Gerona, Lake of Banyoles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 45), 5.10.1955. <bold>France:</bold> 30 ♀♀ (18 ovig.) (CL 5.0–7.0 mm) and 20 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–5.2 mm), Merville, Garrone River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 46), 25.8.2004, coll. R. Liasko and S. Combes; 2 ♀♀ (CL 5.5–6.5 mm), NHM 1955.5.3.11–14, Maine et Loire, Loire River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 47), 3.5.1955; 2 ♀♀ (CL 6.6–7.0 mm), Angers, Sarthe River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 48), 20.9.2000, coll. P. Noél; 2 ♀♀ (CL 5.1–5.6 mm), Mayenne River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 49), 20.9.2000, coll. P. Noél; 3 ♀♀ (CL 6.3–6.5 mm), NMW 467, Rennes, Vilaine River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 50), coll. G. Laponge. <bold>Belgium:</bold> 31 ♀♀ (8 ovig.) (CL 5.2–8.3 mm) and 7 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–6.0 mm), Ombret, Meuse River, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 51), 3.8.1979, coll. C. d' Udekem d' Acoz. <bold>Germany:</bold> 1 ♂ (CL 5.2 mm) Berlin, Tegel Lake, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">52°34.98'N, 13°16.44'E</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 52), 13.9.1995, coll. K. Rudolph and M.L. Zettler; 4 ♀♀ (CL 5.7–7.0 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.0 mm), Havel River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 53), <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">52°23.82'N, 12°17.04'E</named-content>, 26.8.2005 (Saxony–Anhalt) and <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">52°29.82'N, 12°24.30'E</named-content>, 27.8.2005 (Brandenburg), coll. M.L. Zettler. <bold>Austria:</bold> 1 ♀ (CL 7.4 mm), NMW 18315, Danube River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 54), 8.10.1998, coll. Zipel and Melcher. <bold>Italy:</bold> 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–5.7 mm), Centa River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 55), 28.5.1989, coll. C. Froglia; 4 ♀♀ (CL 5.3–5.8 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.6 mm), Nestore River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 56), 11.11.1974, coll. C. Froglia; 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.2–5.6 mm), Ponte Nuovo, Chiascio River, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 57), 9.9.1975, coll. Cianficoni; 2 ovig. ♀♀ (CL 7.0–7.5 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.2 mm), Nera River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 58), 5.6.1971, coll. Moretti; 5 ♀♀ (CL 6.2–6.8 mm) and 7 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–6.3 mm), Tiber River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 59), 10.10.1975 (Nestore), 14.10.1975 (Orte), 13.11.1975 (Umbertide), coll. Cianficoni. <bold>Sicily:</bold> 1 ovig. ♀ (CL 7.5 mm) and 4 ♂♂ (CL 5.4–5.9 mm), San Bartolomeo, Rosmarino River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 60), 13.5.1986, coll. C. Froglia; 2 ♀♀ (CL 5.8–6.4 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.5 mm), Simeto River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 61), 1.9.1978, coll. C. Froglia. <bold>Sardinia:</bold> 7 ♀♀ (4 ovig.) (CL 5.5–7.2 mm) and 2 ♂ (CL 5.0 mm), unknown locality (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 62), 13.9.1977, coll. Cav; 2 ♀ (CL 6.7–7.6 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.6 mm), unknown locality, coll. R.B. Manning. <bold>Corsica</bold>: 3 ♀♀ (1 ovig.) (CL 6.3–6.9 mm) and 1 ♂♂ (CL 5.0 mm), Favello, Taravo River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 63), 10.8.2003, coll. M.L. Zettler; 5 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–5.8 mm), Propriano, Rizzanese River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 64), 13.8.2003, coll. M.L. Zettler; 2 ♀♀ (CL 7.2–7.9 mm) and 4 ♂♂ (CL 5.3–6.0 mm), Bravone, Bravone River, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">42°12.36'N, 09°32.10'E</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 65), 16.8.2003, coll. M.L. Zettler.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Amendments to description">
                        <title>Amendments to description.</title>
                        <p>Rostrum long, dorsal margin straight or slightly curved in the middle and pointed upwards, 3.79–8.70, mostly (82% of the individuals examined) 4.64–6.50, × as long as high, shorter, equal to, or longer than scaphocerite. From 17 to 36 (21–28 in 86% of the individuals examined) pre orbital teeth on dorsal margin of rostrum arranged to tip. One to five, most frequently (90% of the individuals examined) 2–4, post orbital teeth and 1–13, most often (88% of the individuals examined) 4–9, teeth on ventral margin of rostrum. Carapace smooth with pterygos<!--PageBreak-->tomial angle not protruding, rounded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Pleuron of fifth abdominal segment pointed with an acute posterior angle. Telsonwith 2–4, most frequently (95% of the individuals examined) 3–4, pairs of dorsal spines arranged in curved fashion. Distal border of telson with 7–15, mostly (89%) 9–13, spines (4–7 pairs) arranged in a fan-like way. Outermost pair of spines shortest, similar to dorsal spines, adjacent pair stronger, terminating before the inner, finely setulose pairs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A–B</xref>). Antennulary stylocerite with its tip failing to reach, reaching or overreaching distal margin of basal peduncle segment. Anterolateral lobe of basal segment short, round or pointed. Distal segment of antennular peduncle with 0–2, predominantly (93%) 1–2, spines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>). Basal lower endite of maxilla densely covered with long simple setae arranged in 15–22, mostly (84%) 17–20, oblique parallel rows. Endite of maxilla 1.39–1.88, most often (90%) 1.49–1.71, × as long as basal lower endite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). Basal endite of first maxilliped reaching clearly beyond distal end of exopod (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). Distal one-third of terminal segment of third maxilliped bearing 0–8, (1–6 in 91% of the individuals examined), mesial spines and one subdistal lateral spine near the base of larger terminal spine, interpretable as dactylus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G</xref>). Armature along flexor margin of dactylus of third and fourth pereiopod consisting of 5–10 (6–8 in 95% of the individuals) and 5–10 (6–8 in 94% of the individuals) spines respectively. Merus of third and fourth pereiopod with 1–7 (3–5 in 95% of the individuals) and 2–6 (3–5 in 99% of the individuals) spines respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4C–D</xref>). Armature along flexor margin of dactylus of fifth pereiopod consisting of 18–43, mostly (87%) 25–35, spines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4E–F</xref>). Endopod of first male pleopod expanded proximally and with a distal portion elongated and tapering, often with a small protruding lobe in its outer subdistal part. Endopod with 14–30 (16–25 in 86% of the individuals examined), spines arranged on a slightly curved inner margin and 9–17 (10–15 in 92% of the individuals examined), setae arranged on outer margin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Anastasiadou et al. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>). 133–848 eggs of 0.4–0.7 × 0.25–0.4 mm size.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Size">
                        <title>Size.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a large sized species with maximum carapace length to be 6.8 mm in ♂♂, 8.5 mm in ♀♀ and 8.6 mm in ovig. ♀♀.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Molecular characters">
                        <title>Molecular characters.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be differentiated from all other species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> by molecular characters, as demonstrated by the phylogenetic analysis of mtDNA COI sequences. Furthermore, 22 haplotypes from 30 different localities found in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> were not shared by any other species of the genus. Finally, it differs from all the other species in the following nucleotide positions in the COI gene of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen Dour1 (Genbank accession number JX289920), position 213: cytosine (C), position 234: cytosine (C) and position 444: adenine (A).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is found in freshwater habitats of North Africa and West-central Europe (see material examined and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been exhaustively described and illustrated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. (2006)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Anastasiadou et al. (2008)</xref> also re-established and redescribed in detail <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a species currently considered as a synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>. In<!--PageBreak--> the present paper the same material used for the redescriptions of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2008</xref>) was examined. Although <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. (2006)</xref> stated that the “holotype” of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> could not be traced in French institutions, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref> clearly stated that he examined material from “<italic>Maine-et-Loire (H. Milne Edwards, probablement des cotypes de Millet)</italic>”. As Millet and H. Milne Edward were contemporary, and it seemed possible that H. Edwards may have asked for some specimens from the MNHN, this material was recently looked for in the MNHN collection, where the material listed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref> is indeed still present (registration number Na480). However, there appears to be a discrepancy (and thus possible clarification) on the actual specimen label to this information. The specimen label (see Appendix: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) provides the following information: (1) “Maine et Loire”, (2) “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Caridina Desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> Millet”, (3) “A. Milne Edwards det.”, (4) “E.L. Bouvier ver. 1899” and (5) “A. Milne Edwards, 1900”. It is difficult to definitively interpret the label information in view of what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref>, a contemporary of A. Milne-Edwards, wrote, as he may have had access to direct, personal information. However, the sample is herein interpreted as having belonged to the A. Milne-Edwards collection, who died in 1900 (1835–1900) and was then accessioned in the museum collection (label item 5), with the material being examined and verified, i.e “<italic>ver</italic>.” in 1899, by Bouvier (label item 4), but that the material originally was identified by A. Milne Edwards (label item 3), and that the material may not have been seen by H. Milne Edwards (although it may have passed from father to son without being recorded as such on the museum labels). It seems, therefore, impossible to certify that these are indeed syntypic specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hippolyte Desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> Millet, 1831, as indicated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref>. However, in deference to Bouvier’s potential knowledge on the matter and in line with Recommendation 75A (ICZN, 1999), a neotype for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is herein selected from this lot, the largest ovigerous female. The designation of a neotype is deemed justified under Art. 75 (ICZN, 1999), as (1) the taxon is involved in a complex nomenclatorial problem which cannot be solved without fixing the identity of the oldest name; (2) the taxon is differentiated from the other taxa in this complex by having 0–8 mesial spines on terminal segment of third maxilliped, the basal endite of first maxilliped clearly reaching beyond distal end of exopod, having 1–5 post orbital rostral teeth, having a not protruding, rounded pterygostomial angle and by the slightly curved endopod of first male pleopod with its distal part elongated and tapering; (3) the selected specimen is the largest (of only two) ovigerous females in lot MNHN-Na480; (4) the reasons the name-bearing types are considered lost (or the contrary cannot be conclusively proven) are given above (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>); (5) the neotype is from the general locality (Maine et Loire) of the type locality of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> from which no other species is known and thus it corresponds morphologically and genetically with data presented herein and in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. (2006)</xref>; (6) the neotype is selected from the “Maine et Loire” sample in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref>, corresponding to the area mentioned in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">Millet (1831)</xref>; and (7) the neotype has been selected from a sample already belonging to <!--PageBreak-->MNHN (Na480). Therefore, all conditions of Art. 75 are considered to be met and the selection of neotype is justified.</p>
                        <p>In light of the current revision of the species complex across Europe, North Africa and the Middle East, a nomenclatorial problem exists with the nomen, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> var. <italic>occidentalis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref>, for which <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref> did not designate a holotype. As such, the syntypic material of this variety (considered to be equivalent to a subspecies under Art. 45.6.4) includes all the material listed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref> to have originated from North Africa and southern Europe, up to Macedonia. As such, this includes material from the Vardar region as summarily listed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref>, the area from which subsequently <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Karaman (1972)</xref> was described. As the name of Bouvier’s variety would take precedence over <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> as used in the present revision (a precedence which would cause considerable confusion), the herein selected neotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see above) is simultaneously selected as the lectotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> var. <italic>occidentalis</italic> Bouvier, 1913. This being fully justified by the inclusion of the “Maine et Loire” material in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref>’s type series. As a result of this action, the nomen <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Karaman, 1972 can be used for the Macedonian taxon (as used herein), whilst <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> var. <italic>occidentalis</italic> Bouvier, 1913 becomes a junior synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Millet, 1831).</p>
                        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref> also mentions he examined material from Coimbra (Portugal), with those particular specimens send by “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Barboza</tp:taxon-name></italic>” from the Museu Bocage under the name <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaëphyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic>. He further indicates that these almost surely are cotypes from Brito Capello (“presque sûrement des cotypes”). These specimens are still present in the collection of MNHN (registration number Na509), with the label information (see Appendix: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>) corroborating the statement in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref> and as such are herein interpreted as syntypes of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> de Brito Capello, 1867. Under ICZN Art. 75.8, the neotype selected by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Anastasiadou et al. (2008)</xref> is thus set aside by the rediscovery of these syntypes. As the synonymy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> seems certain at present, there appears currently no need to select a lectotype amongst the material. It should however be noted that the type locality of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> de Brito Capello, 1867 reverts back to Coimbra (Portugal) and is no longer São Barnabe River, Algarve, as listed in De Grave &amp; Fransen (2011) (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">García Muñoz et al. 2009</xref>).</p>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished among other characters from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the presence of 0–8 mesial spines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G</xref>) on the terminal segment of third maxilliped (vs. 10–38 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">, 6H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8H</xref> respectively) and by the basal endite of first maxilliped reaching beyond distal end of exopod (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>) (vs. basal endite fails to reach or reaches distal end of exopod in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4F</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">, 6F</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8F</xref> respectively). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in having 0–8 mesial spines on the terminal segment of third maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10H</xref>) but it can be discriminated by the presence of 1–5 post orbital rostral teeth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Anastasiadou et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) (vs. no post orbital teeth present leaving short unarmed proximal gap in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A</xref>).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">orientalis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atyaephyra_orientalis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Bouvier, 1913</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">–4</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hemicaridina Desmaresti</tp:taxon-name><comment>. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Barrois 1893</xref>: 126–134: Figs 1–3.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii var. orientalis</tp:taxon-name><comment> Bouvier, 1913: 65–74, Figs 1, 3C [type locality: Syria].</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmaresti</tp:taxon-name><comment>. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Annandale and Kemp 1913</xref>: 241–244.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaëphyra Desmaresti</tp:taxon-name><comment>. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Bouvier 1925</xref>: 84–89 Figs 159–162, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii orientalis</tp:taxon-name><comment>. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Holthuis 1961</xref>: 5–10, Figs 2C–E, 3C–H; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Kinzelbach and Koster 1985</xref>: 127–133, Fig. 1, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii mesopotamica</tp:taxon-name><comment> Al-Adhub, 1987: 1–4, Fig. 1 [type locality: Shatt Al-Arab River and Hammar Lake, Iraq]. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">Salman 1987</xref>: 27–42, Figs 1–8.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name><comment>. –<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Gorgin 1996</xref>: 662–668, Figs 1–2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Anastasiadou et al. 2004</xref>: 5–13, partim; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">Von Rintelen et al. 2012</xref>: 82–96, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>Turkey:</bold> 3 ♀♀ (CL 4.8–5.0 mm), Antalya, Kirkgoz Spring (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 107), 21.6.2006, coll. M. Özbek; 7 ♀♀ (CL 4.5–5.5 mm), SMF 12174, Akbez, Karasu River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 108), 22.9.1982, coll. R.K. Kinzelbach. <bold>Syria:</bold> 10 ♀♀ (3 ovig.) (CL 5.0–6.0 mm) and 4 ♂♂ (CL 4.0–5.0 mm), SMF 12050, below the dam of Ascharna, Orontes River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 109), 30/31.3.1979, coll. R.K. Kinzelbach; 34 ♀♀ (15 ovig.) (CL 4.1–4.8 mm), SMF 12188, north of M’adan, Euphrates River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 110), 17.8.1978, coll. R.K. Kinzelbach; 3 ♀♀ (2 ovig.) (CL 4.5–5.6 mm), SMF SYR8, Euphrates River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 111), 15/16.6.1998, coll. R. Beck. <bold>Israel:</bold> 3 ♀♀ (2 ovig.) (CL 4.7–5.3 mm) and 2 ♂♂ (CL 3.9–4.0 mm), SMF IES 1189, Te’o Spring (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 112), 16.2.1977; 9 ♀♀ (CL 4.3–6.0 mm) and 4 ♂♂ (CL 3.9–4.0 mm), Hula Lake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 113), 29.1.1981, coll. D. Eurth; 2 ovig. ♀♀ (CL 3.8–3.9 mm), NHM 1913.7.24.3–12, Kinneret Lake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 114), 24.7.1913; 1 ♀ (CL 3.9 mm), Samakh, Kinneret Lake, 6.5.1986, coll. R. Ortal; 1 ♀ (CL 4.4 mm), Zaki River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 115), 6.5.1986, coll. R. Ortal; 1 ♀ (CL 4.0 mm), Jordan River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 116), 6.5.1981, coll. R. Ortal; 1 ♀ (CL 4.2 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 3.8 mm), NHM 1938.1.26.8.12, Jordan River, 26.1.1938. <bold>Jordan:</bold> 2 ♀♀ (1 ovig.) (CL 4.0–4.9 mm), SMF 12057, Al-Azraq Oasis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 117), 24.3.1977, coll. H. Damian. <bold>Iraq:</bold> 12 ♀♀ (CL 5.6–6.8 mm) and 3 ♂♂ (CL 4.5–4.8 mm), Basrah, Garmat Ali marsh (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 118), 24.2.1987, coll. A.H.Y. Al-Adhub; 1 ♀ (CL 5.2 mm), NHM 1919.11.14.5–20, Basrah, Shatt Al-Arab River (Robat creek) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 119), 14.11.1919, coll. Capt. Boulenger; 1 ♂ (CL 4.2 mm), NHM 1919.4.28.2–3, Basrah, Shatt Al-Arab River (Robat creek), 28.4.1919, coll. P.J. Barraud; 4 ♀♀ (1 ovig.) (CL 5.2–5.5 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 4.8 mm), Basrah, Shatt Al-Arab River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 120), 2011, coll. M.D. Naser; 1 ovig. ♀, NHM 1919.11.12.11, Amarah, Tigris River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 121), 12.11.1919, coll. J.O. Cooper Esq.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Amendments to description">
                        <title>Amendments to description.</title>
                        <p>Rostrum long, slender, dorsal margin straight, slightly or strongly curved in the middle and pointed upwards or downwards, 6.0–10.0, most frequently (91% of the individuals examined) 6.5–9.25, × as long as high, <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->shorter or equal to, or longer than scaphocerite (longer in 71% of the individuals examined). 14–29 (18–23 in 80% of the individuals) pre orbital teeth on dorsal margin of rostrum arranged to tip. 0–3, most often (85%) 1–3, post-orbital teeth. 3–13 teeth, mostly (96%) 4–10, arranged on ventral margin of rostrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Carapace smooth with pterygostomial angle not protruding and rounded or bluntly produced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3B–C</xref>). Pleuron of fifth abdominal segment pointed ending in an acute or an obtuse posterior angle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). Telsonwith 3–6, predominantly (93%) 4–5, pairs of dorsal spines arranged in curved fashion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref>). Distal border of telson with 7–12, most often (91%) 8–10, spines (4–5 pairs) arranged in a fork-like or a fan-like way. Outermost pair of spines shortest, similar to dorsal spines, adjacent pair stronger terminating beyond, along with or before (beyond and along with in 64% of the individuals) the inner finely setulose pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3E–F</xref>). Basal segment of antennular peduncle with long stylocerite, with its tip failing to reach, reaching or overreaching the distal end of basal segment. Anterolateral lobe of basal segment short and pointed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3H–I</xref>). Distal segment of antennular peduncle with 0–3, most often (93%) 1–2, spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G</xref>). Basal lower endite of maxilla densely covered with long simple setae arranged in 11–16 (12–15 in 93% of the individuals) oblique parallel rows. Endite of maxilla 1.75–2.20, mostly (93%) 1.81–2.07, × as long as basal lower endite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4G</xref>). Basal endite of first maxilliped failing or reaching to distal end of exopod distal margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4F</xref>). Distal one-third of terminal segment of third maxilliped bearing 10–36 (14–31 in 84% of the individuals), mesial spines and one subdistal lateral spine near the base of larger terminal spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4H</xref>). Armature along flexor margin of dactylus of third and fourth pereiopod consisting of 6–11 (7–10 in 97% of the individuals) and 7–11 (8–10 in 89% of the individuals) spines (including terminal spine) respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4B, 4D</xref>). Merus of third and fourth pereiopod with 6–10 (7–9 in 85% of the individuals) and 5–9 (6–7 in 83% of the individuals) spines respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4A, 4C</xref>). Dactylus of fifth pereiopod with 33–55 (36–49 in 83% of the individuals) spines arranged in comb-like fashion on flexor margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4E</xref>). Endopod of first male pleopod expanded proximally with a distal portion stout and not tapering, often, with a, large protruding lobe in its outer subdistal part. Endopod with 13–38 spines arranged on a strongly curved inner margin and 5–8 setae arranged on outer margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4I</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier et al. 1913</xref>: Fig. 1). 32–158 eggs of 0.5–0.75 × 0.35–0.5 mm in size.</p>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 3.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bouvier, 1913, adult ovig. ♀ (SMF 12050): <bold>A</bold> entire individual <bold>B</bold> detail ofpterygostomial boarder <bold>C</bold> detail ofpterygostomial boarder (adult ♀, SMF 12050) <bold>D</bold> right pleuron of fifth abdominal segment <bold>E</bold> telson <bold>F</bold> distal margin of telson <bold>G</bold> right antennular peduncle <bold>H</bold> right antennular lobe <bold>I</bold> right antennular lobe (adult ♀, SMF 12050).</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 4.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bouvier, 1913, adult ovig. ♀ (SMF 12050): <bold>A</bold> right third pereiopod <bold>B</bold> dactylus of third pereiopod <bold>C</bold> right fourth pereiopod <bold>D</bold> dactylus of fourth pereiopod <bold>E</bold> dactylus of right fifth pereiopod <bold>F</bold> right first maxilliped <bold>G</bold> right maxilla <bold>H</bold> rightterminal segment of third maxilliped. Adult ♂ (SMF 12050): <bold>I</bold> right endopod of first male pleopod.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Size">
                        <title>Size.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a small-medium sized species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic>, with maximum carapace length to be 4.8 mm in ♂♂, 6.8 mm in ♀♀ and 5.5 mm in ovig. ♀♀.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Molecular characters">
                        <title>Molecular characters.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be differentiated from all other species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> by molecular characters, as demonstrated by the phylogenetic analysis of mtDNA COI sequences. Additionally, 5 haplotypes, each from a different location, found in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyraorientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> were not shared by any other species of the genus. It also differs from all the other species in the following nucleotide positions in the COI gene of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen Dour1, position 273: guanine (G), position 276: guanine (G) and position 369: cytosine (C).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is found in freshwater habitats of Middle East, from Turkey to Iraq (see material examined and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>)<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref> after examining the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> material deposited in the MNHN collections he assigned it into two varieties (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii var. orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>) based mainly on differences observed in the endopod of first male pleopod. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii var. orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> was originally described from Syria (from Orontes River, near the Lake Qattinah (Lake Homs), from a stream in Kousseir (probably Qoussair) near Damascus and from Barada River, Ataibe, East of Damascus) and was elevated to subspecies level by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Holthuis (1961)</xref>. Apart from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a second subspecies, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii mesopotamica</tp:taxon-name></italic>, was found to exist in the Middle East and was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Al-Adhub (1987)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Al-Adhub (1987)</xref> described the new subspecies based on the presence of a distinct subterminal process (vs. absent from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and the presence of 50 spines on dactylus of fifth pereiopod (vs. 40 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>). Furthermore he noticed that the rostrum of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii mesopotamica</tp:taxon-name></italic> resembles that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Greece but differs in having the distal ventral part always devoid of teeth. Indeed the individuals from Shatt Al-Arab River had the highest number of spines on dactylus of fifth pereiopod ranging from 41–55 but specimens from the River Orontes were also found with up to 47 spines (33–47). Additionally, male individuals having endopod with a distinct subterminal process were found again in River Orontes as well as in other Middle East Rivers. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Gorgin (1996)</xref>, after studying 150 males from two different localities in Iran found individuals with a distinct subterminal process and without inside the same population. Finally, specimens from Greece belonging to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (as the sample of Holthuis to which Al-Adhub refers to) were found to be also devoid of teeth in the distal part of the rostrum. Even in the illustration included in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Holthuis (1961)</xref> work, the Greek specimen is devoid of teeth in the distal part of the ventral margin. Although the genetic distances within the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> phylogroup were high (0.9%–10.2%) no firm conclusion could be drawn whether the hypothesis of multiple species is valid or not. Sequences from Orontes River (topotypical location of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and from Shatt Al-Arab River (topotypical location of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii mesopotamica</tp:taxon-name></italic>) presented a noticeable mean genetic divergence (5.0%) but still not strong enough to support the hypothesis of different species. Detailed future studies on the morphological and genetic variability within the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> distributed throughout the Middle East will help clarify the relationships between the populations in this region. However, only one species is currently considered to exist, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Therefore, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii mesopotamica</tp:taxon-name></italic> is here proposed as a synonym.</p>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> appears to be morphologically more similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by sharing characters such as the presence of numerous mesial spines (10–38) on terminal segment of third maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">, 6H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8H</xref>). It also shares in common with the other two species the presence of fewer rows of setae (12–16) on basal lower endite of maxilla, the endite of maxilla being 1.75–2.24 × as long as basal lower endite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4G</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">, 6G</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8G</xref>) and basal endite of first maxilliped failing or reaching to distal end of exopod distal margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4F</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">, 6F</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8F</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be separated from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of a pointed antennular lobe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3H–I</xref>) (vs. round in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">, 7H</xref>). Further, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished by the strongly curved and distally <!--PageBreak-->stout and not tapering endopod of male first pleopod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4I</xref>) (vs. slightly curved and distally more or less elongated but always tapering in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6I</xref>; slightly or strongly curved but always its distal part is elongated and tapering (ribbon shaped) in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8I</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from the other four species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> in having 10–36 spines on terminal segment of third maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4H</xref>) (vs. 0–8 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">, 12H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">, 14H</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">stankoi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atyaephyra_stankoi</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Karaman, 1972</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">–6</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra Desmaresti var. occidentalis</tp:taxon-name><comment> Bouvier, 1913: 65–74, Figs 2I, 3I, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii desmarestii</tp:taxon-name><comment>. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Holthuis 1961</xref>: 5–10, Figs 2B, 3B, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii stankoi</tp:taxon-name><comment> Karaman, 1972: 81–84, Figs 3, 6, 9, 10 [type locality: Doirani Lake, Greece].</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name><comment>. –<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Anastasiadou et al. 2004</xref>: 5–13, partim</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name><comment>. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Garcia Muñoz et al. 2009</xref>: 32–42, partim</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name><comment> sp. n. 3. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Christodoulou et al. 2010</xref>: partim</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>Type material.</bold> Neotype: NHM 2012.1475, adult ♀ (CL 6.0 mm), Greece–F.Y.R.O.M., Doirani Lake, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 99), among aquatic plants, 9.11.1992, coll. S. Jovanovich and E. Stojkoska [here designated].</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Non-type material">
                        <title>Non-type material.</title>
                        <p><bold>Greece:</bold> 4 ♀♀ (CL 5.4–5.9 mm), Peloponnesus, Alfeios River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 82), 24.9.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 4 ♀♀ (CL 5.4–5.7 mm), Aitoloacarnania, Ozeros Lake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 83), 22.11.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 2 ovig. ♀♀ (CL 5.5–7.0 mm), Aitoloakarnania, Aitoliko, Acheloos River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 84), 4.4.2002, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 3 ♀♀ (CL 5.0–5.5 mm), Aitoloakarnania, <tp:taxon-name>Trichonida</tp:taxon-name> Lake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 85), 22.10.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 4 ♀♀ (CL 5.1–6.5 mm) Aitoloacarnania, Lysimachia Lake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 86), 22.11.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 1 ♀ (CL 6.9 mm) and 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.1–5.3 mm), Thessalia, Tavropou Lake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 87), 14.11.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 17 ♀♀ (CL 6.0–8.0) and 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.0 mm), Thessalia, Enipeas River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 88), 14.10.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 3 ♀♀ (CL 6.5–7.6 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.5 mm), ZMAUTH G1-910, Thessalia, Mati Tyrnavou Lake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 89), 15.11.1977, coll. A. Koukouras; 1 ♀ (CL 6.8 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.2 mm) Thessalia, Pineios River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 90), 15.11.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 1 ♀ (CL 7.0 mm), Thessalia, Lithaios River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 91), 14.11.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 5 ♀♀ (CL 6.0–7.0 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.0 mm), Thessalia, Gritsas River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 92), 15.11.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 3 ♀♀ (CL 6.0–6.7 mm), Macedonia, Aliakmonas River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 93), 9.9.1974 and 26.11.1978; 4 ♀♀ (2 ovig.) (CL 5.7–6.8 mm), ZMAUTH G1-1005, Macedonia, Vegoritida Lake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 94), 17.6.1968; 4 ♀♀ (1 ovig.) (CL 5.5–6.3 mm), ZMA<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->UTH G1-1018, Thessalia, Agra Lake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 95), 17.6.1968, coll. P. Economides; 12 ♀♀ (CL 5.5–7.0 mm) and 3 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–5.5 mm), Thessalia, Edessaios River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 96), 19.10.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 5 ♀♀ (CL 5.0–5.5 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.0 mm), Thessalia, Kariotissa, Moglenitsa River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 97), 18.10.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 4 ♀♀ (CL 6.0–7.0 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.0 mm), ZMAUTH G1-988, Macedonia, Axios River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 98), 16.7.1971, coll. P. Economides; 11 ♀♀ (CL 5.9–7.3 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.1 mm), Macedonia, Richios River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 100), 26.10.01, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; <bold>Greece</bold>–<bold>F.Y.R.O.M.:</bold> 4 ♀♀ (CL 5.0–5.7 mm), Doirani Lake, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 99), 9.11.1992, coll. S. Jovanovich and E. Stojkoska.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Rostrum long, slender, dorsal margin straight or slightly curved in the middle and pointed upwards, 6.12–8.67, mostly (83% of the examined individuals) 6.25 to 7.54, × as long as high, shorter, equal to, or longer than scaphocerite (longer in 76% of the individuals examined). From 17 to 28 (19–27 in 91% of the individuals) pre orbital teeth on dorsal margin of rostrum arranged up to tip. 0–3, predominantly (96%) 1–3, post-orbital teeth. 2–8, most often (96%) 2–6, teeth arranged on ventral margin of rostrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>). Carapace smooth with pterygostomial angle not protruding, rounded (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>). Pleuron of fifth abdominal segment usually pointed ending in an obtuse (ending in an acute angle in 11% of the individuals) posterior angle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5C–D</xref>). Telsonwith 3–6, most often (93%) 5–6, pairs of dorsal spines arranged in curved fashion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5E</xref>). Distal border of telson with 6–11, mostly (87%) 8–10, spines (3–6 pairs), arranged in a fork-like pattern. Outermost pair of spines shortest, similar to dorsal spines, adjacent pair stronger terminating beyond (or along with) the inner finely setulose pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5E–F</xref>). Basal segment of antennular peduncle with long stylocerite, with its tip failing to reach, reaching or overreaching the distal end of basal segment. Anterolateral lobe of basal segment short and rounded (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5H</xref>). Distal segment of antennular peduncle with 1–4, mostly (93%) 1–3, spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5G</xref>). Basal lower endite of maxilla densely covered with long simple setae arranged in 12–16, (13–15 in 89% of the individuals), oblique parallel rows. Endite of maxilla 1.78–2.08, mostly (89%) 1.84–1.99, × as long as basal lower endite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6G</xref>). Basal endite of first maxilliped failing or reaching to distal end of exopod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6F</xref>). Distal one-third of terminal segment of third maxilliped bearing 11–35, frequently (85%) 16–28, mesial spines and one subdistal lateral spine near the base of larger terminal spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6H</xref>). Armature along flexor margin of dactylus of third and fourth pereiopod consisting of 7–11 (7–9 in 98% of the individuals) and 7–10 (7–9 in 98% of the individuals) spines (including terminal spine) respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6B, 6D</xref>). Merus of third and fourth pereiopod with 3–8 (4–6 in 83% of the individuals examined) and 2–6 (3–5 in 88% of the individuals) spines respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6A, 6C</xref>). Dactylus of fifth pereiopod with 26–47, most often (80%) 32–41, spines arranged in comb-like fashion on flexor margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6E</xref>). Endopod of first male pleopod expanded proximally and with a distal portion either elongated (ribbon shape) or more stout but always tapering. Endopod with 13–17 spines arranged on a slightly curved inner margin and 7–12 setae arranged on the outer margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6I</xref>). 96–195 eggs of 0.6–0.7 × 0.4 mm in size.</p>
                        <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 5.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Karaman, 1972. Neotype, adult ♀ (NHM 2012.1475): <bold>A</bold> entire individual <bold>B</bold> right detail ofpterygostomial boarder <bold>C</bold> right pleuron of fifth abdominal segment <bold>D</bold> right pleuron of fifth abdominal segment (adult ♀) <bold>E</bold> telson <bold>F</bold> distal margin of telson <bold>G</bold> right antennular peduncle <bold>H</bold> right antennular lobe.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 6.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Karaman, 1972. Neotype, adult ♀ (NHM 2012.1475): <bold>A</bold> rightthird pereiopod <bold>B</bold> dactylus of third pereiopod <bold>C</bold> rightfourth pereiopod <bold>D</bold> dactylus of fourth pereiopod <bold>E</bold> dactylus of fifth pereiopod <bold>F</bold> rightfirst maxilliped <bold>G</bold> rightmaxilla <bold>H</bold> right terminal segment of third maxilliped. Adult ♂ (ZMAUTH G1 988): <bold>I</bold> right endopod of first male pleopod.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Size">
                        <title>Size.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a large sized species with maximum carapace length of 5.50 mm in ♂♂, 7.60 mm in ♀♀ and 6.8 mm in ovig. ♀♀.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Molecular characters">
                        <title>Molecular characters.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from all other species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> by molecular characters, as shown by the phylogenetic analysis of mtDNA COI sequences, such as the two unique <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> haplotypes. Furthermore, it differs from all the other species in the following nucleotide positions in the COI gene of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen Dour1, position 192: cytosine (C), position 282: adenine (A), position 320: cytosine (C), position 342: cytosine (C) and position 423: cytosine (C).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is found in freshwater habitats in the mainland of West-central Greece and South F.Y.R.O.M. (see material examined and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier (1913)</xref> assigned the material of MNHN originating from Portugal, France, Corsica, Macedonia, Tunisia, Algeria and Morocco to var. <italic>occidentalis</italic> while the material from Syria he assigned to var. <italic>orientalis</italic>. The material from Macedonia was collected from the region of Vardar (Axios) north of Thessaloniki, from the Lake of Amatovo (drained in the early twentieth century) near Kirdzalar (today called Adendron). The two varieties described by Bouvier were elevated in subspecies level by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Holthuis (1961)</xref> and the var <italic>occidentalis</italic> was re-named to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmaresii desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> since it contained the name-bearing type of the species. Few years later, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Karaman (1972)</xref> described a new subspecies from Doirani Lake which is part of the Vardar (Axios) basin and named it <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> ignoring the available name of Bouvier’s (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii var. occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>). However, after designating a neotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Bouvier’s material the nomen <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii var. occidentalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> becomes unavailable since it becomes a junior synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> remarks) and thus the nomen <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be used for the Macedonian taxon (as used herein).</p>
                        <p>Efforts made to trace Karaman’s type material in the MMNH were unsuccessful. According to the director of the Museum, Dr Petkovski S. (pers. comm.), Karaman’s material is considered lost after a fire that took place in the Museum.</p>
                        <p>A neotype for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is proposed for reasons of taxonomic clarification and stability, as foreseen by Art. 75 (ICZN, 1999). The neotype will contribute to the stability of the taxonomic status of the species and avoid further confusion due to nomenclature (see also <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> remarks). Furthermore, it incorporates novel characteristics that distinguish it from the remaining <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species such as: having 11–35 mesial spines on terminal segment of third maxilliped, basal endite of first maxilliped failing or reaching to distal end of exopod, distal boarder of telson with spines arranged in a fork-like pattern, a rounded antennular lobe, a pterygostomial angle not protruding, and a slightly curved and distally more or less elongated but always tapering endopod of male first pleopod. The name-bearing types are considered lost while the neotype has been collected from Doirani Lake, the same locality from where <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Karaman (1972)</xref> collected <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> type material and it will replace the lost type material.</p>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in having: 11–38 mesial spines on terminal segment of third maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8H</xref>), 12–16 rows of setae on basal lower endite of maxilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6G</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8G</xref>), 3–6 pairs (mostly 4–5) of spines on distal boarder of telson with the second pair to be the strongest and terminating beyond (or along with<!--PageBreak-->) the other pairs arranged in a fork-like pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5E–F</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">, 7E–F</xref>), a rounded antennular lobe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">, 7H</xref>) and the basal endite of first maxilliped failing or reaching to distal end of exopod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6F</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8F</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. in not having a sharply protruding pterygostomial angle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5B</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">, 7B</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of a rounded antennular lobe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5H</xref>) (vs. pointed in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3H–I</xref>). Further, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished by the slightly curved and distally more or less elongated but always tapering endopod of male first pleopod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6I</xref>) (vs. strongly curved and distally stout and not tapering in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4I</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be separated from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of numerous mesial spines (11–35) on terminal segment of third maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6H</xref>) (vs 0–8 mesial spines; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">, 12H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">, 14H</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E57CE407-D38C-4EF2-B4AC-C0B9BEE6EFB1</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atyaephyra_thyamisensis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">–8</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name><comment>. –<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Anastasiadou et al. 2004</xref>: 5–13, partim; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Anastasiadou et al. 2011</xref>: 41–54, Figs 1–6.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name><comment> sp. n. 1. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Christodoulou et al. 2008</xref>: Fig. 4B.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name><comment> sp. n. 3. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Christodoulou et al. 2010</xref>: Fig. 2, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>Type material.</bold> Holotype: NHM 2012.1476, adult ovig. ♀ (CL 7.1 mm), Greece, Epirus, Thyamis River, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">39°32.26'N, 20°09.76'E</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 76), among aquatic plants, 19.3.2005, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; Allotype: NHM 2012.1477, adult ♂ (CL 5.3 mm), same data collection as holotype; Paratypes: NHM 2012.1478–1483, 4 ♀♀ (3 ovig.) (CL 6.0–6.8 mm) and 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–5.3 mm) same data collection as holotype. NHM 2012.1484–1485, 2 ♀ (CL 6.5–7.4 mm), Greece, Epirus, Louros River, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">39°03.14'N, 20°46.26'E</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 72), among aquatic plants, 25.3.2012, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou. OUMNH.ZC 2012-08-001, 4 ♀♀ (2 ovig.) (CL 6.0–7.8 mm) and 2 ♂ (CL 5.2 mm) same data collection as holotype. SMF 43022, 4 ♀♀ (2 ovig.) (CL 5.8–7.1 mm) and 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–5.2 mm) same data collection as holotype. NHMW 25453, 4 ♀♀ (2 ovig.) (CL 5.5–7.5 mm) and 1 ♂♂ (CL 5.0 mm) same data collection as holotype</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Non-type material">
                        <title>Non-type material.</title>
                        <p><bold>Greece:</bold> 2 ♀♀ (CL 5.2–5.5 mm), NHMW 462, Corfu Island (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 75), 1.9.1937, coll. <tp:taxon-name>Stephanides</tp:taxon-name>; 13 ♀♀ (1 ovig.) (CL 5.3–8.1 mm) and 8 ♂♂ (CL 5.2–6.2 mm), Epirus, Thyamis River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 77), 20.5.2000 and 26.10.01, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 20 ♀♀ (15 ovig.) (CL 6.5–7.5 mm) and 3 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–5.7 mm), Epirus, Pamvotida Lake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 78), 24.3.2006, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 20 ♀♀ (CL 5.0–7.0) and 8 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–5.5), Epirus, Ziros Lake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 79), 28.10.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 20 ♀♀ (CL 5.8–8.5 mm) and 4 ♂♂ (CL 5.2–6.4 <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->mm), ZMAUTH D-334, Epirus, Filipiada, Louros River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 80), 20.10.1977, coll. P. Economides; 15 ♀♀ (CL 5.5–8.0) and 6 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–6.0), Louros River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 80), 28.10.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 8 ovig. ♀♀ (CL 6.4–8.0 mm) and 6 ♂♂ (CL 5.3–6.2 mm), NHMW 465, Lefkada Island, Kaligoni, Vardas River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 81), Aug.1929, coll. Beier; 3 ovig. ♀♀ (CL 7.3–8.0 mm) and 3 ♂♂ (CL 5.0–5.9 mm), NHMW 466, Lefkada Island, Kaligoni, Vardas River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 81), 2.10.1932, coll. Beier.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Rostrum long, slender, dorsal margin straight or slightly curved in the middle and pointed upwards, shorter, equal to, or longer than scaphocerite, 6.0–9.50, most often (84% of the examined individuals) 6.33 to 8.76, × as long as high. 18–27 (18–24 in 91% of the individuals) pre orbital teeth on dorsal margin arranged up to tip of rostrum. 0–2, predominantly (84%) 1–2, post-orbital teeth. 4–10 teeth, most often (87%) 5–8, arranged on ventral margin of rostrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>). Carapace smooth with pterygostomial angle bluntly produced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>). Pleuron of fifth abdominal segment pointed with an acute posterior angle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7D</xref>). Telsonwith 5–8, mostly (97%) 5–7, pairs of dorsal spines arranged in curved fashion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7E</xref>). Distal border of telson with 8–12, mostly (86%) 8–10, spines (4–6 pairs) arranged in fork-like pattern. Outermost pair of spines shortest, similar to dorsal spines, adjacent pair stronger terminating beyond (or along with) the finely setulose inner pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7E–F</xref>). Basal segment of antennular peduncle with long stylocerite, with its tip reaching or overreaching the distal end of basal segment. Anterolateral lobe of basal segment short and round (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7H</xref>). Distal segment of antennular peduncle with 1–6, frequently (92%) 2–4, spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7G</xref>). Basal lower endite of maxilla densely covered with long simple setae arranged in 12–16 (13–15 in 80% of the individuals), oblique parallel rows. Endite of maxilla 1.84–2.24, mostly (93%) 1.89–2.05, × as long as basal lower endite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8G</xref>). Basal endite of first maxilliped failing or reaching to distal end of exopod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8F</xref>). Distal third of terminal segment of third maxilliped bearing 13–38 (19–30 in 88% of the individuals) mesial spines and one subdistal lateral spine near the base of larger terminal spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8H</xref>). Armature along flexor margin of dactylus of third and fourth pereiopod consisting of 6–9 (7–9 in 97% of the individuals) and 6–10 (7–9 in 97% of the individuals) spines respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 8B, 8D</xref>). Merus of third and fourth pereiopod with 3–7 (4–6 in 93% of the individuals) and 2–6 (4–5 in 96% of the individuals) spines respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 8A, 8C</xref>). Dactylus of fifth pereiopod with 28–43, usually (82%) 32–40, spines arranged in comb-like fashion on flexor margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8E</xref>). Endopod of first male pleopod expanded proximally and with a distal portion elongated (ribbon shaped) and tapering. Endopod with 14–21 spines arranged on a slightly or strongly curved inner margin and 12–18 setae arranged on outer margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8I</xref>). 172–465 eggs of 0.60–0.7 × 0.40–0.45 mm in size.</p>
                        <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 7.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Holotype, adult ovig. ♀ (NHM 2012.1476): <bold>A</bold> entire individual <bold>B</bold> detail ofleftpterygostomial boarder <bold>C</bold> detail ofrightpterygostomial boarder <bold>D</bold> right pleuron of fifth abdominal segment <bold>E</bold> telson <bold>F</bold> distal margin of telson <bold>G</bold> right antennular peduncle <bold>H</bold> right antennular lobe.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 8.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Holotype, adult ovig. ♀ (NHM 2012.1476): <bold>A</bold> right third pereiopod <bold>B</bold> dactylus of third pereiopod <bold>C</bold> rightfourth pereiopod <bold>D</bold> dactylus of fourth pereiopod <bold>E</bold> right dactylus of fifth pereiopod <bold>F</bold> rightfirst maxilliped <bold>G</bold> right maxilla <bold>H</bold> right terminal segment of third maxilliped. Allotype, adult ♂ (NHM 2012.1477): <bold>I</bold> rightendopod of first male pleopod.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Size">
                        <title>Size.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is a large sized species with a maximum carapace length of 6.4 mm in ♂♂, 8.0 mm in ♀♀ and 8.1 mm in ovig. ♀♀.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Molecular characters">
                        <title>Molecular characters.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is different from all the other species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> by molecular characters, as shown by the phylogenetic analysis of mtDNA COI sequences. The one haplotype found was unique in the genus. Furthermore<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->, it differs from all the other species in the following nucleotide positions in the COI gene of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen Dour1, position 172: cytosine (C), position 207: cytosine (C), position 249: guanine (G), position 258: cytosine (C), position 324: guanine (G), position 348: guanine (G) and position 387: cytosine (C).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology:</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is named after the Thyamis River, Greece, the type locality.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is found in fresh water habitats of North-west Greece as well as in the islands Corfu and Lefkada (see material examined and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
                        <p><bold>Remarks:</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be discriminated from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of a sharply protruding pterygostomial angle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>). It should be noted that this character has been observed to be missing from one side (either the left or the right) in some very large sized individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7C</xref>). This character is shared by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (present in some populations) along with the presence of numerous spines (10–38) on terminal segment of third maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8H</xref>) and the presence of fewer rows of setae (12–16) on basal lower endite of maxilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4G</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8G</xref>). The two species can be distinguished by the presence of a rounded antennular lobe in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7G–H</xref>) (vs. pointed in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3G–I</xref>). Further, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished by the slightly or strongly curved endopod of first male pleopod having its distal part always elongated and tapering (ribbon shaped; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8I</xref>) (vs. strongly curved and distally stout and not tapering in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4I</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be separated easily from the remaining three species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of numerous mesial spines (13–38; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8H</xref>) on terminal segment of third maxilliped (vs. 0–8 mesial spinesin <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">, 12H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">, 14H</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">strymonensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A0C25BDC-4FB3-4C41-A507-5FA0BF6BCFC7</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atyaephyra_strymonensis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">–10</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name><comment>. –<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Anastasiadou et al. 2004</xref>: 5–13, partim; Sket and Zaksek 2009: 786–818.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name><comment> sp. n. 3. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Christodoulou et al. 2008</xref>.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name><comment> sp. n. 4. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Christodoulou et al. 2010</xref>: Fig. 2.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>Type material.</bold> Holotype: NHM 2012.1486, adult ovig. ♀ (CL 7.0 mm), Greece, Macedonia, Mylopotamos Springs (Strymonas River), <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">41°08.90'N, 24°04.29'E</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 102), among aquatic plants, 23.5.2011, coll. M. Christodoulou and M.S. Kitsos. Allotype: NHM 2012.1487, adult ♂ (CL 5.0 mm), same data collection as holotype. Paratypes: NHM 2012.1488–1492, 4 ♀♀ (CL 5.2–7.0 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.0 mm) same data collection as holotype. OUMNH.ZC 2012-08-002 4 ♀♀ <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->(1 ovig.) (CL 5.2–7.0 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.0 mm) same data collection as holotype; SMF 43023 2 ♀♀ (CL 6.7–7.2 mm) and 1 ♂ (CL 5.0 mm) same data collection as holotype; NHMW 25454, 2 ♀♀ (CL 6.1–7.3 mm) same data collection as holotype.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Non-type material">
                        <title>Non-type material.</title>
                        <p><bold>Greece:</bold> 3 ♀♀ (CL 5.4–6.0 mm) Macedonia, Strymonas River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 101), 1.10.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 20 ♀♀ (13 ovig.) (CL 6.3–7.9 mm), Macedonia, Mylopotamos Springs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 102), 4.4.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 9 ♀♀ (CL 5.5–7.1 mm) and 5 ♂♂ (CL 5.1–5.3 mm) Macedonia, Agias Varvaras Springs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 103), 4.4.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 11 ♀♀ (4 ovig.) (CL 6.0–7.4 mm) and 3 ♂♂ (CL 5.1–5.3 mm), Macedonia, Kefalariou Springs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 104), 4.5.2001, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; 2 ♀♀ (CL 6.3 mm) and 2 ♂♂ (CL 5.3–5.6 mm), Thrace, Paradeisos, Nestos River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 105), ZMAUTH G1-1024, 6.7.1972, coll. P. Economides; 14 ♀♀ (CL 5.5–7.3 mm) and 6 ♂♂ (CL 5.1–5.5 mm) Thrace, Kyrnos, Nestos River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 106), 30.9.2002, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Rostrum long, slender, dorsal margin straight or slightly curved in the middle and pointed upwards, 5.89–8.80, mostly (92% of the individuals examined) 6.75–8.80, × as long as high, shorter, equal to, or longer than scaphocerite. 10–29, frequently (92%) 14–23, pre orbital teeth on dorsal margin of rostrum arranged up to tip. Rostrum without post-orbital teeth, leaving a short unarmed proximal gap. With maximally five teeth, mostly (91%) up to three, arranged on ventral margin of rostrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A</xref>). Carapace smooth with pterygostomial angle, not protruding, rounded (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9B</xref>). Pleuron of fifth abdominal segment pointed with an acute posterior angle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9C</xref>). Telsonwith 2–7, predominantly (97%) 3–4, pairs of dorsal spines arranged in curved fashion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9D</xref>). Distal border of telson with 11–15, usually (96%) 12–14, spines (6–8 pairs), arranged in fan-like way. Outermost pair of spines shortest, similar to dorsal spines, adjacent pair stronger terminating before the finely setulose inner pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9D–E</xref>). Basal segment of antennular peduncle with long stylocerite, with its tip failing to reach or reaching the distal end of basal segment. Anterolateral lobe of basal segment short and round (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9G</xref>). Distal segment of antennular peduncle with 0–1 but mostly (87%) with no spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9F</xref>). Basal lower endite of maxilla densely covered with long simple setae arranged in 12–17 (14–16 in 90% of the individuals), oblique parallel rows. Endite of maxilla 1.77–1.95, mostly (89%) 1.78–1.91, × as long as basal lower endite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10G</xref>). Basal endite of first maxilliped failing, reaching or overreaching the distal end of exopod (reaching the end in 65% of the individuals) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10F</xref>). Distal one-third of terminal segment of third maxilliped bearing 1–7 mesial spines and one subdistal lateral spine near the base of larger terminal spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10H</xref>). Armature along flexor margin of dactylus of third and fourth pereiopod consisting of 6–8 (7–8 in 96% of the individuals) and 7–8 spines (including terminal spine) respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10B, 10D</xref>). Merus of third and fourth pereiopod with 3–6 (3–5 in 90% of the individuals) and 3–5 spines respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10A, 10C</xref>). Dactylus of fifth pereiopod with 25–37, mostly (87%) 30–35, spines arranged in comb-like fashion on flexor margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10E</xref>). Endopod of first male pleopod expanded proximally and with a distal portion elongated and tapering, often, with a small, protruding lobe in its outer subdistal part. Endopod with 14–23 spines arranged on a slightly curve<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->d inner margin and 9–15 setae arranged on outer margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10I</xref>). 210–250 eggs of 0.50–0.70 × 0.40–0.50 mm in size.</p>
                        <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 9.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Holotype, adult ovig. ♀ (NHM 2012.1486): <bold>A</bold> entire individual <bold>B</bold> detail of rightpterygostomial boarder <bold>C</bold> right pleuron of fifth abdominal segment <bold>D</bold> telson <bold>E</bold> distal margin of telson <bold>F</bold> right antennular peduncle <bold>G</bold> right antennular lobe.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 10.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Holotype, adult ovig. ♀ (NHM 2012.1486): <bold>A</bold> rightthird pereiopod <bold>B</bold> dactylus of third pereiopod <bold>C</bold> right fourth pereiopod <bold>D</bold> dactylus of fourth pereiopod <bold>E</bold> dactylus of fifth pereiopod <bold>F</bold> rightfirst maxilliped <bold>G</bold> right maxilla <bold>H</bold> rightterminal segment of third maxilliped. Allotype, adult ♂ (NHM 2012.1487): <bold>I</bold> right endopod of first male pleopod.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Size">
                        <title>Size.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is a large sized species with maximum carapace length to be 5.6 mm in ♂♂, 7.9 mm in ♀♀ and 7.5 mm in ovig. ♀♀.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Molecular characters">
                        <title>Molecular characters.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is unique in the genus in having 2 haplotypes not found in any of the other species. Also, it differs from all the other species in the following nucleotide positions in the COI gene of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen Dour1, position 201: cytosine (C), position 252: guanine (G), position 303: cytosine (C), position 309: thymine (T), position 318: guanine (G), position 319: adenine (A), position 367: thymine (T), position 393: cytosine (C) and position 453: thymine (T).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology:</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is named after the Strymon (Strymonas) River, Greece, the type locality.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is found in North-western Greece in the Rivers Strymon and Nestos (see material examined and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is unique in the combination of the following characters: (a) absence of post orbital teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A</xref>), (b) leaving a short unarmed proximal gap on dorsal surface of rostrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A</xref>), (b) having a round anterolateral lobe on basal segment of antennular peduncle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9F–G</xref>), (c) having a not protruding, rounded pterygostomial angle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9C</xref>), (d) endite of maxilla 1.77–1.95 × as long as basal lower endite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10G</xref>) and having 1–7 mesial spines in the terminal segment of third maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10H</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> in having fewer spines in the terminal segment of third maxilliped. However <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs by the absence of post-orbital teeth, leaving a short unarmed proximal gap on dorsal surface of rostrum and by the endite of maxilla being 1.77–1.95 × as long as basal lower endite (vs. 1.49–1.71). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in having fewer mesial spines in the terminal segment of third maxilliped.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">acheronensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:EBF698A2-82F9-49E8-89DA-8C4EB7588939</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atyaephyra_acheronensis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">–12</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name><comment> sp. n. 2. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Christodoulou et al. 2008</xref>: Fig. 4A.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name><comment> sp. n. 2. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Christodoulou et al. 2010</xref>: Fig. 2, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name><comment>. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Franjević et al. 2010</xref>: 159–166.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>Type material.</bold> Holotype: NHM 2012.1493, 1 ovig. ♀ (CL 5.9 mm), Greece, Epirus, Acherontas River, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">39°13.96'N, 20°29.11'E</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 71), among aquatic plants, 15.4.2012, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou (Sequenced specimen: Ach1).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Non-type material">
                        <title>Non-type material.</title>
                        <p><bold>Greece:</bold> 1 ♀ (CL 7.6 mm) (Sequenced specimen: Lour1) and 1 ovig. ♀ (CL 7.0 mm) (Sequenced specimen: Lour2), Greece, Epirus, Louros River, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">39°03.14'N, 20°46.26'E</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 72), 15.4.2012, coll. Ch. Anastasiadou; <bold>Slovenia:</bold> 1 ♂ (CL 5.1 mm), Dragonja River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 66), Aug.1971 (Sequenced specimen: Drag1).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Rostrum long, dorsal margin straight, 6.28–6.66 × as long as high, equal to or longer than scaphocerite. 19–26 pre orbital teeth on dorsal margin of rostrum arranged up to tip. With 1–3 post orbital teeth and 3–8 teeth on ventral margin of rostrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11A</xref>). Carapace smooth with pterygostomial angle not protruding, rounded (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11B</xref>). Pleuron of fifth abdominal segment pointed with an acute posterior angle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11C</xref>). Telsonwith four pairs of dorsal spines arranged in curved fashion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11D</xref>). Distal border of telson with 12–15 spines (6–8 pairs) arranged in a fan-like pattern. Outermost pair of spines shortest, similar to dorsal spines, adjacent pair stronger terminating before the finely setulose, inner pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11D–E</xref>). Antennulary stylocerite with its tip failing to reach or reaching distal margin of basal peduncle segment. Anterolateral lobe of basal segment short and round (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11G</xref>). Distal segment of antennular peduncle with 1–2 spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11F</xref>). Basal lower endite of maxilla densely covered with long simple setae arranged in 18–20 oblique parallel rows. Endite of maxilla 1.56–1.65 × as long as basal lower endite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12G</xref>). Basal endite of first maxilliped reaching clearly beyond distal end of exopod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12F</xref>). Distal one-third of terminal segment of third maxilliped bearing 1–5 mesial spines and one subdistal lateral spine near the base of larger terminal spine, interpretable as dactylus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12H</xref>). Armature along flexor margin of dactylus of third and fourth pereiopod consisting of 5–7 and 6–7 spines respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 12B, 12D</xref>). Merus of third and fourth pereiopod with 4–6 and 3–4 spines respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 12A, 12C</xref>). Armature along flexor margin of dactylus of fifth pereiopod consisting of 27–38 spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12E</xref>). Endopod of first male pleopod expanded proximally and with a distal portion elongated (ribbon shaped) and tapering. Endopod with 18 spines arranged on a slightly curved inner margin and 12 setae arranged on outer margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12I</xref>). 579–1117 eggs of 0.40–0.55 × 0.25–0.35 mm in size.</p>
                        <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 11.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Holotype, adult ovig. ♀ (NHM 2012.1493): <bold>A</bold> entire individual <bold>B</bold> detail of rightpterygostomial boarder <bold>C</bold> right pleuron of fifth abdominal segment <bold>D</bold> telson <bold>E </bold>distal margin of telson <bold>F</bold> right antennular peduncle <bold>G</bold> right antennular lobe.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F12" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 12.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Holotype, adult ovig. ♀ (NHM 2012.1493): <bold>A</bold> rightthird pereiopod <bold>B</bold> dactylus of third pereiopod <bold>C</bold> right fourth pereiopod <bold>D</bold> dactylus of fourth pereiopod <bold>E</bold>  dactylus of fifth pereiopod <bold>F</bold> rightfirst maxilliped <bold>G</bold> right maxilla <bold>H</bold> rightterminal segment of third maxilliped. Adult ♂: <bold>I</bold> right endopod of first male pleopod.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g012.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Size">
                        <title>Size.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is a large sized species with maximum carapace length to be 5.1 mm in ♂♂, 7.6 mm in ♀♀ and 7.0 mm in ovig. ♀♀.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Molecular characters">
                        <title>Molecular characters.</title>
                        <p>Molecular information based on the COI sequences provides compelling evidence that is a well defined species.<italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is unique in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> in having 2 haplotypes not shared by any other species. Furthermore, it differs from all its congeners in the following nucleotide positions in the COI gene of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen Dour1, position 255: adenine (A) and position 318: cytosine (C). Finally, the mean genetic distances between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and the remaining <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species range from 8.3% to 23.8% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.is named after the Acheron (Acherontas) River, Greece, the type locality.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is found in freshwater habitats of Croatia (Krka River), Slovenia (Dragonja River) and Greece (Acherontas River and Louros River) (see material examined and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Although this study was based on a limite<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->d number of specimens, it is postulated that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. occurs in more rivers covering an area ranging from Croatia to Greece.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>In addition to the type- and non type-material we investigated the morphology of the following specimens originating from the Balkan Peninsula: 6 ♀♀ collected from Dragonja River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 66), Slovenia; 3 ♀♀ collected from Jadro River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 67), NHMW 460 and 4 ♀♀ (3 ovig.) and 1 ♂ from Ombla River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 69), NHMW 459, Croatia; 2 ♂♂ collected from Krupa River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 68), NHMW 458, Bosnia and Herzegovina; 9 ♀♀ and 12 ♂♂ from Aoos River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 70), Albania; 47 ♀♀ (13 ovig.) and 9 ♂♂ from Acherontas River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 71), Greece, 10 ♀♀ and 2 ♂♂ collected from Louros River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 72), Greece, 2 ♀♀ from Pamisos River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 73), Greece, 4 ♀♀ and 1 ♂ sampled from Evrotas River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 74), NHM 1987.93, Greece. However, without sequencing the individuals, their placement to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. can’t be made with certainty.</p>
                        <p>Out of the 135 characters examined (see Appendix: Table 1) there were no morphological features distinguishing <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Nevertheless, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. presents a more limited variability in the values of its morphological characters than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. can easily be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of fewer mesial spines (1–5) on terminal segment of third maxilliped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12H</xref>) (vs. 10–38 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">, 6H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8H</xref>) and by the basal endite of first maxilliped overeaching distal end of exopod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12F</xref>) (vs. failing to reach or reaching distal end in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4F</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">, 6F</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8F</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. can be separated from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of 1–3 post orbital rostral teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11A</xref>) (vs. no post orbital teeth present leaving short unarmed proximal gap in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A</xref>) and by the endite of maxilla being 1.56–1.65 × as long as basal lower endite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12G</xref>) (vs. 1.77–1.95 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10G</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:94C1EC2A-1667-4456-8721-D10F03CDF4E6</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Atyaephyra_tuerkayi</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 13</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">–14</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii orientalis</tp:taxon-name><comment>. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Kinzelbach and Koster 1985</xref>: 127–134, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name><comment> n. sp. 2. – <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Christodoulou et al. 2010</xref>: Fig. 2, partim.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>Type material.</bold> Holotype: adult ♀ (CL 6.2 mm), SMF 43020, Syria, Nahr Al-Kabir River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 122), at bridge near the coastal road, 5.3.1979, coll. R.K. Kinzelbach (Sequenced specimen: Nah1); Paratype: 1 ♀ (CL 7.1 mm), SMF 43021 same data as the holotype (Sequenced specimen: Nah2).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Rostrum long, dorsal margin slightly curved in the middle and pointed upwards 6.43–6.66 × as long as high, shorter than or equal to scaphocerite. <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->19–23 pre orbital teeth on dorsal margin of rostrum arranged up to tip. With two post orbital teeth and 4–7 teeth on ventral margin of rostrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13A</xref>). Carapace smooth with pterygostomial angle not protruding, rounded (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13B</xref>). Pleuron of fifth abdominal segment pointed with an acute posterior angle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13C</xref>). Telsonwith four pairs of dorsal spines arranged in curved fashion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13D</xref>). Distal border of telson with 9 spines (5 pairs) arranged in fan-like pattern. Outermost pair of spines shortest, similar to dorsal spines, adjacent pair stronger terminating before the finely setulose, inner pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13E</xref>). Antennulary stylocerite with its tip failing to reach or reaching distal margin of basal peduncle segment. Anterolateral lobe of basal segment short and round (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13G</xref>). Distal segment of antennular peduncle with 1–2 spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13F</xref>). Basal lower endite of maxilla densely covered with long simple setae arranged in 18–20 oblique parallel rows. Endite of maxilla 1.58–1.59 × as long as basal lower endite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14G</xref>). Basal endite of first maxilliped reaching clearly beyond distal end of exopod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14F</xref>). Distal one-third of terminal segment of third maxilliped bearing 1–6 mesial spines and one subdistal lateral spine near the base of larger terminal spine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14H</xref>). Armature along flexor margin of dactylus of third and fourth pereiopod consisting of 6–7 and 6–7 spines respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figs 14B, 14D</xref>). Merus of third and fourth pereiopod with 4 and 3 spines respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figs 14A, 14D</xref>). Armature along flexor margin of dactylus of fifth pereiopod consisting of 28 spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14E</xref>).</p>
                        <fig id="F13" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 13.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Holotype, adult ♀ (SMF 43020): <bold>A</bold> entire individual <bold>B</bold> detail of rightpterygostomial boarder <bold>C</bold> right pleuron of fifth abdominal segment <bold>D</bold> telson <bold>E</bold> distal margin of telson <bold>F</bold> right antennular peduncle <bold>G</bold> right antennular lobe.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g013.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F14" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 14.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Holotype, adult ♀ (SMF 43020): <bold>A</bold> rightthird pereiopod <bold>B </bold>dactylus of third pereiopod <bold>C</bold> right fourth pereiopod <bold>D</bold> dactylus of fourth pereiopod <bold>E</bold> dactylus of fifth pereiopod <bold>F</bold> rightfirst maxilliped <bold>G</bold> right maxilla <bold>H</bold> rightterminal segment of third maxilliped.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-229-053-g014.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Size">
                        <title>Size.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a large sized species with maximum carapace length to be 7.1 mm for ♀♀</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Molecular characters">
                        <title>Molecular characters.</title>
                        <p>A haplotype found in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is not shared by any other species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Additionally, it differs from all the other species in the following nucleotide positions in the COI gene of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen Dour1, position 174: guanine (G), position 207: adenine (A), position 246: adenine (A), position 318: thymine (T), position 321: adenine (A), position 339: adenine (A), position 357: cytosine (C), position 372: thymine (T), position 399: thymine (T), position 417: adenine (A) and position 441: cytosine (C). Finally, the mean genetic distances between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and the other species were ranging from 19.7% to 25.7% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is named after Professor Michael Türkay, in appreciation of his contribution to the study of Decapoda.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is found in the Nahr Al-Kabir River situated between Syria and Lebanon (see material examined and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>In addition to the type-material we investigated the morphology of the 23 female individuals (6 ovig.) and 7 males originating from Nahr Al-Kabir River (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, stn 122; SMF 12189, SMF 12191, SMF 12192). All the individuals examined (including the sequenced ones) were morphologically identical. However, their placement to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, sp. n. has still to await sequencing. Since no male or ovigerous individual was sequenced observation regarding the form of the endopod of first male pleopod and number of eggs carried by the female were not included in the description. But observations were made in other individuals of the same sample and population and thus given here: endopod of first male pleopod expanded proximally an<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->d with a distal portion elongated and tapering, endopod with 9–16 spines arranged on a slightly curved inner margin and 9–11 setae arranged on outer margin. 430–450 eggs of 0.45–0.50 × 0.30–0.35 mm in size. Maximum carapace length to be 5.7 mm for ♂♂, 7.9 mm for ♀♀ and 7.6 mm for ovig. ♀♀.</p>
                        <p>Out of the 135 characters examined (see Appendix: Table 1) there were no morphological features distinguishing <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. However, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. can easily be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of fewer mesial spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14H</xref>) (1–6) on terminal segment of third maxilliped (vs. 10–38 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">, 6H</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8H</xref>) and by the basal endite of first maxilliped overreaching distal end of exopod (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14F</xref>) (vs. failing to reach or reaching distal end in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4F</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">, 6F</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 8F</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. can be separated from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of 1–3 post orbital rostral teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13A</xref>) (vs. no post orbital teeth present leaving short unarmed proximal gap in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A</xref>) and by the endite of maxilla being 1.58–1.59 × as long as basal lower endite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14G</xref>) (vs 1.77–1.95 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10G</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Given the highly structured nature of freshwater habitats and the limited potential for dispersal of the freshwater species (mainly due to natural barriers) in combination with the wide distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the Mediterranean region, a hypothesis under which several species are expected to be harbored in the genus seemed highly possible.</p>
            <p>However, until recently, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> was considered as a monotypic genus. Over the last 100 years many authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Bouvier 1913</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Holthuis 1961</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">Karaman 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Kinzelbach and Koster 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Al-Adhub 1987</xref>) have attempted to challenge this perception. However, the high intra- and inter-population variability, which made even the previously proposed subspecies questionable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Gorgin 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Anastasiadou et al. 2004</xref>) along with the lack of a complete series of samples covering all the known distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic>, proved to be far more challenging than many taxonomists would ever anticipate.</p>
            <p>In the latest revision of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Garcia Muñoz et al. 2009), which was based on the genetic information deriving from two mitochondrial genes (COI, 16S), two species were recognized while a third was proposed but without confirming it. In the current study seven species are defined, based both on morphological and molecular data. This difference in numbers is attributed to the limited geographical focus of the former study, which was primarily carried out on material collected from the Western Mediterranean area.</p>
            <p>After an exhaustive study of a large number of specimens from 20 different countries and a thorough examination of more than 135 morphological characters, including somatometric distances, new characters were found which could differentiate species or groups of species within the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic>. One of these characters is the number of mesial spines on the terminal segment of the third maxilliped according to which <!--PageBreak-->two main groups can be distinguished. The first group is characterized by 10–38 mesial spines and comprises three species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> whereas the second by 1–8 mesial spines including the remaining four, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p>
            <p>The species included in the first group can subsequently be distinguished by a series of features, e.g. presence-absence of a protruding pterygostomial angle, shape of antennular lobe and shape of endopod of first male pleopod. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are morphologically and phylogenetically well defined. In the phylogenetic tree they represent three well supported clades (16.7%–22.6% divergent from each other). In the second group, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is also a well defined species morphologically and can be distinguished from the remaining members by a combination of characters such as the lack of post orbital teeth, presence of a short unarmed proximal gap on rostrum and ratio of basal lower endite of maxilla in relation to the whole maxilla endite. The genetic divergence observed between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and its closest congeners by morphology is quite high (21.9%–25.4%). Thus, both morphological and molecular data show congruent patterns and jointly support its recognition as a distinct species within the genus. In addition, although <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. seems to be morphologically closer to the members of the second group e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., genetically it is more closely related to the other two species of the first group from Greece (e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>)with which it forms a strongly supported phylogroup (genetic divergence range: 11.9%–18.2%).</p>
            <p>No diagnostic morphological characters were found to distinguish the species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. from each other, a fact which is mainly caused by the high morphological variability observed in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However, their genetic distinctiveness coupled with their discrete geographical distribution provides enough evidence to distinguish the three species as distinct taxa.</p>
            <p>The range of genetic divergence observed between the specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (TrN distances: 5.9%–11.6%, Uncorrected p-distances: 5.3%–8.7%) is comparable to those found for other cryptic or sibling species of freshwater shrimps (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Page et al. 2005a</xref>, Uncorrected p-distances: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caridina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. A vs <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caridina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. B or C: 8.4–10.9%; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caridina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. B vs <italic><tp:taxon-name>Caridina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. C: 6.7–8.8%), freshwater crabs (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Jesse et al. 2011</xref>, Uncorected p-distances: interspecific variability between 14 <italic><tp:taxon-name>Potamon</tp:taxon-name></italic> species range: 3.1%–11.2%) as well as for other decapod sibling or well defined species (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Jones and Macpherson 2007</xref>, TrN distances: interspecific variability between 14 <italic><tp:taxon-name>Munidopsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> species range: 1.5%–19.6%). The mean genetic divergence observed between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (8.3 %) was the smallest among the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species (remaining genetic distances ranging from 11.9 to 25.7%). This level of divergence was also evident in morphology, indicating a more recent speciation event within the genus (compared to the ones that gave rise to the other species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and thus less time for these two species to diverge both morphologically and genetically.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, the fact that no haplotypes were shared between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. would suggest that the populations of shrimps from both species,<!--PageBreak--> although recently evolved, had independent evolutionary histories for a relatively long period of time. Additional support, although further research is still needed, comes from their geographical distribution since <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. seems to be allopatric. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is found in the western Balkan Peninsula, ranging from Croatia to Greece. In Greece, this species is found only on the west side of the mainland reaching most probably as far as South Peloponnese although with a remarkable fragmented distribution. In comparison <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is distributed in West-central Europe and North Africa. It should be noted here that the native distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is limited to Southern Europe and its presence in North-Central Europe up to the Danube River is believed to have been caused by its dispersal through the canals that were opened to connect the main rivers of Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Dhur and Massard 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">Moog et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Grabowski et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">Straka and Špaček 2009</xref>). Geographical barriers like the Alps and the Balkan mountains that isolated the Balkan drainages preventing faunal exchanges with the rest of Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Economou et al. 2007</xref>) could also account for this secluded population. Although, the current evidence deriving from mitochondrial data along with the geographic distribution supports the discrimination of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> as a distinct species, further support could come from additional mitochondrial sequence data (especially from the Balkan peninsula) as well as by combining information provided by nuclear sequence data.</p>
            <p>The monophyly of the species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, although supported by NJ, was poorly or not supported at all by BI and ML analyses, respectively. In the study of Garcia Muñoz et al. (2009) the monophyly of this species, based on the COI sequences, was strongly supported. This difference should be attributed to the larger number of sequences used in this study. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Millet, 1831) does not comprise a strongly supported genetically distinct group and appears as a not well resolved part of the phylogeny. However, the genetic distances observed within this group are quite small in comparison with the other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species and this in combination with the morphological data supports the consideration of all the populations inside this group as one taxonomic entity. More sequence and morphological data, especially from the area of South Portugal and Morocco (the monophyly of the species is strongly supported once the sequences originating from Morocco and South Portugal material are removed), as well as other molecular markers are needed in order for the relationships within <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> to be clarified.</p>
            <p>In the southwestern part of the Mediterranean area, only two species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> have been described to date: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic>. These two species had been considered synonyms until <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Anastasiadou et al. (2008)</xref> resurrected <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> after studying material from São Barnabé River (Odelouca River) in South Portugal. In their study Garcia Muñoz et al. (2009), stated that the hypothesis of the two distinct species could not be supported although they did note some genetic variability in the specimens originating from South Iberian Peninsula. Similar results are obtained in the current study. Sequences from North African and South Iberian individuals presented a noticeable mean genetic divergence (3.1% and 2.3% respectively) from the rest of west European and Tunisian sequences, but although noticeable is still weak to sup<!--PageBreak-->port the hypothesis of different species. A high variability in morphological characters, especially in the individuals from the South Iberia was also observed. Characters such as the length and height of the rostrum (the tendency is for rostra to be longer and narrower) and the number of rows in maxilla basal lower endite (usually 15–18) varied greatly from the typical form present in North Iberia and the rest of Europe as well as Tunisia (shorter and broader rostra, 17–21 rows on maxilla basal lower endite). Genetic diversity among the South and North-central Iberia populations is observed in many other freshwater species whereas only in a few of them is it robust enough to justify distinct species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Doadrio and Carmona 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Durand et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">Sanjur et al. 2003</xref>). An explanation for this should be sought in the eventful geological history as many basins of the Iberian Peninsula almost dried up and the southwestern part of the Peninsula became completely isolated during the Messinian period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">Sanjur et al. 2003</xref>). In addition, the genetic diversity observed mainly between the Moroccan and remaining populations should be sought again to the geological history and the isolation of the North-west Africa from Europe and where dispersal between these land mass, across the Gibraltar strait ceased to be an option since Pliocene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">Sanjur et al. 2003</xref>).</p>
            <p>The Tunisian populations, on the other hand, are more closely related to the western European ones, probably due to the past connections through the Sicily Strait with European populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Butler et al. 1999</xref>).</p>
            <p>The second cryptic species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. has been found only in the River Nahr Al-Kabir which is located along the borders of Lebanon with Syria. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is completely isolated geographically from the other two morphologically closest to it species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. In fact <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is surrounded by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> populations which show a wide distribution from Turkey to Iraq. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra tuerkayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is genetically well discriminated from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (genetic distances are 23.0% and 22.2% respectively) as well as from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> that is found in the adjacent areas (genetic distance is 19.7%). The genetic distances are among the highest observed between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species and by far exceed currently published records of intra-population variability of other fresh water decapods (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Jesse et al. 2011</xref>). Furthermore, they are comparable with genetic distances of COI sequences described elsewhere for taxa recognized at the generic level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Avise 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Lefébure et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Matzen da Silva et al. 2011</xref>). Therefore such an extensive differentiation should be attributed to speciation.</p>
            <p>In the area of the Middle East, two subspecies were previously described, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bouvier, 1913 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii mesopotamica</tp:taxon-name></italic> Al-Adhub, 1987. However, no observable morphological characters where found that could differentiate them (see remarks of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>). Furthermore, although the genetic distances within the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> phylogroup were high (0.9%–10.2%) no firm conclusion could be drawn whether the hypothesis of multiple species is valid or not. Sequences from Orontes River (topotypical location of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and from Shatt Al-Arab River (topotypical location of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii mesopotamica</tp:taxon-name></italic>) presented a noticeable mean genetic divergence (5.0%) but still not strong enough to support the hypothesis of different species. Detailed future studies on the morphological and genetic variability within<!--PageBreak--> the samples of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> distributed throughout the Middle East will help clarify the relationships between the populations in this region, however given the present data, only one species is considered to exist, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra orientalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <p>Four species (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra stankoi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra strymonensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.) were found to co-exist in Greece with well defined and clearly separated distributions. Only two species (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra acheronensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.) were found to co-exist in the same river (River Louros, Epirus). Multiple individuals collected from the Louros estuary and further upstream, dating back to 1977 until 2001 were examined. These specimens were all identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra thyamisensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. However, in a recent sample (2012) both species were found. Probably, this could be attributed to fish transfers or translocation where shrimps could have accidentally been introduced. Additionally, the distance between the estuaries of the Rivers Louros and Acherontas is less than 30 km making human mediated dispersal, between the two watersheds, highly possible. Furthermore, numerous translocations of fish were made within Greece over the last 70 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Economidis et al. 2000</xref>) making this scenario even more justified. However, the natural co-existence of the two species cannot be entirely excluded.</p>
            <p>It is surprising that four out of the seven <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species examined for the present study are recorded from Greece and three of these are endemic. Greece is considered to be a faunal and floral biodiversity hot spot within the Mediterranean region where freshwater fauna is not an exception (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">Reyjol et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Jesse et al. 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Jesse et al. (2011)</xref> after studying the diversity of the freshwater <italic><tp:taxon-name>Potamon</tp:taxon-name></italic> crabs, revealed the existence of 14 species within the greater Mediterranean region. Eight of these species (three endemic and five with limited distribution in adjacent countries) were found in Greece. High diversity and endemism is recorded in other freshwater groups too, such as fishes. Greece harbours the largest number of fish species of any region in the Mediterranean basin where the number of endemic species exceeds 45% of the total number of native species (130) recorded (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Economou et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Blondel et al. 2010</xref>). Freshwater endemism in Greece is considered as one of the highest in the Mediterranean region and has been ascribed to its eventful geological history combined with complex climatic events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Bobori et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Economou et al. 2007</xref>).</p>
            <p>The importance of morphology versusmolecular data in order to resolve the phylogeny of a taxon still provides a forum for scientific debate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Tautz et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Blaxter 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Page et al. 2005b</xref>). Although additional work is needed towards the exhibited morphological variability within the genus, the data provided by the present study demonstrate a case in which conventional and molecular taxonomy do not provide different patterns but, rather, complimentary. Finally, an additional step was taken by considering the molecular validation of the two cryptic species which couldn’t be supported by morphological data alone. It seems, therefore, that when both molecular and morphological effort is combined towards a “total evidence” approach a whole greater than the sum of its parts emerges which is instrumental in our understanding the diversity of life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Page et al. 2005b</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We are very grateful to the following researchers who provided us with material either as loan or as a gift: Dr Chrysa Anastasiadou (University of Ioannina, Greece), Prof. Sonia Dhaouadi-Hassen (University of Carthage, Tunisia), Dr Cedric d’ Udekem d’ Acoz (Royal Belgian Institute of Natural Sciences, Belgium), Prof. Manuel Graça and Dr Veronica Ferreira (University of Coimbra, Portugal), Dr Carlo Froglia (Italy), Mr Ahmad Ghane (Inland Waters Aquaculture Research Centre, Iran), Dr Jure Jugovic (University of Ljubljana, Slovenia), Dr Christophe Lejeusne (Doñana Biological Station, Spain), Prof. Mohammed Melhaoui (University of Oujda, Morocco), Prof. Jose Luis Moreno Alcaraz (University of Castilla-La Mancha, Spain), Mr Murtada D. Naser (University of Basrah, Iraq), Dr Javier Oscoz (University of Navarra, Spain), Ass. Prof. Murat Özbek (Ege University, Turkey), Dr Michael L. Zettler (Leibniz Institute for Baltic Sea Research,Germany), Mrs Niovi Christodoulou and Mr Andreas Savvides (Wageningen University, Netherlands). Also, we are very grateful to the following researchers that allowed us access to Museum collections: Dr Paul F. Clark (NHM), Dr Sammy De Grave (OUMNH), Dr Peter Dworschak (NMW), Dr Pier Noél (MNHN), Dr Svetozar Petkovski (MMNH) and Professor Michael Türkay (SMF). Furthermore, we will like to thank Dr Timothy J. Page (Griffith University, Australia) for offering us four COI sequences and Ass. Prof. Nikos Poulakakis (University of Crete, Greece) for supplying us with the DNA extraction protocol. The authors will like to thank Dr Sammy De Grave and Dr Arthur Anker for their help in finding Bouvier’s material in NHMN. Specifically we will like to thank Dr Arthur Anker who went through the collection as well as for taking the photos of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> material. The senior author will like to thank Dr De Grave for his useful comments and help through some difficult issues dealing with the nomenclature code of zoology. For their helpful comments and critical reading we will like to thank Dr Paul Clark and Dr Christos Arvanitidis. We will also like to thank Mrs Kristin Pietratus (SMF), Mrs Miranda Lowe (NHM), Mrs Paula Martin-Lefevre and Dr Laure Corbari (MNHN) for their help with the loaned material from Museum collections. We also acknowledge the help of Stelios Derivianakis, Katerina Oikonomaki and Vaso Terzoglou in the genetic lab. The senior author will like to thank Synthesys: the European Union-funded Integrated Activities grant that supported her for a monthly visit to the NHM. Also the senior author will like to specially thank Dr Paul Clark for his supervision. Finally, the authors, gratefull aknowledge the three reviewers for their very usufull comments and suggestions that improved significantly the manuscript. The senior author will like to acknowledge the State Scholarships Foundation for supporting partially her studies. This study was partially funded by MARBIGEN: “Supporting research potential for MARine BIodiversity and GENomics in the Eastern Mediterranean” and ViBRANT: “Virtual Biodiversity Research and Access Network for Taxonomy”.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Adhub</surname> <given-names>AHY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> On a new subspecies of a freshwater shrimp (Decapoda, Atyidae) from the Shatt Al-Arab River, Iraq.</article-title> <source>Crustaceana </source> <volume>53</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/156854087X00565">10.1163/156854087X00565</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Anastasiadou</surname> <given-names>Ch</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitsos</surname> <given-names>M-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koukouras</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Redescription of <italic>Atyaephyra desmarestii</italic> (Millet, 1831) (Decapoda, Caridea, Atyidae) based on topotypical specimens.</article-title> <source>Crustaceana </source> <volume>79</volume> (<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1195</fpage>-<lpage>1207</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/156854006778859597">10.1163/156854006778859597</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Anastasiadou</surname> <given-names>Ch</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitsos</surname> <given-names>M-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koukouras</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Redescription of <italic>Atyaephyra rosiana</italic> de Brito Capello, 1867 (Decapoda, Caridea, Atyidae) based on a population close to the topotypical area.</article-title> <source>Crustaceana </source> <volume>81</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>191</fpage>-<lpage>205</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/156854008783476215">10.1163/156854008783476215</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Anastasiadou</surname> <given-names>Ch</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koukouras</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mavidis</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chartosia</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mostakim</surname> <given-names>Md</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christodoulou</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aslanoglou</surname> <given-names>Ch</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<source> Morphological variation in <italic>Atyaephyra desmarestii</italic> (Millet, 1831) within and among populations over its geographical range. Meditteranean Marine Science 5 (2): 5–13. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.medit-mar-sc.net/files/200812/15-1703457.pdf">http://www.medit-mar-sc.net/files/200812/15-1703457.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Anastasiadou</surname> <given-names>Ch</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ntakis</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leonardos</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> Larval development of the freshwater shrimp <italic>Atyaephyra desmarestii</italic> (Millet, 1831) <italic>sensu lato</italic> (Decapoda, Caridea, Atyidae) and morphological maturation from juveniles to adults. Zootaxa 2877: 41–54. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2011/f/z02877p054f.pdf">http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2011/f/z02877p054f.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Annandale</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kemp</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1913</year>)<source> The Crustacea Decapoda of the Lake of Tiberias. Journal and Proceedings of the Asiatic Society of Bengal, New Series 9 (6): 241–258. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://decapoda.nhm.org/pdfs/24601/24601.pdf">http://decapoda.nhm.org/pdfs/24601/24601.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Avise</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<source> Phylogeography: the history and formation of species.</source> <publisher-name>Harvard University Press, Cambridge</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Massachusetts</publisher-loc>, <lpage>447</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrois</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1893</year>)<source> Liste des décapodes fluviatiles recueillis en Syrie suivie de quelques considérations sur le genre <italic>Caridine</italic>. Revue Biologique du Nord de la France 5 (4): 125–134. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ia700304.us.archive.org/22/items/revuebiologiqued05lill/revuebiologiqued05lill.pdf">http://ia700304.us.archive.org/22/items/revuebiologiqued05lill/revuebiologiqued05lill.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjourson</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<source> Band-stab PCR: a simple technique for the purification of individual PCR products. Nucleic Acids Research 20 (17): 4675. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/20.17.4675">10.1093/nar/20.17.4675</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blaxter</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> The promise of a DNA taxonomy.</article-title> <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences </source> <volume>359</volume> (<issue>1444</issue>): <fpage>669</fpage>-<lpage>679</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2003.1447">10.1098/rstb.2003.1447</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blagoderov</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brake</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgiev</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penev</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rycroft</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agosti</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catapano</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>VS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Streamlining taxonomic publication: a working example with Scratchpads and ZooKeys.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys </source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.50.539">10.3897/zookeys.50.539</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blondel</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aronson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bodiou</surname> <given-names>J-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boeuf</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source> The Mediterranean Region: biological diversity in space and time, 2nd edn.</source> <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>, <lpage>392</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bobori</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Economidis</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurakis</surname> <given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Freshwater ﬁsh habitat science and management in Greece.</article-title> <source>Aquatic Ecosystem Health and Management </source> <volume>4</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>381</fpage>-<lpage>391</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/146349801317276053">10.1080/146349801317276053</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolivar</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1892</year>)<source> Lista de la colección de crustáceos de España y Portugal del Museo de Historia Natural de Madrid. Actas de la Sociedad Española de Historia Natural 21: 124–141. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bibdigital.rjb.csic.es/spa/Libro.php?Libro=1163">http://bibdigital.rjb.csic.es/spa/Libro.php?Libro=1163</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouvier</surname> <given-names>E-L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>)<source> <italic>Dugastella marocana</italic>, crevette primitive nouvelle de la famille des Atyidés. Comptes Rendus Hebdomadaires des Séances de l’Académie des Sciences 155 (21): 993–998. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://archive.org/details/ComptesRendusAcademieDesSciences0155">http://archive.org/details/ComptesRendusAcademieDesSciences0155</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouvier</surname> <given-names>E-L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1913</year>)<source> Les variations d’une crevette de la famille des Atyidées, l’<italic>Atyaephyra Desmaresti</italic> Millet. Bulletin du Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle 19 (2): 65–74. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/27226">http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/27226</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouvier</surname> <given-names>E-L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1925</year>)<article-title> Recherches sur la morphologie, les variations et la distribution systématique des crevettes d’eau douce de la famille des Atyidés.</article-title> <source>Encyclopédie Entomologique </source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>365</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smoot</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juvekar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Do</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewey</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pachter</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Fast Statistical Alignment. PLoS Computational Biology 5 (5): e1000392. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000392">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000392</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brito Capello</surname> <given-names>F de</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1867</year>)<source> Descripção de algumas especies novas ou pouco conhecidas de crustaceos e arachnidios de Portugal e possessões portuguezas do Ultramar. Memorias da Academia Real das Sciencias de Lisboa 4 (1): 1–17. http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/30746#page/5/mode/1up</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname> <given-names>RWH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McClelland</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> Calibrating the duration and timing of the Messinian salinity crisis in the Mediterranean: linked tectonoclimatic signals in thrust-top basins of Sicily. Journal of the Geological Society, London 156: 827–835. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.see.leeds.ac.uk/structure/tectonics/messinian/mescycles.pdf">http://www.see.leeds.ac.uk/structure/tectonics/messinian/mescycles.pdf</ext-link> , </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1144/gsjgs.156.4.0827">10.1144/gsjgs.156.4.0827</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Christodoulou</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitsos</surname> <given-names>M-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chartosia</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koukouras</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<source> The status of the genus <italic>Atyaephyra</italic>: comparisonof <italic>Atyaephyra desmarestii</italic> and <italic>Atyaephyra rosiana</italic> with different populations from Greece. Ninth Colloquium Crustacea Decapoda Mediterranea, Torino (Italy), September 2008. Dipartimento di Biologia Animale e dell’Uomo, Torino University and Museo Regionale di Scienze Naturali of Torino, 41.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Christodoulou</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koukouras</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thessalou-Legaki</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source>Progress on the assessment of the taxonomic status of the circum-Mediterranean genus <italic>Atyaephyra</italic> de Brito Capello, 1867 (Decapoda, Atyidae). Twenty First International Senckenberg Conference: Freshwater Decapoda, Frankfurt au Maine (Germany), December 2010. Senckenberg Research Institute and Natural History Museum, 33.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fawcett</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurwood</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Biogeographic history of an Australian freshwater shrimp, <italic>Paratya australiensis</italic> (Atyidae): the role life history transition in phylogeographic diversification.</article-title> <source>Molecular Ecology </source> <volume>15</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>1083</fpage>-<lpage>1093</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2006.02852.x">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2006.02852.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Importance of cryptic species for identifying ‘representative’ units of biodiversity for freshwater conservation.</article-title> <source>Biological Conservation </source> <volume>141</volume> (<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>2821</fpage>-<lpage>2831</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2008.08.018">10.1016/j.biocon.2008.08.018</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Creaser</surname> <given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1936</year>)<source> Crustaceans from Yucatan. In: Pearse AS, Creaser EP, Hall FG (Eds) The cenotes of Yucatan. A zoological and hydrographic survey. Carnegie Institution of Washington, Washington, 117–132. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://decapoda.nhm.org/pdfs/25249/25249.pdf">http://decapoda.nhm.org/pdfs/25249/25249.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>De Grave</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fransen</surname> <given-names>CHJM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> Carideorum catalogus: the recent species of the dendrobranchiate, stenopodidean, procarididean and caridean shrimps (Crustacea, Decapoda). Zoologische Mededelingen, Leiden 85 (9): 195–588. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.zoologischemededelingen.nl/85/nr02/a01">http://www.zoologischemededelingen.nl/85/nr02/a01</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhur</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massard</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<source> Étude historique et faunistique des invertébrés immigrés ou introduits dans la Moselle luxembourgeoise et ses affluents. Bulletin de la Société des Naturalistes Luxembourgeois 96: 127–156. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vliz.be/imis/imis.php?module=ref&amp;refid=208304">http://www.vliz.be/imis/imis.php?module=ref&amp;refid=208304</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Doadrio</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmona</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<source> Testing freshwater Lago Mare dispersal theory on the phylogeny relationships of Iberian cyprinid genera <italic>Chondrostoma</italic> and <italic>Squalius</italic> (Cyprinoformes, Cyprinidae). Graellsia 59 (2–3): 457–473. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://graellsia.revistas.csic.es/index.php/graellsia/article/view/260/260">http://graellsia.revistas.csic.es/index.php/graellsia/article/view/260/260</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dormitzer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1853</year>)<source> <italic>Troglocaris Schmidtii</italic>. Lotos 3: 85–88. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ia700306.us.archive.org/3/items/lotoszeitschrift03deut/lotoszeitschrift03deut.pdf">http://ia700306.us.archive.org/3/items/lotoszeitschrift03deut/lotoszeitschrift03deut.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suchard</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaut</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> Bayesian phylogenetics with BEAUti and the BEAST 1.7.</article-title> <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution </source> <volume>29</volume> (<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1969</fpage>-<lpage>1973</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mss075">10.1093/molbev/mss075</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Durand</surname> <given-names>J-D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianco</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laroche</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilles</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Insight into the origin of endemic Mediterranean ichthyofauna: phylogeography of <italic>Chondrostoma</italic> genus (Teleostei, Cyprinidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of Heredity </source> <volume>94</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>315</fpage>-<lpage>328</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jhered/esg074">10.1093/jhered/esg074</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Economidis</surname> <given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitriou</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pagoni</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michaloudi</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Natsis</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Introduced and translocated fish species in the inland waters of Greece.</article-title> <source>Fisheries Management and Ecology </source> <volume>7</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>239</fpage>-<lpage>250</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2400.2000.00197.x">10.1046/j.1365-2400.2000.00197.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Economou</surname> <given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giakoumi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vardakas</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbieri</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoumboudi</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zogaris</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> The freshwater ichthyofauna of Greece – an update based on a hydrographic basin survey. Mediterranean Marine Science 8 (1): 91–166. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.medit-mar-sc.net/files/200812/15-1813054.pdf">http://www.medit-mar-sc.net/files/200812/15-1813054.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Excoffier</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lischer</surname> <given-names>HEL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Arlequin suite ver 3.5: a new series of programs to perform population genetics analyses under Linux and Windows.</article-title> <source>Molecular Ecology Resources </source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>564</fpage>-<lpage>567</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-0998.2010.02847.x">10.1111/j.1755-0998.2010.02847.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrer Galdiano</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1924</year>)<source> Una nueva especie del género <italic>Atyaephira</italic> (Decap., Atyidae). Boletín de la Real Sociedad Española de Historia Natural 24: 210–213. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bibdigital.rjb.csic.es/ing/Libro.php?Libro=1232">http://bibdigital.rjb.csic.es/ing/Libro.php?Libro=1232</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Folmer</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeh</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrijenhoek</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<source> DNA primers for amplification of mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit I from diverse metozoan invertebrates. Molecular Marine Biology and Biotechnology3 (5): 294–299. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mbari.org/staff/vrijen/PDFS/Folmer_94MMBB.pdf">http://www.mbari.org/staff/vrijen/PDFS/Folmer_94MMBB.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Franjević</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalafatić</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerovec</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gottstein</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source> Phylogeny of cave-dwelling atyid shrimp <italic>Troglocaris</italic> in the Dinaric Karst based on sequences of three mitochondrial genes. Periodicum Biologorum 112 (2): 159–166. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=87840">http://hrcak.srce.hr/index.php?show=clanak&amp;id_clanak_jezik=87840</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>García Muñoz</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodríguez</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>García Raso</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuesta</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Genetic evidence for cryptic speciation in the freshwater shrimp genus <italic>Atyaephyra</italic> de Brito Capello (Crustacea, Decapoda, Atyidae). Zootaxa2025: 32–42. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2009/f/z02025p042f.pdf">http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2009/f/z02025p042f.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorgin</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<source> The first record of two species of freshwater shrimps (Decapoda, Caridea, Atyidae) from Iran. Crustaceana 69 (5): 662–668. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/20105244?uid=2129&amp;uid=2134&amp;uid=2&amp;uid=70&amp;uid=4&amp;sid=21101302264147">http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/20105244?uid=2129&amp;uid=2134&amp;uid=2&amp;uid=70&amp;uid=4&amp;sid=21101302264147</ext-link> , </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/156854096X00664">10.1163/156854096X00664</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grabowski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jażdżewski</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konopacka</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Alien Crustacea in Polish waters – Introduction and Decapoda. Oceanological and Hydrobiological Studies 34 (1): 43–61. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://153.19.140.20/obce/Baltic_Aliens/Grabowski.pdf">http://153.19.140.20/obce/Baltic_Aliens/Grabowski.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guindon</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dufayard</surname> <given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefort</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anisimova</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hordijk</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gascuel</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> New algorithms and methods to estimate Maximum-Likelihood phylogenies: assessing the performance of PhyML 3.0.</article-title> <source>Systematic Biology </source> <volume>59</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>307</fpage>-<lpage>321</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syq010">10.1093/sysbio/syq010</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Haan</surname> <given-names>W de</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1833–1850</year>)<source> Crustacea. In: von Siebold PF (Ed) Fauna Japonica sive descriptio animalium, quae in itinere per Japoniam, jussu et auspiciis superiorum, qui summum in India Batava imperium tenent, suspecto, annis 1823–1830 collegit, notis, observationibus et adumbrationibus illustravit. Lugduni-Batavorum, Arnz, 1–243. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://decapoda.nhm.org/references/pdfpick.html?id=12488&amp;pdfroot=http://decapoda.nhm.org/pdfs">http://decapoda.nhm.org/references/pdfpick.html?id=12488&amp;pdfroot=http://decapoda.nhm.org/pdfs</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heller</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1862</year>)<source> Neue Crustaceen, gesammelt während der Weltumseglung der k.k. Fregatte Novara. Zweiter vorläufiger Bericht. Verhandlungen der kaiserlich-königlichen zoologisch-botanischen Gesellschaft in Wien 12: 519–528. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://decapoda.nhm.org/pdfs/25686/25686.pdf">http://decapoda.nhm.org/pdfs/25686/25686.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B44"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heller</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1863</year>)<source> Die Crustaceen des südlichen Europa. Crustacea Podophthalmia. Mit einer Übersicht über die horizontale Verbreitung sämmtlicher europäischer Arten. Wilhem Braumüller, Wien, 336 pp. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://archive.org/details/diecrustaceendes00hell">http://archive.org/details/diecrustaceendes00hell</ext-link> , </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.13110">10.5962/bhl.title.13110</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B45"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holthuis</surname> <given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>)<source> Report on a collection of Crustacea Decapoda and Stomatopoda from Turkey and the Balkans. Zoologische Verhandelingen 47: 1–67. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.repository.naturalis.nl/document/148913">http://www.repository.naturalis.nl/document/148913</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B46"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holthuis</surname> <given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<source> The recent genera of the caridean and stenopodidean shrimps (Crustacea, Decapoda): with an appendix on the order Amphionidacea.</source> <publisher-name>Nationaal Natuurhistorisch Museum</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Leiden</publisher-loc>, <lpage>328</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B47"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jesse</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schubart</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname></surname> <given-names>KlausS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title>Identification of a cryptic lineage within <italic>Potamon fluviatile</italic> (Herbst) (Crustacea, Brachyura, Potamidae).</article-title> <source>Invertebrate Systematics </source> <volume>24</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>348</fpage>-<lpage>356</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/IS10014">10.1071/IS10014</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B48"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jesse</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grudinski</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klaus</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Streit</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfenninger</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Evolution of freshwater crab diversity in the Aegean region (Crustacea, Brachyura, Potamidae).</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution </source> <volume>59</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2010.12.011">10.1016/j.ympev.2010.12.011</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B49"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Joly</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1843</year>)<source> Études sur les mœurs, de développement et les métamorphoses d’une petite salicoque d’eau douce(<italic>Caridina Desmarestii</italic>), suivies de quelques réflexions sur les métamorphoses des crustacés décapodes en général. Annales des Sciences Naturelles, Zoologie 19: 34–86. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/47973">http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/47973</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B50"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macpherson</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Molecular phylogeny of the East Pacific squat lobsters of the genus <italic>Munidopsis</italic> (Decapoda, Galatheidae) with the descriptions of seven new species.</article-title> <source>Journal of Crustacean Biology </source> <volume>27</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>477</fpage>-<lpage>501</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1651/S-2791.1">10.1651/S-2791.1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B51"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Karaman</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Über eine neue Süsswassergarnelenunterart <italic>Atyaephyra desmarestii stankoi</italic> n. ssp. (Decapoda, Atyidae) aus Mazedonien.</article-title> <source>Fragmenta Balcanica </source> <volume>9</volume> (<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>81</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B52"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinzelbach</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koster</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<source> Die Süßwassergarnele <italic>Atyaephyra desmaresti</italic> (Millet 1832) in den Levante-Ländern (Crustacea, Decapoda, Atyidae). Senckenbergiana Biologica 66 (1/3): 127–134.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B53"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Leach</surname> <given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1813–1814</year>)<article-title> Crustaceology.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brewster</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>The Edinburgh Encyclopædia, Volume 7, A.</issue-title> <source>Balfour, Edinburgh</source>: <fpage>383</fpage>-<lpage>437</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B54"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefébure</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Douady</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gouy</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibert</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Relationship between morphological taxonomy and molecular divergence within Crustacea: proposal of a molecular threshold to help species delimitation.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution </source> <volume>40</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>435</fpage>-<lpage>447</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2006.03.014">10.1016/j.ympev.2006.03.014</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B55"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Macpherson</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machordom</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Use of morphological and molecular data to identify three new sibling species of the genus <italic>Munida</italic> Leach, 1820 (Crustacea, Decapoda, Galatheidae) from New Caledonia.</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History </source> <volume>39</volume> (<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>819</fpage>-<lpage>834</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222930400002473">10.1080/00222930400002473</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B56"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Matzen da Silva</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Creer</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunha</surname> <given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname> <given-names>FO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname> <given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> Systematic and evolutionary insights derived from mtDNA COI barcode diversity in the Decapoda (Crustacea, Malacostraca). PLoS ONE 6 (5): e19449. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0019449">10.1371/journal.pone.0019449</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B57"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Millet</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1831</year>)<source> Description d’une nouvelle espèce de crustacé, l’<italic>Hippolyte</italic> de Desmarets. Mémoires de la Société d’Agriculture, Sciences et Arts d’Angers 1: 55–57, Plate 1.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B58"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Milne Edwards</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1837</year>)<source> Histoire naturelle des crustacés, comprenant l’anatomie, la physiologie et la classification de ces animaux. Volume 2. Librairie Encyclopédique de Roret, Paris, 532 pp. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/bibliography/6234">http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/bibliography/6234</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B59"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moog</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nesemann</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zitek</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melcher</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Erstnachweis der Süßwassergarnele <italic>Atyaephyra desmaresti</italic> (Millet 1831) (Decapoda) in Österreich.</article-title> <source>Lauterbornia </source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B60"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortmann</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1890</year>)<source> Die Decapoden-Krebse des Strassburger Museums, mit besonderer Berücksichtung der von Herrn Dr. Döderlein bei Japan und bei den Liu-Kiu-Inseln gesammelten und z. Z. im Strassburger Museum aufbewahrten Formen. I. Die Unterordnung Natantia Boas. Zoologische Jahrbücher. Abteilung für Systematik, Geographie und Biologie der Thiere 5: 437–542. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biostor.org/reference/5004">http://biostor.org/reference/5004</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B61"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortmann</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1895</year>)<source> A study of the systematic and geographical distribution of the decapod family Atyidae Kingsley. Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia 1894: 397–416. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/18073">http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/18073</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B62"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005a</year>)<article-title> Historical transoceanic dispersal of a freshwater shrimp: the colonization of the South Pacific by the genus <italic>Paratya</italic> (Atyidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of Biogeography </source> <volume>32</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>581</fpage>-<lpage>593</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2699.2004.01226.x">10.1111/j.1365-2699.2004.01226.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B63"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choy</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005b</year>)<article-title> The taxonomic feedback loop: symbiosis of morphology and molecules.</article-title> <source>Biology Letters </source> <volume>1</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>139</fpage>-<lpage>142</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsbl.2005.0298">10.1098/rsbl.2005.0298</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B64"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> Radically different scales of phylogeographic structuring within cryptic species of freshwater shrimp (Atyidae, <italic>Caridina</italic>). Limnology and Oceanography52 (3): 1055–1066. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aslo.org/lo/toc/vol_52/issue_3/1055.pdf">http://www.aslo.org/lo/toc/vol_52/issue_3/1055.pdf</ext-link> , </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4319/lo.2007.52.3.1055">10.4319/lo.2007.52.3.1055</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B65"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname> <given-names>WF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<source> Shrimps down under: evolutionary relationships of subterranean crustaceans from Western Australia (Decapoda, Atyidae, <italic>Stygiocaris</italic>). PLoS ONE 3(2): e1618. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0001618">10.1371/journal.pone.0001618</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B66"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelseneer</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1886</year>)<source> Note sur la présence de <italic>Caridina Desmaresti</italic> dans les eaux de la Meuse. Bulletin du Musée Royal d’Histoire Naturelle de Belgique 4: 211–222. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/120880">http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/120880</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B67"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> jModelTest: phylogenetic model averaging.</article-title> <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution </source> <volume>25</volume> (<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1253</fpage>-<lpage>1256</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msn083">10.1093/molbev/msn083</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B68"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafinesque</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1814</year>)<source> Précis des découvertes et travaux somiologiques de m.r. CS Rafinesque-Schmaltz entre 1800 et 1814 ou choix raisonné de ses principales découvertes en zoologie et en botanique, pour servir d’introduction à ses ouvrages futurs.</source> <publisher-name>Royal Typographie Militaire</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Palerme</publisher-loc>, <lpage>56</lpage> pp.doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.6135">10.5962/bhl.title.6135</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B69"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafinesque</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1815</year>)<source> Analyse de la nature, ou tableau de l’univers et des corps organisés. L’imprimerie de Jean Barravecchia, Palerme, 224 pp. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k98061z/">http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k98061z/</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B70"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Reyjol</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hugueny</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pont</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianco</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beier</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caiola</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casals</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowx</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Economou</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haidvog</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noble</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Sostoa</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigneron</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Virbickas</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Patterns in species richness and endemism of European freshwater fish.</article-title> <source>Global Ecology and Biogeography </source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1466-822x.2006.00264.x">10.1111/j.1466-822x.2006.00264.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B71"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Grave</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname> <given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> A new atyid genus and species from Madagascar (Crustacea, Decapoda, Caridea). Zootaxa 3162: 31–38. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2012/f/z03162p038f.pdf">http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2012/f/z03162p038f.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B72"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Salman</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Larval development of <italic>Atyaephyra desmaresti mesopotamica</italic> Al-Adhub (Decapoda, Atyidae) reared in the laboratory.</article-title> <source>Investigacion Pesquera</source> <volume>51</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>42</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/156854087X00484">10.1163/156854087X00484</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B73"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanjur</surname> <given-names>OI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmona</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doadrio</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Evolutionary and biogeographical patterns within Iberian populations of the genus <italic>Squalius</italic> inferred from molecular data.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution </source> <volume>29</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S1055-7903(03)00088-5">10.1016/S1055-7903(03)00088-5</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B74"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frati</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckenbach</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crespi</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flook</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<source>Evolution, weighting and phylogenetic utility of mitochondrial gene sequences and a compilation of conserved polymerase chain reaction primers. Annals of the Entomological Society of America87 (6):651–701. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hydrodictyon.eeb.uconn.edu/projects/cicada/resources/reprints/Simon_ea_1994.pdf">http://hydrodictyon.eeb.uconn.edu/projects/cicada/resources/reprints/Simon_ea_1994.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B75"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sket</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zakšek</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> European cave shrimp species (Decapoda, Caridea, Atyidae), redefined after a phylogenetic study; redefinition of some taxa, a new genus and four new <italic>Troglocaris</italic> species.</article-title> <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society </source> <volume>155</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>786</fpage>-<lpage>818</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.2008.00473.x">10.1111/j.1096-3642.2008.00473.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B76"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Straka</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Špaček</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> First record of alien crustaceans <italic>Atyaephyra desmarestii</italic> (Millet, 1831) and <italic>Jaera istri</italic> Veuille, 1979 from the Czech Republic.</article-title> <source>Aquatic Invasions </source> <volume>4</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>397</fpage>-<lpage>399</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3391/ai.2009.4.2.18">10.3391/ai.2009.4.2.18</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B77"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title>MEGA5: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods.</article-title> <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution </source> <volume>28</volume> (<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>2731</fpage>-<lpage>2739</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msr121">10.1093/molbev/msr121</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B78"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Taramelli</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1864</year>)<source> Sui crostacei di forme marine viventi nelle acque dolci e specialmente sul <italic>Palaemon palustris</italic> di Martens. Lettera del Signor Torquato Taramelli al Socio Prof. G. Balsamo Crivelli. Atti della Società Italiana di Scienze Naturali, Milano 6 (3): 363–371. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ia601209.us.archive.org/8/items/attidellasocieti6272soci/attidellasocieti6272soci.pdf">http://ia601209.us.archive.org/8/items/attidellasocieti6272soci/attidellasocieti6272soci.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B79"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tautz</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arctander</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minelli</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogler</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> A plea for DNA taxonomy.</article-title> <source>Trends in Ecology and Evolution </source> <volume>18</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>70</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0169-5347(02)00041-1">10.1016/S0169-5347(02)00041-1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B80"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Udekem d’ Acoz</surname> <given-names>C d’</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> Inventaire et distribution des crustacés décapodes de l’Atlantique nord-oriental, de la Méditerranée et des eaux continentales adjacentes au nord de 25°N. Collection Patrimoines Naturels, Volume 40, Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris, 383 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B81"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Von Rintelen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roe</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stelbrink</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhajda</surname> <given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iliffe</surname> <given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Rintelen</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> Drawn to the dark side: a molecular phylogeny of freshwater shrimps (Crustacea, Decapoda, Caridea, Atyidae) reveals frequent cave invasions and challenges current taxonomic hypotheses.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution </source> <volume>63</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>82</fpage>-<lpage>96</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2011.12.015">10.1016/j.ympev.2011.12.015</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B82"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zakšek</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sket</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trontelj</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of the cave shrimp <italic>Troglocaris</italic>: evidence of a young connection between Balkans and Caucasus.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution </source> <volume>42</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>223</fpage>-<lpage>235</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2006.07.009">10.1016/j.ympev.2006.07.009</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
        <sec sec-type="Appendix">
            <title>Appendix</title>
            <p>List of morphological characters studied and photos of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and &quot;<italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic>&quot; material examined by Bouvier (1913). (doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.229.3919.app">10.3897/zookeys.229.3919.app</ext-link>) File format: Mictosoft Office Document (docx).</p>
            <p><bold>Explanation note:</bold> A list of 135 morphological characters (67 meristic and 68 somatometric distances) examined in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> species is given. Schematic drawings of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra</tp:taxon-name></italic> appendages showing the studied somatometric characters are supplied. Furthermore, photos of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra desmarestii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Atyaephyra rosiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> material, collected from Maine et Loire (France) and Coimbra (Portugal) respectively, examined by Bouvier (1913) are given.</p>
            <p><bold>Copyright notice:</bold> This dataset is made available under the Open Database License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/odbl/1.0/">http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/odbl/1.0/</ext-link> ). The Open Database License (ODbL) is a license agreement intended to allow users to freely share, modify, and use this Dataset while maintaining this same freedom for others, provided that the original source and author(s) are credited.</p>
        </sec>
    </back>
</article>