<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.251.3616</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>On the identity of the type species of the genus 
                    <italic>Telema</italic> (Araneae, Telemidae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Wang</surname>
                        <given-names>Chunxia</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Ribera</surname>
                        <given-names>Carles</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Li</surname>
                        <given-names>Shuqiang</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100101, China
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Institut de Recerca de la Biodiversitat (IRBio) and Departament de Biologia Animal, Universitat de Barcelona, Avinguda Diagonal 645, 08028 Barcelona, Spain
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, China
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Shuqiang Li (<email xlink:type="simple">lisq@ioz.ac.cn</email>)
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Y. Marusik</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>18</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>251</issue>
            <fpage>11</fpage>
            <lpage>19</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>7</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>23</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Chunxia Wang, Carles Ribera, Shuqiang Li</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Simon, 1882, the type species of genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema</tp:taxon-name></italic>, is the only species of family <tp:taxon-name>Telemidae</tp:taxon-name> reported from Europe and all other 39 congeners occur far from it.However, it has never been properly described. In this paper <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic> is redescribed and illustrated.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>diagnosis</kwd>
                <kwd>haplogynae</kwd>
                <kwd>cave</kwd>
                <kwd>Eurasia</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema</tp:taxon-name></italic> and its type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic> were described by Eugene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Simon (1882)</xref> in the family <tp:taxon-name>Leptonetidae</tp:taxon-name>. The genus was later treated as a member of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Teleminae</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Fage (1913)</xref>, which was subsequently elevated to the status of family level, <tp:taxon-name>Telemidae</tp:taxon-name> Fage, 1913, by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Petrunkevitch (1923)</xref>. The family <tp:taxon-name>Telemidae</tp:taxon-name> now contains 8 genera and 61 species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Platnick 2012</xref>) from tropical Africa, East and Southeast Asia, and North and Central America. Its type genus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema</tp:taxon-name></italic> Simon, 1882, <!--PageBreak-->is the largest genus in the family, with 40 species occurring in Guatemala, Southwest Europe, and East and Southeast Asia.
            </p>
            <p>Prior to make global revision of the genus we decided to study the type species, which is insufficiently known, and to redescribe it details. This can allow us and other researches to conduct regional revisions of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Although several authors provided descriptions of the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Simon 1893</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Fage 1913</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Yaginuma 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ribera and Mateos 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Le Peru 2011</xref>), the morphological characters were not sufficiently detailed. Further, no information existed on the status of type material in Paris (Christine Rollard, personal communication). We made great efforts to find the species at the type locality, but failed. This suggested that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a restricted distribution. The species is known from six localities in Mount Canigó (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Juberthie 1985</xref>) in the French Department of the Oriental Pyrenees. All localities were above 900 meters in elevation. More recently, this species has been recorded from la Cova del Far in the province of Girona, Spain, at 1100 meters in elevation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ribera and Mateos 2000</xref>). However, Juberthie (personal communication) indicated that no specimens were recovered in five localities of Mount Canigó, and a recently conducted (2006–2007) survey in Cova del Far (Girona-Spain) also failed to detect specimens.
            </p>
            <p>We had the chance to collect some specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Telemidae</tp:taxon-name> in a cave near the type locality of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic> in 2011. The small cave was located next to Highway D115A, approximately 2000 meters from Banys de la Preste on the way to Prats of Molló, France (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">42°24.43'N, 2°24.37'E</named-content>, elevation 1097 meters), which is approximately 9000 meters from the type locality. After comparing the specimen with original description, we treat them as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the type species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Herein, we describe these specimens.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods">
            <title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>Specimens were collected by direct searching, and subsequently were examined and measured using a Leica M205 C stereomicroscope. Further details were studied and measured with an Olympus BX41 compound microscope. The copulatory organs were examined and illustrated after they were dissected from the spiders’ bodies. Vulva were removed and treated in lactic acid before illustration. The right palp of male spider was illustrated. The specimens were preserved in an 80% ethanol solution. Photos were taken with an Olympus C7070 wide zoom digital camera (7.1 megapixels) mounted on an Olympus SZX12 stereomicroscope. The images were montaged using Helicon Focus image stacking software. All measurements were given in millimeters. Leg measurements were shown as: total length (femur, patella, tibia, metatarsus, tarsus). Leg segments were measured on their dorsal side.</p>
            <p>The studied specimens were deposited in the Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing (IZCAS).<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <sec sec-type="Family Telemidae Fage, 1913">
                <title>Family <tp:taxon-name>Telemidae</tp:taxon-name> Fage, 1913
                </title>
                <sec sec-type="Genus Telema Simon, 1882">
                <title>Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema</tp:taxon-name></italic> Simon, 1882
                </title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Telema</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">tenella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Telema_tenella</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Simon, 1882</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">–5</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Simon 1882</xref>: 205 (♂♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Simon 1893</xref>: 284, f. 240, 244 (♂); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Fage 1913</xref>: 510, pl. 48–49, f. 1–21 (♂♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Yaginuma 1974</xref>: 15, f. 1 (♂); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Le Peru 2011</xref>: 142, f. 176 (♂♀).</comment>
                            </tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Not examined.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>1 ♂ and 1 ♀ (IZCAS), unnamed cave, Banys de la Preste to Prats of Molló, France [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">42°24.43'N, 2°24.37'E</named-content>, 1097 meters], Carles Ribera leg.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic> differs from other congeners by the distinct shape of male palp and female spermatheca. It is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema wunderlichi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Song &amp; Zhu, 1994, a species from Hunan, China, but can be distinguished by the shape of carapace, five tiny denticles on the retromargin of chelicerae (four in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema wunderlichi</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and bent embolus (straight in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema wunderlichi</tp:taxon-name></italic>).
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><bold>Male</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Total length 1.40. Carapace 0.60 long, 0.55 wide. Abdomen 0.70 long, 0.64 wide. Sternum 0.40 long, 0.34 wide. Carapace, chelicerae, endites and labium yellow. Sternum and legs yellowish-white. Carapace with one pair of setae on clypeus, three medially and four on ocular area. Eyeless. Chelicerae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4E</xref>) with one tooth and four tiny granulous denticles on the promargin, and five tiny granulous denticles on the retromargin of fang furrow. Anterior edge of labium with 4 strong and 8 small bristles. Patella I–IV dorsally with one long seta distally, tibia III IV with one long seta dorsally (position 0.5). Leg measurements: I 4.40 (1.33, 0.23, 1.32, 0.93, 0.59); II 3.91 (1.17, 0.23, 1.09, 0.86, 0.56); III 2.87 (0.87, 0.19, 0.75, 0.62, 0.44); IV 3.54 (1.09, 0.23, 0.94, 0.75, 0.53). Abdomen blue, covered with long setae. Male palp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2B–D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A–B, D</xref>). Bulb light yellow, pyriform, with embolus the only projection erected distally; embolus lamellar, curving, short, approximately 1/5 the length of bulb, and weakly sclerotized at the distal part.
                        </p>
                        <p><bold>Female</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A–B</xref>). Similar to male in coloration and general features. Total length 1.30. Carapace 0.60 long, 0.55 wide. Abdomen 0.65 long, 0.65 wide. Sternum 0.40 long, 0.34 wide. Leg measurements: I 4.37 (1.33, 0.23, 1.32, 0.93, 0.56); II 3.92 (1.09, 0.23, 1.25, 0.81, 0.54); III 2.88 (0.71, 0.19, 0.86, 0.59, 0.53); IV 3.58 (0.94, 0.23, 1.09, 0.78, 0.54). Genital area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>) with a row of setae on epigynal area and a row of stout setae posterior to epigastric furrow. Spermatheca (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3C–D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B–C</xref>) elongate, transparent, and tube-shaped, with the distal part curving ventrally.
                        </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>In Pyrenees: France (Pyrénées-Orientales: caves Sainte-Marie and Can Britxot near La Preste; cave Sirach near Ria; caves Can Pey and La Fou near Arles-sur-Tech; copper mine near La Preste), Spain (Gerona, Cueva del Far).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion">
                        <title>Discussion.</title>
                        <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema</tp:taxon-name></italic> contains 40 species distributed in Spain, France, Guatemala, Japan, Singapore, Borneo, Thailand, Vietnam, and China. Compared with the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, some species in the genus have one prolateral apophysis on the cymbium; most species from China have a lager body size, more pigmented bodies, stronger embolus; and the species from Singapore, Borneo, and Thailand have different spermatheca in the female, either thin and strongly spiral or short and swelling. The taxonomic status of the species in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema</tp:taxon-name></italic> needs to be studied further as well as distributional limits of the genus.
                        </p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 1.</label>
                            <caption><p>Subadultfemale hanging beneath web. Photo byEnric Planas in an unnamed cave in Banys de la Preste to Prats of Molló, France.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-011-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 2.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic>,male. Based on material from an unnamed cave in Banys de la Preste to Prats of Molló, France. <bold>A</bold> Habitus, dorsal view <bold>B</bold> Embolus tip, apical view <bold>C</bold> Right palp, retrolateral view <bold>D</bold> Right palp, prolateral view.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-011-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 3.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, female. Based on material from an unnamed cave in Banys de la Preste to Prats of Molló, France. <bold>A</bold>. Habitus, dorsal view <bold>B</bold> Habitus, ventral view <bold>C</bold> Copulatory organ, dorsal view <bold>D</bold> Copulatory organ, lateral view.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-011-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 4.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic>,male. Based on material from an unnamed cave in Banys de la Preste to Prats of Molló, France. <bold>A</bold> Right palp, retrolateral view B Right palp, prolateral view <bold>C</bold> Colulus, ventral view <bold>D</bold> Embolus tip, apical view <bold>E</bold> Chelicerae, posterior view. Scale bars: <bold>A, B, E</bold> 0.10 mm; <bold>C, D</bold> 0.05 mm.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-011-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 5.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Telema tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, female. Based on material from an unnamed cave in Banys de la Preste to Prats of Molló, France. <bold>A</bold> Genital area, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Copulatory organ, dorsal view <bold>C</bold> Copulatory organ, lateral view <bold>D</bold> Pedicel, dorsal view. Scale bars: <bold>A</bold>, 0.05 mm; <bold>B, C, D</bold> 0.10 mm.</p>
                            </caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-251-011-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                </sec>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>The manuscript benefited greatly from comments by Y. M. Marusik (Magadan, Russia), Robert W. Murphy (Toronto, Canada) and two anonymous reviewers. This study was supported by project CGL2004-05771/BOS from Spanish Government to Carles Rib<!--PageBreak-->era.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fage</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1913</year>)<article-title> Etudes sur les Araignées cavernicoles. II. Revision des Leptonetidae. In Biospelogica, XXIX.</article-title> <source>Archive De Zoologie Expérimentale Et Genéralé </source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>479</fpage>-<lpage>576</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Juberthie</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Cycle vital de <italic>Telema tenella</italic> dans la grotte-laboratoire de Moulis et strategies de reproduction chez les araignées cavenicoles.</article-title> <source>Mémoires de Biospéologie </source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Peru</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> The spiders of Europe, a synthesis of data: Atypidae to Theridiidae.</article-title> <source>Mémoires de la Société Linnéenne de Lyon </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>522</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrunkevitch</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1923</year>)<article-title> On families of spiders.</article-title> <source>Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences </source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>180</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1749-6632.1920.tb55355.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1749-6632.1920.tb55355.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname> <given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> The world spider catalog, version 13.0. American Museum of Natural History. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://research.amnh.org/iz/spiders/catalog/" xlink:type="simple">http://research.amnh.org/iz/spiders/catalog/</ext-link> [accessed 10 August 2012]</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribera</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mateos</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> <italic>Telema tenella</italic> (Simon, 1882) (Telemidae) y <italic>Argyroneta aquatica</italic> (Clerck, 1758) (Argyronetidae), dos nuevas familias de araneidos para la fauna ibérica.</article-title> <source>Revista Ibérica de Aracnología </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1882</year>)<article-title> Etudes Arachnologiques. 13e Mémoire. XX. Descriptions d’espèces et de genres nouveaux de la famille des Dysderidae.</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société entomologique de France </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>-<lpage>240</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1893</year>)<source> Histoire naturelle das araignées.</source> Volume <volume>1</volume>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>488</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname> <given-names>DX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> On some species of cave arachnids of China.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>YY</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed.</role>) <source>Sixtieth Anniversary of the Founding of China Zoological Society: Memorial Volume Dedicated to the Hundredth Anniversary of the Birthday of the Late Prof. Sisan Chen (Z. Chen).</source> <publisher-name>Science and Technology Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>, <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaginuma</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<article-title> A telemid spider occurs in Japan.</article-title> <source>Atypus </source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>14</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>