<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.208.3326</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    <italic>Mariapanteles</italic> (Hymenoptera, Braconidae), a new genus of Neotropical microgastrine parasitoid wasp discovered through biodiversity inventory
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Whitfield</surname>
                        <given-names>James B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7A98AB5F-552D-4437-8F5D-C593CA713506</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Fernández-Triana</surname>
                        <given-names>José L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:4469D91F-BBC1-4CBF-8263-EBFE2A95E4BF</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Janzen</surname>
                        <given-names>Daniel H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:4491369A-CFA6-4614-AC09-1137CCD06F9A</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Hallwachs</surname>
                        <given-names>Winnie</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:68F37FFD-B6AB-49AD-A1AD-1C84B2FB94C9</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Smith</surname>
                        <given-names>M. Alex</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:E46EE6EB-E096-4FCD-BF5A-F91D4A8294EE</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Cardinal</surname>
                        <given-names>Sophie</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:9D43F9ED-9B25-4C55-A99E-84D62F7204C0</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Entomology, 320 Morrill Hall, 505 S. Goodwin Ave., University of Illinois, Urbana, IL 61801 USA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Department of Integrative Biology &amp; the Biodiversity Institute of Ontario, University of Guelph, Guelph, Ontario, N1G 2W1 CANADA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Canadian National Collection of Insects, Ottawa, ON K1A 0C6, CANADA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A4">
                <label>4</label>Canadian National Collection of Insects, Ottawa, ON K1A 0C6, CANADA
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: James B. Whitfield (<email xlink:type="simple">jwhitfie@life.illinois.edu</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Gavin Broad</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>17</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>208</issue>
            <fpage>61</fpage>
            <lpage>80</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>4</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>29</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>James B. Whitfield, José L. Fernández-Triana, Daniel H. Janzen, Winnie Hallwachs, M. Alex Smith, Sophie Cardinal</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:51CE38E7-5FB4-4D70-8574-7D27FD935233</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new genus of microgastrine parasitoid wasps, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield &amp; Fernández-Triana, <bold>gen. n.</bold>, is described from rain forests of the Neotropics. The new genus is related to the common and speciose genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but can be distinguished from the latter by having a complete transverse carina on the propodeum which forks around the spiracles. A molecular analysis based on data from COI from specimens of the proposed new genus plus possibly related genera confirms its generic distinctness. A key to two known species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles felipei</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield, <bold>sp. n.</bold> (Costa Rica) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles dapkeyae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fernández-Triana, <bold>sp. n.</bold> (Brazil) is provided. Evidence from collections suggests that there are other undescribed Neotropical congenerics. Specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> were likely confused in the past with the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Beyarslania</tp:taxon-name></italic> (referred to as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xenogaster</tp:taxon-name></italic> until recently) but present information suggests that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Beyarslania</tp:taxon-name></italic> is restricted to the Afrotropical region while the Neotropical species clearly belong to a different genus, which we propose as new.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Microgastrinae</kwd>
                <kwd>new genus</kwd>
                <kwd>Area de Conservación Guanacaste</kwd>
                <kwd>Costa Rica</kwd>
                <kwd>Brazil</kwd>
                <kwd>Neotropics</kwd>
                <kwd>parasitoid wasp</kwd>
                <kwd>rain forest</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>In the past few decades, biodiversity inventories in the neotropics have begun to incorporate intensive rearing programs for caterpillars, their food plants, and their parasitoids. The most extensive of these programs is in the Area de Conservación de Guanacaste (ACG) in northwestern Costa Rica. ACG contains 130,000 terrestrial hectares of contiguous conserved dry forest, cloud forest, and rain forest, extending from the Pacific Ocean to 2,000 m elevation and then down into the Caribbean lowlands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Janzen 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Janzen and Hallwachs 2011</xref>). The caterpillar/plant/parasitoid inventory is one of the main components of ACG conservation (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Janzen and Hallwachs 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Janzen et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Smith et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">2007</xref>, 2008; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Sharkey et al. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Burns et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Schauff et al. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Gauld and Janzen 2004</xref>). <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> have been one of the most intensively studied groups of ACG parasitoids (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Valerio et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Smith et al. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Grinter et al. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Deans et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Whitfield et al. 2011</xref>), but many hundreds of species of these tiny wasps still remain to be discovered and described. Microgastrines are probably the single most speciose higher taxon of parasitoids of <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> (Whitfield 1995, 1997), and it is estimated that 800+ species occur in ACG alone (Janzen and Hallwachs, inventory in progress).</p>
            <p>The ACG inventory has encountered a rain forest species of <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> that superficially resembles the rare Old World genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Beyarslania</tp:taxon-name></italic> - widely known as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xenogaster</tp:taxon-name></italic> until a recent nomenclatural change (Kocak and Kemal 2009). This genus is only known from a single described species from South Africa, but undescribed species have been thought to exist in the Neotropics (Whitfield 1997; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Campos and Diego 2001</xref>). As we studied the ACG specimens and other similar Neotropical specimens, we realized that these undescribed species are more informatively placed in a new genus, which we erect and describe here along with descriptions of two species contained within it. A molecular phylogenetic analysis based on data from the COI (“barcoding”) gene is included to provide a further test of the monophyly of this putative new genus.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
            <title>Methods</title>
            <p>The specimens for this study came from two main sources: the ACG inventory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Janzen and Hallwachs 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Janzen et al. 2009</xref>) and unsorted Neotropical wasps from the Canadian National Collection of Insects (CNC) in Ottawa. The genotype for the new genus has been deposited in the Smithsonian Institution (NMNH) and the remaining specimens have been deposited in the CNC, Illinois Natural History Survey (INHS) and the Natural History Museum, London (BMNH).<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <p>The morphological terms and morphological measurements follow mostly Wharton and Sharkey (1997) and Valerio and Whitfield (2009).</p>
            <p>Photos were taken with a Keyence VHX-1000 Digital Microscope, using a lens with a range of 13–130×. Plates for the illustrations were prepared using Adobe Photoshop, but images were not digitally enhanced.</p>
            <p>DNA barcodes for these and all other ACG inventory <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> were obtained using DNA extracts prepared from single legs using a glass fibre protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Ivanova et al. 2006</xref>). Extracts were re-suspended in 30 μl of dH2O, and a 658-bp region near the 5’ terminus of the COI gene was amplified using standard primers (LepF1–LepR1) following established protocols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Smith et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">2007</xref>, 2008). If the initial 658 bp amplification was not successful composite sequences were generated using internal primers. Primer information for individuals sequences can be retrieved from the Barcode of Life Data System (BOLD) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Ratnasingham and Hebert 2007</xref>) using the accessions detailed in the online supplementary table , but primers are as detailed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Smith et al. (2008)</xref>. Full details of methodology are as in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Smith et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">2007</xref>, 2008). All sequence data are available on BOLD (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.barcodinglife.org">www.barcodinglife.org</ext-link> ) in the public Dataset, “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name>), a new genus of Neotropical microgastrine parasitoid wasp discovered through biodiversity inventory”. All collection information, BOLD, and GenBank accessions for all sequences are listed in the Table in online supplementary materials.</p>
            <p>All available DNA barcodes for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> (32 New World species, most of which are undescribed) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> (2 species) that were at least 300 bp longwere downloaded from BOLD (see the online supplementary table). DNA barcodes for selected species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Prasmodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diolcogaster</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Microplitis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cotesia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neoclarkinella</tp:taxon-name></italic> were also downloaded to be used as outgroups in the phylogenetic analyses. Genbank accession numbers of all sequences used are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. Prior to analysis, identical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> sequences were removed from the dataset so that each unique sequence was only represented once. Sequences were aligned in Geneious Pro 5.5.6 (Drummond et al. 2011) using default settings for MUSCLE alignment. The first character was deleted from the aligned matrix because most sequences were missing this character. Bayesian phylogenetic analysis was performed in MrBayes v.3.1.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Ronquist and Huelsenbeck 2003</xref>) through the CIPRES Science Gateway V.3.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Miller et al. 2010</xref>). Model selection was based on Bayesian Information Criteria as implemented in JModelTest v.0.1.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Posada 2008</xref>). Two independent analyses with 4 chains each were run in parallel for 10 million generations under a GTR+I+G model. The parameter trace files of each run were observed in Tracer v.1.5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Rambaut and Drummond 2009</xref>) to verify that the runs had converged on the same stationary distribution, and to decide on the appropriate number of generations to discard as burn-in. A maximum clade credibility tree was constructed from these 18 million post-burn-in generations in TreeAnnotator v1.7.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Rambaut and Drummond 2012</xref>). The above protocol was followed for two additional analyses in which all 3<sup>rd</sup> codon positions were removed from the dataset to correct for potential problems stemming from saturation in 3<sup>rd</sup> codon positions of COI.</p>
            <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
								<label>Table 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Specimens included in the COI molecular analyses and their GenBank Accession numbers. Sample IDs are DHJPAR numbers (assigned to ACG specimens submitted to BOLD) or other IDs submitted to BOLD. More complete data on all specimens are included in Appendix 1.</p></caption>
                <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taxon</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample ID</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genbank Accession Number</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Rodriguez03</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0012802</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ847281" xlink:type="simple">JQ847281</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Rodriguez05</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0012285</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/EU396474" xlink:type="simple">EU396474</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Rodriguez169</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0038032</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ848826" xlink:type="simple">JQ848826</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cotesia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield03</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0013374</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ848576" xlink:type="simple">JQ848576</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Diolcogaster</tp:taxon-name></italic> Choi04</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0004153</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ549146" xlink:type="simple">HQ549146</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles dapkeyae</tp:taxon-name></italic> F.-T.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNCHYM 03387</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ849377" xlink:type="simple">JQ849377</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles felipei</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0025453</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ549955" xlink:type="simple">HQ549955</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles felipei</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0025443</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JN282317" xlink:type="simple">JN282317</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Microplitis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0031685</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ548870" xlink:type="simple">HQ548870</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Neoclarkinella</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.jft10</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WAM 0011</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ852287" xlink:type="simple">JQ852287</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Neoclarkinella</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.jft11</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GOU 0608</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ849914" xlink:type="simple">JQ849914</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Prasmodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield02</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0038222</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ548705" xlink:type="simple">HQ548705</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Prasmodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield05</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0012956</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ548880" xlink:type="simple">HQ548880</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles gouleti</tp:taxon-name></italic> F.-T.</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAM 0874</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ848150" xlink:type="simple">JQ848150</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. jft8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNCHYM 03312</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ849707" xlink:type="simple">JQ849707</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. jft16</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNCHYM 03343</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ575645" xlink:type="simple">JQ575645</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. jft19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNCHYM 03355</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ850586" xlink:type="simple">JQ850586</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. jft23</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNCHYM 03372</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ850275" xlink:type="simple">JQ850275</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. jft23</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNCHYM 03372</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ850275" xlink:type="simple">JQ850275</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. jft23</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNCHYM 03369</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ854346" xlink:type="simple">JQ854346</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. jft25</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNCHYM 03377</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ853286" xlink:type="simple">JQ853286</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. jft25</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNCHYM 03377</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ853286" xlink:type="simple">JQ853286</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.jft29</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10BBHYM-1279</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ852886" xlink:type="simple">JQ852886</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.jft29</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Micro0094</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ852261" xlink:type="simple">JQ852261</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.jft29</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Micro0269</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ850735" xlink:type="simple">JQ850735</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield01</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0004755</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ849938" xlink:type="simple">JQ849938</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield02</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0025345</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ850204" xlink:type="simple">JQ850204</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield05</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0031341</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ852695" xlink:type="simple">JQ852695</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield05</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0026205</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ549736" xlink:type="simple">HQ549736</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield05</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0033906</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ576585" xlink:type="simple">JQ576585</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield06</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0031347</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ930249" xlink:type="simple">HQ930249</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield06</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0031191</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ849350" xlink:type="simple">JQ849350</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield06</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0034081</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ853689" xlink:type="simple">JQ853689</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield07</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0013217</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ852406" xlink:type="simple">JQ852406</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield08</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0026281</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ849770" xlink:type="simple">JQ849770</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield09</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0027627</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JN281617" xlink:type="simple">JN281617</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield09</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0027692</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HM430666" xlink:type="simple">HM430666</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield09</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0027392</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ849832" xlink:type="simple">JQ849832</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield09</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0026088</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ854468" xlink:type="simple">JQ854468</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield09</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0026012</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ853711" xlink:type="simple">JQ853711</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield09</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0026026</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ549676" xlink:type="simple">HQ549676</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield09</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0027661</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ576067" xlink:type="simple">JQ576067</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield09</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0033842</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ550374" xlink:type="simple">HQ550374</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield09</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0031297</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ855464" xlink:type="simple">JQ855464</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield10</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0012880</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ854478" xlink:type="simple">JQ854478</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield11</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0031742</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ847036" xlink:type="simple">JQ847036</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield12</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0025380</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ550092" xlink:type="simple">HQ550092</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield14</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0025854</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ549888" xlink:type="simple">HQ549888</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield15</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0025751</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ849472" xlink:type="simple">JQ849472</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield17</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0026060</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JN281784" xlink:type="simple">JN281784</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield18</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0027669</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ853458" xlink:type="simple">JQ853458</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0027440</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ848147" xlink:type="simple">JQ848147</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0026033</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ847890" xlink:type="simple">JQ847890</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0026268</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ852987" xlink:type="simple">JQ852987</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0027440</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ848147" xlink:type="simple">JQ848147</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0026033</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ847890" xlink:type="simple">JQ847890</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0026268</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ852987" xlink:type="simple">JQ852987</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0025022</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ926353" xlink:type="simple">HQ926353</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0026008</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ850045" xlink:type="simple">JQ850045</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0025959</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ849085" xlink:type="simple">JQ849085</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0025866</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ852050" xlink:type="simple">JQ852050</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0026534</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ550096" xlink:type="simple">HQ550096</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0027150</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HQ548886" xlink:type="simple">HQ548886</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0025831</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ574919" xlink:type="simple">JQ574919</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield20</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0040493</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ849256" xlink:type="simple">JQ849256</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield20</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0027329</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ848647" xlink:type="simple">JQ848647</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield20</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0039680</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ848927" xlink:type="simple">JQ848927</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield20</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0041914</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ847496" xlink:type="simple">JQ847496</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield21</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0038402</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/EU396445" xlink:type="simple">EU396445</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield21</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0027221</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JN282176" xlink:type="simple">JN282176</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield23</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0031749</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ852705" xlink:type="simple">JQ852705</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield27</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHJPAR0043058</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/JQ850352" xlink:type="simple">JQ850352</ext-link></td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
            </table-wrap>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <sec sec-type="Molecular confirmation of Mariapanteles monophyly">
                <title>Molecular confirmation of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> monophyly</title>
                <p>Evidence (beyond the morphologcial data presented below) for the separation of these two genera comes from DNA barcode data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 13</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">14</xref>). When comparing the two species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> to 32 species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> (most of them undescribed) for which there are CO1 sequences available in BOLD (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.boldsystems.com">www.boldsystems.com</ext-link> ), the two genera are recovered as separate groups.</p>
                <p>Bayesian analysis of the COI sequences, with and without 3<sup>rd</sup> codon positions included, clearly supports <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> as being a separate distinct group from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 13</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">14</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> was recovered as being monophyletic with posterior probability (PP) of 1 when 3<sup>rd</sup> codon positions were included and PP of 0.8 when 3<sup>rd</sup> codon positions were removed. Monophyly of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> was recovered with PP of 1 in both analyses. Furthermore, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> was not recovered as the sister group to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> in either analysis. Several other genera included as potentially disrupting <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> monophyly also failed to do so in the analyses, so we have concluded that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> is indeed a distinct genus<!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:917FB3C2-D102-4884-9FC4-787CC81AD5E9</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Mariapanteles</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Whitfield &amp; Fernández-Triana</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">–12</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                        <title>Type species.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles felipei</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield sp. n., by present designation.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Genus diagnosis">
                        <title>Genus diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Propodeum with a complete transverse carina that forks around spiracles and reaches the lateral margin of propodeum, where it intersects a raised lateral carina. Fore wing without areolet (veins r-m and 3RS absent). First mediotergite with a sharp median groove on the basal half. The only other genera of Neotropical microgastrines with a complete transverse carina on the propodeum, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Clarkinella</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Prasmodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>, both lack a medial groove on the first mediotergite and have an areolet in the forewing (a small areolet in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Clarkinella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a large and quadrangular one in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Prasmodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> in fore wing venation, shape of mediotergites 1 and 2, and general appearance of the body. However, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> has an elongate, bifurcate glossa, lacks a complete transverse carina on the propodeum, and the hypopygium has a large translucent fold with many pleats; the glossa of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> is not bifurcate and the hypopygium has a median translucent fold with no or only a few pleats visible.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Body length 2.4–2.6 mm, fore wing length 2.6–2.9 mm, antenna about the same length as body. Pronotum with two lateral grooves present, the lower one excavated. Mesoscutum more or less uniformly sculptured by impressed punctures. Mesoscutum 1.3–1.4× wider than long. Mesoscutum and scutellum uniformly covered by dense, pale yellowish pilosity. Scutellum length/width at base 1.0-1.1X. Scutellar suture broad, with 4–8 costulae. Posterior band of scutellum polished. Scutellar lateral face with the polished area thin (15–25% the face height) and about half the face width. Mesopleuron mostly smooth and glabrous, except for punctures on the anterior margin and setae on all margins. Metapleuron mostly smooth, with some punctures and setae in the apical half; metapleuron with a crenulate, longitudinal sulcus running from lower margin near metacoxa through spiracle. Metapleural carina raised, with a short lamella. Propodeum mostly smooth; median carina well defined and raised its entire length, and with a clearly complete transverse carina that reaches the spiracles and forks around them (there may also be additional, shorter transverse carinae, some of them radiating from the median carina but not reaching the spiracles). Transverse carina on propodeum delimiting two areas, the anterior, basal one being more or less horizontal; the posterior, apical one is declivous. Mediotergite 1 mostly smooth and with a deep medial groove on its basal half; slightly widening for the first quarter of its length, then narrowing towards apex. Mediotergite 2 mostly smooth, transverse, subtriangular to trapezoidal in shape. Mediotergite 3 and following, unsculptured, polished and with sparse setae. Hypopygium mostly inflexible but with a medial, translucent fold ventrally where none or few (1–2) pleats are distinguishable. Ovipositor sheaths fully setose, 0.7× as long as metatibia length. Metacoxa long, surpassing the length of the third metasomal tergite. Metatibial inner spur longer than outer spur, and <!--PageBreak-->about half the length of metatarsomere 1. Metafemur more than 3.0× as long as wide. Fore wing without an areolet, vein R1a longer than stigma length, and vein r and 2RS evenly curved to very slightly arched (with no clear limits between the two veins). Hind wing with edge of vannal lobe medially straight to slightly concave and with uniformly distributed setae that are shorter than those at base and apex of the lobe.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>The genus occurs in Central and South American rain forests. We describe two new species, one from Costa Rica (ACG, from rain forest at 400m) and one from Brazil (Mato Grosso and Goiás; the localities are presumed to have been rain forests at the time the specimens were collected). The CNC collection contains two additional specimens from other areas of Brazil that may represent additional species, but because they are singletons we do not describe them here. It is likely that more species of this new genus will be found in Neotropical rain forests.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology">
                        <title>Biology.</title>
                        <p>Unknown. All specimens have been collected with Townes-type Malaise traps.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> is dedicated to María Marta Chavarría Díaz of ACG and San Jose, Costa Rica, in recognition of her 30+ years of dedication to Costa Rican conservation, biodiversity systematics, and biodiversity development throughout Costa Rica, and very specifically within Area de Conservación de Guanacaste.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                        <title>Comments.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> is closely related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic>,and future revisions of the phylogeny of <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> might find that its erection renders <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> paraphyletic. For example, and according to Mason (1981), some species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> could have a multiple or indefinite transverse carina, in which case the complete transverse carina in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> might be seen as the extreme in a continuum from having no transverse carina to having the complete transverse carina of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However, we consider that the presence of a complete transverse carina on the propodeum, forking around the propodeal spiracles, may be a strong autapomorphy that defines <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic>. There are only four other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> with a similar, complete transverse carina on the propodeum: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Beyarslania</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Clarkinella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neoclarkinella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Prasmodon</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However, they all appear to be only distantly related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> because they all lack a sharp median groove on mediotergite 1 and/or have an areolet in the fore wing.</p>
                        <p>The described species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> never have a complete transverse carina. Most of the specimens in collections just have a simple median carina, with only few species having irregular transverse striations arising along the length of the median carina (but even in those cases they never reach the spiracle and never form a fork around them). One example can be seen in the original description and pictures of the species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles gouleti</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fernández-Triana, from Canada (Figure 18, page 24, in Fernández-Triana 2010). However, the carination pattern is not comparable to a complete transverse carina – as displayed by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                        <p>The presence of a bifurcate glossa is a strong autapomorphy for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> (it is only present in three other distantly related <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> genera: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Napamus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Promicrogaster</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sendaphne</tp:taxon-name></italic>). Furthermore, the differences between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> with respect to the pleated area of the hypopygium are also consistent in the separation of these two genera.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <p>Currently <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapan</tp:taxon-name></italic><italic>teles</italic> has nine described species (Yu et al. 2009), and a wide distribution within the New World, ranging from Canada to South America (one of the species has also been introduced to Hawaii (Coulson 1992)). The actual number of species is much higher, and we have seen in collections several dozen undescribed species, mostly from the Neotropics. The vast majority of those specimens are remarkably invariant in having a bifurcate glossa and in lacking a transverse carina on the propodeum.</p>
                        <p>For all of the above reasons along with the molecular results, we have decided that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a distinct, separate genus that may be closely related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                        <p>As for the former records of Neotropical species of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Beyarslania</tp:taxon-name></italic> (at that time called <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xenogaster</tp:taxon-name></italic>) (Whitfield 1997; Campos 2001), these are based on confusion with specimens of what we have described here as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Based on the available evidence, we now consider <italic><tp:taxon-name>Beyarslania</tp:taxon-name></italic> to be restricted to the African tropics. The Neotropical specimens thought to belong to that genus should be identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to Mariapanteles species described here">
                        <title>Key to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> species described here</title>
                        <table-wrap content-type="key" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body colour mostly yellow in females and males —at most, males with tergite 3+ brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>); scutellum mostly smooth and scutellar suture with 4-6 costulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 12</xref>); propodeum with a complete transverse carina that is clearly independent of other smaller transverse carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9, 12</xref>) [Mato Grosso and Goiás, Brazil]</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles dapkeyae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body colour in females mostly orange-yellowish but with some areas brown or reddish brown (apical edge of scutellum, metascutellum, some carina on propodeum, central area on mediotergites 3+) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), male with much darker coloration, especially in the interocellar area, mesosoma and metasoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>); scutellum with impressed punctures and scutellar suture with 6-8 costulae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>); propodeum with a completely transverse carinae not always clearly delimited from other smaller transverse carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>) [ACG, northwestern Costa Rica]</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles felipei</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Species descriptions">
            <title>Species descriptions</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">felipei</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:2A5E1320-5C93-45FE-AEB0-AF9382929A78</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Mariapanteles_felipei</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Whitfield</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–6</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype">
                    <title>Holotype.</title>
                    <p><bold>Female</bold> (NMNH).COSTA RICA: Alajuela Province, Sector Rincon Rain Forest of ACG, Caribe, Rio Francia, 400 m, latitude 10.90093, longitude -85.28915; 11–17.vii.2007, Malaise Trap. Voucher code: DHJPAR0025453.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratype">
                    <title>Paratype.</title>
                    <p>Male (NMNH).Same data as for holotype, except for collecting date: 22-28.viii.2007. Voucher code: DHJPAR0025443.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Female.</bold> Antenna about the same length as body; body length 2.6 mm; forewing 2.9 mm. Head: face with shallow and sparse punctures and sparse, uniformly distributed setae; face width at antennal base/face width at clypeus edge: 1.1×; intertentorial pit distance/face width at clypeus edge: 0.5×; compound eye height/head height: 0.8×; head height/width: 0.8×; face width at antennal base/head maximum width: 0.6×; malar space/basal width of mandible 1.3×; clypeus width/height: 3.1×. Length/width of flagellomeres: 2nd (2.3×), 8th (2.5×), 14th (1.3×). Length of flagellomere 2<sup>nd</sup>/length of flagellomere 14<sup>th</sup>: 2.2×. Ocello-ocular distance/posterior ocelli diameter: 2.3×; distance between posterior ocelli/ocelli diameter: 1.4×.</p>
                    <p>Mesosoma. Pronotum with two lateral grooves, the lower one excavated. Mesoscutum more or less uniformly sculptured by impressed punctures (distance between punctures about the same as their diameter). Mesoscutum 1.4× wider than long. Mesoscutum and scutellum uniformly covered by dense, pale-coloured pilosity. Scutellum similarly sculptured to mesoscutum. Scutellum length/width at base 1.0×. Scutellar suture broad, with 6-8 costulae. Posterior band of scutellum polished. Scutellar lateral face with polished area less than 30% the face height and about half the face width. Mesopleuron mostly smooth and glabrous, except for punctures on the anterior margin and setae on the all margins; separated from metapleuron by a crenulated sulcus. Metapleuron mostly smooth, with some punctures and setae in the apical half; metapleuron with a crenulate, longitudinal sulcus running from lower margin near metacoxa through spiracle. Metapleural carina raised with a short lamella. Propodeum mostly smooth, with a median carina well defined and raised its entire length; and with a clearly complete transverse carina that reaches the spiracles and forks around them (also with additional, shorter transverse carinae, some of them radiating from the median carina but not reaching the spiracles). Transverse carina on propodeum delimiting two areas, the anterior, basal one being more or less horizontal, while the posterior, apical one is declivous.</p>
                    <p>Metasoma. Mediotergite 1 mostly smooth and with a deep medial groove over its basal half; slightly widening for the first quarter of its length, then narrowing towards apex; basal width/apical width 2.1×; length/apical width 4.8×. Mediotergite 2 mostly smooth, transverse, subtriangular to trapezoidal in shape; basal width/apical width 0.4×; length/apical width 0.4×. Mediotergite 3 1.5× the length of mediotergite 2. Mediotergite 3 and following unsculptured, polished and with sparse setae. Hypopygium mostly inflexible but with a median, translucid fold ventrally where no pleats are distinguishable. Ovipositor sheaths fully setose, 0.7× as long as metatibia length.</p>
                    <p>Legs. Metacoxa long, surpassing the length of the third metasomal tergum. Metatibial inner spur 1.6× the length of outer spur, and 0.6× the length of metatarsomere 1. Metafemur 3.2× as long as wide.</p>
                    <p>Wings. Vein R1a 1.3× as long as stigma length. Stigma 3.1× as long as wide. Length of R1a about 12× as long as the distance between its end and the end of 3RSb. Vein r and 2RS evenly curved to very slightly arched, with no clear limits between the two veins. Vein 2M about the same length of vein (RS+M)b. Edge of vannal lobe of hind wing medially straight to slightly concave and with uniformly distribute setae which are shorter than those at base and apex of the lobe.<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p>Colour: Mostly an orange-yellowish species. Antennal flagellomere and dorsal part of scape brown. Apical edge of scutellum, metascutellum and some carina on propodeum, reddish-brown. Central area on mediotergites 3 and following dark brown. Forewing stigma and most of the wing veins dark brown.</p>
                    <p>Male. Like the female except for darker coloration as follows: interocellar area, propodeum, metascutellum, apical edge of scutellum, most of the lateral face of scutellum, and most of mediotergites 2+, dark brown to black.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–6.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles felipei</tp:taxon-name></italic> Whitfield. <bold>1</bold> Dorsal habitus, female <bold>2</bold> Dorsal habitus, male <bold>3</bold> forewing, female <bold>4</bold> head and mesoscutum, dorsal view, female <bold>5</bold> hypopygium and ovipositor, lateral view <bold>6</bold> metanotum and propodeum, female, dorsal view.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-208-061-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>The known specimens were captured in July-August 2007 (full rainy season) by the same Malaise trap placed in old growth rain forest understory on the banks of Rio Francia, where it crosses the access road through Sector Rincon Rain Forest of ACG, at 400 m.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Molecular data">
                    <title>Molecular data.</title>
                    <p>The two known specimens bear the same DNA barcode. The nucleotide sequence in fasta format is:</p>
                    <p>&gt;<italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles felipei</tp:taxon-name></italic></p>
                    <p>ATTTTATATTTTTTATTTGGAATATGATCTGGAATATTAGGATTTTCATTAAGAATAATTATCCGATTAGAGTTAGGCACACCAGGAAGATTAATTAGAAATGATCAAATCTATAATAGAATTGTTACATCACATGCTTTTATCATAATTTTTTTTATAGTTATACCAATTATAATTGGAGGATTTGGTAATTATTTAATTCCATTAATATTAGCAACTCCTGATATATCATTCCCACGAATAAATAATATGAGATTTTGATTACTAATTCCTTCATTATTTTTATTAATTTTTAGAAGATTTATTAATACAGGAGTAGGTACAGGTTGAACAGTTTATCCACCTTTATCATCAAATTTAGGACATAGAGGTATATCAGTTGATTTAGGAATCTTTTCTCTACATTTAGCAGGAGCCTCATCAATTATAGGAGCAATTAATTTTATTACAACAATTAAAAATATACGAGTTAAATTATTAAAAATAGATAAAATTTCTTTATTTACTTGATCAGTTTTAATTACAGCAATTTTATTATTATTATCTTTACCAGTTTTAGCAGGAGCAATTACTATACTTTTAACAGACCGAAATTTAAATACATCATTTTTTGATCCTTCAGGAGGTGGGGATCCAATTTTATACCAACATTTATTT</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles felipei</tp:taxon-name></italic></bold> is dedicated toLuis Felipe Chavarría Díaz of ACG and San Jose, Costa Rica, in recognition of his 30+ years of dedication to Costa Rican conservation, biodiversity systematics, and biodiversity development throughout Costa Rica, and very specifically within Area de Conservación de Guanacaste.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p>The biology of this species, collected with Malaise traps, is unknown. Since its inception in 1978, the ACG caterpillar and parasitoid inventory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Janzen et al. 2009</xref>) has achieved <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> rearings from 9,000+ wild-caught caterpillars and has Malaise-trapped 5,000+ individual <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> in dry forest, cloud forest and rain forest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Janzen and Hallwachs 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Smith et al. 2008</xref>); this intense effort has yielded only two conspecific individuals of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic>, both from the same Malaise trap a few weeks apart. While this may suggest that the species is “rare”, it has been the experience of the ACG inventory that when the wasp is finally reared and therefore its host caterpillar known, or the Malaise trap is placed in the “right” place, it may well be found to be common.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">dapkeyae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:EF2F8657-FEBB-4AEE-8501-06B104771B86</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Mariapanteles_dapkeyae</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Fernández-Triana</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–12</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype">
                    <title>Holotype.</title>
                    <p><bold>Female</bold> (CNC).BRAZIL: Mato Grosso, Sinop; x-xi.1975, Malaise Trap; M. Alvarenga col.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratype">
                    <title>Paratype.</title>
                    <p>5 Females and 4 Males (CNC, with 1 female each deposited in INHS and BMNH). Same data as for holotype, except for collecting date (x.1974 for all specimens but two males with collecting date: x.1975). Two males deposited in the CNC have DNA Voucher codes: CNCHYM 03387 and CNCHYM 07145. 1 Female (CNC). BRAZIL: Goiás, Jatai; xi.1972; F. M. Oliveira col.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Female.</bold> Antenna about the same length as body; body length 2.4 mm; forewing 2.6 mm. Head. Face with shallow and sparse punctures and sparse, uniformly distributed setae. Face width at antennal base/face width at clypeus edge: 1.1×; intertentorial pit distance/face width at clypeus edge: 0.4×; compound eye height/head height: 0.8×; head height/width: 0.8×; face width at antennal base/head maximum width: 0.5×; malar space/basal width of mandible 1.4×; clypeus width/height: 3.5×. Length/width of flagellomeres: 2nd (2.4×), 8th (2.5×), 14th (1.3×). Length of flagellomere 2<sup>nd</sup>/length of flagellomere 14<sup>th</sup>: 2.2×. Ocello-ocular distance/posterior ocelli diameter: 2.2×; distance between posterior ocelli/ocelli diameter: 1.3×.</p>
                    <p>Mesosoma. Pronotum with two lateral grooves present, the lower one excavated. Mesoscutum more or less uniformly sculptured by shallowly impressed punctures (distance between punctures about the same as their diameter). Mesoscutum 1.3× wider than long. Mesoscutum and scutellum uniformly covered by dense, pale yellow pilosity. Scutellum mostly smooth, with very shallow and sparse punctures. Scutellum length/width at base 1.1×. Scutellar suture broad, with 4-6 costulae. Posterior band of scutellum polished. Scutellar lateral face with polished area less than 20% the face height and less than half the face width. Mesopleuron mostly smooth and glabrous, except for punctures on the anterior margin and setae on all margins; separated from metapleuron by crenulate sulcus. Metapleuron mostly smooth, with some punctures and setae in the apical half; metapleuron with a crenulated, longitudinal sulcus running from lower margin near metacoxa through spiracle. Metapleural carina raised with a short lamella. Propodeum mostly smooth; with a median carina well defined and raised its entire length; and with a clearly complete transverse carina that reaches the spiracles and forks around them (there are also additional, shorter transverse carinae). Transverse carina on propodeum delimiting two areas, the anterior, basal one that is more or less horizontal, and the posterior, apical one is declivous.</p>
                    <p>Metasoma. Mediotergite 1 mostly smooth and with a deep medial groove over its basal half; slightly widening for the first quarter of its length, then narrowing t<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->owards apex; basal width/apical width 1.5×; length/apical width 3.3×. Mediotergite 2 mostly smooth, transverse, subtriangular to trapezoidal in shape; basal width/apical width 0.3×; length/apical width 0.4×. Mediotergite 3 1.5× the length of mediotergite 2. Mediotergite 3 and following unsculptured, polished and with sparse setae. Hypopygium mostly inflexible but with a median, translucid fold ventrally where 1–2 weak pleats are sometimes distinguishable. Ovipositor sheaths fully setose, 0.7× as long as metatibia length.</p>
                    <p>Legs. Metacoxa long, surpassing the length of the third metasomal tergum. Metatibial inner spur 1.4× the length of outer spur, and 0.5X the length of metatarsomere 1. Metafemur 3.2× as long as wide.</p>
                    <p>Wings. Vein R1a 1.3× as long as stigma length. Stigma 3.3× as long as wide. Length of R1a about 14× as long as the distance between its end and the end of 3RSb. Vein r and 2RS evenly curved to very slightly arched, with no clear limits between the two veins. Vein 2M about the same length of vein (RS+M)b. Edge of vannal lobe of hind wing medially straight to slightly concave and with uniformly distribute setae which are shorter than those at base and apex of the lobe.</p>
                    <p>Colour: Mostly yellow, with antennal flagellomere, forewing stigma and most of the wing veins, light brown.</p>
                    <p>Male. Mostly like females, but some specimens with darker interocellar area and mediotergites 3+. We associate these males with these females because of their morphological similarity.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 7–12.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles dapkeyae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fernandez-Triana. <bold>7</bold> lateral habitus, female <bold>8</bold> dorsal habitus, female <bold>9</bold> fore wing, female <bold>10</bold> head and mesoscutum, dorsal view, female <bold>11</bold> hypopygium and ovipositor, lateral view <bold>12</bold> metanotum, propodeum and anterior metasomal tergites, female, dorsal view.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-208-061-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>The specimens were collected with Malaise traps in two Brazilian localities (less than 1000 km apart) which are presumed to have been rain forests at the time of collecting.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Molecular data">
                    <title>Molecular data.</title>
                    <p>Two paratype male specimens rendered partial barcodes (361 bp for the one with DNA voucher code CNCHYM 03387, and 164 bp for the one with DNA voucher code CNCHYM 07145). The nucleotide sequence shown below corresponds to the longer sequence in the barcode region of COI:</p>
                    <p>&gt;<italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles dapkeyae</tp:taxon-name></italic></p>
                    <p>TAAGATTTTGATTATTAATTCCATCTTTATTTATATTAATTTTTAGAAGATTTATTAATACAGGAGTAGGTACAGGTTGAACAGTATACCCACCATTATCATCAAATTTAAGACATAGGGGCATATCAGTCGATTTAAGAATTTTTTCTTTACATTTAGCAGGAACTTCATCAATTATAGGAGCAATTAATTTTATTACAACAATTAAAAATATACGAGTTAAATTATTTAAAATAAATAAAATTTCTTTATTTAATTGATCAGTTTTAATTACAGCAATTTTATTATTATTATCATTACCAGTATTAGCAGGTGCTATTACTATACTTTTAACAGATCGAAATTTAAATACATCATTTTT</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>This species is dedicated to Tanya Heckmann Dapkey of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA, in recognition of her seven years of diligent and highly accurate sorting, processing, databasing, and de-legging ACG microgastrine wasps for DNA barcoding.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p>The biology of this species, collected with Malaise traps, is unknown. In the CNC collection there are two additional specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapan<!--PageBreak-->teles</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Brazil: one female from Piedra Azul, Minas Gerais; and one male from Rio Javari, Estirar do Equador, Amazonas. Both specimens differ morphologically from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles dapkeyae</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Additionally, the male specimen (with DNA voucher code CNCHYM 03380) rendered a partial DNA barcode (164bp) which has 7 base pairs<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> different (4.3 %) from the barcoded specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles dapkeyae</tp:taxon-name></italic>. We believe those two specimens may represent additional species, but because they are singletons we have not described them as new species here.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 13.</label>
                        <caption><p>Maximum clade credibility tree for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> based on Bayesian analysis of COI sequences, with 3<sup>rd</sup> codon positions included (see text for details). Values at nodes are posterior probabilities.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-208-061-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 14.</label>
                        <caption><p>Maximum clade credibility tree for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> based on Bayesian analysis of COI sequences, with 3<sup>rd</sup> codon positions excluded (see text for details). Values at nodes are posterior probabilities.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-208-061-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>We emphatically and gratefully acknowledge the support of the ACG parataxonomist team in finding and rearing the caterpillars, their parasitoids and their hyperparasitoids, and Area de Conservacion Guanacaste (ACG) for preserving the forests in which they live, and the Guanacaste Dry Forest Conservation Fund, the Wege Foundation, the International Conservation Fund of Canada, the JRS Biodiversity Foundation, Jessie Hill, and the University of Pennsylvania for funding portions of the research. This study was also supported by NSF DEB 0515699 to DHJ and by a Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) Discovery Grant to MAS. Laboratory analyses of these sequences were funded by the Government of Canada through Genome Canada and the Ontario Genomics Institute (2008-0GI-ICI-03).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> DNA barcodes of closely related (but morphologically and ecologically distinct) species of skipper butterflies (Hesperiidae) can differ by only one to three nucleotides.</article-title> <source>Journal of the Lepidopterists’ Society </source> <volume>61</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>138</fpage>-<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> DNA barcodes and cryptic species of skipper butterflies in the genus <italic>Perichares</italic> in Area de Conservación Guanacaste, Costa Rica.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences </source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>6350</fpage>-<lpage>6355</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0712181105">10.1073/pnas.0712181105</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Campos</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diego</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Lista de los generos de avispas parasitoides Braconidae (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonoidea) de la region neotropical.</article-title> <source>Biota Colombiana </source> <volume>2</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>232</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Deans</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Taxonomy and natural history of the microgastrine genus <italic>Alphomelon</italic> Mason (Hymenoptera: Braconidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of Hymenoptera Research </source> <volume>12</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashton</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buxton</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duran</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heled</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kearse</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markowitz</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moir</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stones-Havas</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturrock</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thierer</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> Geneious v5.5.6, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneious.com/">http://www.geneious.com/</ext-link> ​</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> The systematics and biology of the Costa Rican species of parasitic wasps in the <italic>Thyreodon</italic> genus-group (Hymenoptera: Ichneumonidae).</article-title> <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society </source> <volume>141</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>-<lpage>351</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.2004.00116.x">10.1111/j.1096-3642.2004.00116.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grinter</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield,</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Connahs,</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyer</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> A key to New World <italic>Distatrix</italic> Mason (Hymenoptera: Braconidae), with descriptions of six new reared Neotropical species.</article-title> <source>Journal of Insect Science </source> <volume>9</volume> (<issue>25</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1673/031.009.2901">10.1673/031.009.2901</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanova</surname> <given-names>NV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewaard</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> An inexpensive, automation-friendly protocol for recovering high-quality DNA.</article-title> <source>Molecular Ecology Notes </source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>998</fpage>-<lpage>1002</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1471-8286.2006.01428.x">10.1111/j.1471-8286.2006.01428.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Costa Rica’s Area de Conservación Guanacaste: a long march to survival through non-damaging biodevelopment.</article-title> <source>Biodiversity </source> <volume>1</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/14888386.2000.9712501">10.1080/14888386.2000.9712501</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> Joining inventory by parataxonomists with DNA barcoding of a large complex tropical conserved wildland in northwestern Costa Rica. PLoS ONE 6(8): e18123. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0018123">10.1371/journal.pone.0018123</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> Philosophy, navigation and use of a dynamic database (“ACG Caterpillars SRNP”) for an inventory of the macrocaterpillar fauna, and its food plants and parasitoids, of the Area de Conservacion Guanacaste (ACG), northwestern Costa Rica <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://janzen.sas.upenn.edu">http://janzen.sas.upenn.edu</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blandin</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cadiou</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chacon</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dapkey</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deans</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Espinoza</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franclemont</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haber</surname> <given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname> <given-names>JPW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hausmann</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitching</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafontaine</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landry</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemaire</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montero</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munroe</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rab Green</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnasingham</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rawlins</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robbins</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rougerie</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharkey</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solis</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiaucourt</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weller</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willmott</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodley</surname> <given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Integration of DNA barcoding into an ongoing inventory of complex tropical biodiversity. Molecular Ecology Resources 9 (Supplement 1): 1–26. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-0998.2009.02628.x">10.1111/j.1755-0998.2009.02628.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertrand</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> Reading the complex skipper fauna of one tropical place. PLoS ONE 6(8): e19874. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0019874">10.1371/journal.pone.0019874</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfeiffer</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source> “Creating the CIPRES Science Gateway for inference of large phylogenetic trees” in Proceedings of the Gateway Computing Environments Workshop (GCE), 14 Nov. 2010, New Orleans, LA 1–8.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<source> jModelTest: Phylogenetic model averaging. Molecular Biology and Evolution25: 1253. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msn083">10.1093/molbev/msn083</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaut</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Tracer v1.5, Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer">http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaut</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drummond</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> TreeAnnotator v1.7.0, Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk">http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnasingham</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> BOLD : The Barcode of Life Data System (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.barcodinglife.org">www.barcodinglife.org</ext-link> ).</article-title> <source>Molecular Ecology Notes </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>364</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1471-8286.2007.01678.x">10.1111/j.1471-8286.2007.01678.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronquist</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> MRBAYES 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference under mixed models.</article-title> <source>Bioinformatics </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1572</fpage>-<lpage>1574</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btg180">10.1093/bioinformatics/btg180</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schauff</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Taxonomy and ecology of Costa Rican <italic>Euplectrus</italic> (Hymenoptera: Eulophidae), parasitoids of caterpillars (Lepidoptera).</article-title> <source>Journal of Hymenoptera Research </source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>181</fpage>-<lpage>230</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharkey</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clutts</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dapkey</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> <italic>Lytopylus</italic> Forster (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Agathidinae) species from Costa Rica, with an emphasis on specimens reared from caterpillars in Area de Conservacion Guanacaste.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Shcherbakov</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname> <given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharkey</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title> Advances in the Systematics of Fossil and Modern Insects: Honouring Alexandr Rasnitsyn.</issue-title> <source>ZooKeys </source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.130.1569">10.3897/zookeys.130.1569</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deans</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Extreme diversity of tropical parasitoid wasps exposed by iterative integration of natural history, DNA barcoding, morphology and collections.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the USA</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>12359</fpage>-<lpage>12364</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0805319105">10.1073/pnas.0805319105</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> DNA barcodes affirm that 16 species of apparently generalist tropical parasitoid flies (Diptera, Tachinidae) are not all generalists.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences </source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>4967</fpage>-<lpage>4972</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0700050104">10.1073/pnas.0700050104</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodley</surname> <given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> DNA barcodes reveal cryptic host-specificity within the presumed polyphagous members of a genus of parasitoid flies (Diptera: Tachinidae).</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences </source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>3657</fpage>-<lpage>3662</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0511318103">10.1073/pnas.0511318103</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Valerio</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Review of world <italic>Parapanteles</italic> Ashmead (Hymenoptera: Braconidae: Microgastrinae), with descriptions of fourteen new Neotropical species and the first description of the final instar larvae.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>2084</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arias Penna</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Review of the New World microgastrine braconid wasp genus <italic>Venanus</italic> Mason, with descriptions of three new Neotropical species.</article-title> <source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America </source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>1119</fpage>-<lpage>1127</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1603/AN10048">10.1603/AN10048</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
        </ref-list>
        <app-group>
        <app id="Appendix">
            <title>Appendix 1</title>
            <p>Detailed information about collection, BOLD, and GenBank number of species. (doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.208.3326.app">10.3897/zookeys.208.3326.app</ext-link>) File format: Excel spreadsheet (xls).</p>
            <p><bold>Explanation note:</bold> Appendix I contains all available DNA barcodes for Pseudapanteles (32 New World species, most of which are undescribed) and Mariapanteles (2 species) that were at least 300 bp long were downloaded from BOLD.</p>
        </app>
        </app-group>
    </back>
</article>