<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.236.3434</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Taxonomic revision of 
                    <italic>Bracalba</italic> Dodd (Hymenoptera, Platygastridae s.l.), a parasitoid wasp genus endemic to Australia
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Burks</surname>
                        <given-names>Roger A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:F792CF45-EB70-458B-85B8-D1AF8A30936F</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Masner</surname>
                        <given-names>Lubomír</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:FA505310-F606-4F6C-A1DF-74B9A0055B2E</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Johnson</surname>
                        <given-names>Norman F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:3508C4FF-F027-445F-8417-90AB4AB8FE0D</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Austin</surname>
                        <given-names>Andrew D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:DE71F924-750D-490D-84A7-F5960066F7CC</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Evolution, Ecology, and Organismal Biology, The Ohio State University, 1315 Kinnear Road, Columbus, OH 43212, U.S.A.
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada, K.W. Neatby Building, Ottawa, ON K1A 0C6, Canada
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Australian Centre for Evolutionary Biology and Biodiversity, School of Earth and Environmental Sciences, The University of Adelaide, SA 5005, Australia
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Roger A. Burks (<email xlink:type="simple">burks.roger@gmail.com</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: M. Buffington</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>2</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>236</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>53</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>29</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>9</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Roger A. Burks, Lubomír Masner, Norman F. Johnson, Andrew D. Austin</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:724528A4-B2C4-4FDB-8702-2734A4DDDC5B</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The endemic Australian parasitic wasp genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Platygastridae</tp:taxon-name>) is revised. Sixteen species are recognized: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba cuneata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dodd, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba laminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dodd and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba nigrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Dodd) are redescribed and thirteen new species are recognized; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba clavata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba globosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba hesperia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba intermedia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba magnirubra</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba parvirubra</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba pinnula</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba plana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba propodealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba sculptifrons</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba sparsa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba tricorata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba tridentata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, <bold>sp. n.</bold> The genus is found continent-wide but mostly south of the Tropic of Capricorn, and with the highest species diversity occurring in the Pilbara and south-western regions of Western Australia. The hosts of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> are unknown but specimens reared from eggs confirm that the genus is associated with orthopteran hosts. A preliminary phylogeny of species did not indicate that species groups were monophyletic, but they are retained despite paraphyly because they are convenient for specimen identification.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Platygastroidea</kwd>
                <kwd>Platygastridae s.l.</kwd>
                <kwd>Scelionidae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Bracalba</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>Scelioninae</kwd>
                <kwd>key</kwd>
                <kwd>revision</kwd>
                <kwd>database</kwd>
                <kwd>endemism</kwd>
                <kwd>parasitoid</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The <tp:taxon-name>Platygastroidea</tp:taxon-name> are a highly diverse component of the Australian parasitoid wasp fauna with 666 described species in 80 genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">ABRS 2012</xref>). However, like most parasitoid families, the real species richness of the group is very much larger than this. The scope of this disparity was recently indicated in a revision of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Idris (Ceratobaeus)</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Iqbal and Austin 2000</xref>) that resulted in an initial four-fold increase in species to 130+ taxa, and this increase appears to generally hold true for revisions of other platygastroid genera.</p>
            <p>The first Australian scelionids were described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Walker (1839)</xref> from material collected by Charles Darwin along the east coast of the continent. However, the majority of Australian species (63%) were described by A.P. Dodd between 1913 and 1939 and, testament to his taxonomic abilities, virtually all of his species remain valid, although many have been transferred to other genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Johnson 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">ABRS 2012</xref>). Other than the taxonomic treatment of a number of small genera by various authors, the most influential post-Dodd studies on the Australian fauna have been the revision of the telenomine genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psix</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Johnson and Masner 1985</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trissolcus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Johnson 1991</xref>), the spider-associated genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baeus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Stevens and Austin 2007</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Idris (Ceratobaeus)</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Iqbal and Austin 2000</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mirobaeoides</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Austin 1986</xref>), the acridid egg parasitoid genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Scelio</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Dangerfield et al. 2001</xref>), and the generic overview provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Galloway and Austin (1984)</xref>. Platygastroids are mostly endoparasitoids of insect and spider eggs, including all taxa previously accommodated in the family <tp:taxon-name>Scelionidae</tp:taxon-name>, while many platygastrids (<italic>s.str</italic>.) oviposit either in the egg or early larva of gall midges (<tp:taxon-name>Cecidomyiidae</tp:taxon-name>) and complete their development in the larvae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Austin and Field 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Austin et al. 2005</xref>).</p>
            <p>The current study focuses on one of the few genera, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dodd, that is endemic to the Australian continent. Among other characters, the genus is recognised by its stout, sculptured body, obviously setose eyes, face with pronounced frontal depression, and very long fore wing postmarginal vein (R1). Previously known from only three species, two from south-eastern Queensland and one from south-western Western Australia, this revision treats 16 species in total. In addition, we document the distribution of all species, present a key to their identification, and undertake a preliminary analysis of species-level relationships.</p>
            <p>The contributions of the individual authors are as follows; R.A. Burks: character definition, species concept development; key development, imaging, capture of specimen data, manuscript preparation, phylogenetic analysis and illustration; L. Masner: specimen acquisition, and generic overview; N.F. Johnson: generic concept development and manuscript preparation ; A.D. Austin: initial species concept development, manuscript preparation, and taxonomic overview.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods">
            <title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>Specimens examined were provided by the following collections: The American Entomological Institute, Gainesville, Florida, USA (AEIC)<sup>1</sup>; Australian Museum, Sydney, Australia (AMSA)<sup>2</sup>; Australian National Insect Collection, Canberra, Australia (ANIC)<sup>3</sup>; The Natural History Museum, London, United Kingdom (BMNH)<sup>4</sup>; Canadian National Collection of Insects, Arachnids and Nematodes, Ottawa, Canada (CNCI)<sup>5</sup>; Museum of Victoria, Entomology, Melbourne, Australia (MVMA)<sup>6</sup>; Museum of Comparative Zoology, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA (MCZC)<sup>7</sup>; C.A. Triplehorn Insect Collection, Ohio State University, Columbus, Ohio (OSUC)<sup>8</sup>; Queensland Primary Industries and Fisheries Insect Collection, Indooroopilly, Australia (QDPC)<sup>9</sup>; Queensland Museum, Brisbane, Australia (QMBA)<sup>10</sup>; R.M. Bohart Museum, University of California, Davis, USA (UCDC)<sup>12</sup>; Western Australian Museum, Perth, Australia (WAMP)<sup>13</sup>; Waite Insect and Nematode Collection, Adelaide, Australia (WINC)<sup>14</sup>. South Australian and Northern Territory holotypes for species newly described in this manuscript are deposited in the South Australian Museum, Adelaide, Australia (SAMA)<sup>11</sup>.</p>
            <p>This revision is a product of the <tp:taxon-name>Platygastroidea</tp:taxon-name> Planetary Biodiversity Inventory, funded by the U.S. National Science Foundation (N.F. Johnson, Ohio State University; A.D. Austin, University of Adelaide; Principal Investigators). One objective of this project is to use biodiversity informatics resources to accelerate taxonomic processes, making real-time collaboration possible within a community of researchers. Data associated with specimens examined in this study can be accessed at hol.osu.edu and by entering the unique specimen identifier (e.g. OSUC 238448) in the search form. Morphological terminology follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Mikó et al. (2007)</xref>, except for: 1) antennal features discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bin (1981)</xref>, 2) anteclypeus and postclypeus used sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Dangerfield et al. (2001)</xref>, 3) dorsal epomial carina and vertical epomial carina, which are mentioned by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Masner and Johnson (2007)</xref> and defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Talamas et al. (2011)</xref>, 4) a newly coined “metasomal bend,” which is a ventrad bend occurring near the midlength of the 4th metasomal segment, and 5) ovipositor features described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Austin and Field (1997)</xref>. Surface sculptural terms are used in part based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Eady (1968)</xref>, with general terms added for descriptive purposes: “mesh” to define a polygonal, ovate or circular area enclosed by raised or sunken borders; “septa” to define distinctive borders that enclose meshes; and “interspaces” to define areas separating individual sculptural features. Note that sculptural septa can be differentiated, as in the longitudinal septa being much stronger than the transverse septa. They are also repeated corresponding to the number of sculptural meshes present. The aforementioned terminology is used instead of calling all raised sculpture “carinae,” which would remove all recognizable meaning from the word. Instead, “carina” is used for a raised sculptural element that does not correspond to repeated enclosed meshes. Life science identifiers (LSIDs) can be resolved at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org">http://lsid.tdwg.org</ext-link>  (i.e. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zoobank.org/?lsid=urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E5095F58-4603-4796-9D22-03A759">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E5095F58-4603-4796-9D22-03A759B7B29</ext-link>).</p>
            <p><!--PageBreak--><bold>Illustration and data citations.</bold> Photographs were taken using a Visionary Digital BK+ Imaging System, November 2010 model, with either a K2 Long Distance Microscope or a 65 mm varifocal lens. Source photos were stacked using Zerene Stacker version 1.04 and enhanced using Adobe Photoshop CS5.</p>
            <p><bold>Phylogenetic analysis.</bold> An exact search using implicit enumeration (branch-and-bound) was performed using TNT (Tree analysis using New Technology) version 1.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Goloboff et al. 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">2008</xref>). Bootstrapping was performed with 1,000 replicates using New Technology searches at an initial level of 95. The outgroup specimens coded in this analysis were from an undescribed species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chromoteleia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ashmead from Belize, (OSUC 064028, OSUC 064021), chosen because of the overall morphological similarity between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chromoteleia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic>. A total of 42 characters were used, of which 38 were parsimony informative (see Appendix II for characters and matrix).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E5095F58-4603-4796-9D22-03A759B7B29</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:457</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Dodd</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Dodd 1931</xref>: 78 (original description. Type: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba laminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dodd, by original designation); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Muesebeck and Walkley 1956</xref>: 336 (citation of type species); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Masner 1976</xref>: 22, 23 (description, key to separate <italic><tp:taxon-name>Baryconus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Förster, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dodd, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chromoteleia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ashmead, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyscelio</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kieffer); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Galloway and Austin 1984</xref>: 8, 13 (diagnosis, list of species described from Australia, keyed); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Johnson 1992</xref>: 354 (catalog of world species); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Austin and Field 1997</xref>: 18, 68 (structure of ovipositor system, discussion of phylogenetic relationships, genus misplaced in <tp:taxon-name>Baryconini</tp:taxon-name>).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Eye setose; frontal depression present; antenna 12-segmented; netrion present; postmarginal vein of fore wing present, longer than marginal and stigmal veins; mesotibia and metatibia each with 1 spur; metascutellum setose dorsally and ventrally; ovipositor <italic><tp:taxon-name>Scelio</tp:taxon-name></italic>-type.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body length: 2.75–6.88 mm (n=78).</p>
                    <p><bold>Head</bold>. Head shape in dorsal view: transverse. Hyperoccipital carina: absent. Occipital carina: present laterally, broadly interrupted medially; present, complete medially. Occipital carina sculpture: crenulate. OOL: lateral ocellus nearly contiguous with inner orbits, OOL &lt; 0.5 OD. Upper frons: convex, without frontal shelf. Scrobe shape: frons with shallow unmargined depression above antennal foramina. Frons sculpture: areolate rugose, transversely striate within scrobe; areolate rugose,<!--PageBreak--> scrobe sparsely punctate. Submedian carina: absent. Orbital carina: absent. Inner orbits: diverging ventrally. IOS/EH: IOS slightly less than EH. Interantennal process: triangular in lateral view, well-developed. Central keel: absent. Antennal foramen opening: nearly anteriorly. Lower frons striae: absent. Malar sulcus: present. Compound eye size: of normal proportions, not significantly reduced. Compound eye setation: densely setose; sparsely setose. Gena: narrow, weakly convex, receding behind posterior orbit. Clypeus shape: transversely rectangular. Apical margin of clypeus: rounded; with a small median point. Anteclypeus: absent. Postclypeus: absent. Labrum: not visible. Mandible shape: moderate. Mandibular teeth: apex with 2, acute, subequal teeth; apex tridentate, teeth acute, middle tooth distinctly shortest. Arrangement of mandibular teeth: transverse. Number of maxillary palpomeres: 4. Shape of maxillary palpomeres: cylindrical. Number of labial palpomeres: 2.</p>
                    <p><bold>Antenna</bold>. Number of antennomeres in female: 12. Number of antennomeres in male: 12. Insertion of radicle into A1: parallel to longitudinal axis of A1. Shape of A1: more or less cylindrical, not flattened. Length of A3 of female: distinctly longer than A2. Number of clavomeres in female antenna: 8. Claval formula of female antenna: A12-A7/1-2-2-2-2-2; A12-A6/1-2-2-2-2-2-2; A12-A6/1-2-2-2-2-2-1. Arrangement of doubled multiporous plate sensilla on female clava: in longitudinal pairs. Tyloid distribution on male antenna: A5 only. Shape of male flagellum: filiform.</p>
                    <p><bold>Mesosoma</bold>. Mesosoma shape in dorsal view: longer than wide. Mesosoma shape in lateral view: longer than high. Medial portion of transverse pronotal carina: absent. Posterior apex of pronotum in dorsal view: straight, bifid apically to articulate with tegula. Vertical epomial carina: absent. Dorsal epomial carina (lateral portion of transverse pronotal carina of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Vilhelmsen et al. (2010)</xref>): absent. Central pronotal area: vertical, not visible in dorsal view. Lateral face of pronotum: weakly concave below position of dorsal epomial carina. Netrion: present. Netrion shape: moderately wide, closed ventrally. Anterior portion of mesoscutum: vertical, flexed ventrally to meet pronotum. Mesoscutum shape: pentagonal in outline, posterolateral corner rounded. Skaphion: absent. Notauli: present, percurrent. Parapsidal lines: absent. Admedial lines: absent. Transscutal articulation: well-developed, crenulate. Shape of mesoscutellum: quadrate to trapezoidal. Armature of mesoscutellum: absent. Surface of mesoscutellum: convex throughout. Median longitudinal furrow on mesoscutellum: absent; present. Shape of axillula: small, dorsal margin sinuate. Metascutellum in dorsal view: clearly differentiated. Metascutellar armature: produced into flattened plate. Metascutellar setation: setose dorsally and ventrally. Metapostnotum: not defined externally. Extent of metasomal depression of propodeum: percurrent, extending anteriorly to anterior margin of propodeum. Lateral propodeal projection: well-developed, extending clearly beyond anterior margin of T1. Mesopleural carina: absent or strongly abbreviated, present only near mid coxa. Mesal course of acetabular carina: projecting anteriorly, but too short to intercede between fore coxae. Mesopleural pit: absent. Sternaulus: absent. Posterodorsal corner of mesopleuron: rounded anteriorly.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak--><bold>Legs</bold>. Number of mid tibial spurs: 1. Number of hind tibial spurs: 1. Dorsal surface of hind coxa: smooth. Hind tibia shape: cylindrical, ecarinate. Trochantellus: indicated by transverse sulcus on femur.</p>
                    <p><bold>Wings</bold>. Wing development of female: macropterous. Wing development of male: macropterous. Tubular veins in fore wing: present. Bulla of fore wing R: absent. Extent of marginal venation of fore wing: distinct marginal or postmarginal veins developed. Origin of r-rs in fore wing: arising at junction of R/R1 with costal margin. Development of basal vein (Rs+M) in fore wing: nebulous, weakly pigmented. Development of R in hind wing: elongate, extending to costal margin.</p>
                    <p><bold>Metasoma</bold>. Number of external terga in female: 6. Number of external sterna in female: 6. Number of external terga in male: 8. Number of external sterna in male: 7. Shape of metasoma: acuminate, widest submedially. Laterotergites: present, narrow. Laterosternites: present. T1 of female: raised medially into low, rectangular or subelliptical platform, laterally depressed. Relative size of metasomal terga: T2–T4 largest, subequal in size. Terga with basal crenulae: T1–T4. Sublateral carinae on terga: absent. Median longitudinal carina on metasomal terga: absent; present. Distribution of felt fields: absent. Ovipositor type: Scelio-type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Austin and Field 1997</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Dodd did not specify the source of the name for this genus, but presumably it is derived the name of the Queensland town of Bracalba. (Dodd also used the names of Merriwa, NSW and Nyleta, QLD for other genera.) He originally combined this name with two species epithets of variable gender, both coined in feminine form: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba cuneata</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba laminata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, clearly indicating that he intended <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> to be a feminine noun.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been collected only from Australia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), and has seldom been collected north of the Tropic of Capricorn. The furthest north that any <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been collected was at 24°39'S, and only two species have been found north of Alice Springs, NT. Location records show that the highest species diversity occurs in the Pilbara and south-western regions of Western Australia.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p>Collection events for each <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. * = species known from only one locality.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology">
                    <title>Biology.</title>
                    <p>The hosts of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> are unknown but the structure of the ovipositor (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Scelio</tp:taxon-name></italic>-type; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Austin and Field 1997</xref>) and specimens reared from eggs confirm that the genus is associated with orthopteran hosts. These eggs could not be identified beyond the ordinal level.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Relationships among species">
                    <title>Relationships among species.</title>
                    <p>The implicit enumeration search found two optimum trees of 166 steps (strict consensus: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> was monophyletic with respect to the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chromoteleia</tp:taxon-name></italic> outgroup (bootstrap = 100). Intuitively-based species groups were not monophyletic in the analysis, but this was likely due to homoplasy resulting from inclusion of many sculptural and coloration characters that have mainly descriptive value. Species with a bend at metasomal segment 4 in females did not form a monophyletic group, but this was complicated by the smooth transition in this character from being distinctively present to clearly absent. One feature that was helpful in determining species group, but which was not reported in the key because it was too difficult to accurately and consistently assess, was the lateral margin of the dorsal axillar area. In the <italic>cuneata</italic>-group, the dorsal axillar area was essentially triangular, broadening posteriorly,<!--PageBreak--> with the lateral margin sometimes forming a posterior tooth. In the <italic>laminata</italic>-group the dorsal axillar area was generally more nearly semicircular, broadest at midlength, and with the lateral margin not forming a posterior tooth. Apparent variation, and difficultly in observing this character with confidence, caused us to omit it from the key.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p>Strict consensus phylogram of two most parsimonious trees for species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> using implicit enumeration (branch-and-bound exact search), score = 166. Bootstrap support values found using TNT new technology search (set initial level = 95). Bremer support values above 1, and bootstrap values about 50% indicated on branches.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to species of Bracalba">
                    <title>Key to species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic></title>
                    <p><bold>Note:</bold> It is imperative to consult figures when using the below key, as shape features of the metascutellum and metasoma are very important in identifying <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> species with any hope of accuracy.</p>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibles bidentate with no hint of a third tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 11</xref>), teeth narrowly separated and of nearly the same length. Females: T4 without bend or hump (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">, 7</xref>); fore wings extending to middle of T5 or beyond when folded over body</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (<italic>cuneata</italic>-group)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandibles either tridentate with a small middle tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 40</xref>) or very rarely bidentate, but with teeth broadly separated and/or dorsal tooth much longer than ventral tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 52</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">, 58</xref>). Females: T4 with or without bend or hump (bend: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 33</xref>, hump: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 56</xref>); fore wings extending only to middle or apex of T4 when folded over body</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (<italic>laminata</italic>-group)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><!--PageBreak-->2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metascutellum flat (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 12–13</xref>), not projecting dorsally. Male: A3 short: 1.1–1.2× as long as broad (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 13</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba plana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metascutellum projecting dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">, 7</xref>). Male: A3 over 1.5× as long as broad</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesoscutellum sparsely foveolate, with smooth interspaces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 8</xref>). Mesoscutum smoothly and regularly convex anteriorly and posteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 7–8</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba globosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks,sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mesoscutellum densely foveolate, interspaces with irregular longitudinal rugae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Mesoscutum abruptly convex only anteriorly, flattened or irregularly convex posteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3–4</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba cuneata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dodd</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propodeum with sharp protrusions (from lateral propodeal area) protruding dorsally immediately posterior to metascutellum, reaching at least the same height as the dorsal surface of metascutellum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figs 47–48</xref>). Males unknown</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba propodealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks,sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propodeum without such protrusions</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metascutellum strongly narrowed apically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 28</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">, 32</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">, 36</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">, 40</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">, 55</xref>), tapering to an incised or narrowly truncate apex that is narrower than the maximum metascutellar length; metasomal bend or hump present in females (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 33</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">56</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metascutellum with apex broadly truncate, as broad or broader than total metascutellar length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 14</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">, 19</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 24</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">, 43</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">, 47</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">, 60</xref>); metasomal bend present or absent in females</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesosoma truncate anteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 28</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">, 32</xref>), with antero-lateral pronotal corners protruding anteriorly. Metascutellum incised apically</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesosoma smoothly rounded anteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 36</xref>), with antero-lateral pronotal corners much weaker, more rounded, and not protruding anteriorly. Metascutellar apex variable</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesoscutellum without median carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 32</xref>). Females with a mostly reddish metasoma and very large body (at least 6.5 mm long)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba magnirubra</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks,sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesoscutellum with median carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 28</xref>). Color of metasoma in females unknown. Female body length 4.25 mm [using <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Dodd’s (1930)</xref> description, which is probably an underestimate]</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba laminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dodd</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennal scrobes crossed by transverse carinae that meet at torular triangle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 38</xref>). Females unknown</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba nigrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Dodd)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Antennal scrobes foveolate or smooth. Females with hump near midlength T4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 41</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">, 56</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennal scrobes smooth and distinct. Clypeus with blunt median carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 42</xref>). Female: S6 without apical incision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 42</xref>); T5, S5 with many strong longitudinal carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 40, 42</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba parvirubra</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks,sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Antennal scrobes foveolate and indistinct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 57</xref>). Clypeus without median carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 58</xref>). Female: S6 with strong apical incision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 59</xref>); T5, S5 with at most a median carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 55, 59</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba sparsa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks,sp. n.<!--PageBreak--></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frontal depression with strong longitudinal carina that is crossed by a strong transverse carina dorsally. Clypeus with median carina and transverse dorsal carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 53</xref>). Metascutellum broadly trapezoidal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 51</xref>). Females: metasoma reddish, T5 and S5 with many longitudinal carinae, S6 without apical notch (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 54</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba sculptifrons</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Frontal depression without such a set of carinae. Clypeus with weaker or no carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 20</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">, 45</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">, 64</xref>). Metascutellum variable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 19</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">, 62</xref>). Females: metasoma brown to black, T5, S5, and S6 variable</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metascutellum elongate-trapezoidal with concave lateral margins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 62</xref>). Female: S6 with strong apical notch (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 65</xref>); T5, S5 with distinct longitudinal carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 62, 65</xref>). Males unknown</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba tridentata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Metascutellum broadly trapezoidal with straight lateral margins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 19</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">, 43</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">, 60</xref>), or subrectangular to weakly convex with irregular lateral margins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 14</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 24</xref>). Female: S6 without apical notch (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 17</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">, 23</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">, 46</xref>); T5, S5 variable</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesoscutellum with a set of incomplete median longitudinal grooves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 19</xref>). Middle mandibular tooth almost as long as the other two (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 20</xref>). Clypeus with weak median carina. Female: S5 with longitudinal carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 23</xref>). Males unknown</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba hesperia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks ,sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mesoscutellum without median grooves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 43</xref>). Middle mandibular tooth tiny, much smaller than the other two (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 16</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 26</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">, 45</xref>). Clypeus without median carina. Female: S5 with or without carinae</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesoscutellum sparsely foveolate, with broad interspaces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 60</xref>). Female: S5 with longitudinal carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 61</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba tricorata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mesoscutellum densely foveolate (interspaces very narrow) except sometimes a small smooth antero-median area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 14</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 24</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">, 43</xref>). Female: S5 finely foveolate, without longitudinal carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 17</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">, 46</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metascutellum trapezoidal in dorsal view, with straight lateral margins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 43</xref>). Female: Antenna with seven apical segments bearing large ventral sensilla, forming a more or less distinct 7-segmented club that includes A6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba pinnula</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metascutellum in dorsal view irregularly subrectangular or cushion-like, with irregular margins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 14</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">, 24</xref>). Female: Antenna with large ventral sensilla on only the six apical segments, these expanded into a 6-segmented club that is distinct from A6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 14–15</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesoscutellum with fine wrinkles or carinae in interspaces between foveolae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 14</xref>). Female: T6 broader than long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 14</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba clavata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mesoscutellum with smooth interspaces between foveolae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 24</xref>); occasionally smaller foveolae may be present in the interspaces, or the interspaces themselves could be raised to form large wrinkles. Female: T6 longer than broad (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 24</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba intermedia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Burks, sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <sec sec-type="Bracalba cuneata Species Group">
                <title><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba cuneata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Species Group</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">cuneata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:10EC007E-A303-4847-BDD9-29AF68935211</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:4126</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_cuneata</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Dodd</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3–6</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>15</sup></xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba cuneata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Dodd 1931</xref>: 80 (original description); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Galloway 1976</xref>: 87 (type information); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Galloway and Austin 1984</xref>: 99 (figure of antenna); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Johnson 1992</xref>: 354 (catalogued).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 3.25–4.00 mm (n=29). Color of antenna beyond radicle: yellowish-brown. Radicle color: same as scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 2.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: short and dense. Frontal depression: smooth dorsally, ventrally with longitudinal carina and with additional carinae arising from medial margins of antennal foramina. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: but without other sculpture. Clypeal median carina: absent. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular teeth: two, separated by narrow incision. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: reticulate-rugose with strong dorsoventral carinae. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: truncate anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: foveolate with broad longitudinal septa. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: triangularly expanded or with posterior tooth, broadest posteriorly. Mesoscutellar sculpture: densely foveolate. Metascutellum in dorsal view: trapezoidal with broad apex. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: apex protruding dorsally. Femoral depression: crossed by rounded carinae. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly. Leg color: yellowish-brown except for dorsal external part of coxae and sometimes tarsomeres 2-5.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: black to dark reddish brown. Median lobe of T1: with 7 or more longitudinal carinae, or with median smooth area interrupting carinae. Metasoma at middle of T4: without bend. T5 median carina: absent. Longitudinal sculptural septa <!--PageBreak-->on T5: weak, blunt and hardly raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. T6: as broad or broader than long. T6 laterotergite: overlapping S6. S4 median carina: absent. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: absent. Apex of S6: without notch.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. Body length 3.12–3.80 mm (n=15). Flagellomere length: A3 over 1.5× as long as broad, most others as long or longer than broad. T7: flat and posteriorly truncate.</p>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 3–6.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba cuneata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dodd, holotype female (QMBA HY4733). <bold>3</bold> Dorsal habitus <bold>4</bold> Lateral habitus, female (OSUC 238135) <bold>5</bold> Head, anterior view <bold>6</bold> Metasomal sterna 5–6, ventral view. Morphbank<sup>15</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 with 2 large ventral sensilla; 2 mandibular teeth; anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area truncate anteriorly; metascutellum trapezoidal in dorsal view, with a broad apex, protruding dorsally; metasomal bend absent; T4–T6 without median carina, S4–S6 without median carina; T6 broader than long; S6 without apical notch.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=4126">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=4126</ext-link> </p>
                        <p><bold>Associations</bold>. Collected near flowering <italic><tp:taxon-name>Scaevola spinescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> R. Br.: [<tp:taxon-name>Asterales</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Goodeniaceae</tp:taxon-name>]</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: QLD, Chinchilla, 8.II.1928, A. P. Dodd, QMBA HY4733 (deposited in QMBA). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 2 females, OSUC 238448-238449 (ANIC). Other material: AUSTRALIA: 32 females, 20 males, OSUC 238516 (BMNH); OSUC 238120, 238123-238128, 238130-238153, 238159-238166, 238171-238173, 238176, 238180-238181, 238188, 238201-238202 (CNCI); OSUC 376915 (MCZC); OSUC 238451, QM Reg. No. T35161 (QDPC); OSUC 231779 (WINC).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                        <title>Comments.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba cuneata</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the most commonly collected species of its genus. Our concept of this speciesincludes some slight variation in metascutellar length and pronotal sculpture. This variation included many intermediates and did not correlate with other characters or with collection locality.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">globosa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:68361C59-4610-4DD5-94CB-0BEB86CA2BB1</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302153</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_globosa</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 7–11</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>16</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 3.12–3.25 mm (n=2). Color of antenna beyond radicle: entirely dark. Radicle color: lighter than scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 2.</p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: short and dense. Frontal depression: smooth dorsally, torular triangle foveolate with 1 transverse carina extending laterally from inner margin of antennal foramen. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: but without other sculpture. Clypeal median carina: absent. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular color: dark basally<!--PageBreak--> and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas. Mandibular teeth: two, separated by narrow incision. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: reticulate-rugose without any strong carinae.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: weakly rounded anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: foveolate with slightly stronger longitudinal septa. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: triangularly expanded or with posterior tooth, broadest posteriorly. Mesoscutellar sculpture: densely foveolate with slightly stronger longitudinal septa. Metas<!--PageBreak-->cutellum in dorsal view: trapezoidal with broad apex. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: apex protruding dorsally. Femoral depression: crossed by rounded carinae. Leg color: dark except for tibiae, 2nd trochanter, and tarsomeres 2-5. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: black to dark reddish brown. Median lobe of T1: with a set of rugae that merge with one another. Metasoma at middle of T4: without bend. Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: without protrusions. T5 median carina: absent. Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5: weak, blunt and hardly raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. T6: as broad or broader than long. T6 laterotergite: overlapping S6. S4 median carina: absent. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: absent. Apex of S6: without notch.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. Body length 2.88 mm (n=1). Flagellomere length: A3 over 1.5× as long as broad, most others as long or longer than broad. T7: flat and posteriorly truncate.</p>
                        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 7–11.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba globosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,paratype female (OSUC 148612). <bold>7</bold> Lateral habitus <bold>8</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view <bold>9</bold> Metasomal sterna 5–6, ventral view <bold>11</bold> Head, ventral view, holotype female (OSUC 148701) <bold>10</bold> Head, anterior view. Morphbank<sup>16</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 with 2 large ventral sensilla; 2 mandibular teeth; anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area weakly rounded anteriorly; metascutellum trapezoidal with a broad apex, extending dorsally; metasomal bend absent; T4–T6 without median carina, S4–S6 without median carina; T6 broader than long; S6 without apical notch. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba globosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> is very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba cuneata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but differs mainly in mesosomal shape and sculpture. The metascutellum also differs subtly between most specimens of the two species, being smaller in most <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba globosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba plana</tp:taxon-name></italic> is also very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba globosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but has a very different mesosomal shape.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Latin adjective, named after the convex mesoscutum of most specimens in this species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302153">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302153</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: WA, Kalbarri National Park, 12.XII-19.XII.1986, malaise trap/pan trap, J. S. Noyes, OSUC 148701 (deposited in WAMP). Paratype: AUSTRALIA: 1 female, OSUC 148612 (CNCI).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">plana</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:DF77087E-2227-4528-854C-9EE7F7BC7AF1</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302159</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_plana</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figures 12–13</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>17</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 2.75–3.13 mm (n=3). Color of antenna beyond radicle: mostly dark, ventral parts of pedicel apex, A4-A12 variably lighter. Radicle color: lighter than scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 2.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: short and dense. Frontal depression: with many irregularly transverse rugae. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: absent between antennal foramina. Clypeal median carina: absent. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas. Mandibular teeth: two, separated by narrow incision. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: deeply reticulate-rugose with some septa much stronger than others, forming distinct rows differing in height.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: weakly rounded anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: densely foveolate. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: triangularly expanded or with posterior tooth, broadest posteriorly. Mesoscutellar sculpture: sparsely foveolate, with large smooth interspaces. Metascutellum in dorsal view: semicircular. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: flat. Femoral depression: centrally smooth, peripherally foveolate. Leg color: coxae dark, leg becoming gradually lighter apically. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: black to dark reddish brown. Median lobe of T1: with 7 or more longitudinal carinae. Metasoma at middle of T4: without bend. Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: without protrusions. T5 median carina: absent. Longitudinal sculp<!--PageBreak-->tural septa on T5: weak, blunt and hardly raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. T6: as broad or broader than long. T6 laterotergite: overlapped by rim from S6. S4 median carina: absent. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: absent. Apex of S6: without notch.</p>
                        <p><italic>Males</italic>. Body length 2.75–3.00 mm (n=2). Flagellomere length: A3 1–1.2× as long as broad, most others transverse. T7: flat and posteriorly truncate.</p>
                        <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 12–13.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba plana</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,holotype female (OSUC 230804). <bold>12</bold> Dorsal habitus, paratype male (OSUC 148706) <bold>13</bold> Dorsal habitus. Morphbank<sup>17</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 with 2 large ventral sensilla; 2 mandibular teeth; anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area weakly rounded anteriorly; metascutellum trapezoidal with a broad apex, flat dorsally; metasomal bend absent; T4–T6 without median carina, S4–S6 without median carina; T6 broader than long; S6 without apical notch. This species is very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba globosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but differs mainly in having a shorter, more flat metascutellum and shorter flagellomeres in males.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Latin adjective, referring to the flat mesoscutum, mesoscutellum, and metascutellum of most specimens of this species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302159">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302159</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: NT, Centre for Zone Research (CSIRO), Alice Springs, XI-1992, malaise trap, Austin &amp; Dangerfield, OSUC 230804 (deposited in SAMA). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 5 females, 3 males, OSUC 148706, 238115, 238168, 238170 (CNCI); OSUC 230802-230803, 230805-230806 (WINC).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                        <title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>Most specimens have a flat mesoscutum and mesoscutellum, but these features were not constant within this species nor in others of the genus.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Bracalba laminata species group">
                <title><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba laminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> species group</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">clavata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C75BF55D-ADB0-417C-8AF3-EE4E46370C15</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302166</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_clavata</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 14–18</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>18</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 3.25–3.38 mm (n=2). Color of antenna beyond radicle: mostly dark, ventral parts of pedicel apex, A4-A12 variably lighter. Radicle color: base lighter than scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 6. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 0.</p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: short and dense. Frontal depression: with many irregularly transverse rugae, or smooth dorsally, ventrally with oblique carinae converging on a longitudinal ruga. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: forming a complete connection between antennal foramina medially. Clypeal median carina: absent. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown<!--PageBreak--> between these areas. Mandibular teeth: three, but middle tooth tiny. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: deeply reticulate-rugose with some septa much stronger than others, forming distinct rows differing in height.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: weakly rounded anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: foveolate with broad longitudinal septa. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: triangularly expanded or with posterior tooth, broadest posteriorly. Mesoscutellar sculpture: densely foveolate but with smooth central area. Metascutellum in dorsal <!--PageBreak-->view: strongly transverse, subrectangular. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: flat, or convex. Femoral depression: centrally smooth, peripherally foveolate. Leg color: coxae, femora (aside from their apices), and at least the last two tarsomeres dark, otherwise yellowish brown. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: not protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: black to dark reddish brown. Median lobe of T1: with 7 or more longitudinal carinae. Metasoma at middle of T4: with very weak bend. Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: with tooth-like protrusions. T5 median carina: absent. Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5: strong, sharply raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. T6: as broad or broader than long. T6 laterotergite: overlapping S6. S4 median carina: present. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: absent. Apex of S6: without notch.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. Body length 2.75–3.25 mm (n=5). Flagellomere length: A3 over 1.5× as long as broad, most others as long or longer than broad. T7: flat and posteriorly truncate.</p>
                        <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 14–18.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba clavata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,holotype female (OSUC 384555). <bold>14</bold> Dorsal habitus <bold>15</bold> Lateral habitus, paratype female (OSUC 384558) <bold>16</bold> Head, ventral view, paratype female (OSUC 384559) <bold>17 </bold>Metasomal sterna 5–6, ventral view, paratype male (OSUC 384556) <bold>18</bold> Dorsal habitus. Morphbank<sup>18</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 without large ventral sensilla, separate and much smaller than A7 (therefore only 6 distinct claval segments present); 3 mandibular teeth with the middle tooth much smaller than the others; metascutellum subrectangular and very short; metasomal bend present but very weak; sculpture posterior to metasomal bend with longitudinal and transverse septa of about equal strength and hardly different from those anterior to the bend; T4–T6 without longitudinal carina; S4–S6 with longitudinal carina; T6 about as long as broad; S6 without apical notch. This species is very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba pinnula</tp:taxon-name></italic> and to some species without a T4 bend. It differs in the unusual antenna, short metascutellum, and in its shorter wings that reach only to the middle of T4.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Latin adjective meaning “clavate,” named for the clavate antenna with its distinct separation between the 6-segmented club and the basal flagellomeres.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302166">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302166</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: SA, Brookfield Conservation Park, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°21'S, 139°29'E</named-content>, 24.XI–26.XI.1992, yellow pan trap, I. Naumann &amp; J. C. Cardale, OSUC 384555 (deposited in ANIC). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 2 females, 6 males, OSUC 230820, 367520, 384556, 384558-384559, 384564-384566 (ANIC).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">hesperia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:1D575B7A-FD40-4392-B7A5-B0EF403B0168</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302154</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_hesperia</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figures 19–23</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>19</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 5.76–6.06 mm (n=2). Color of antenna beyond radicle: entirely dark. Radicle color: same as scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 1.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: short and sparse. Frontal depression: smooth dorsally, torular triangle foveolate with transverse carinae lateral to this area. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: wrinkle-like with a median peak. Clypeal median carina: present. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas. Mandibular teeth: three of roughly equal size. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: reticulate-rugose without any strong carinae.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: weakly rounded anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: densely foveolate. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: with a semicircular expansion, broadest near midlength. Mesoscutellar sculpture: densely foveolate with one or two median longitudinal channels. Metascutellum in dorsal view: trapezoidal with broad apex. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: convex. Femoral depression: centrally smooth, peripherally foveolate. Leg color: dark except for trochanters, tips of femora and tibiae, and tarsomeres 1-4. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: black to dark reddish brown. Median lobe of T1: with 7 or more longitudinal carinae. Metasoma at middle of T4: with metasomal bend and abrupt transition in sculpture. Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: without protrusions. T5 median carina: absent. or present. Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5: weak, blunt and hardly raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. T6: longer than broad. T6 laterotergite: overlapped by rim from S6. S4 median carina: absent. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: not directed posteriorly, arising from center of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: absent. Apex of S6: without notch.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. unknown.</p>
                        <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 19–23.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba hesperia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,holotype female (OSUC 148713). <bold>19</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view <bold>20</bold> Head, ventral view <bold>21</bold> Lateral habitus; <bold>22</bold> Metasomal terga 5–6, dorsal view <bold>23</bold> Metasomal sterna 5–6, ventral view. Morphbank<sup>19</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 with 1 large ventral sensillum; 3 mandibular teeth of approximately equal length; metascutellum broadly trapezoidal with a broad and slightly concave apex; metasomal bend present but weak; sculpture posterior to metasomal bend with transverse septa about as strong as the longitudinal septa; T4–T6 and S4–S6 without median carina; T6 longer than broad; S6 without apical notch. This species is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba tridentata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but in that species S6 has a strong apical notch. It is also near <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba nigrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but no complete female specimens of that species are known.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Latin adjective, referring to the geographic distribution of this species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302154">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302154</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: WA, 3km W Walpole, Keystone Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°59.01'S, 116°40.76'E</named-content>, no date, yellow pan trap, George, Hawks &amp; Munro, OSUC 148713 (deposited in WAMP). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 2 females, OSUC 148702, 238154 (CNCI).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                        <title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>Some singleton specimens similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba hesperia</tp:taxon-name></italic> have been examined but left undescribed, most collected from Western Australia. They all exhibit a stronger metasomal bend and stronger longitudinal sculpture posterior to the bend than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba hesperia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but are variable in these and other characters. Together these specimens and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba hesperia</tp:taxon-name></italic> may represent members of a species complex. Some specimens within this complex possess longitudinal median grooves on the mesoscutellum, but this character may be variable within species.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">intermedia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D1FA6338-2827-4D30-AF06-849208F4A6E6</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302155</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_intermedia</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figures 24–27</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>20</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 3.25–3.88 mm (n=7). Color of antenna beyond radicle: entirely dark. Radicle color: lighter than scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 6. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 0.</p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: short and dense. Frontal depression: medially smooth, torular triangle sparsely foveolate, or foveolate dorsally, torular triangle foveolate, areas lateral to it with transverse carinae. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: absent. Dorsal clypeal margin: bordering antennal foramina, absent between them. Clypeal median carina: absent. Ventral clypeal margin: convex. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas. Mandibular teeth: three, but middle tooth tiny. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: reticulate-rugose without any strong carinae.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: weakly rounded anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: foveolate with slightly stronger longitudinal septa. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: triangularly expanded or with posterior tooth, broadest posteriorly. Mesoscutellar sculpture: densely foveolate with slightly stronger longitudinal septa. Metascutellum in dorsal view: strongly transverse, subrectangular. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: flat. Femoral depression: centrally smooth, peripherally foveolate. Leg color: coxae, femora (aside from their apices), and at least the last two tarsomeres dark, otherwise yellowish brown. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: black to dark reddish brown. Median lobe of T1: with a set of rugae that merge with one another. Metasoma at middle of T4: without bend. Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: without protrusions. T5 median carina: absent. Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5: weak, blunt and hardly raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. T6: longer than broad. T6 laterotergite: overlapping S6. S4 median carina: present. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: absent. Apex of S6: without notch.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. Body length 2.62–3.25 mm (n=18). Flagellomere length: A3 over 1.5× as long as broad, most others as long or longer than broad. T7: flat and posteriorly truncate.</p>
                        <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 24–27.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba intermedia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,paratype female (OSUC 180713). <bold>24</bold> Dorsal habitus <bold>25 </bold>Ventral habitus, paratype female (OSUC 148707) <bold>26</bold> Head, ventral view, paratype male (OSUC 227576) <bold>27</bold> Dorsal habitus. Morphbank<sup>20</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 without large ventral sensilla; 3 mandibular teeth with middle tooth much smaller than the others; metascutellum broad and subrectangular, <!--PageBreak-->very short; metasomal bend absent; T4–T6 without median carina, S4–S6 with at least a vague median carina; T6 longer than broad; S6 without apical notch. The antenna and short metascutellum help distinguish it from similar species. It is very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba pinnula</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but differs in having a much shorter metascutellum. It is also very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba clavata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but has no distinct metasomal bend and has a longer T6 in females.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Latin adjective, referring to its unusual mixture of characters.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302155">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302155</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined. </title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: WA, via Dwellingup, Yarragil 4P Catchment, 18.II-25.II.1981, malaise trap, A. Postle, OSUC 230811 (deposited in QMBA). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 8 females, 23 males, OSUC 148705, 148707-148708, 180713, 238105-238109, 238111, 238179, 238182, 238184-238186 (CNCI); OSUC 230809-230810, 230812, 230814, 238450 (QDPC); OSUC 227572-227578, 230801, 238454, 238457, 384567 (WINC).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                        <title>Comments.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba intermedia</tp:taxon-name></italic> lacks a metasomal bend, but the three mandibular teeth, elongate metasoma, and sculptural features suggest that it belongs in the <italic>laminata</italic> group. Specimens from the eastern localities tend to be slightly smaller and have some reduction in sculpture, but are retained in our concept of this species.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">laminata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4C6F2E7E-3E8C-4973-AC72-D02632852D69</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:4127</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_laminata</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Dodd</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figures 28–31</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>21</sup></xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba laminata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Dodd 1931</xref>: 78 (original description); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Galloway 1976</xref>: 88 (type information); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Johnson 1992</xref>: 354 (catalogued).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 2.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. Body length = 3.38 mm (n=1). Flagellomere length: A3 over 1.5× as long as broad, most others as long or longer than broad. Ocular setae: long and dense. Frontal depression: densely foveolate. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: absent between antennal foramina. Clypeal median carina: absent. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular teeth: three, but middle tooth tiny. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: deeply reticulate-rugose with some septa much stronger than others, forming distinct rows differing in height. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: truncate anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: foveolate with slightly stronger longitudinal septa. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: with a semicircular expansion, broadest near midlength. Mesoscutellar sculpture: densely foveolate with a longitudinal carina. Metascutellum in dorsal view: elongate-trapezoidal but with incised apex. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: apex protruding dorsally. Femoral depression: crossed by rounded carinae. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly. T7: arched and posteriorly concave.</p>
                        <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 28–31.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba laminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Dodd, allotype male (QMBA HY4732A). <bold>28</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view <bold>29</bold> Head, anterior view <bold>30</bold> Metasomal terga 6–8, posterior view, holotype female (QMBA HY4732H) <bold>31</bold> Antenna, ventral view. Morphbank<sup>21</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Males: Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area semicircularly expanded; mesosoma broadly truncate anteriorly; mesoscutellum with median carina; metascutellum elongate-trapezoidal with incised apex.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=4127">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=4127</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material Examined">
                        <title>Material Examined. </title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: QLD, Gogango, 40mi W Rockhampton, III-1928, A. P. Dodd, QMBA HY4732H (deposited in QMBA). Allotype: AUSTRALIA: 1 male, QMBA HY4732A (QMBA). Other material: AUSTRALIA: 3 males, OSUC 365210-365212 (UQIC).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                        <title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>Only the antenna and a few legs of the female holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba laminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> remain. The syntopic allotype male strongly resembles the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba nigrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but differs in the presence of a partial median carina on the mesoscutellum, the anteriorly truncate mesosoma, and denser sculpturing on the thoracic dorsum. No other female specimens are known aside from the holotype. The allotype shares characteris<!--PageBreak-->tics with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba hesperia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba magnirubra</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba tridentata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but differs enough that it cannot definitively be associated with any of these species.</p>
                        <p>Because the antenna and some legs of the holotype remains, they now represent the holotype. A neotype cannot be properly designated without first requesting that the existing holotype be set aside. This was considered unnecessary, as the antenna clearly belongs to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic>, based on the number and arrangement of ventral sensilla. Therefore, there is no doubt that the holotype agrees with our concept of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic>. There is also no reason to conclude that the allotype male would be from a different species than the female, based on its morphology compared with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Dodd’s (1931)</xref> description of the now lost parts of the female’s body.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">magnirubra</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:48277EF5-2342-478C-8BDE-3B3F2AF0790E</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302156</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_magnirubra</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figures 32–35</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>22</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 6.50–6.88 mm (n=3). Color of antenna beyond radicle: mostly dark, extreme base of scape becoming reddish. Radicle color: lighter<!--PageBreak--> than scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 1.</p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: long and sparse. Frontal depression: medially smooth, torular triangle sparsely foveolate. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: interrupted by a median areole below interantennal process. Clypeal median carina: present. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas. Mandibular teeth: three, but middle tooth tiny. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: reticulate-rugose without any strong carinae.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: protruding anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: densely <!--PageBreak-->foveolate. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: with a semicircular expansion, broadest near midlength. Mesoscutellar sculpture: densely foveolate. Metascutellum in dorsal view: elongate-trapezoidal but with incised apex. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: apex protruding dorsally, or convex. Femoral depression: crossed by rounded carinae. Leg color: reddish but with at least last two tarsomeres dark. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: reddish, with last segment variably dark. Median lobe of T1: with 7 or more longitudinal carinae. Metasoma at middle of T4: with metasomal bend and abrupt transition in sculpture. Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: with tooth-like protrusions. T5 median carina: present. Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5: strong, sharply raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: not directed posteriorly, arising from center of sculptural mesh. T6: longer than broad. T6 laterotergite: overlapping S6. S4 median carina: present. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: not directed posteriorly, arising from center of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: not meeting apically. Apex of S6: with notch.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. Body length 4.75–5.00 mm (n=5). Flagellomere length: A3 over 1.5× as long as broad, most others as long or longer than broad. T7: arched and posteriorly concave.</p>
                        <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 32–35.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba magnirubra</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,paratype female (OSUC 238178). <bold>32</bold> Dorsal habitus <bold>34</bold> Head, ventral view, holotype female (OSUC 148715) <bold>33</bold> Lateral habitus, paratype female (OSUC 238112) <bold>35</bold> Metasomal sterna 5–6, ventral view. Morphbank<sup>22</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 with 1 large ventral sensillum; 3 mandibular teeth with middle tooth smaller than the others; metascutellum trapezoidal and relatively long, with a truncate or slightly incised apex; metasomal bend present; sculpture posterior to metasomal bend with strong longitudinal septa but without transverse septa; T4–T6 and S4–S6 with median carina; T6 longer than broad; S6 with apical notch.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Compound adjective using the Latin adjectives magnus and ruber.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302156">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302156</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: SA, 32km N Renmark, Amalia Dam, xeric mallee scrub, MT 4, ROM 2000040, Bookmark Biosphere Reserve, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">33°53'S, 140°43'E</named-content>, 263m, 15.II–15.IV.2000, malaise trap, D. C. Darling, OSUC 148715 (deposited in SAMA). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 4 females, 6 males, OSUC 365208, 367506-367507 (ANIC); OSUC 238112, 238117-238119, 238121-238122, 238178 (CNCI).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                        <title>Comments. </title>
                        <p>This is the largest-bodied species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic> known. It resembles <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba sculptifrons</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba sparsa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but differs from both in a large number of characters.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">nigrescens</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3692A700-53E1-4B03-8247-BEE9AC332619</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:4128</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_nigrescens</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>(Dodd)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figures 36–39</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank
                            <sup>23</sup></xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Chromoteleia nigrescens</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Dodd 1920</xref>: 329 (original description); Masner 1965: 71 (type information).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba nigrescens</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Dodd): <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Dodd 1931</xref>: 80 (generic transfer); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Galloway 1976</xref>: 88 (type information); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Johnson 1992</xref>: 354 (catalogued).<!--PageBreak--></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. Body length 3.38 mm (n=1). Flagellomere length: A3 over 1.5× as long as broad, most others as long or longer than broad. Ocular setae: long and dense. Frontal depression: with many irregularly transverse rugae. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: absent between antennal foramina. Clypeal median carina: absent. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular teeth: three, but middle tooth tiny. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: deeply reticulate-rugose with some septa much stronger than others, forming distinct rows differing in height. Mandibular color: mostly reddish brown, dark at teeth.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: weakly rounded anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: sparsely foveolate, with large smooth interspaces. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: with a semicircular expansion, broadest near midlength. Mesoscutellar sculpture: sparsely foveolate, with large smooth interspaces. Metascutellum in dorsal view: elongate-trapezoidal but with incised apex. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: apex protruding dorsally. Femoral depression: crossed by rounded carinae. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly. Leg color: coxae and at least the last three tarsomeres dark, otherwise yellowish. T7: arched and posteriorly concave.</p>
                        <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 36–39.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba nigrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Dodd) holotype male (B.M. TYPE HYM. 9.499). <bold>36</bold> Head and mesosoma, dorsal view <bold>37</bold> Metasomal terga 6–8, postero-lateral view <bold>38</bold> Head, anterior view <bold>39</bold> Head, ventral view. Morphbank<sup>23</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Males: Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area semicircularly expanded; mesosoma weakly rounded anteriorly; mesoscutellum without median carina; metascutellum elongate-trapezoidal with incised apex.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=4128">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=4128</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, male, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chromoteleia nigrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic>: <bold>AUSTRALIA:</bold> WA, Yallingup, 1.XII-12.XII.1913, R. E. Turner, B.M. TYPE HYM. 9.499 (deposited in BMNH).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                        <title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>The male holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba nigrescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> cannot be associated with any known female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba</tp:taxon-name></italic>. It is very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba laminata</tp:taxon-name></italic> even though the two species occur on opposite sides of the Australian continent. These species may be closely related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba hesperia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba tridentata</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">parvirubra</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9B615296-D426-4E5E-937A-9AC299199003</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302157</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_parvirubra</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figures 40–42</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>24</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 3.38–3.63 mm (n=3). Color of antenna beyond radicle: mostly dark, extreme base of scape becoming reddish. Radicle color: same as scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 1.</p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: long and sparse. Frontal depression: smooth dorsally, torular triangle foveolate, areas lateral to it smooth. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from <!--PageBreak-->antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: arched, interrupted by broad median carina. Clypeal median carina: present. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas. Mandibular teeth: three, but middle tooth tiny. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: deeply reticulate-rugose with some septa much stronger than others, forming distinct rows differing in height.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: protruding anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: foveolate with slightly stronger longitudinal septa. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: with a semicircular expansion, broadest near midlength. Mesoscutellar sculpture: densely foveolate with one or two median longitudinal channels. Metascutellum in dorsal view: elongate-trapezoidal but with incised apex. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: flat, or convex. Femoral depression: crossed by many sharply defined carinae. Leg color: yellowish-brown except for dorsal external part of coxae and sometimes tarsomeres 2-5. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: centrally reddish with some vague dark intrusions, peripherally becoming black. Median lobe of T1: with 7 or more longitudinal carinae. Metasoma at<!--PageBreak--> middle of T4: with metasomal bend and abrupt transition in sculpture. Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: with tooth-like protrusions. T5 median carina: absent. Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5: strong, sharply raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. T6: as broad or broader than long. T6 laterotergite: overlapped by rim from S6. S4 median carina: present. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: forming complete peripheral carina. Apex of S6: without notch.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak--><italic>Male</italic>. unknown.</p>
                        <fig id="F12" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 40–42.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba parvirubra</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,holotype female (OSUC 238194). <bold>40</bold> Dorsal habitus <bold>41 </bold>Lateral habitus <bold>42</bold> Ventral habitus. Morphbank<sup>24</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g012.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 with 1 large ventral sensillum; 3 mandibular teeth with middle tooth much smaller than the others; metascutellum trapezoidal and strongly narrowing to an incised apex; metasomal bend present; sculpture posterior to metasomal bend with strong longitudinal and transverse septa; T4–T6 without distinct median carina; S4–S6 with median carina; T6 about as broad as long; S6 without apical notch. This species is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba sculptifrons</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba sparsa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but lacks the S6 notch and frontal carinae.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Compound adjective using the Latin adjectives parvus and ruber.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302157">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302157</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: WA, 20km N Denmark, 16.I.1987, J. S. Noyes, OSUC 238194 (deposited in WAMP). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 3 females, OSUC 238191, 238193, 238196 (CNCI).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">pinnula</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:29EE41F2-7AE8-46F5-AE0C-C9250E6A5771</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302158</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_pinnula</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figures 43–46</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>25</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 3.37–3.75 mm (n=7). Color of antenna beyond radicle: entirely dark. Radicle color: lighter than scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 1, or 2.</p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: short and dense. Frontal depression: with many strong transverse carinae, sparsely foveolate at torular triangle. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: absent between antennal foramina. Clypeal median carina: absent. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas. Mandibular teeth: three of roughly equal size. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: deeply reticulate-rugose with some septa much stronger than others, forming distinct rows differing in height.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: weakly rounded anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: densely foveolate. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: with a semicircular expansion, broadest near midlength. Mesoscutellar sculpture: densely foveolate. Metascutellum in dorsal view: trapezoidal with broad apex. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: flat, or convex. Femoral depression: centrally smooth, peripherally foveolate. Leg color: coxae and femora dark, but tibiae, tarsi, and sometimes 2nd trochanters yellowish brown. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: black to dark reddish brown. Median lobe of T1: with a set of rugae that merge with one another. Metasoma at middle of T4: with metasomal bend<!--PageBreak--> and abrupt transition in sculpture. Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: without protrusions. T5 median carina: absent. Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5: weak, blunt and hardly raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. T6: as broad or broader than long. T6 laterotergite: overlapping S6. S4 median carina: present. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: absent. Apex of S6: without notch.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. Body length 2.75–3.13 mm (n=4). Flagellomere length: A3 over 1.5× as long as broad, most others as long or longer than broad. T7: flat and posteriorly truncate.</p>
                        <fig id="F13" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 43–46.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba pinnula</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,paratype female (OSUC 231794). <bold>43</bold> Dorsal habitus <bold>45</bold> Head, ventral view, holotype female (OSUC 231797) <bold>44</bold> Lateral habitus <bold>46</bold> Metasomal sterna 5–6, ventral view. Morphbank<sup>25</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g013.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 with 1 or 2 large sensilla; 3 mandibular teeth of approximately equal length; metascutellum trapezoidal with a broad and truncate or slightly concave apex; metasomal bend present but very weak; sculpture posterior to metasomal bend with longitudinal and transverse septa of about equal height and hardly differing from those anterior to the bend; T4–T6 and S4-S5 without median carina; S4 sometimes with a slight median carina; T6 longer than broad; S5 with longitudinal septa not stronger than transverse septa; S6 without apical notch. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba pinnula</tp:taxon-name></italic> has only a very slight metasomal bend, and therefore it can easily be confused <!--PageBreak-->with those species that lack the bend. It differs from most of these species in that the fore wings reach to the middle of T4, and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba intermedia</tp:taxon-name></italic> in having a long and trapezoidal metascutellum.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Latin noun, meaning “a small fin.” This is considered to be a noun in apposition to the generic name.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302158">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302158</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: WA, WA122401, 7km N Stirling Range National Park, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°19'S, 118°11'E</named-content>, 900ft, 24.XII.1994, malaise trap, L. S. Kimsey &amp; R. B. Kimsey, OSUC 231797 (deposited in WAMP). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 12 females, 11 males, OSUC 149756 (AEIC); OSUC 230822-230824, 367508, 367512-367519 (ANIC); OSUC 148700, 231780-231781 (CNCI); OSUC 238452 (QDPC); OSUC 179086, 179088-179089, 231794-231796 (UCDC).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">propodealis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F867EC04-0D6C-43C9-8BF8-E134A5C8D488</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302160</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_propodealis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figures 47–50</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>26</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 3.62–3.88 mm (n=3). Color of antenna beyond radicle: entirely dark. Radicle color: base lighter than scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 1.</p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: short and dense. Frontal depression: present as a vague smooth triangle. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: absent between antennal foramina. Clypeal median carina: absent. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas. Mandibular teeth: three, but middle tooth tiny. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: deeply reticulate-rugose with some septa much stronger than others, forming distinct rows differing in height.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: weakly rounded anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: foveolate with broad longitudinal septa. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: with a semicircular expansion, broadest near midlength. Mesoscutellar sculpture: sparsely foveolate, with large smooth interspaces. Metascutellum in dorsal view: very short, subrectangular. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: convex. Femoral depression: irregularly foveolate but not crossed by carinae. Leg color: coxae, femora (aside from their apices), and at least the last two tarsomeres dark, otherwise yellowish brown. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: with longitudinal tooth-like crest extending dorsally above level of metascutellum. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: black to dark reddish brown. Median lobe of T1: with 7 or more longitudinal carinae. Metasoma at middle of T4: with metasomal bend and abrupt<!--PageBreak--> transition in sculpture. Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: without protrusions. T5 median carina: absent. Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5: weak, blunt and hardly raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. T6: longer than broad. T6 laterotergite: overlapping S6. S4 median carina: present. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: not directed posteriorly, arising from center of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: absent. Apex of S6: without notch.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak--><italic>Male</italic>. unknown.</p>
                        <fig id="F14" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 47–50.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba propodealis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,holotype female (OSUC 227590). <bold>47</bold> Dorsal habitus, paratype female (OSUC 227591) <bold>48</bold> Lateral habitus, paratype female (OSUC 238190) <bold>49</bold> Head, ventral view <bold>50</bold> Metasomal sterna 5–6, ventral view. Morphbank<sup>26</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g014.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 with 1 large ventral sensillum; 3 mandibular teeth with the middle tooth much smaller than the others; metascutellum subrectangular, very short and broad; anteromedial margins of lateral propodeal area extending dorsally above the metascutellar surface as distinct protrusions; metasomal bend extremely weak; sculpture posterior to metasomal bend with longitudinal septa stronger than those anterior to the bend, transverse septa as strong or slightly weaker than longitudinal septa; T4–T6 and S6 without median carina, S4-S5 with median carina; S6 without apical notch.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>An adjective, combining the anatomical term propodeum with the Latin adjectival suffix -alis, referring to its unique propodeum.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302160">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302160</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: WA, Mount Cooke, 28.I-17.II.1991, malaise trap, M. S. Harvey &amp; J. M. Waldock, OSUC 227590 (deposited in WAMP). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 2 females, OSUC 238190 (CNCI); OSUC 227591 (WINC).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                        <title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>The propodeum in this species is unique among the specimens studied. It is very difficult to determine in all examined specimens if the metasomal bend is present or not.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sculptifrons</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:F99233BD-F270-46FF-8E14-9507C07E6D9C</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302161</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_sculptifrons</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figures 51–54</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>27</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 5.75–6.13 mm (n=2). Color of antenna beyond radicle: entirely dark. Radicle color: same as scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 2.</p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: short and dense. Frontal depression: with irregular rugae indicating large foveae. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: angular, emarginate medially. Clypeal median carina: present. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas. Mandibular teeth: three, but middle tooth tiny. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: reticulate-rugose with strong dorsoventral carinae.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: truncate anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: densely foveolate. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: with a semicircular expansion, broadest near midlength. Mesoscutellar sculpture: densely foveolate. Metascutellum in dorsal view: trapezoidal with broad apex. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: apex protruding dorsally. Femoral depression: centrally smooth, peripherally foveolate. Leg color: coxae and at least the last three tarsomeres dark, otherwise reddish. Anterior<!--PageBreak--> corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: T2 to flat part of T4, troughs of S1 to variable part of S5 reddish, otherwise dark. Median lobe of T1: with 7 or more longitudinal carinae. Metasoma at middle of T4: with metasomal bend and abrupt transition in sculpture. Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: without protrusions. T5 median carina: absent. Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5: strong, sharply raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: not directed <!--PageBreak-->posteriorly, arising from center of sculptural mesh. T6: longer than broad. T6 laterotergite: overlapping S6. S4 median carina: present. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: not directed posteriorly, arising from center of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: not meeting apically. Apex of S6: without notch.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. unknown.</p>
                        <fig id="F15" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 51–54.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba sculptifrons</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,paratype female (OSUC 148704). <bold>51</bold> Dorsal habitus <bold>53 </bold>Head, ventral view <bold>54</bold> Metasomal sterna 5–6, ventral view, holotype female (OSUC 231799) <bold>52 </bold>Lateral habitus. Morphbank<sup>27</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g015.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 with 2 large ventral sensilla; 3 mandibular teeth, with middle tooth much smaller than the others; metascutellum broadly trapezoidal with a broad truncate apex; metasomal bend present; sculpture posterior to metasomal bend strong longitudinal septa and weaker transverse septa; T4–T6 and S4–S6 with or without median carina; T6 longer than broad; S6 without apical notch. This species is very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba magnirubra</tp:taxon-name></italic> in coloration and in having a relatively large body, but it differs in many characters, especially in lacking the apical S6 notch in females.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Used as a noun in apposition to the generic name, derived from a combination of the Latin participle sculptus and noun frons, referring to its strong network of frontal carinae.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map"><title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302161">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302161</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: WA, ~25km E Perth, John Forrest National Park, 23.XII-27.XII.1986, J. S. Noyes, OSUC 231799 (deposited in WAMP). Paratype: AUSTRALIA: 1 female, OSUC 148704 (CNCI).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">sparsa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C947CBC7-D26E-4001-AE11-3A8EDD4873A3</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302162</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_sparsa</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figures 55–59</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>28</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 3.37–4.00 mm (n=6). Color of antenna beyond radicle: reddish-brown, darker at scape apex, pedicel, and A3. Radicle color: lighter than scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 1.</p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: long and sparse. Frontal depression: with irregular rugae indicating large foveae. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: forming a complete connection between antennal foramina medially. Clypeal median carina: absent. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas. Mandibular teeth: two, separated by narrow incision. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: reticulate-rugose without any strong carinae.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: truncate anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: densely foveolate. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: with a semicircular expansion,<!--PageBreak--> broadest near midlength. Mesoscutellar sculpture: densely foveolate. Metascutellum in dorsal view: trapezoidal but tapering to narrow apex. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: apex protruding dorsally. Femoral depression: crossed by rounded carinae. Leg color: entirely reddish. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: mostly reddish, variably dark at T4 bend, T5-T6, with variable smaller dark areas elsewhere. Median lobe of T1: with 7 or more longitudinal carinae. Metasoma at middle of T4: with metasomal bend and abrupt transition in sculpture. <!--PageBreak-->Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: with tooth-like protrusions. T5 median carina: absent. Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5: strong, sharply raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: not directed posteriorly, arising from center of sculptural mesh. T6: as broad or broader than long. T6 laterotergite: overlapping S6. S4 median carina: present. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: not directed posteriorly, arising from center of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: not meeting apically. Apex of S6: with notch.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. Body length 3.5 mm (n=1). Flagellomere length: A3 over 1.5× as long as broad, most others as long or longer than broad. T7: arched and posteriorly concave.</p>
                        <fig id="F16" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 55–59.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba sparsa</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,holotype female (OSUC 231798). <bold>55</bold> Dorsal habitus <bold>56</bold> Lateral habitus <bold>58</bold> Head, ventral view, paratype female (OSUC 238205) <bold>57</bold> Head, anterior view <bold>59</bold> Metasomal sterna 5–6, ventral view. Morphbank<sup>28</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g016.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 with 1 large ventral sensillum; 2 mandibular teeth; metascutellum subtrapezoidal but strongly tapering to a narrow truncate apex; metasomal bend expressed as a raised hump with posterior metasomal segments not tilted downwards; sculpture posterior to metasomal hump with strong longitudinal and transverse septa; T4–T6 without longitudinal carina; T6 broader than long; S4–S6 with longitudinal carina; S6 with apical notch.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Latin participle meaning “scattered,” recalling the sparsely distributed setae of this species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302162">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302162</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: WA, Toodyay, 31.X.1979, R. M. Bohart, OSUC 231798 (deposited in WAMP). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 4 females, 3 males, OSUC 230821 (ANIC); OSUC 148703, 238204-238206, 238208 (CNCI); OSUC 55870 (OSUC).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                        <title>Comments.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba sparsa</tp:taxon-name></italic> represents a distinctive element within the genus, with its unique metasoma and unusual metascutellum.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">tricorata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D54F676D-1EEF-4B40-88DA-CFB9583628C5</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302163</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_tricorata</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figures 60–61</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank<sup>29</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 3.88–4.25 mm (n=4). Color of antenna beyond radicle: entirely dark. Radicle color: same as scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 1.</p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: short and sparse. Frontal depression: with many strong transverse carinae, sparsely foveolate at torular triangle. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: bordering antennal foramina, absent between them. Clypeal median carina: absent. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular color: mostly yellowish brown, dark at teeth. Mandibular teeth: three, but middle tooth tiny. Smooth area obliquely posterior to la<!--PageBreak-->teral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: deeply reticulate-rugose with some septa much stronger than others, forming distinct rows differing in height.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: weakly rounded anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum: foveolate with slightly stronger longitudinal septa. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: with a semicircular expansion, broadest near midlength. Mesoscutellar sculpture: sparsely foveolate, with large smooth interspaces. Metascutellum in dorsal view: trapezoidal with broad apex. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: convex. Femoral depression: crossed by rounded carinae. Leg color: coxae, femora (aside from their apices), and at least the last two tarsomeres dark, otherwise yellowish brown. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma color: black to dark reddish brown. Median lobe of T1: with a set of rugae that merge with one another. Metasoma at middle of T4: with very weak bend. Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: without protrusions. T5 median carina: absent. Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5: weak, blunt and hardly raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. T6: as broad <!--PageBreak-->or broader than long. T6 laterotergite: overlapped by rim from S6. S4 median carina: absent. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: forming complete peripheral carina. Apex of S6: without notch.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. Body length 3.75–4.00 mm (n=3). Flagellomere length: A3 over 1.5× as long as broad, most others as long or longer than broad. T7: arched and posteriorly concave.</p>
                        <fig id="F17" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 60–61.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba tricorata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,holotype female (OSUC 238541). <bold>60</bold> Dorsal habitus <bold>61 </bold>Ventral habitus. Morphbank<sup>29</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g017.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 with 1 large ventral sensillum; 3 mandibular teeth with the middle tooth much smaller than the others; metascutellum broadly trapezoidal with a broad apex that is truncate or sometimes slightly incised; metasomal bend present but very weak; sculpture posterior to metasomal bend with transverse septa about as strong as the longitudinal septa; T4–T6 without median carina, S4–S6 with or without median carina; T6 about as broad as long; S5 with longitudinal septa much stronger than transverse septa; S6 without apical notch. This species is very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba pinnula</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but has distinctly different ventral metasomal sculpture.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Latin participle meaning “tricky,” named for its strong similarity to some other species and its very subtle metasomal bend.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302163">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302163</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: WA, 20km N Denmark, 16.I.1987, J. S. Noyes, OSUC 238541 (deposited in WAMP). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 3 females, 3 males, OSUC 148699, 238192, 238195, 238197, 238199-238200 (CNCI).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Bracalba</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">tridentata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:193C973C-CFBA-48E9-8F82-34589E44F32E</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_concepts:302164</object-id>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Bracalba_tridentata</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Burks</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figures 62–65</xref>
                        <xref>Morphbank
                            <sup>30</sup></xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. Body length 5.12–5.38 mm (n=3). Color of antenna beyond radicle: entirely dark. Radicle color: same as scape. Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla: 7. Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6: 1.</p>
                        <p>Ocular setae: long and sparse. Frontal depression: with many irregularly transverse rugae. Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen: present. Dorsal clypeal margin: arched, interrupted by broad median carina. Clypeal median carina: present. Ventral clypeal margin: with a small median point. Mandibular color: dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas. Mandibular teeth: three, but middle tooth tiny. Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus: present. Genal sculpture: deeply reticulate-rugose with some septa much stronger than others, forming distinct rows differing in height.</p>
                        <p>Dorsal pronotal area: not set off by carina ventrally. Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area: truncate anteriorly. Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum:<!--PageBreak--> densely foveolate. Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area: with a semicircular expansion, broadest near midlength. Mesoscutellar sculpture: densely foveolate. Metascutellum in dorsal view: trapezoidal with broad apex, or elongate-trapezoidal but with incised apex. Dorsal surface of metascutellum: apex protruding dorsally. Femoral depression: crossed by 4-6 dorsal carinae, 7-8 ventral carinae interrupted by central smooth area. Leg color: yellowish-brown except for dorsal external part of coxae and sometimes tarsomeres 2-5. Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina: flat, without tooth. Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area: protruding posteriorly.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Metasoma color: black to dark reddish brown. Median lobe of T1: with 7 or more longitudinal carinae. Metasoma at middle of T4: with metasomal bend and abrupt transition in sculpture. Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga: without protrusions. T5 median carina: absent. Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5: strong, sharply raised. Transverse sculptural septa on T5: about as strong as the longitudinal septa. T5 setae: not directed posteriorly, arising from center of sculptural mesh. T6: as broad or broader than long. T6 laterotergite: overlapping S6. S4 median carina: absent. Transverse sculptural septa on S5: weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa. S5 setae: not directed posteriorly, arising from center of sculptural mesh. Lateral carinae of S6: not meeting apically. Apex of S6: with notch.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>. unknown.</p>
                        <fig id="F18" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 62–65.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba tridentata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.,paratype female (OSUC 238116). <bold>62</bold> Dorsal habitus <bold>64 </bold>Head, ventral view, metasomal sterna 5–6, ventral view <bold>65</bold> Metasomal sterna 5–6, ventral view, holotype female (OSUC 238113) <bold>63</bold> Lateral habitus. Morphbank<sup>30</sup></p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-236-001-g018.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>. A6 with 1 large ventral sensillum; middle mandibular tooth present but much smaller than the others; metascutellum broadly trapezoidal and with a broadly truncate apex that may have a conspicuous median notch; metasomal bend strong; sculpture posterior to metasomal bend distinctly different from that anterior to it, with very weak transverse septa and strong longitudinal septa; T6 about as long as broad; S6 with apical notch. This species is very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba hesperia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but S6 in that species does not have an apical notch. It is also similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bracalba sparsa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but that species has a unique metasomal bend and metascutellar shape.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>Latin adjective, named for the usually 3-pronged pattern formed apically by dark cuticle on T6.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Link to distribution map">
                        <title>Link to distribution map.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302164">http://hol.osu.edu/map-full.html?id=302164</ext-link> </p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype, female: AUSTRALIA: SA, 32km N Renmark, Amalia Dam, xeric mallee scrub, MT 4, ROM 2000041, Bookmark Biosphere Reserve, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">33°53'S, 140°43'E</named-content>, 263m, 15.II-15.IV.2000, malaise trap, D. C. Darling, OSUC 238113 (deposited in SAMA). Paratypes: AUSTRALIA: 2 females, OSUC 238114, 238116 (CNCI).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>We thank L. Musetti, J. Jennings, J. Cora, A. Valerio, S. Mantel, D. Stringer, and other members of the PBI team, for assistance with specimens, photographs, and databasing. This work was funded by the National Science Foundation under grant No. DEB–0614764 to N.F. Johnson and A.D. Austin, and by the Australian Biological Resources Study grant 208-058 to A.D. Austin.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>ABRS</surname></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> Australian Faunal Directory. Platygastroidea. Australian Biological Resources Study, Canberra. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.environment.gov.au/biodiversity/abrs/online-resources/fauna/afd/taxa/PLATYGASTROIDEA">http://www.environment.gov.au/biodiversity/abrs/online-resources/fauna/afd/taxa/PLATYGASTROIDEA</ext-link>  [accessed on 21 May 2012]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<source> A taxonomic revision of <italic>Mirobaeoides</italic> Dodd (Hymenoptera Scelionidae). Australian Journal of Zoology 34: 315–337.<sup>31</sup> </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/ZO9860315">10.1071/ZO9860315</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<source> The ovipositor system of scelionid and platygastrid wasps (Hymenoptera: Platygastroidea): comparative morphology and phylogenetic implications. Invertebrate Taxonomy11: 1–87. <sup>32</sup> </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/IT95048">10.1071/IT95048</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowton</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Systematics, evolution and biology of scelionid and platygastrid wasps. Annual Review of Entomology 50: 553–582. </source><sup>33</sup> doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ento.50.071803.130500">10.1146/annurev.ento.50.071803.130500</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bin</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<source> Definition of female antennal clava based on its plate sensilla in Hymenoptera Scelionidae Telenominae. Redia 64: 245–261.<sup>34</sup></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dangerfield</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<source> Biology, Ecology and Systematics of Australian Scelio, wasp parasitoids of locust and grasshopper eggs. CSIRO Publications: Collingwood, Victoria, 254 pp.<sup>35</sup></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dodd</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1920</year>)<source> Notes on the exotic Proctotrupoidea in the British and Oxford University Museums, with descriptions of new genera and species. Transactions of the Entomological Society of London 1919: 321–382. <sup>36</sup> </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2311.1920.tb00008.x">10.1111/j.1365-2311.1920.tb00008.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dodd</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1931</year>) <source>The genus <italic>Oxyscelio</italic> Kieffer, its synonymy and species, with a description of one new genus (Hymenoptera: Proctotrypoidea). Proceedings of the Royal Society of Queensland 42: 71–81.</source><sup>37</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eady</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<source> Some illustrations of microsculpture in the Hymenoptera. Proceedings of the Royal Entomological Society of London, (A) 43: 66–72.<sup>38</sup> </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3032.1968.tb01029.x">10.1111/j.1365-3032.1968.tb01029.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Galloway</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>)<source> The types of Australian species of the subfamily Scelioninae (Hymenoptera: Scelionidae). Queensland Journal of Agricultural and Animal Sciences 33: 83–114. <sup>39</sup></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Galloway</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<source> Revision of the Scelioninae (Hymenoptera: Scelionidae) in Australia. Australian Journal of Zoology Supplementary Series 99: 1–138. <sup>40</sup> </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/AJZS099">10.1071/AJZS099</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Goloboff</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farris</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nixon</surname> <given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<source> T.N.T. – Tree Analysis Using New Technology, version 1.1. Computer software and manual, available at: (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.zmuc.dk/public/phylogeny">http://www.zmuc.dk/public/phylogeny</ext-link> ).</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Goloboff</surname> <given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farris</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nixon</surname> <given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<source> TNT: a free program for phylogenetic analysis. Cladistics 24: 774–786. <sup>41</sup> </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-0031.2008.00217.x">10.1111/j.1096-0031.2008.00217.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<source> Systematics of the wasp genus <italic>Ceratobaeus</italic> Ashmead (Hymenoptera: Scelionidae) from Australasia: parasitoids of spider eggs. Records of the South Australian Museum Monograph Series6: 1–164. <sup>42</sup></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<source> Revision of Australasian <italic>Trissolcus</italic> species (Hymenoptera: Scelionidae). Invertebrate Taxonomy5: 211–39. <sup>43</sup> </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/IT9910211">10.1071/IT9910211</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<source> Catalog of world Proctotrupoidea excluding Platygastridae. Memoirs of the American Entomological Institute 51: 1–825. <sup>44</sup></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masner</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<source> Revision of the genus <italic>Psix</italic> Kozlov &amp; Lê (Hymenoptera: Scelionidae). Systematic Entomology 10: 33–58. <sup>45</sup>  </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3113.1985.tb00562.x">10.1111/j.1365-3113.1985.tb00562.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Masner</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <source>Revisionary notes and keys to world genera of Scelionidae (Hymenoptera: Proctotrupoidea). Memoirs of the Entomological Society of Canada 97: 1–87. </source><sup>46</sup> doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/entm10897fv">10.4039/entm10897fv</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Masner</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> <italic>Xentor</italic>, a new endemic genus from Fiji (Hymenoptera: Platygastroidea: Scelionidae) and description of three new species. Fiji Arthropods, 9: 11–20.<sup>47</sup> </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1206/0003-0082(2007)3551[1:TANGON]2.0.CO;2">10.1206/0003-0082(2007)3551[1:TANGON]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikó</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilhelmsen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masner</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pénzes</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> Skeletomusculature of Scelionidae (Hymenoptera: Platygastroidea): head and mesosoma. Zootaxa 1571: 1–78. <sup>48</sup> </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1206/0003-0082(2007)3551[1:TANGON]2.0.CO;2">10.1206/0003-0082(2007)3551[1:TANGON]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Muesebeck</surname> <given-names>CFW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walkley</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1956</year>)<source> Type species of the genera and subgenera of parasitic wasps comprising the superfamily Proctotrupoidea (order Hymenoptera). Proceedings of the United States National Museum 105: 319–419. <sup>49</sup> </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5479/si.00963801.3359.319">10.5479/si.00963801.3359.319</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname> <given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Systematics, distribution and biology of the Australian ‘micro-flea’ wasps, <italic>Baeus</italic> spp. (Hymenoptera: Scelionidae): parasitoids of spider eggs. Zootaxa 1499: 1–45.</source> <sup>50</sup></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Talamas</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masner</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> Revision of the <italic>Paridris nephta</italic> species group (Hymenoptera, Platygastroidea, Platygastridae). ZooKeys 133: 49–94.<sup>51</sup> </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.133.1613">10.3897/zookeys.133.1613</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilhelmsen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikó</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krogmann</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source> Beyond the wasp-waist: structural diversity and phylogenetic significance of the mesosoma in apocritan wasps (Insects: Hymenoptera). Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society 159: 22–194.<sup>52</sup> </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.2009.00576.x">10.1111/j.1096-3642.2009.00576.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1839</year>)<source> Monographia Chalciditum. Vol. II. Hyppolite Baillière, London, 100 pp. <sup>53</sup></source></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
        <sec sec-type="Endnotes">
            <title>Endnotes</title>
            <p>1	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1008">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1008</ext-link> </p>
            <p>2	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:32975">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:32975</ext-link> </p>
            <p>3	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:32981">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:32981</ext-link> </p>
            <p>4	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1009">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1009</ext-link> </p>
            <p>5	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1012">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1012</ext-link> </p>
            <p>6	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:33928">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:33928</ext-link> </p>
            <p>7	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:33791">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:33791</ext-link> </p>
            <p>8	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1014">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:1014</ext-link> </p>
            <p>9	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34157">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34157</ext-link> </p>
            <p>10	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34161">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34161</ext-link> </p>
            <p>11	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34982">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34982</ext-link> </p>
            <p>12	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34411">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34411</ext-link> </p>
            <p>13	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34578">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34578</ext-link> </p>
            <p>14	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34593">urn:lsid:biocol.org:col:34593</ext-link> </p>
            <p>15	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799328">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799328</ext-link> </p>
            <p>16	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799329">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799329</ext-link> </p>
            <p>17	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799330">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799330</ext-link> </p>
            <p>18	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799331">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799331</ext-link> </p><!--PageBreak-->
            <p>19	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799332">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799332</ext-link> </p>
            <p>20	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799333">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799333</ext-link> </p>
            <p>21	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799334">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799334</ext-link> </p>
            <p>22	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799335">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799335</ext-link> </p>
            <p>23	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799336">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799336</ext-link> </p>
            <p>24	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799337">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799337</ext-link> </p>
            <p>25	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799338">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799338</ext-link> </p>
            <p>26	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799339">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799339</ext-link> </p>
            <p>27	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799340">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799340</ext-link> </p>
            <p>28	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799341">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799341</ext-link> </p>
            <p>29	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799342">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799342</ext-link> </p>
            <p>30	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799343">http://www.morphbank.net/?id=799343</ext-link> </p>
            <p>31	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:111">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:111</ext-link> </p>
            <p>32	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:20940">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:20940</ext-link> </p>
            <p>33	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21201">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21201</ext-link> </p>
            <p>34	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:131">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:131</ext-link> </p>
            <p>35	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:9560">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:9560</ext-link> </p>
            <p>36	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:409">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:409</ext-link> </p>
            <p>37	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:404">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:404</ext-link> </p>
            <p>38	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21506">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21506</ext-link> </p>
            <p>39	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:353">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:353</ext-link> </p>
            <p>40	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:463">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:463</ext-link> </p>
            <p>41	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-0031.2008.00217.x">http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-0031.2008.00217.x</ext-link></p>
            <p>42	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:8079">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:8079</ext-link> </p>
            <p>43	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:633">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:633</ext-link> </p>
            <p>44	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:229">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:229</ext-link> </p>
            <p>45	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:657">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:657</ext-link> </p>
            <p>46	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:311">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:311</ext-link> </p>
            <p>47	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21304">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21304</ext-link> </p>
            <p>48	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21300">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21300</ext-link> </p>
            <p>49	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:240">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:240</ext-link> </p>
            <p>50	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21213">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:21213</ext-link> </p>
            <p>51	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:23583">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:23583</ext-link> </p>
            <p>52	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:23221">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:23221</ext-link> </p>
            <p>53	<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:528">http://lsid.tdwg.org/urn:lsid:biosci.ohio-state.edu:osuc_pubs:528</ext-link> </p>
        </sec>
				<app-group>
        <app id="appendix1">
            <title>Appendix 1</title>
            <p><bold>Characters</bold></p>
            <p><italic>Color of antenna beyond radicle</italic></p>
            <p>1. entirely dark</p>
            <p>2. entirely reddish</p>
            <p>3. mostly dark, extreme base of scape becoming reddish</p>
            <p>4. reddish-brown, darker at scape apex, pedicel, and A3</p>
            <p>5. mostly dark, ventral parts of pedicel apex, A4-A12 variably lighter</p>
            <p>6. yellowish-brown</p>
            <p>7. dark except for pedicel apex</p>
            <p>8. claval segments brown, basal segments yellowish</p>
            <p><italic>Radicle color</italic></p>
            <p>1. same as scape</p>
            <p>2. base lighter than scape</p>
            <p>3. lighter than scape</p>
            <p><italic>Number of claval segments with ventral gustatory sensilla</italic></p>
            <p>1. 6</p>
            <p>2. 7</p>
            <p><italic>Number of ventral gustatory sensilla on A6</italic></p>
            <p>1. 1</p>
            <p>2. 2</p>
            <p>3. 0</p>
            <p><italic>Ocular setae</italic></p>
            <p>1. short and dense</p>
            <p>2. long and sparse</p>
            <p>3. short and sparse</p>
            <p>4. long and dense</p>
            <p>5. absent</p>
            <p><italic>Frontal depression ventral sculpture</italic></p>
            <p>1. with transverse rugae</p>
            <p>2. with large areoles</p>
            <p>3. smooth or foveolate</p>
            <p>4. with median longitudinal carina</p>
            <p>5. inapplicable (frontal depression absent)<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <p><italic>Frontal depression dorsal sculpture</italic></p>
            <p>1. with transverse rugae</p>
            <p>2. with large areoles</p>
            <p>3. smooth or foveolate</p>
            <p>4. with median longitudinal carina</p>
            <p>5. inapplicable (frontal depression absent)</p>
            <p><italic>Smooth depression extending dorsolaterally from antennal foramen</italic></p>
            <p>1. absent</p>
            <p>2. present</p>
            <p><italic>Dorsal clypeal margin</italic></p>
            <p>1. absent between antennal foramina</p>
            <p>2. interrupted by a median areole below interantennal process</p>
            <p>3. interrupted by median carina</p>
            <p>4. complete only between antennal foramina medially</p>
            <p>5. wrinkle-like with median peak</p>
            <p>6. angular, emarginate medially</p>
            <p>7. uniformly arched without interruption</p>
            <p><italic>Clypeal median carina</italic></p>
            <p>1. present</p>
            <p>2. absent</p>
            <p><italic>Ventral clypeal margin</italic></p>
            <p>1. straight</p>
            <p>2. with a small median point</p>
            <p>3. convex</p>
            <p>4. concave</p>
            <p><italic>Mandibular color</italic></p>
            <p>1. dark basally and at teeth, becoming lighter reddish brown between these areas</p>
            <p>2. entirely dark</p>
            <p>3. mostly yellowish brown, dark at teeth</p>
            <p>4. mostly reddish brown, dark at teeth</p>
            <p><italic>Mandibular teeth</italic></p>
            <p>1. three of roughly equal size</p>
            <p>2. two, separated by narrow incision</p>
            <p>3. three, but middle tooth tiny</p>
            <p>4. two, broadly separated by an angled flat area</p><!--PageBreak-->
            <p><italic>Smooth area obliquely posterior to lateral ocellus</italic></p>
            <p>1. present</p>
            <p>2. absent</p>
            <p><italic>Genal sculpture</italic></p>
            <p>1. reticulate-rugose with strong dorsoventral carinae</p>
            <p>2. reticulate-rugose without any strong carinae</p>
            <p>3. deeply reticulate-rugose with some septa much stronger than others, forming distinct rows differing in height</p>
            <p><italic>Dorsal pronotal area</italic></p>
            <p>1. not set off by carina</p>
            <p>2. set off by carina</p>
            <p><italic>Anterolateral corner of dorsal pronotal area</italic></p>
            <p>1. protruding anteriorly</p>
            <p>2. truncate anteriorly</p>
            <p>3. weakly rounded anteriorly</p>
            <p><italic>Sculpture of posteromedian area of mesoscutum</italic></p>
            <p>1. sparsely foveolate, with large smooth interspaces</p>
            <p>2. with many longitudinal carinae</p>
            <p>3. densely foveolate</p>
            <p>4. foveolate with broad longitudinal septa</p>
            <p>5. foveolate with slightly stronger longitudinal septa</p>
            <p>6. foveolate, with some interspersed additional tiny foveae</p>
            <p><italic>Lateral margin of dorsal axillar area</italic></p>
            <p>1. not expanded</p>
            <p>2. broadly expanded</p>
            <p>3. triangularly expanded or with posterior tooth, broadest posteriorly</p>
            <p>4. with a semicircular expansion, broadest near midlength</p>
            <p><italic>Mesoscutellar sculpture</italic></p>
            <p>1. densely foveolate</p>
            <p>2. sparsely foveolate, with large smooth interspaces</p>
            <p>3. densely foveolate with one or two median longitudinal channels</p>
            <p>4. densely foveolate but with smooth central area</p>
            <p>5. densely foveolate with slightly stronger longitudinal septa</p>
            <p>6. foveolate, with some interspersed additional tiny foveae</p>
            <p>7. densely foveolate with a longitudinal carina</p>
            <p>8. medially smooth except for a few irregular carinae<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <p><italic>Metascutellum in dorsal view</italic></p>
            <p>1. strongly transverse, subrectangular</p>
            <p>2. trapezoidal with broad apex</p>
            <p>3. trapezoidal but tapering to narrow apex</p>
            <p>4. elongate-trapezoidal but with incised apex</p>
            <p>5. very short, subrectangular</p>
            <p>6. semicircular</p>
            <p>7. elongate-rectangular</p>
            <p><italic>Dorsal surface of metascutellum</italic></p>
            <p>1. flat</p>
            <p>2. apex protruding dorsally</p>
            <p>3. convex</p>
            <p><italic>Femoral depression</italic></p>
            <p>1. crossed by rounded carinae</p>
            <p>2. irregularly foveolate but not crossed by carinae</p>
            <p>3. smooth, not crossed by carinae</p>
            <p>4. crossed by 4-6 dorsal carinae, 7-8 ventral carinae interrupted by central smooth area</p>
            <p>5. centrally smooth, peripherally foveolate</p>
            <p>6. shallowly sculptured but not crossed by carinae</p>
            <p>7. crossed by many sharply defined carinae</p>
            <p><italic>Leg color</italic></p>
            <p>1. entirely dark</p>
            <p>2. entirely reddish</p>
            <p>3. coxae dark, all else reddish</p>
            <p>4. coxae, femora (aside from their apices), and at least the last two tarsomeres dark, otherwise yellowish brown</p>
            <p>5. coxae and at least the last three tarsomeres dark, otherwise reddish</p>
            <p>6. reddish but with at least last two tarsomeres dark</p>
            <p>7. dark except for 2nd trochanter of fore leg and mid leg, tip of mid and hind metatibia</p>
            <p>8. reddish except for variable antero-dorsal portion of coxae</p>
            <p>9. dark except for trochanters, tips of femora and tibiae, and tarsomeres 1-4</p>
            <p>10. coxae and femora dark, but tibiae, tarsi, and sometimes 2nd trochanters yellowish brown</p>
            <p>11. dark except for tips of tibiae and at least 1st tarsomere</p>
            <p>12. yellowish-brown except for dorsal part of coxae and sometimes tarsomeres 2-5</p>
            <p>13. dark except for tibiae, 2nd trochanter, and tarsomeres 2-5</p>
            <p>14. dark, except trochanters, femoral apices, variable parts of tibiae, and tarsi pale</p>
            <p>15. coxae, femora, and apical two tarsomeres dark, trochanters, tibiae, and other tarsomeres yellowish brown</p>
            <p>16. coxae dark, leg becoming gradually lighter apically</p>
            <p><!--PageBreak-->17. coxae and at least the last three tarsomeres dark, otherwise yellowish</p>
            <p>18. entirely yellowish</p>
            <p><italic>Anterior corner of lateral propodeal carina</italic></p>
            <p>1. flat, without tooth</p>
            <p>2. with longitudinal tooth-like crest extending dorsally above level of metascutellum</p>
            <p><italic>Posteromedial corner of lateral propodeal area</italic></p>
            <p>1. not protruding posteriorly</p>
            <p>2. protruding posteriorly</p>
            <p><italic>Metasoma color</italic></p>
            <p>1. black to dark reddish brown</p>
            <p>2. entirely reddish</p>
            <p>3. reddish, with last segment variably dark</p>
            <p>4. reddish, with last two segments dark</p>
            <p>5. reddish, with last 2.5 segments dark</p>
            <p>6. T2 to flat part of T4, troughs of S1 to variable part of S5 reddish; otherwise dark</p>
            <p>7. mostly reddish, variably dark at T4 bend, T5-T6, with variable smaller dark areas elsewhere</p>
            <p>8. centrally reddish with some vague dark intrusions, peripherally becoming black</p>
            <p><italic>Median lobe of T1</italic></p>
            <p>1. with 7 or more longitudinal carinae</p>
            <p>2. with a set of rugae that merge with one another</p>
            <p>3. with median smooth area interrupting carinae</p>
            <p>4. with 6 carinae</p>
            <p>5. with 5 carinae</p>
            <p><italic>Metasoma at middle of T4</italic></p>
            <p>1. with metasomal bend and abrupt transition in sculpture</p>
            <p>2. without bend</p>
            <p>3. with very weak bend</p>
            <p><italic>Posterolateral margins of metasomal terga</italic></p>
            <p>1. with tooth-like protrusions</p>
            <p>2. without protrusions</p>
            <p><italic>T5 median carina</italic></p>
            <p>1. absent</p>
            <p>2. present<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <p><italic>Longitudinal sculptural septa on T5</italic></p>
            <p>1. strong, sharply raised</p>
            <p>2. weak, blunt and hardly raised</p>
            <p><italic>Transverse sculptural septa on T5</italic></p>
            <p>1. about as strong as the longitudinal septa</p>
            <p>2. weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa</p>
            <p><italic>T5 setae</italic></p>
            <p>1. directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh</p>
            <p>2. not directed posteriorly, arising from center of sculptural mesh</p>
            <p><italic>T6</italic></p>
            <p>1. longer than broad</p>
            <p>2. as broad or broader than long</p>
            <p><italic>T6 laterotergite</italic></p>
            <p>1. overlapped by rim from S6</p>
            <p>2. overlapping S6</p>
            <p><italic>S4 median carina</italic></p>
            <p>1. absent</p>
            <p>2. present</p>
            <p><italic>Transverse sculptural septa on S5</italic></p>
            <p>1. weak or absent, much weaker than the longitudinal septa</p>
            <p>2. about as strong as the longitudinal septa</p>
            <p><italic>S5 setae</italic></p>
            <p>1. directed posteriorly, arising from anterior edge of sculptural mesh</p>
            <p>2. not directed posteriorly, arising from center of sculptural mesh</p>
            <p><italic>Lateral carinae of S6</italic></p>
            <p>1. forming complete peripheral carina</p>
            <p>2. not meeting apically</p>
            <p>3. absent</p>
            <p>4. weak and ruga-like, becoming indistinct posteriorly</p>
            <p><italic>Apex of S6</italic></p>
            <p>1. without notch</p>
            <p>2. with notch</p>
            <p>3. roundly concave</p>
            <p><!--PageBreak--><italic>Flagellomere length</italic></p>
            <p>1. A3 over 1.5× as long as broad, most others as long or longer than broad</p>
            <p>2. A3 1–1.2× as long as broad, most others transverse</p>
            <p><italic>T7</italic></p>
            <p>1. arched and posteriorly concave</p>
            <p>2. flat and posteriorly truncate</p>
            <sec sec-type="Matrix">
                <title>Matrix</title>
                <p>Chromoteleia sp.	7002444010221101223052200H02111000100020011</p>
                <p>Bracalba_cuneata	50110[23][23]16111000[01]132[04]11001B0[02]101001100020011</p>
                <p>Bracalba_globosa	02110[23][23]161110100242111001C01101001100020011</p>
                <p>Bracalba_plana	4211000101110200222150401F00101001001020111</p>
                <p>Bracalba_clavata	41020[03][02]13112020023230[02]400300200001110020001</p>
                <p>Bracalba_hesperia	00102021401001002232124018000[01]1000000120?1?</p>
                <p>Bracalba_intermedia	0202022061220100242400401301101000110020011</p>
                <p>Bracalba_laminata	??11302101120200143631001???????????????0?0</p>
                <p>Bracalba_magnirubra	221012211012010002303[12]001520010110110111000</p>
                <p>Bracalba_nigrescens	????300101120230203131001G??????????????0?0</p>
                <p>Bracalba_parvirubra	201012012012020004323[02]601B70000001010000?0?</p>
                <p>Bracalba_pinnula	021[01]00010110020022301[02]401901001001111020011</p>
                <p>Bracalba_sculptifrons	00110[13][13]150120000123011401450000110110110?1?</p>
                <p>Bracalba_propodealis	0110022101120200233142111300001000111120?1?</p>
                <p>Bracalba_tricorata	0010200101120220243112001301201001000000010</p>
                <p>Bracalba_sparsa	3210122131110100123021001160000111110111000</p>
                <p>Bracalba_tridentata	00101001201202001230[13]1301B00000011100111?1?<!--PageBreak--></p>
            </sec>
        </app>
        <app id="appendix2">
            <title>Appendix 2</title>
            <p>Taxonomic records for all records used in the present paper. (doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.236.3434.app2)">10.3897/zookeys.236.3434.app2)</ext-link> File format: DarwinCore Archive.</p>
            <p><bold>Explanation note:</bold> Darwin Core Archive (DwC-A) is the preferred format for publishing data to the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) network. Together with Dublin Core (on which its ideas are based), it is used by GBIF and others to encode data about organism names, taxonomies and species information.</p>
        </app>
        <app id="appendix3">
            <title>Appendix 3</title>
            <p>Locality records for all records used in the present paper. (doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.236.3434.app3)">10.3897/zookeys.236.3434.app3)</ext-link> File format: DarwinCore Archive.</p>
            <p><bold>Explanation note:</bold> Darwin Core Archive (DwC-A) is the preferred format for publishing data to the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) network. Together with Dublin Core (on which its ideas are based), it is used by GBIF and others to encode data about organism names, taxonomies and species information.</p>
        </app>
				</app-group>
    </back>
</article>