<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>ZooKeys</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.127.1670</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title><italic>Callosphecodes</italic>, a little-known bee
(Hymenoptera, Halictidae, Sphecodes)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Rasmussen</surname>
                        <given-names>Claus</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Michener</surname>
                        <given-names>Charles D.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Biological Sciences, Aarhus University, Ny Munkegade 114, DK-8000 Aarhus C, Denmark</aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Division of Entomology, Natural History Museum and Dept. of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, 1501 Crestline Drive, University of Kansas, Lawrence, Kansas 66045, USA</aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Claus Rasmussen (<email xlink:type="simple">alrunen@yahoo.com</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Michael Engel</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
            	    <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>8</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>127</issue>
            <fpage>61</fpage>
            <lpage>68</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>7</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>4</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Claus Rasmussen, Charles D. Michener</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Friese, 1909, a synonym or perhaps subgenus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Latreille, 1804, is known on the basis of one female of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes ralunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Friese, 1909)from New Britain and one female and one male of a similar species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Rayment, 1935) from northeastern Australia. The male is here described for the first time and the females of the two species are compared for the first time. In spite of considerable collecting, only these three specimens have appeared in over a century. Descriptions and illustrations are provided.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Apoidea</kwd>
                <kwd>Anthophila</kwd>
                <kwd>Halictinae</kwd>
                <kwd>Halictini</kwd>
                <kwd>Sphecodina</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Sphecodes</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>New Britain</kwd>
                <kwd>Bismarck Archipelago</kwd>
                <kwd>Australia</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>cleptoparasite</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Even in parts of the world where there has been little investigation of the bee fauna, taxa of bees so distinctive as to have received genus-group names a century or more ago have usually been collected several times so that multiple specimens are now known. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Friese, 1909, however, until now has been known from only two female specimens of different species from localities over 1500 km apart. A third specimen, a male, is herein reported for the first time. To judge by the lack of pollen manipulating <!--PageBreak-->and carrying structures in females, this is a cleptoparasitic group. Many cleptoparasites are uncommon, and it seems possible that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a rare insect, not only in collections but also in the field.</p>
            <p>We follow various earlier authors in considering <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> to be a synonym or possibly a subgenus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Latreille, 1804, which is the most common and widespread genus of cleptoparasitic Halictinae. This cleptoparasitic group was given subtribal status as the Sphecodina in the tribe Halictini (subfamily Halictinae) in the phylogenetic study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Pesenko (2000)</xref>. Nonetheless, the two species that have been placed in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> have a distinctive appearance different from that of the many other species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Such other species are 4 to 15 mm in length, usually black with a partly or wholly red metasoma, but males in particular may be entirely black. A female at a host cell destroys the egg of the host and replaces it with her own. Further information on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> biology can be found in works by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Ordway (1964)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Eickwort and Eickwort (1972)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Torchio (1975)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Sick et al. (1994)</xref>, and summarized by (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Michener (2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">2007</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="History"><title>History</title>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> was proposed as a subgenus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Friese (1909)</xref> but in the same paper, in describing the included species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> was treated as a genus. The only species included at that time was <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes ralunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Friese (1909)</xref>, based on a single female presumably from Ralum, New Britain, in the Bismarck Archipelago (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">04°21'S, 152°17'E</named-content> ). By error, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Friese (1925)</xref> indicated that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> had been described from Australia in 1912. It was separated from typical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> by its large size (but it is much smaller than the larger typical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and by the metallic blue black metasoma. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Meyer (1920)</xref> repeated Friese’s description and because of the metallic coloration, suggested that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> was close to the neotropical genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Temnosoma</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Smith (1853)</xref>. The latter, however, is a very different cleptoparasite of the halictid tribe Augochlorini.</p>
            <p>Subsequent views on the position of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> have varied from a distinct genus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Friese 1925</xref>) to synonymy with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Michener 1944</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">2007</xref>) or a subgenus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Michener, 1965). These viewpoints were not based on additional information about the type species, for the type and only known specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes ralunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> was not reexamined. After inquiring about the specimen from personnel of the Magyar Természettudományi Múzeum, Budapest, and the Museum für Naturkunde der Humboldt-Universität, Berlin, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Michener (2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">2007</xref>) concluded that the specimen was probably lost. It has been found, however, in good condition in the Berlin museum and was borrowed for study by C.R.; all the labels were illustrated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Rasmussen and Ascher (2008</xref>, fig. 8).</p>
            <p>A second specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> was described as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mellitidia manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Rayment 1935</xref>) on the basis of a single female collected in 1934 by Martin J. Manski at Cairns (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">16°55'S, 145°46'E</named-content> ) in northern Queensland, Australia. It is not clear why it<!--PageBreak--> was placed by Rayment in a nomiine genus whose females, unlike cleptoparasites, have a strong scopa. Placement of this species in the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> was by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Michener (1965)</xref>, who saw the type, but association with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> was not certain since the type of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes ralunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> was not then available. The holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is in the Australian National Insect Collection, Canberra, and has been borrowed by C.R. for direct comparison with that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes ralunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. They are very similar, certainly both constituting the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> group. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Michener (1978)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Cardale (1993)</xref> included <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic> not merely in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> but in the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> s. str.</p>
            <p>Also, in the Australian National Insect Collection, was found a male, judged on the basis of similarity to the female and on geography, to be <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic>. It was collected in 1980 by Josephine C. Cardale in Mount Webb National Park (15.045S, 145.07E), Queensland, Australia, about 100 km from Cairns, the type locality for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <p>When reviewing the cleptoparasitic groups of Halictidae, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Michener (1978)</xref> differentiated the genera such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eupetersia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Blüthgen, 1928, from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic>; see also (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Michener (2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">2007</xref>). It is apparent that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, contrary to earlier suggestions (Michener, 1978), is not the same as any such genera but, as we have indicated above, does not differ appreciably from ordinary <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The principle difference mentioned in the literature between such <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the metallic blue, greenish or purplish black metasoma of the latter, independently mentioned by both Friese and Rayment in describing the two species. Yet, at least at present, the metallic tints of the specimens are extremely feeble, scarcely detectable, the metasoma being essentially black.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description</title>
            <p>The following descriptive comments, largely following the pattern of Michener’s (1978) account of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, are based on the three known specimens of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> group, that is <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes ralunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic>manskii</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">13</xref>). The description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Michener (1978)</xref> indicates the variation in many characters among the species of the genus. Notes below on the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eupetersia</tp:taxon-name></italic> are inserted to counter the suggestion mentioned in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Michener (2000</xref>, 2007) that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Callosphecodes</tp:taxon-name></italic> might be a senior synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eupetersia</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1–5.</label>
                <caption><p>Holotype female of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes ralunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>: <bold>1</bold> lateral habitus <bold>2</bold> metasoma <bold>3</bold> facial aspect <bold>4</bold> dorsolateral aspect of head and pronotum <bold>5</bold> dorsal aspect of mesosoma and head.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-127-061-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 6–12.</label>
                <caption><p>Holotype female of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic>: <bold>6</bold> lateral habitus <bold>7</bold> metasoma <bold>8</bold> dorsal habitus <bold>9</bold> mesosoma including propodeum <bold>10</bold> facial aspect <bold>11</bold> hypostomal carina with tooth at posterior end <bold>12</bold> forewing pattern.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-127-061-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Both sexes: Black, metasomal terga with feeble bluish, purplish, or blue green metallic tints (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">7</xref>); wings strongly infuscated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 12</xref>). Punctation of head and thorax coarse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 4</xref>; moderately fine in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eupetersia</tp:taxon-name></italic><bold>);</bold> punctures of mesoscutum, especially posteriorly, widely separated (by much more than puncture diameter) by shining surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 5</xref>). Head in facial view much wider than long, clypeus more than twice as wide as long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 3 and 10</xref>). Eyes hairless. Hairs of antennal flagellum all very short. Preoccipital carina strong and distinct. Posterior end of hypostomal carina with tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 11</xref>). Pronotum with horizontal surface of collar almost absent medially, forming lateral angle below which a vertical ridge extends downward; vertical ridge approaching or merging with a more laterally directed ridge that extends toward coxal base; another carina from lateral angle extends across posterior lobe of pronotum. Anterior <!--PageBreak-->extremity of mesoscutum convex. Scutellum gently biconvex because of feeble longitudinal median depression. Propodeum with dorsal area strongly areolate, about as long as scutellum, area broadly rounded posteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 9</xref>); posterior and lateral surfaces of propodeum with few short plumose hairs in addition to longer hairs. Wings with hairs rather long and dense throughout (as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eupetersia</tp:taxon-name></italic>); stigma moderate; marginal cell pointed at apex; free part of marginal cell beyond submarginal cells longer than part subtended by submarginal cells, which part extends well beyond apex of stigma. Second and third submarginal cells each receiving a recurrent vein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 12</xref>). First metasomal tergum broader than long. Second tergum in lateral view with base somewhat<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> depressed forming weak constriction between first and second terga. Posterior margins of terga 2 – 4 broadly depressed, hairless, impunctate.</p>
            <p>Female: Mandible with large subapical tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 10</xref>; unlike <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eupetersia</tp:taxon-name></italic>). Labrum with broad, flat apical process about two thirds as broad as long. Legs robust, hind femur about three times as long as broad; basitibial plate elevated; long hairs on outer side of hind tibia plumose; hind tibial spine finely serrate. Fifth metasomal tergum, unlike preceding terga, with apical margin fringed except middle part of margin which has smooth, hairless area in front of fringeless part of margin. Pygidial plate broader than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eupetersia</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            <p>Male: Antennae longer than those of female, flagellum thickened (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 13</xref>; unlike <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eupetersia</tp:taxon-name></italic>), somewhat crenulate, first flagellar segment broader than long, second longer than first, both first and second shorter than subsequent segments but not very short as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eupetersia</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Labrum not visible on specimen. Second hind tarsal segment longer than third, base broader than base of third. Gonocoxite finely striate, without margined depression as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eupetersia</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Gonocoxite with basal setose lobe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 15 and 16</xref>).</p>
            <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 13–14.</label>
                <caption><p>Male of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic>: <bold>13</bold> dorsal habitus; <bold>14</bold> dorsolateral aspect of head and pronotum.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-127-061-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 15–16.</label>
                <caption><p>Male genitalia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic>: <bold>15</bold> Dorsalventral view of genitalia; <bold>16</bold> 7th metasomal sternum.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-127-061-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <p>Specific differences: The holotypes (both females) are very similar and we have no way of knowing whether the differences between them are specific differences or indicate variation within a species. The differences (observed by CR) are as follows: Lateral margin of propodeum (immediately below metanotum) in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes ralunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> largely areolate, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic> widely strigulate and less areolate. Gena of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes ralunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sparsely covered with plumose, light colored setae, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic> densely covered with white setae. Flagellum in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes ralunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> ferruginous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 3</xref>), in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic> dark brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 10</xref>). Measurements are as follows for the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes ralunensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> holotype female: Total body length about 10 mm; forewing length (including tegula) 8.8 mm; head width 3.1 mm; head length (anterior margin of clypeus to summit of vertex) 2.5 mm; mesoscutum width 2.1; mesoscutum length 2.0 mm. The <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic> holotype female: Total body length about 12 mm; forewing length (including tegula) 9.5 mm; head width 3.2 mm; head length (anterior margin of clypeus to summit of vertex) 2.5 mm; mesoscutum width 2.3; mesoscutum length 2.0 mm. <!--PageBreak-->Male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sphecodes manskii</tp:taxon-name></italic>: Total body length about 11 mm; forewing length (including tegula) 8.1 mm; head width 2.9 mm; head length (anterior margin of clypeus to summit of vertex) 2.5 mm; mesoscutum width 2.3; mesoscutum length 2.2 mm.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We are very thankful to the curators for loan of the specimens: Frank Koch of the Museum für Naturkunde der Humboldt-Universität, Berlin, and Nicole Fisher of the Australian National Insect Collection, Canberra. Also to Carlsberg Foundation for support (C.R.) and Lars Vilhelmsen and Verner Michelsen of the Natural History Museum of Denmark for providing access to the imaging system.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blüthgen</surname><given-names>PAV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1928</year>)<article-title> 2. Beitrag zur Kenntnis der äthiopischen Halictinae (Hym. Apid.). I. Die Gattung <italic>Eupetersia</italic> nov. gen.</article-title> <source>Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift </source> <volume>1928</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardale</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Hymenoptera: Apoidea</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>WWK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maynard</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Zoological catalogue of Australia</source>, Vol. <volume>10</volume>. <publisher-name>AGPS</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Canberra</publisher-loc>, x + <lpage>406</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eickwort</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eickwort</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Aspects of the biology of Costa Rican halictine bees, III. <italic>Sphecodes kathleenae</italic>, a social cleptoparasite of <italic>Dialictus umbripennis</italic> (Hymenoptera: Halictidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society </source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>-<lpage>541</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Friese</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1909</year>)<article-title> Die Bienenfauna von Neu-Guinea.</article-title> <source>Annales Historico-Naturales Musei Nationalis Hungarici (Természettudományi Múzeum évkönyve) </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>288</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Friese</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>)<article-title> Zur Bienenfauna von Neu-Guinea und Oceanien. Übersicht des von den Herren Dahl, Finsch, Krämer, Moszkowski, Neuhaus, Schoede und L. Schultze in den letzten Jahren dem Zoologischen Museum in Berlin überwiesenen Forschungsmaterials.</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen aus dem Zoologischen Museum in Berlin </source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>96</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Friese</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1925</year>)<article-title> Über die Urbienengattung <italic>Temnosoma</italic> Sm.</article-title> <source>Zoologische Jahrbücher, Abteilung für Systematik, Geographie und Biologie der Tiere </source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>534</fpage>-<lpage>536</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Latreille</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1804</year>)<article-title> Tableau méthodique des insectes. Classe huitième. Insectes, Insecta.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Latreille</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>Nouveau dictionnaire d’histoire naturelle, appliquée aux arts, principalement à l’agriculture et à l’économie rurale et domestique: par une société de naturalistes et d’agriculteurs: avec des figures tirées des trois règnes de la nature, Vol.</issue-title> <source>24. Déterville, Paris</source>: <fpage>129</fpage>-<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1920</year>)<article-title> Apidae - Sphecodinae</article-title>. <source>Archiv für Naturgeschichte</source>. Abteilung A <volume>85</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>): <fpage>79</fpage>–160, 161–<lpage>242</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Michener</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1944</year>)<article-title> Comparative external morphology, phylogeny, and a classification of the bees.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History </source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>326</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Michener</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>)<article-title> A classification of the bees of the Australian and south Pacific regions.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History </source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>362</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Michener</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>)<article-title> The parasitic groups of Halictidae (Hymenoptera, Apoidea).</article-title> <source>University of Kansas Science Bulletin </source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>291</fpage>-<lpage>339</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Michener</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<source> The bees of the world</source>. <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc>, xiv+[1]+<lpage>913</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Michener</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> The bees of the world, second edition</source>. <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc>, xvi+<lpage>953</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ordway</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<article-title> <italic>Sphecodes pimpinellae</italic> and other enemies of <italic>Augochlorella</italic> (Hymenoptera: Halictidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society </source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>-<lpage>152</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pesenko</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year> (“1999”))<article-title> Phylogeny and classification of the family Halictidae revised (Hymenoptera: Apoidea).</article-title> <source>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society </source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>-<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ascher</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Heinrich Friese (1860–1948): Names proposed and notes on a pioneer melittologist (Hymenoptera, Anthophila).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1833</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>118</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rayment</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1935</year>)<source> A cluster of bees; sixty essays on the life-histories of Australian bees, with specific descriptions of over 100 new species, and an introduction by E.</source> <publisher-name>F. Phillips. Endeavour</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Sydney</publisher-loc>, <lpage>752</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayasse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tengö</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engels</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lübke</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Host-parasite relationships in six species of <italic>Sphecodes</italic> bees and their halictid hosts: Nest intrusion, intranidal behavior, and Dufour’s gland volatiles.</article-title> <source>Journal of Insect Behavior </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>117</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1853</year>)<source> Catalogue of the Hymenopterous insects in the collection of the British Museum.</source> <publisher-name>Part I, Andrenidæ and Apidæ. British Museum (Natural History)</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>266</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Torchio</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>)<article-title> The biology of <italic>Perdita nuda</italic> and descriptions of its immature forms and those of its <italic>Sphecodes</italic> parasite (Hymenoptera: Apoidea).</article-title> <source>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society </source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>-<lpage>279</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>