<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
	
	    <front>

        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>

        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.59.483</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new species of Harpactea (Araneae, Dysderidae) from Aegean region of Turkey</article-title>
            </title-group>
	
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Kunt</surname>
                        <given-names>Kadir Boğaç</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <aff>
                        Turkish Arachnological Society. Eserköy Sitesi 9/A Blok No:7 TR-06530 Ümitköy, Ankara, Turkey
                    </aff>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:13EEAB4A-F696-41D7-A323-2333410BF5D7</uri>
                </contrib>
                
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Özkütük</surname>
                        <given-names>Recep Sulhi</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <aff>
                        Department of Biology, Faculty of Science, Anadolu University, TR- 26470 Eskişehir, Turkey
                    </aff>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7A21C546-989F-417F-BCC3-8D682CCF2B62</uri>
                </contrib>

                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Kaya</surname>
                        <given-names>Rahşen S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <aff>
                        Department of Biology, Faculty of Arts and Sciences, Uludağ University, TR-16059, Bursa, Turkey
                    </aff>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:C1C30791-CEB7-4273-987A-FEA2F0E1C09B</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>

            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Kadir Boğaç Kunt (<email xlink:type="simple">chaetopelma@gmail.com</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Dmitry Logunov</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>

            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>1</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>59</issue>
            <fpage>39</fpage>
            <lpage>45</lpage>

            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>21</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>13</day>
                    <month>6</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
            </history>

            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Kadir Boğaç Kunt, Recep Sulhi Özkütük, Rahşen S. Kaya</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:A7EF89A6-FE57-461C-81E3-861E9CE421D2</self-uri>

            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new species of the spider genus <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea</tp:taxon-name> Bristowe, 1939 is described from the Aegean region of Turkey – <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea erseni</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (males only). Detailed morphological description and illustrations of the new species are provided. The relationships of the new species are discussed.</p>
            </abstract>
	
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Dysderidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Harpactea</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>Turkey</kwd>
            </kwd-group>

        </article-meta>
    </front>
    
    <body>

        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The family <tp:taxon-name>Dysderidae</tp:taxon-name> C. L. Koch, 1837 is represented by 504 species in 24 genera worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Platnick 2010</xref>). <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea</tp:taxon-name> Bristowe, 1939 is a species rich genus with 155 described taxa and is particularly diverse in the Mediterranean region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Platnick 2010</xref>). Most of the species appear to be endemics with restricted distributions in the Mediterranean, with only a few found in adjacent areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Řezáč 2008</xref>). So far, 19 species of <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea</tp:taxon-name> have been recorded from Turkey, 17 of which are endemic to the country (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bayram et al. 2010</xref>). However, most of these species are still poorly known and have not been revised since their original descriptions. Nevertheless, the diversity of <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea</tp:taxon-name> in Turkey is high in comparison to well-studied adjacent countries such as Azerbaijan (14 species), Bulgaria (19 species), Georgia (10 species) and Greece (24 species) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Bosmans and Chatzaki 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Otto and Dietzold 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Lazarov 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Lazarov and Naumova 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Van Keer and Bosmans 2010</xref>).</p><!--PageBreak-->
            <p>During our surveys of the Turkish spider fauna we found one undescribed species of <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea</tp:taxon-name> in the Aegean region, which is described herein.</p>
        </sec>

        <sec sec-type="Material and methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Three males were collected from İzmir province in the Aegean region of Turkey (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) using a hand aspirator. The specimens were preserved in 70% ethanol and deposited in the Museum of the Turkish Arachnological Society. Digital images of the pedipalp were taken with a Leica DFC290 digital camera attached to a Leica M205 C stereomicroscope and 5–15 photographs were taken in different focal planes and combined. All measurements are in mm. Terminology for the body measurements and copulatory organ structures were taken from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Chatzaki and Arnedo (2006)</xref>. The following abbreviations were used in the text: AL, abdominal length; CL, carapace length; CWmax, maximum carapace width; CWmin, minimum carapace width; AME, anterior median eyes; PLE, posterior lateral eyes; PME, posterior median eyes; AMEd, diameter of anterior median eyes; PLEd, diameter of posterior lateral eyes; PMEd, diameter of posterior median eyes; ChF, length of cheliceral fang; ChG, length of cheliceral groove; ChL, total length of chelicera (lateral external view); Ta, tarsus; Me, metatarsus, Ti, tibia; Pa, patella; Fe, femur; Tr, trochanter; C, coxa; D, dorsal; Pl, prolateral; Rl, retrolateral; V, ventral; CO, conductor; E, embolus; T, tegulum; MTAS, Museum of the Turkish Arachnological Society, Ankara, Turkey.</p>

            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Type locality of <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea erseni</tp:taxon-name> sp. n (*).</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/483/supp/ZooKeys-059-039-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
        </sec>

        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Harpactea</tp:taxon-name> Bristowe, 1939</p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Harpactea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">erseni</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    	<object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E8F34578-2D22-4893-A7FC-BD1520B159BA</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">9</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>

                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined:</title>
                    <p>Holotype ♂ (MTAS) İzmir Province, Yamanlar Mountain, Karagöl [38°33'26.00N; 27°13'11.00E], 28. XI. 2008, under stones, leg. K.B.Kunt. Paratypes: 2 ♂ (MTAS) same data as holotype.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>

                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Derivatio nominis"><title>Derivatio nominis:</title>
                    <p>The new species is dedicated to “Ersen Aydın Yağmur” who made a great contribution to our knowledge of Turkish scorpions and who is a good friend of the authors.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>

                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis:</title>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Harpactea erseni</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. differs from other Turkish <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea</tp:taxon-name> species (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Nosek 1905</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Alicata 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Brignoli 1978a</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Brignoli 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bayram et al. 2009</xref>) in the structure of the pedipalp of the male. However, the palpal structures of <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea erseni</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. are close to <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea strandjica</tp:taxon-name> Dimitrov, 1997 and <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea terveli</tp:taxon-name> Lazarov, 2009 described from Bulgaria (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Lazarov 2009</xref>). The new species can be distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea terveli</tp:taxon-name> by the different shape of the embolus and conductor; and from <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea strandjica</tp:taxon-name> by having a thinner, curved embolus without a bifurcated tip.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>

                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments"><title>Comments:</title>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Harpactea</tp:taxon-name> is one of the most endemic and speciose dysderid genera in Turkey, with 17 endemics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bayram et al. 2010</xref>). Most of the endemic species have restricted distributions and occur at high elevations, such as the mountain ranges of the Mediterranean, and the north and central Anatolian regions. This distribution pattern presumably results from the combination of topography, proximate biogeographical subregions, the high number of different biotopes and the climate of Anatolia, all of which play a special role in speciation. In short, the Anatolian <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea</tp:taxon-name> fauna is characterized by a high level of local endemism, and by limited co-occurrence of species in the adjacent zoogeographical regions. However, one question can be raised regarding the newly described species: is the male a specimen of a previously described species known only from the female (presumably from Turkey or neighboring countries)? According to our morphometric data, our samples are larger than all previously described <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea</tp:taxon-name> species from Turkey (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Brignoli 1978a</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">b</xref>), supporting our conclusion that it is in fact a new species, rather than the male of a previously described female.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>

                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Measurements (holotype)"><title>Measurements (holotype):</title>
                    <p>AL 4.05; CL 3.45; CWmax 2.25; CWmin 1.35; AMEd 0.15; PLEd 0.13; PMEd 0.10; ChF 0.76; ChG 0.34; ChL 1.35 mm. Leg measurements are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1.</xref></p>

                    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Table 1.</label>
                        <caption><p>Leg measurements of <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea erseni</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</p></caption>
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Legs</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tr</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.15</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pa</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ti</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.55</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.46</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Me</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.50</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.55</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.90</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.92</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>

                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description:</title>
                    <p>Carapace light brown, with smooth surface and distinct fovea. AME, PLE and PME closely grouped; AME separated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Sternum, labium, gnathocoxae and chelicerae yellowish-brown. Sternum with long, thin hairs near the margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>). Cheliceral groove with four teeth: retromargin with two teeth, including a tiny one at the base of the groove; promargin with two strong teeth of equal size close to each other. Top of the labium and gnathocoxae with short, strong hairs, sparsely distributed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>). Abdomen greyish-light brown, with short, thin blackish hairs over the entire surface. Legs yellowish-light brown with sparse blackish setae. Leg IV &gt; Leg I &gt; Leg II &gt; Leg III. Tarsi with three claws. Tarsi III and IV with fine scopulae. Legs III and IV with fine metatarsal scopulae covering slightly less than the distal half of<!--PageBreak--> the segment (ventral surface only). Dorsal part of coxae III and IV with 2–6 spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>). Details of leg spination are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2.</xref></p>
                    <p>Palpal organ with globular bulb and curved, black embolus tapering towards the tip. Conductor same colour as embolus and hook-shaped at the tip and with a tuberculum on the mid-part (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 6–9</xref>). Female unknown.</p>

                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 2–5.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Harpactea erseni</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. 2 Carapace 3 Sternum 4 Right chelicer, ventral view 5 Coxae IV, dorsal view.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/483/supp/ZooKeys-059-039-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
        
                    <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Table 2.</label>
                        <caption><p>Leg spination of <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea erseni</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</p></caption>
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Legs</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</th>
                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</th>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-3 D</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5-6 D</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tr</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 Pl</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 1 Pl</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, 2, 2 D</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 2, 2 D, 2-4 Rl</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pa</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 D</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 Rl</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ti</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 Pl, 1 Rl, 2, 1, 2 V</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 1, 1 Pl, 1, 1 Rl, 5-6 V</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Me</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 Pl, 1, 1 Pl, 5-6 V</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 Pl, 4 Rl, 3-5 V</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ta</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
		    
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 6–9.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Harpactea erseni</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., general appearance of right bulb 6–8 Prolateral view 7–9 Retrolateral view CO Conductor E Embolus T Tegulum (Scale lines: 0.5 mm)</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/483/supp/ZooKeys-059-039-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>

                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>

        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>According to the classification of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Deeleman-Reinhold (1993)</xref>, <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea erseni</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. belongs in the rubicunda (D) species group which is characterized by having a globular palpal body, a massive embolus and conductor and patellae-coxae with spines. Up until now 20 (including the new species) <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea</tp:taxon-name> species have been reported from Turkey. Although the diversity of this genus in Turkey is comparatively high, it can be expected that the actual diversity will be even higher because many regions with favourable habitats for <tp:taxon-name>Harpactea</tp:taxon-name> remain to be studied in Turkey. Therefore, we expect that more species will be found in the future.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>

    <back>
        <ack>
            <label>Acknowledgements</label>
            <p>We are very grateful to Dr. Christo Deltshev and Dr. Stoyan Lazarov (Sofia; Bulgaria) for their valuable comments regarding the new species. The English of the final draft was kindly checked by Dr. David Penney (Manchester; UK).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Alicata</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1974</year>)<article-title> Su una nuova specie di Harpactea (Araneae, Dysderidae) della Turchia.</article-title> <source>Animalia</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayram</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunt</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danışman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2010</year>) <source>The checklist of the spiders of Turkey, Version 10.1.0.</source> <publisher-name>Ankara: Turkish Arachnological Society</publisher-name>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.spidersofturkey.com" xlink:type="simple">http://www.spidersofturkey.com</ext-link> [accessed 17.V.2010]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brignoli</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1978a</year>) <article-title>Ragni di Turchia IV. Leptonetidae, Dysderidae ed Agelenidae nuovi o interessanti di grotte della Turchia meridionale (Araneae).</article-title> <source>Quaderni del Museo di Speleologia</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brignoli</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1978b</year>) <article-title>Ragni di Turchia V. Specie nuove o interessanti, cavernicole ed epigee, di varie famiglie (Araneae)</article-title>. <source>Revue Suisse de Zooogie 85</source>: <fpage>461</fpage>–<lpage>541</lpage>.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brignoli</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1979</year>)<article-title> Spiders from Turkey, VI. Four new species from the coast of the Black Sea (Araneae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British Arachnological Society</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>310</fpage>-<lpage>313</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosmans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatzaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2005</year>) <article-title>A catalogue of the spiders of Greece. A critical review of all spider species cited from Greece with their localities</article-title>. <source>Arachnological contributions. Newsletter of the Belgian Arachnological Society</source>. <volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatzaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnedo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the epigean representatives of the spider subfamily Harpacteinae (Araneae: Dysderidae) on the island of Crete.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1169</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Deeleman-Reinhold</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The genus Rhode and the harpacteine genera Stalagtia, Folkia, Minotauria, and Kaemis (Araneae, Dysderidae) of Yugoslavia nad Crete, with remark on the genus Harpactea.</article-title> <source>Revue Arachnologique</source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>105</fpage>-<lpage>135</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazarov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A new spider species from Bulgaria, Harpactea terveli sp. n. (Araneae: Dysderidae)</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Academic Research</source>. <volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazarov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A new spider species Harpactea krumi sp. n. from Bulgaria (Araneae, Dysderidae)</article-title>. <source>Acta Zoologica Bulgarica</source>. <volume>62</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazarov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naumova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Two new Harpactea species from Bulgaria (Araneae: Dysderidae)</article-title>. <source>Revue Suisse de Zooogie</source> <volume>117</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nosek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1905</year>)<article-title> Araneiden, Opilionen und Chernetiden.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Penther</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zederbauer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Ergebnisse einer naturwissenschaftlichen Reise zum Erdschias-Dagh (Kleinasien). Annales des naturhistorischer Museum</source>, <publisher-loc>Wien</publisher-loc> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>114</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietzold</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2006</year>) <source>Caucasian Spiders, A faunistic database on the spiders of the Caucasus. Version 1.3.</source> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://caucasus-spiders.info" xlink:type="simple">http://caucasus-spiders.info</ext-link> [accessed 17.V.2010]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2010</year>) <source>The world spider catalog, Version 10.5. New York: American Museum of Natural History</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://research.amnh.org/entomology/spiders/catalog/DYSDERIDAE.html" xlink:type="simple">http://research.amnh.org/entomology/spiders/catalog/DYSDERIDAE.html</ext-link> [accessed 17.V.2010]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Řezáč</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Description of Harpactea sadistica n. sp. (Araneae: Dysderidae) — a haplogyne spider with reduced female genitalia.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1698</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Keer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosmans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2010</year>) <article-title>On some new Harpactea and Stalagtia Species from Lesbos, Greece (Araneae: Dysderidae)</article-title>. <source>Acta Zoologica Bulgarica</source>. <volume>61</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>