<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.218.2380</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>New species of 
                    <italic>Vomerina</italic> Winterton (Diptera, Therevidae, Agapophytinae) from Australia
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Winterton</surname>
                        <given-names>Shaun L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:37F5AC48-EC3A-47ED-902B-2BD1467CCA72</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Ferguson</surname>
                        <given-names>David J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:63734EC6-6992-43F6-A1BD-1450E16F1EA6</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>California State Collection of Arthropods, California Department of Food &amp; Agriculture, Sacramento, California, USA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Australian National Insect Collection, CSIRO Ecosystem Sciences, Black Mountain, Canberra, Australia
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Shaun L Winterton (<email xlink:type="simple">wintertonshaun@gmail.com</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: M.Hauser</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>30</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>218</issue>
            <fpage>65</fpage>
            <lpage>75</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>17</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>27</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Shaun L. Winterton, David J. Ferguson</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple"> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:30728FEF-8D76-4C05-8F30-E3249532B64D</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Two new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina</tp:taxon-name></italic> Winterton, 2007 (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina comapenis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina micora</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>) are described from New South Wales (Australia).</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Asiloidea</kwd>
                <kwd>Therevidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Australia</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The endemic Australasian stiletto fly (<tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Therevidae</tp:taxon-name>) fauna is exclusively placed in two subfamilies, <tp:taxon-name>Agapophytinae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Therevinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Winterton 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">2011</xref>). A key to genera of the region can be found in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Winterton (2011)</xref>. <tp:taxon-name>Therevinae</tp:taxon-name> are a diverse, cosmopolitan subfamily while <tp:taxon-name>Agapophytinae</tp:taxon-name> are endemic to Australasia and South America. <tp:taxon-name>Agapophytinae</tp:taxon-name> comprise 197 species in 26 genera; 23 genera in Australasia and three genera (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Entesia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Oldroyd, 1968, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Melanothereva</tp:taxon-name></italic> Malloch, 1932 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pachyrrhiza</tp:taxon-name></italic> Philippi, 1865) in Argentina and Chile (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Winterton 2006</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina</tp:taxon-name></italic> Winterton, <!--PageBreak-->2007 is a previously monotypic Australian genus of distinctively black stiletto flies with a matte white to silver pleural stripe. The genus can be differentiated from all other <tp:taxon-name>Agapophytinae</tp:taxon-name> by this coloration, and by the male gonocoxites having a large plow-shaped ventral lobe and lacking a medial atrium. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the putative sister genus to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bonjeania</tp:taxon-name></italic> Irwin &amp; Lyneborg, 1989, another endemic Australian genus of 18 described species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Winterton 2007</xref>). Two new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina comapenis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina micora</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.) are described and figured herein from New South Wales (Australia). A revised diagnosis of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina</tp:taxon-name></italic> and a key to species are also presented.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Adult morphological terminology follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">McAlpine (1981)</xref> as modified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Winterton et al. (1999a)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Winterton (2006)</xref>. Genitalia were macerated in 10% KOH at room temperature for one day to remove soft tissue, then rinsed in distilled water and dilute acetic acid, and dissected in 80% ethanol. Preparations were then placed into glycerine, with images made with the aid of a digital camera. Specimen images at different focal points were taken using a digital camera and subsequently combined into a serial montage image using Helicon Focus (©HeliconSoft). Genitalia preparations were placed in glycerine in a genitalia vial mounted on the pin beneath the specimen. The following collection acronyms are cited in the text: Australian National Insect Collection (Canberra) (ANIC), Australian Museum (AM).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Vomerina</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7781FCA5-2F6F-49CF-B629-1CAB9799A914</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Vomerina</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Winterton, 2007</tp:taxon-authority>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                    <title>Type species.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina humbug</tp:taxon-name></italic> Winterton, 2007: 22.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Body length 6.5–8.0 mm. Body glossy black with matte white (or silver) lateral stripe of dense pubescence on pleuron, usually extending to anterior segments of abdomen; male frons wider than ocellar tubercle at narrowest point; parafacial setae absent; male with single row of postocular setae; lower frons and face slightly to greatly protruding anteriorly; antenna length shorter than or equal to head length; scape cylindrical or bulbous; flagellum conical, style terminal; sternum with medial furrow lacking setal pile; posterior surface of mid coxa lacking setal pile; wing cell <italic>m<sub>3</sub></italic> closed; elongate velutum patches present on fore and hind femora; femora without macrosetae; male genitalia without medial atrium, inner gonocoxal process absent or greatly reduced; ventral lobe large, plowshare-shaped, projecting posteromedially with dense medial covering of velutum; dorsal apodeme of parameral sheath well sclerotized; ejaculatory apodeme and lateral ejaculatory apodeme short; gonocoxal apodeme much shorter than<!--PageBreak--> gonocoxite length; female with three spermathecae; spermathecal ducts joined to common spermathecal sac duct; acanthophorite spines A1 and A2 present, well developed.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Winterton (2007)</xref> erected <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina</tp:taxon-name></italic> based on the male of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina humbug</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The stripe of pubescence on the lower portion of the pleuron is distinctively matte white (almost glaucous gray) in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina humbug</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina comapenis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., where it continues onto the posterior surface of the head and onto the anterior segments of the abdomen. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina micora</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., the stripe of dense pubescence is present only on the thorax and is silver. This type of pleural stripe is also found in many species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bonjeania</tp:taxon-name></italic> (e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bonjeania zwicki</tp:taxon-name></italic> Winterton, 2007) and numerous species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Parapsilocephala</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kröber, 1912 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acraspisa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kröber, 1912. There is a distinct similarity in body shape between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina</tp:taxon-name></italic> and certain <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bonjeania</tp:taxon-name></italic> species such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bonjeania webbi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Winterton 2007</xref> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bonjeania bapsis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Winterton, 2007. All have a conical head and similar body shape, but most <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bonjeania</tp:taxon-name></italic> species lack the distinct pleural stripe of pubescence, have a medial atrium and small ventral lobe on the male gonocoxites, while females have only a single spermatheca.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Included species">
                    <title>Included species.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina comapenis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina humbug</tp:taxon-name></italic> Winterton, 2007, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina micora</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to Vomerina species">
                    <title>Key to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina</tp:taxon-name></italic> species</title>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing with costal area slightly infuscate, rest of wing hyaline; frons strongly projecting anteriorly; scape longer than flagellum, bulbous; pale setae on katatergite</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina humbug</tp:taxon-name></italic> Winterton, 2007</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wing infuscation more extensive; frons projecting only slightly; scape shorter than flagellum, cylindrical, not bulbous; dark setae on katatergite</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matte white lateral pubescence extending from pleuron onto anterior segments of abdomen as a continuous stripe; hind tibia with yellow band midway</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina comapenis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">–2</xref>)</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silver lateral pubescence on pleuron only, absent from abdomen; hind tibia without yellow band</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina micora</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">–7</xref>)</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Vomerina</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">comapenis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9249B712-FFB3-47A7-A34F-89EC0ECE7461</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Vomerina_comapenis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">–4</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                    <title>Type material.</title>
                    <p>– <bold>Holotype</bold> male, AUSTRALIA: <bold>New South Wales:</bold> Boonanghi State Forest, 24 km W Kempsey, vic.[inity of] ‘The Blowhole’ [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">-31.0747, 152.5663</named-content>], 8.x.1993, G. &amp; A. Williams, riparian zone, dry rainforest (AM).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Wing dark infuscate; frons slightly projecting around antennal base; scape cylindrical, shorter than flagellum, not bulbous; black setae on katatergite; white pubescence on pleuron extending onto abdomen; male abdomen black apically; articulated inner gonocoxal process present, greatly reduced.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body length: 7.0 mm. <italic>Head</italic>. Frons flat, surface rugose-striated medially, wider than ocellar tubercle at narrowest point, antennal base positioned low on frons; lower frons and face slightly protruding around antennal base; frons glossy black, silver-grey pubescence along eye margin; short setae sparsely distributed on lower frons; narrow medial stripe of silver pubescence around antennal bases on face, parafacial and along margin of eye; ocellar tubercle flat, glossy black; occiput concave, black, overlain with dense grey pubescence; single row of very short, black postocular setae; gena black, overlain with white pubescence admixed with white, elongate setae; palpus and labellum brown-black with sparse, dark setae; antenna black, onl<!--PageBreak-->y slightly shorter than head; short dark setae on scape and pedicel; scape shorter than flagellum length, cylindrical, with grey pubescence; flagellum conical with brownish suffusion. <italic>Thorax</italic>. Black, scutum and scutellum overlain with grey-black pubescence admixed with relatively short, dark setae; scutum with narrow, faint dorsocentral and medial stripe of pale grey pubescence; scutal macrosetae black; pleuron, sternum and coxae glossy black; distinctive broad stripe of matte white to silver pubescence along pleuron length; elongate pale setae on proepisternum, katepisternum and coxae, black setae on anepisternum and katatergite; legs black with pale setae of various lengths on femora, dark yellow band midway on mid and hind tibiae and basitarsus; wing smoky infuscate; venation dark; haltere brown-black; scutal chaetotaxy (pairs): notopleural, <!--PageBreak-->4; supra alar, 1; post alar, 1; dorsocentral, 1–2; scutellar, 1. <italic>Abdomen</italic>. Glossy black, uniform scattered pale setae, longer laterally, white-grey pubescence laterally on sternites 1–3. <italic>Male genitalia</italic>. Gonocoxite with outer gonocoxal processes reduced; articulated inner gonocoxal process greatly reduced; gonostylus broad; ventral lobe large, plowshare-shaped, projecting posteroventrally with velutinous pubescence on ventral surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">–4</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina comapenis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male habitus, oblique view. Body length = 7.0 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-218-065-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina comapenis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male habitus, lateral view. Body length = 7.0 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-218-065-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 3.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina comapenis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male terminalia, lateral view. Scale line = 0.2 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-218-065-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 4.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina comapenis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male terminalia, ventral view. Scale line = 0.2 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-218-065-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The species epithet is derived from the Latin, <italic>coma</italic> hairy; <italic>penis</italic>, intromitant organ; referring to the vestiture of the male genitalia.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina comapenis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is muchsmaller in body size to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina humbug</tp:taxon-name></italic> and can be further distinguished by the frons being only slightly projecting, a non-bulbous antennal scape and darker wings. This species is distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina micora</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the lateral velutum stripe extending onto the abdomen, abdomen uniformly black, and the scutum lacking grey pubescent dorsocentral stripes. The female is unknown.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Vomerina</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">micora</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:79F15746-5D56-4BB6-8D2A-4CF20E68AC0F</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Vomerina_micora</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">–7</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                    <title>Type material.</title>
                    <p><bold>– Holotype</bold> female, AUSTRALIA: <bold>New South Wales:</bold> South Black Range, 8 km E Hoskinstown, Fluoro U.V. light trap [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">-35.4183, 149.5347</named-content>], 11.ii.2010, 1180m D. J. Ferguson (ANIC 29 029246)</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Wing dark infuscate; scape cylindrical, shorter than flagellum; black setae on katatergite; silver pubescence on pleuron not extending onto abdomen; scutum with two faint dorsocentral stripes bordering a darker medial stripe; female abdominal segments 7–8 orange.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body length: 6.5 mm. <italic>Head</italic>. Frons flat, rugose-striated medially, wider than ocellar tubercle at narrowest point, antennal base positioned low on frons; lower frons and face protruding only slightly with curved ridge above antennal base; frons glossy black, short setae sparsely distributed on upper frons, silver-grey pubescence on parafacial, oral cavity and along eye margin; ocellar tubercle flat, black; occiput concave, black, overlain with grey pubescence; few relatively strong short black postocular setae followed by weaker setae in several irregular rows; elongate black setae along lower postocular admixed with white setae along gena; gena black, overlain with silver-grey pubescence; palpus and labellum brown-black with sparse, dark setae; antenna two-thirds length of head; scape and pedicel black with short dark setae; scape about half length of flagellum, cylindrical, with grey pubescence; flagellum with red-brownish suffusion and grey pubescence. <italic>Thorax</italic>. Glossy black; scutum and scutellum overlain with grey-black pubescence<!--PageBreak--> admixed with relatively short, dark setae; scutum with pair of narrow dorsocentral stripes of sparse pale-grey pubescence bordering a darker medial stripe; scutal macrosetae black; pleuron and sternum glossy black; broad stripe of silver pubescence along pleuron from proepisternum to hind coxa; fore and middle coxae dark brown, hind coxa black; posterior surface of hind coxa with silver pubescence; elongate pale setae on proepisternum and coxae, black setae on katatergite; fore and middle femora dark brown, hind femur black; elongate yellowish-grey velutum patches to ventral surface of hind and apical half of fore femora; pale setae of various lengths on all femora; tibiae black to dark brown; mid and hind basitarsi dark yellow basally; wing dark infuscate, venation and stigma dark grey; haltere matte brown; scutal chaetotaxy (pairs): notopleural, 4; supra alar, 1; post alar, 1; dorsocentral, 4; scutellar, 1. <italic>Abdomen</italic>. Glossy black with short dark setae distributed evenly; erect whitish setae laterally on segments 1 and 2; segments 7 and 8 orange in colour with sparse, erect black setae. <italic>Female genitalia</italic>. Three spermathecae and a relatively small, simple spermathecal sac.</p>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 5.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina micora</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female habitus. Body length = 8.0 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-218-065-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 6.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina micora</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female habitus, oblique view. Body length = 8.0 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-218-065-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 7.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina micora</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female habitus, lateral view. Body length = 8.0 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-218-065-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The species epithet is derived from Latin, <italic>mico</italic> shine; <italic>ora</italic> border; reference to the silver-grey pubescence border of the eye.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                    <title>Comments.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina micora</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. is more slender in body than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina humbug</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina comapenis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and can be distinguished by the dorsocentral stripes on the scutum, short, cylindrical scape, and the pleural stripe not extending onto the abdomen. The orange terminal abdominal segments may prove to be a sexually dimorphic character, as is found in many other therevid species. The male is unknown.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We thank Mr. Chris Manchester (CSIRO) for preparing the photographic images of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Vomerina micora</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. This research was supported by the National Science Foundation (NSF-DEB-0614213) and the Australian Biological Resource Study (ABRS-209-48) to SLW. Statements and viewpoints expressed herein do not necessarily reflect the opinion of NSF or ABRS<!--PageBreak-->.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McAlpine</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<article-title> Morphology and terminology-Adults. In: McAlpine JF, Peterson BV, Shewell GE, Teskey HJ, Vockeroth JR, Wood DM (Eds) Manual of Nearctic Diptera.</article-title> <source>Research Branch, Agriculture Canada Monograph </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Winterton</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeates</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999a</year>)<article-title> Systematics of <italic>Nanexila</italic> Winterton &amp; Irwin, gen. nov. (Diptera: Therevidae) from Australia.</article-title> <source>Invertebrate Taxonomy </source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>308</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/IT97029">10.1071/IT97029</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Winterton</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeates</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999b</year>)<article-title> Phylogenetic revision of the <italic>Taenogera</italic> Kröber genus-group (Diptera: Therevidae), with descriptions of two new genera.</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Entomology</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>274</fpage>-<lpage>290</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1440-6055.1999.00126.x">10.1046/j.1440-6055.1999.00126.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Winterton</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> New species of <italic>Eupsilocephala</italic> Kröber from Australia (Diptera: Therevidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1372</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Winterton</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> New species of <italic>Acraspisoides</italic> Hill &amp; Winterton and <italic>Bonjeania</italic> Irwin &amp; Lyneborg (Diptera: Therevidae: Agapophytinae), with the description of a new genus.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1438</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Winterton</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Revision of the stiletto fly genus <italic>Neodialineura</italic> Mann (Diptera: Therevidae): an empirical example of cybertaxonomy.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>2157</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Winterton</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> New stiletto flies in the genera <italic>Acupalpa</italic> Kröber and <italic>Pipinnipons</italic> Winterton (Diptera: Therevidae: Agapophytinae) described using cybertaxonomic tools.</article-title> <source>Zookeys </source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>