<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.255.3774</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Twentieth century occurrence of the Long-Beaked Echidna 
                    <italic>Zaglossus bruijnii</italic> in the Kimberley region of Australia
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Helgen</surname>
                        <given-names>Kristofer M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Miguez</surname>
                        <given-names>Roberto Portela</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>James L. Kohen</surname>
                        <given-names></given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname> Lauren E. Helgen</surname>
                        <given-names></given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Division of Mammals, Department of Vertebrate Zoology, National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, P.O. Box 37012, MRC 108, Washington, D.C. 20013-7012, USA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Mammal Section, Department of Life Sciences, The Natural History Museum, Cromwell Road, London SW7 5BD, UK
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Department of Biological Sciences, Macquarie University, North Ryde, NSW 2109, Australia
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: W. Bogdanowicz</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>28</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>255</issue>
            <fpage>103</fpage>
            <lpage>132</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>5</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>31</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Kristofer M. Helgen, Roberto Portela Miguez, James L. Kohen,  Lauren E. Helgen</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The monotreme genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the largest egg-laying mammal, comprises several endangered taxa today known only from New Guinea. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is considered to be extinct in Australia, where its apparent occurrence (in addition to the large echidna genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Megalibgwilia</tp:taxon-name></italic>) is recorded by Pleistocene fossil remains, as well as from convincing representations in Aboriginal rock art from Arnhem Land (Northern Territory). Here we report on the existence and history of a well documented but previously overlooked museum specimen (skin and skull) of the Western Long-Beaked Echidna (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic>) collected by John T. Tunney at Mount Anderson in the West Kimberley region of northern Western Australia in 1901, now deposited in the Natural History Museum, London. Possible accounts from living memory of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> are provided by Aboriginal inhabitants from Kununurra in the East Kimberley. We conclude that, like <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is part of the modern fauna of the Kimberley region of Western Australia, where it apparently survived as a rare element into the twentieth century, and may still survive.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Extinction</kwd>
                <kwd>Kimberley</kwd>
                <kwd>monotreme</kwd>
                <kwd>Pleistocene survival</kwd>
                <kwd>rock art</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Zaglossus</italic>
<!--PageBreak-->                
                </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The egg-laying mammals, or monotremes (Monotremata), are the sister group to all other extant mammals and are known as living animals only from the Australian continent, incorporating the modern landmasses of Tasmania, Australia, and New Guinea, which share a continental shelf that is periodically united during times of lowered sea levels as a single continuous landmass (“Sahul” or “Meganesia”). There are two extant monotreme families. The platypus, <tp:taxon-name>Ornithorhynchidae</tp:taxon-name>, is represented by a single living genus and species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ornithorhynchus anatinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Shaw, 1799), a semi-aquatic monotreme distributed throughout eastern Australia from tropical Queensland south to Tasmania and Kangaroo Island. The echidnas, <tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossidae</tp:taxon-name>, are classified in two living genera, the smaller short-beaked echidna (genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>), represented by one species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus aculeatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Shaw, 1792), and the larger long-beaked echidnas (genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>), with three living species currently recognized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Flannery and Groves 1998</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus aculeatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is one of the most widely distributed Meganesian mammals, occurring in a wide range of habitats throughout Tasmania, Australia, and much of New Guinea. The long-beaked echidnas, today known only from New Guinea, are inhabitants of rainforests and subalpine meadows—<italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Peters and Doria, 1876), distributed in western New Guinea, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bartoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thomas, 1907a), distributed in central and eastern New Guinea, mainly at higher elevations, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus attenboroughi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Flannery and Groves, 1998, reported to date only from the Cyclops Mountains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Flannery and Groves 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Groves 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Baillie et al. 2009</xref>), an outlying mountain range along the north coast of New Guinea (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).
            </p>
            <p>Though <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is regarded as the only extant echidna in Australia, until the late Pleistocene several additional tachyglossids, all larger than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, occurred in Australia. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Megalibgwilia owenii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Krefft, 1868) (often called <italic><tp:taxon-name>Megalibgwilia ramsayi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a junior synonym, in current literature) was a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>-sized echidna (estimated mass <italic>circa</italic> 10 kg, but more robust than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and with a less elongate or downcurved rostrum) known from Pleistocene localities in New South Wales (Wellington Caves), South Australia (Naracoorte), Tasmania (Montagu Caves and King Island), and south-western Western Australia (Tight Entrance Cave) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">Murray 1978b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Griffiths et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B111">Turney et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">Prideaux et al. 2010</xref>), indicating a distribution centered on more temperate regions of the continent. “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>” <italic>hacketti</italic> Glauert, 1914, the largest monotreme yet discovered (estimated mass <italic>circa</italic> 20 kg), is documented only from Pleistocene postcranial remains from south-western Western Australia (Mammoth Cave); its generic placement has always been provisional pending the discovery of cranial material or detailed comparative taxonomic study of tachyglossid postcrania (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Griffiths et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Long et al. 2002</xref>). Postcranial remains of a relatively gracile <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>-sized echidna, provisionally referred to the living <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, have been reported from the Pleistocene of South Australia (Henschke’s Quarry Cave at Naracoorte) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Murray 1978a</xref> [but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">Pledge (1980)</xref>, who considered this more likely a “giant <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>”]), and Aboriginal rock art corresponding to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> cf. <italic>bruijnii</italic>) is compellingly recorded from Arnhem Land, Northern Territory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">Murray and Chaloupka 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Lewis 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Chaloupka and Murray 1986</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Thus, at least four echidna species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus aculeatus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Megalibgwilia oweni</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic>“Z.” hacketti</italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> cf. <italic>bruijnii</italic>, constitute the known Quaternary tachyglossid fauna of the Australian continent south of New Guinea.
            </p>
            <p>Here we report an overlooked modern museum specimen (skin, skull, and forelimb skeleton) of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> that was apparently collected in 1901 in the West Kimberley region of north-western Australia by the Australian naturalist and collector John T. Tunney (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Based on an agreement between Lord L. Walter Rothschild, the eccentric naturalist who built up an astonishingly large personal collection of natural history specimens in his private museum in Tring (in the county Hertfordshire outside of London), and Bernard Henry Woodward, the London-born director of the Western Australian Museum in Perth, Tunney was commissioned by Rothschild to travel through some of the most remote areas of northern Australia in the first years of the twentieth century in order to collect butterflies, moths, mammals, and birds for Tring, and Aboriginal cultural artifacts for the museum at Perth. From April 1901 to November 1903, in a pioneering effort, Tunney collected natural history specimens and cultural artifacts along a transect that extended from the Pilbara Region in Western Australia to the South Alligator River in Northern <!--PageBreak-->Territory, before returning to Perth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B104">Thomas 1904a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Hartert 1905</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B118">Whittell 1954</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B100">Storr 1966</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Gray 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Chadwick 2008</xref>). On this northern Australian expedition, Tunney obtained the first specimens of various mammals previously unknown to science, including the small dasyurid marsupial <italic><tp:taxon-name>Antechinus bellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thomas, 1904a), the rats <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rattus tunneyi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thomas, 1904a) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rattus colletti</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thomas, 1904c), and two larger mammals, both kangaroos—the Black Wallaroo <italic><tp:taxon-name>Macropus bernardus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">Rothschild 1904</xref>) and Rothschild’s Rock-Wallaby <italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrogale rothschildi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thomas, 1904b). Tunney also collected what were to become the type specimens of several other then-undescribed mammal taxa known by a few other museum specimens at the time, including the small dasyurid marsupial <italic><tp:taxon-name>Phascogale pirata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thomas, 1904a; the West Kimberley and Northern Territory subspecies of the wallaroo (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Macropus robustus woodwardi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thomas, 1901, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Macropus robustus alligatoris</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thomas, 1904a, respectively); and the Arnhem Land subspecies of the Nabarlek or Pygmy Rock-Wallaby, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrogale concinna canescens</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thomas, 1909.
            </p>
            <p>Despite the importance of Tunney’s mammalogical collections, no full report on these materials has ever been published. The most important account is M.R. Oldfield Thomas’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B104">1904a</xref>) preliminary discussion written after receipt and early review of Tu<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->nney’s material received at the Tring Museum. (The Tunney collection was transferred, along with the rest of Rothschild’s mammal collections, from Tring to the Natural History Museum, London, in 1939 following Rothschild’s death in 1937.) One of the most important Tunney specimens that was never critically reported is what appears to be a north-western Australian specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> collected in 1901, which we discuss here. This specimenchallenges current thinking about the timing of extinction of the genus in Australia and offers new insight into northern Australian biogeography and the ecology of this critically endangered monotreme lineage.
            </p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Map of the Greater Australian continent. Map includes an outline of the larger land mass know as “Sahul” or “Meganesia” that forms when the continental shelf (dark grey) is exposed during glaciation. Overlaid is the modern distribution of the three recognized species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bartoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> (red), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (yellow), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus attenboroughi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (blue diamond), with the Kimberley record of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted by a yellow star. Other possible Australian records of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> cf. <italic>bruijnii</italic> are numbered by general locality: <bold>1</bold> Pleistocene fossil remains from Naracoorte, South Australia, referred to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> cf. <italic>bruijnii</italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Murray (1978a)</xref> <bold>2</bold> Aboriginal rock art (probably late Pleistocene in age) from Arnhem Land, Northern Territory (see Figure 2) <bold>3</bold> Aboriginal reports of a second, larger echidna taxon, in addition to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, present in the East Kimberley (Kununurra, Western Australia) in recent (20th century) memory (see text).</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-103-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 2.</label>
                <caption><p>Australian rock art of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Photograph of an Aboriginal rock art illustration from Arnhem Land depicting the characteristic long and down-curved beak (and whitish head of some specimens) of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">Murray and Chaloupka 1984</xref>). Photograph by G. Chaloupka.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-103-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 3.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Dramatis personae</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Clockwise from top: Australian natural history collector John T. Tunney (1871–1929), preparing specimens on the northern Australian expeditionary efforts during which his <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen was collected; M.R. (Michael Rogers) Oldfield Thomas (1858–1929), mammal taxonomist at the British Museum (Natural History), London, who studied the Tunney <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen; Lord L. (Lionel) Walter Rothschild (1868–1937), eccentric collector and naturalist who used his family fortune to amass a very large personal scientific collection, which became the Zoological Museum at Tring and included the Tunney <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen. Tunney portrait courtesy of the Western Australian Museum, Perth; Rothschild and Thomas portraits courtesy of the Natural History Museum, London.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-103-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
            <title>Methods</title>
            <sec sec-type="Museums">
                <title>Museums</title>
                <p>Specimens discussed in this paper are stored in the collections of the American Museum of Natural History, New York , USA (AMNH); the Natural History Museum, London, UK (BMNH); the Museum of Comparative Zoology, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA (MCZ); the Museum Zoologicum Bogor, Cibinong, Indonesia (MZB); the National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C., USA (USNM); and the Western Australian Museum, Perth, Australia (WAM).</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <sec sec-type="The Kimberley Zaglossus specimen">
                <title>The Kimberley Zaglossus specimen</title>
                <p>During a visit to the Natural History Museum, London, in 2009, the first author studied a museum skin of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (BMNH 1939.3315; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5"></xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6"></xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7"></xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8"></xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>), bearing original tags from John T. Tunney, stored among supposedly unprovenanced specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. This skin also has an associated cranium, mandibles, and distal right forelimb elements, which were extracted from the study skin early in the twentieth century (see below). The tags record the collection of this specimen from Mount Anderson, an inland locality in the West Kimberley region of north-western Western Australia, on 20 November 1901 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>).
                </p>
                <p>Tunney’s typical tags (used by Tunney and some other collectors from the Western Australian Museum in Perth) were strong card tags preprinted with the following categories (see figure in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Chadwick [2008]</xref>): (on one side of the card) “No.” (i.e., field number), “Date” (i.e., date of collection), “Sex” (i.e., male or female), “Colour of Iris” (i.e., eye color, used by Tunney for birds, but generally not for mammals), “Colour of Leg” (used by Tunney for birds, but not for mammals), “Name” (given by Tunney either as the scientific or common name of the species), “Loc.” (i.e., the collection locality); and (on the other side of the card) “Nature of Place where caught” (i.e., habitat), <!--PageBreak-->“Rare or Common” (i.e., an indication of abundance), “H + B.” (i.e., length of head and body), “T.” (i.e., length of tail), and “H. F.” (i.e., length of hind foot).</p>
                <p>Tunney’s tag, written in his characteristic handwriting, and tied with thick sturdy string to the right hindfoot of the specimen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>), bears an original field number (347), a date (“20 Nov. 1901”), reports the specimen’s collection from “conglomerate hills” (“Nature of Place where caught”) at “Mt Anderson (W Kimberley)” (locality),  and indicates that it was “Rare” (a classification only occasionally reported on his mammal tags). Tunney originally marked the sex of the animal as female (“♀”), which was later corrected in pen on the tag to “young ♂” (reflecting a mammal difficult to sex, as echidnas can be). Tunney left the “Name” field blank on his tag, which is somewhat unusual—he usually reported a scientific or common name on his mammal tags. This may indicate that Tunney was uncertain exactly what species he had before him. Tunney also usually reported standard length measurements on tags for his mammal and bird specimens (i.e., head-body, tail, and hind foot lengths), but in this case he gave the measurements of the specimen only as “21 inches over back from tip to tip” and “under measurement 20 inches”, indicating a mammal for which the head-body and tail lengths were unusually difficult to measure. Thetotal study skin, as now prepared, still measures about 21 inches measured over the dorsum and 20 inches measured along the underside. The specimen also bears a smaller field tag, worn and dirty, that is made of cloth-like paper, attached to the right hindleg with wire, and bearing only the field number, “N 347” (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>).
                </p>
                <p>The specimen is a well-made study skin, with the hindlegs directed posteriorly and the forelegs folded back against the underside (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). It was originally prepared with the skull and parts of the limbs retained intact inside the skin (the skull and right forelimb were apparently later removed from the skin and prepared in England—see below). The pelage is quite pale brown, and the specimen is rather sparsely furred, with mostly white spines, and has spines invading the sides of the belly, claws only on the middle three digits of both forefeet and both hindfeet, and hindleg spurs.
                </p>
                <p>This specimen was misidentified as a Short-beaked echidna before its skull was extracted and studied. Identified by field number (347), it was listed as “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Echidna aculeata</tp:taxon-name></italic>” (i.e., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus aculeatus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) when it was sent from Australia to Rothschild at Tring, and identified as such in a letter dated 25 April 1904 sent by Bernard Woodward to Oldfield Thomas in London, discussing details of the mammal specimens collected by Tunney (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>). Soon after its arrival at Tring, ectoparasite specimens taken from this skin formed the basis for the description of a new species of tick, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Amblyomma australiense</tp:taxon-name></italic>, by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">Neumann (1905)</xref>, and a new species of flea, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Echidnophaga liopus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Jordan and Rothschild (1906)</xref>. Both of these publications still listed the identity of the host as “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Echidna aculeata</tp:taxon-name></italic>” (these parasitological discoveries are discussed further below).
                </p>
                <p>Though the identification of this specimen as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has gone unreported in the literature until now, we are not the first researchers to notice that this specimen provides a modern record for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Western Australia. Oldfield Thomas, arguably the greatest mammalogical taxonomist of all time, examined Tunney’s specimens when they arrived in England, and made notes that indicate he understood Tunney’s<!--PageBreak--> specimen was a Kimberley <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Thomas would have known that the Tunney skin in question was a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> rather than a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> the moment he saw it, even if Rothschild was unaware of this. Thomas apparently removed the skull (the skull, by its lack of sutural ossifications, shows the animal to be a nearly mature subadult) and the bones of the right forelimb (articulated radius, ulna, and forefoot) from the study <!--PageBreak-->skin. The skull is intact apart from some missing basicranial fragments and is labelled “Kimberley” in Thomas’ handwriting on the palate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>); it also bears two labels in Thomas’ handwriting, one identifying the specimen as an “imm[ature]. Zaglossus, coll[ected by]. Tunney” and the other noting that the skull compares favorably to an immature specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Fakfak (western New Guinea) preserved in the Zoological Museum in Amsterdam. The dentary is also marked in ink with the word “Kimberley” in Thomas’ handwriting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). Thomas labeled the forelimb “Zaglossus Kimberley N.W.A. (Tunney)” (i.e., N.W.A. = north-western Australia) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). These labels indicate to us that Thomas recognized that the specimen was indeed a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and that he was satisfied that it had been collected by Tunney in the Kimberley region of Australia. We suspect that Thomas extracted the right forelimb elements from the skin of the specimen to see if its humerus was preserved. He would have wanted to compare it to the humeri of the large fossil echidnas that had previously been described from Australia; the holotypes of two large echidna taxa described from the Australian Pleistocene (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Echidna owenii</tp:taxon-name></italic> Krefft, 1868, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Echidna ramsayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Owen, 1884, now classified in the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Megalibgwilia</tp:taxon-name></italic>) are right humeri (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Mahoney and Ride 1975</xref>). Only the radius, ulna, and distal elements of the manus were present in the skin, however. An x-ray of the skin confirms that the right forelimb and skull of this specimen were indeed extracted from the skin, with their impressions, still evident inside the skin, closely matching the osteological elements.
                </p>
                <p>It is not clear on what date Thomas extracted the skull and forelimb of the Tunney specimen, but he may have written the accompanying labels after 1907 (or replaced them with newer labels if he had written them earlier), because until at least 1907 Thomas was apparently under the impression that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acanthoglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (rather than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) was the correct generic name for the long-beaked echidnas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B107">Thomas 1907a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B108">1907b</xref>), though usage of this name wavered at the time. Universally accepted usage of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Gill 1877</xref>, which predates the generic synonyms <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acanthoglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Gervais 1877a</xref> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Proechidna</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Gervais 1877b</xref>(names which had previously enjoyed wide usage), followed from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Allen’s (1912)</xref> influential monograph on the genus, though earlier authors, including Rothschild, had regularly pointed out that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was the earliest generic name (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Gill 1885</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">Palmer 1895</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Coues 1895</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">Rothschild 1905a</xref>). In any case, Thomas died in 1929 (Thomas and Tunney both passed away in June 1929) without discussing Tunney’s <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen in any publication, which is surprising considering that Thomas was such a prolific author of papers on mammals (he produced approximately 1100 publications on mammal taxonomy, naming 2900 mammal taxa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Hill 1990</xref>]). We can identify several reasons why Thomas may not have prioritized publishing a note about this specimen. The most important might be Rothschild’s eccentric penchant for echidnas (along with kangaroos—similar to his personal interest in ratites amongst his ornithological collections [M. Rothschild 1983]), which may have excluded Thomas from freely publishing on these holdings at Tring. Rothschild permitted Thomas to publish many papers based on Tring mammals, but Rothschild was very fond of kangaroos and echidnas, keeping various kinds alive at his family’s estate (M. Rothschild 1983), and it seems he preferred to publish reviews<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> of Tring’s kangaroos and echidnas on his own, except perhaps where Thomas chose to name them in Rothschild’s honor (as in the case of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrogale rothschildi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thomas, 1904b). This may have suited Thomas fine, as Rothschild’s publications on kangaroos and echidnas were often premature and incompletely prepared and reasoned (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">Rothschild 1903</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">1904</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">1905b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">1905c</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">1907</xref>) (with some important exceptions, such as the tree kangaroo monograph published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B92">Rothschild and Dollman 1936</xref>), in general falling far short of Thomas’ authoritative command of these groups, which was established early in Thomas’ career (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B102">Thomas 1888</xref>). Another reason that Thomas did not publish on the specimen could be that it was not clearly describable as a new taxon (the Thomasian special focus), the single specimen available being indistinguishable from specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> from western New Guinea. With the wealth of clearly new mammal taxa Thomas had available to describe, he may have set this echidna specimen to the side, hoping that additional Australian specimens, especially a mature specimen or a series, might become available so that he could better understand the characteristics of the Kimberley <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.
                </p>
                <p>While Thomas’ impressions as to the identity of the Tunney <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen seem clear, it is not clear whether Rothschild was aware that the specimen was a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>,or if so, whether he accepted its authenticity. Rothschild published several observations on echidna taxonomy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">Rothschild 1892</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">1905a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">1913</xref>), including one co-authored with Thomas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B110">Thomas and Rothschild 1922</xref>), and one in which Thomas abstained or was excluded from authorship (Rothschild, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B110">Thomas and Rothschild 1922</xref>). Like Thomas, Rothschild never mentioned Tunney’s <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen in a publication before he died in 1937. In 1939, the Tring mammal collection was transferred to the BMNH, and most of it is now housed at South Kensington. This is when the echidna specimen was given the BMNH accession number 1939.3315. The BMNH Mammalogy accession register only mentions a skin for this specimen, raising the possibility that the skull (which confirmed the identity of the specimen beyond doubt to Thomas) had been retained on loan by Thomas at South Kensington, perhaps to be described one day, and was only reunited with the skin on its permanent arrival to the BMNH in 1939. Importantly, the Tunney <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen bears a third tag, added to the right hind leg either at the Tring Museum or when the specimen arrived with the Rothschild Bequest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>). This tag disputes the Tunney association of the specimen, noting, “other label apparently does not belong to this specimen” on one side, and “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijni goodfellowi</tp:taxon-name></italic> see Nov. Zoologicae vol 20, 1913” on the other side. The author of this label has been identified as Fred Young, who was a taxidermist at the Tring Zoological Museum, by Effie Ward, Tring librarian. The 1913 paper mentioned on this tag (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">Rothschild 1913</xref>) discusses <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens at BMNH and Tring that Rothschild was aware of in 1913, and lists them by taxon, age, sex, and preparation. The Tunney <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen, being an immature male skin (and, possibly, extracted skull) is not clearly associable with any specimens identified in this paper. The paper in question provides a taxonomic key for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> identification, and we take the tag’s reference to this <italic><tp:taxon-name>Novitates Zoologicae</tp:taxon-name></italic> paper to refer to this key. In effect, our understanding is that the person who wrote the message on this <!--PageBreak-->third tag resorted to using Rothschild’s key, and discovered that the Tunney specimen keys out to Rothschild’s concept of “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii goodfellowi”</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a taxon then considered endemic to the island of Salawati (= Salwaty, a continental island off the coast of western New Guinea)in Rothschild’s taxonomic scheme. We suggest that, on account of this specimen’s keyed identification, the writer of this last skin tag seems to have discounted the possibility that Tunney’s original tag details could be correct, and that this was done without any critical examination of the background and data associated with this specimen or consideration of Thomas’ extraction and examination of the skull and forelimb.
                </p>
                <p>From the beginning of our investigations regarding this specimen, we have of course considered whether its original Tunney field tags truly belong to it, or whether they might have been transferred to it by mistake, as the latest tag associated with the specimen implies. However, several lines of evidence point to the fact that Tunney’s<!--PageBreak--> tags were always associated with an echidna, and that this tag was not likely to have been transferred by mistake from a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen to a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen.
                </p>
                <p>In addition to Tunney’s original tag, two sources—correspondence between Perth and London/Tring, and several parasitological publications—establish that Tunney’s specimen (his field number 347) was definitely an echidna, such that we are certain that its original tags were not transferred by mistake from a specimen of some other kind of animal. The specimen was mentioned in the original export paperwork, and discussed in parasitological literature, as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus aculeatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (originally as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Echidna aculeata</tp:taxon-name></italic>), and its tag data, including the difficulty of sexing and the style of measurement, suggest an echidna. Thus the only conceivable mix-up could involve a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen collected by Tunney, with tags that became disassociated from the original specimen, and later erroneously attached to a specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> that came from New Guinea. However, we believe that Tunney’s original tags from Mt. Anderson are authentically associated with this <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen for several reasons. First, the nature and timing of any putative specimen switch is difficult to understand. Tunney collected only a few <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> during his expeditions in northern Australia, and these seem to be accounted for in the WAM and BMNH collections, and we note with interest that these tags were written somewhat differently. For example, on the tag of the only Tunney-collected <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> at BMNH, Tunney provided the name <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->of the species as “Echidna” (left blank on the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> tag), and stated its abundance as “numerous” (“Rare” in the case of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen). Second, such a switch would have to have taken place after the echidna specimen arrived at Tring (in 1903-1904), not earlier in Perth, because no <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen was available in Perth—Tunney never collected in New Guinea, and the WAM has apparently never had a modern <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen in their mammal collection (as judged by details from the WAM accession register). But any switch must have already happened by the time that Thomas first inspected the Tunney specimens sent to Tring, as it seems clear that Thomas accepted that Tunney’s specimen number 347 was a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> collected in the Kimberley region once he was able to make confirming examinations of its skull and forelimb. Thomas had already published one report on Tunney’s 1903-1904 shipment to Tring by 1904 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B104">Thomas 1904a</xref>), indicating that any switch that was unbeknownst to Thomas must have occurred at the very point of arrival at Tring. This is not impossible, but it is very difficult to imagine, especially in light of Rothschild’s clearly very active interest in all incoming echidnas. The Tunney skin came with two original tags, a small tag with field number wired to the leg, and a heavier card tag tied to a leg with strong twine. Both tags would need to have been removed from a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen, and reattached by mistake to one of Rothschild’s few and precious <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> skins at Tring, which is unlikely. A decade later, there were still only 13 <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens identified in the Tring collection, and it is clear from Rothschild’s publications that these were highly valued and carefully curated by Rothschild (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">Rothschild 1913</xref>). In summary, it is highly implausible to envision a switch-up in Perth or in Tring that could explain how tags from an Australian <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen would have become mistakenly associated with a specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> that originated from New Guinea.
                </p>
                <p>Another important consideration is the size of the animal measured by Tunney. Tunney’s tag gives the specimen’s total length measurement as 21 inches (= 533 mm), and this value matches very well the size of the study skin to which it is currently attached, as measured with a flexible measuring tape. This body size measurement is consistent with either a subadult <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (i.e., like the specimen to which it is attached) or an unusually large adult <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Total length measurements of 539-1000 mm have been reported for adult <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Allen 1912</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">Rothschild 1913</xref>). Extremely large <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens only rarely reach the lower limit of this size range. Typical lengths for adult <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> are in the range of 300-450 mm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B120">Wood Jones 1923</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Menkhorst and Knight 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Augee 2005</xref>). An unusually large and aged male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus aculeatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (USNM 283961) from Groote Eylandt, Northern Territory, measuring 555 mm in total length (original field measurements), approximates a maximum body size for the genus. This specimen is by far the largest <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the USNM collection (of about 40 specimens), and is among the very largest and most robust of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens in world museums by skin and skull size (K. Helgen and G. Perri, in litt, 2012). In summary, only the largest <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> outliers on record could match the size of the echidna reported on Tunney’s tag, Tunney’s measurements are consistent with the dimensions of a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> nearing cranial maturity, and Tunney’s measurements are a match for the actual dimensions of the specimen to which his tags are attached<!--PageBreak-->.
                </p>
                <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 4.</label>
                    <caption><p>Study skin of the Kimberley <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (BMNH 1939.3315), bearing the original field tags of John T. Tunney. From top: dorsal, ventral, right lateral, and left lateral views. Scale bar = 5 cm.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-103-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 5.</label>
                    <caption><p>Cranium and dentaries of the Kimberley <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (BMNH 1939.3315). From top: dorsal view of the cranium, dorsal view of the dentaries, ventral view of the cranium, ventral view of the dentaries, and, at bottom, close-up views of Thomas’ labeling of “Kimberley” on the specimen’s palate (left) and dentary (right). Scale bar = 20 cm.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-103-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 6.</label>
                    <caption><p>Articulated right forelimb elements of the Kimberley <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (BMNH 1939.3315). Associated label notes “Zaglossus Kimberley N.W.A. (Tunney)” in Thomas’ handwriting. Ventral view above, dorsal view below. Scale bar = 5 cm.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-103-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 7.</label>
                    <caption><p>John Tunney’s original field labels attached to the skin of BMNH 1939.3315. <bold>A</bold> front of card skin tag (attached with sturdy twine to right ankle of study skin) bearing original data, providing the specimen’s field number, date of collection, age and sex, and locality <bold>B</bold> back of same card skin tag bearing original data, detailing the specimen’s measurements, context of collection, and abundance <bold>C</bold> cloth tag bearing original field number (“N 347”), wired tightly to right ankle of study skin. See text for details.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-103-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 8.</label>
                    <caption><p>Specimen export list. A list of specimens shipped from Perth to Tring included in a letter, dated 25 April 1904, from Bernard Woodward at the Western Australian Museum to Oldfield Thomas, detailing the transfer of Tunney specimens to Rothschild at Tring. The list includes his number 347 (now BMNH 1939.3315), an echidna identified as “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Echidna aculeata</tp:taxon-name></italic>” (i.e. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus aculeatus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) prior to Thomas’ examination of the specimen in London, where he realized it is a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>; we have circled and highlighted this entry in the list.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-103-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 9.</label>
                    <caption><p>Non-original tag (views of front and back) added at Tring or BMNH, and apparently bearing the handwriting of Tring taxidermist Fred Young. The tag bears a note suggesting that the original labels must be incorrect because the specimen corresponds to Rothschild’s concept of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijni goodfellowi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, then considered endemic to the Indonesian island of Salawati, following his 1913 key (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">Rothschild 1913</xref>). The note seems to indicate that knowledge of the importance of this specimen has been obscured since or before the specimen’s transfer from Tring to BMNH, as it was assumed by Young to be a mistake.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-255-103-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="The specimen’s locality">
                <title>The specimen’s locality</title>
                <p>The tag locality provided by Tunney for the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen is “Mt. Anderson, W Kimberley.” First named in 1879 by Alexander Forrest in his “North-West Expedition” from DeGrey to Darwin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Forrest 1880</xref>), Mount Anderson is situated near the Grant Ranges, along the Fitzroy River about 90 km southeast of Derby at approximately 18<sup>o</sup>02'S, 123<sup>o</sup>56'E (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B100">Storr 1966</xref>). In early October, Tunney sailed from Port Hedland to Derby, where he arrived about October 11, and he collected at and in the vicinity of Mount Anderson from the end of October to late November (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B100">Storr 1966</xref>), during which time (20 November 1901) the echidna was collected.
                </p>
                <p>Inland areas of the West Kimberley were settled by white Australians for sheep and cattle pastoralism in the aftermath of Forrest’s surveys (since 1881) but the region has historically been very sparsely inhabited by both European and Aboriginal communities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Bolton 1952</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">Speck 1964</xref>) and remains so today. Tunney’s visit to the area took place in the early decades of the region’s utilization for livestock. It was the first reconnaissance for mammals in this region, and the immediate area remains zoologically little known today. On its tag, Tunney characterized the habitat of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen as “conglomerate hills”, suggesting that the animal was found in a rocky area, <!--PageBreak-->where echidnas would surely make their burrows. The only other mammals obtained by Tunney at Mount Anderson were specimens of the large macropodids <italic><tp:taxon-name>Megalibgwilia antilopinus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Megalibgwilia robustus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (specimens at BMNH). Birds collected by Tunney at Mount Anderson included the Varied Lorikeet (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Psitteuteles versicolor</tp:taxon-name></italic>), Red-backed Fairywren (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Malurus melanocephalus cruentatus</tp:taxon-name></italic>), and Brown Goshawk (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Accipiter fasciatus cruentus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) (specimens in the AMNH ornithological collections).
                </p>
                <p>The distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in New Guinea is today centered on montane tropical rainforests (but open areas of subalpine grassland are also prime habitat, and some areas of lowland forest and limestone country are also utilized). It might thus be expected that the last areas of survival for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> populations in the Kimberley would be in the region’s many tiny and scattered evergreen rainforest fragments, which are largely distributed to the north of the Fitzroy River (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">McKenzie et al. 1991</xref>). However, the Mount Anderson area is reasonably well watered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">Registrar et al. 1902</xref>), and its inaccessibility, sparse human population, and the availability of rugged, steep, rocky areas may explain its importance in hosting a late-surviving remnant population of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Australia. Six decades after Tunney’s visit, in their review of “Lands of the West Kimberley Area”, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">Speck et al. (1964</xref>: 191) discussed the Grant Ranges-Mt. Anderson area under their classification of “inaccessible country” and “inaccessible pasture land”, describing it thus:
                </p>
                <p>&quot;<italic>Environment. The rugged mountain ranges, elevated plateaux, steep hills, and associated valleys have a complex geological pattern with quartzites, sandstones, shales, slates, schists, basalt, dolerite, and limestone. It is mostly rough, inaccessible, unproductive, and undeveloped. Soils are varied but characteristically skeletal with extensive outcrop</italic>.
                </p>
                <p><italic>Composition. Most of the lands are within the higher-rainfall area and the vegetation of these parts is an open woodland with moderate shrub layer and grassy ground storey of curly spinifex pasture type…. In the lower-rainfall parts the vegetation is more stunted and open and the grass layer is hard spinifex… Grasses other than spinifex are poorly represented. Edible top feed is also scanty</italic>.
                </p>
                <p><italic>Pastoral Value. Only where these lands are adjacent to better country is utilization possible. They are more likely to have a nuisance value. They are generally well watered and therefore provide a hideout for scrub bulls, increasing the difficulty of herd management and mustering. At best it will remain extremely poor pastoral country</italic>.
                </p>
                <p><italic>Reaction to Grazing, and Management. Much of the area is unstocked and there is little or no evidence of pasture degradation or denudation except in isolated, restricted areas adjacent to watering points</italic>.&quot;
                </p>
                <p>A visual representation of the vegetation currently present around Mount Anderson today can be seen with mapping resources available in the online resource <italic>Atlas of Living Australia</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://spatial.ala.org.au/" xlink:type="simple">http://spatial.ala.org.au/</ext-link>), which indicates that present vegetation is dominated by “Acacia open woodlands” but also includes some small areas of “Rainforest and vine thickets.” We suggest that these latter habitats (rainforest, vine thickets) would be relevant remnant habitat for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and that these habitats were likely more expansive at the time of Tunney’s visit to the region well over a century ago in 1901.
                </p>
                <p>Relatively inaccessible and sparsely inhabited rocky areas provide some of the most important remaining areas of occurrence for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in New Guinea, on the southern<!--PageBreak--> and northern slopes of the Central Cordillera, and in limestone country throughout the “Bird’s Neck” region in the west of the island. That similarly remote and sparsely inhabited areas of northern Australia apparently sheltered at least one remnant population of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> into the twentieth century is an astonishing realization, and serves as strong encouragement for wildlife researchers to undertake surveys of remote candidate areas of northern Australia with the goal of establishing whether <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> may still exist in any rainforest fragments or rugged gorges across the Kimberley.
                </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Taxonomy, biogeography, and the Kimberley Zaglossus">
                <title>Taxonomy, biogeography, and the Kimberley <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                </title>
                <p>We confidently identify the Kimberley specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> as the Western Long-Beaked Echidna, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, otherwise known only from the western portion of the island of New Guinea, which it matches in size, cranial features, claw number, and pelage features. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the only echidna taxon that typically lacks claws on the first and fifth digits of all feet (the claw conformation seen in the Kimberleyspecimen), and always lacks a claw on the first digit of the hindfeet (a claw is always present on the first digit of the hindfoot in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bartoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Flannery and Groves 1998</xref>). As Oldfield Thomas noted, the subadult skull of the Kimberley specimen is a good match in overall size and shape for specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> that are of equivalent age (as judged by cranial development, in terms of robustness and sutural ossification). The relatively short and modest (rather than long and heavy) growth of fur in between the spines on the dorsum, relatively pale brown (rather than blackish brown) pelage, presence of some black-tipped spines on the dorsum, and presence of visible spines on the underside, are external features that in combination are typical only of lowland populations of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, such as those recorded from the land-bridge island of Salawati, the adjacent Vogelkop coast at Sorong, and the Fakfak and Charles Louis Ranges in the Bird’s Neck region (skins especially at the BMNH, MCZ, and MZB).
                </p>
                <p>The Western Long-beaked echidna, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, occurs in western New Guinea in habitats from as low as sea level up to the top of the highest peaks in the Vogelkop Peninsula—in the Tamrau and Arfak Ranges (to 2900 m)—and from the land-bridge island of Salawati in the west, to the “Bird’s Neck region” of New Guinea in the east, extending as far east as the Fakfak Range and possibly the Charles Louis Ranges on the western edge of the Central Cordillera (in the south) and possibly to the eastern shores of Geelvink (= Cenderawasih) Bay (in the north) (Rothschild in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B110">Thomas and Rothschild 1922</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B113">Van Deusen and George 1969</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Flannery 1995a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">1995b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Flannery and Groves 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Aplin et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Helgen 2007</xref>). The Eastern long-beaked echidna, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bartoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>, does not usually occur in habitats below about 1000 m, with low-elevation records known only in far south-eastern New Guinea at Collingwood Bay (down to 0–200 m) and in the vicinity of Haia on the south side of the Central Cordillera in east-central New Guinea (down to about 500–600 m).
                </p>
                <p>Though previously recorded only from western New Guinea, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> taxon occurring in closest geographical proximity to the Kimberley <!--PageBreak-->region, and is the only <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> regularly documented in lowland contexts. Given that similar relevant habitats, including sparsely inhabitated limestone country and remnant rainforests, are to be found across the Kimberley region, it does not surprise us that the modern Kimberley representative of the genusshould be <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic>. We envision a late Pleistocene distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> that extended across rugged, rocky country and rainforests along the western parts of the Sahul Shelf, comprising much of the area between Australia and New Guinea that has been inundated by the Arafura Sea since the terminal Pleistocene, thus connecting the restricted Recent range from the Vogelkop Peninsula in the north to the Kimberley region and Arnhem Land in the south.
                </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Ectoparasites from the Kimberley Zaglossus">
                <title>Ectoparasites from the Kimberley <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                </title>
                <p>The Kimberley <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen, while overlooked in mammalogical literature, has been referenced with surprising regularity in parasitological papers. It is the “symbiotype” (i.e., host to the type series; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Frey et al. [1992]</xref>) for two ectoparasite taxa, the flea <italic><tp:taxon-name>Echidnophaga liopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Jordan and Rothschild, 1906; and the ixodid tick <italic><tp:taxon-name>Amblyomma  australiense</tp:taxon-name></italic> Neumann, 1905. In all of the parasitological literature in which Tunney’s specimen is referenced, the specimen is mistakenly referred to as a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">Neumann 1905</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Jordan and Rothschild 1906</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">Robinson 1926</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">Roberts 1953</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Dunnet and Mardon 1974</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Keirans 1982</xref>), obscuring until now the correct host association of these parasites.
                </p>
                <p>The flea <italic><tp:taxon-name>Echidnophaga liopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is so far documented firmly only from Tunney’s <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen and is unknown to date in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Echidnophaga</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens attributed to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Echidnophaga liopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in literature, which come from Indian rodents (Rothschild and Jordan 1906), seem more likely to represent a distinct Asian species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Dunnet and Mardon 1974</xref>). Out of interest, we note that two of the most commonly recorded and host-specific fleas of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus aculeatus</tp:taxon-name></italic>—<italic><tp:taxon-name>Echidnophaga ambulans</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bradiopsyllae echidnae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Dunnet and Mardon 1974</xref>)—have not been recovered from Tunney’s specimen.
                </p>
                <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">Neumann (1905)</xref> originally described the Australian tick <italic><tp:taxon-name>Amblyomma australiense</tp:taxon-name></italic> based on examplars in the N.C. Rothschild collection taken from Tunney’s <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">Robinson 1926</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Roberts 1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Keirans 1982</xref>). Apart from this original record from Tunney’s <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a few other records of occurrence are available for this apparently northern Australian tick; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B101">Taylor (1913)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Roberts (1964)</xref> recorded it from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> at Townsville in Queensland, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">Robinson (1926)</xref> recorded it from a unidentified large lizard at Darwin in Northern Territory, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">Roberts (1964)</xref> recorded it from an “unspecified snake”, also at Darwin. The closely related tick <italic><tp:taxon-name>Amblyomma echidnae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Roberts, 1953, considered by some to be conspecific with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Amblyomma australiense</tp:taxon-name></italic> (but held as distinct, pending critical study, by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Guglielmone et al. [2009]</xref>) is apparently known to date only from Australian <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">Roberts 1953</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">1964</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">1970</xref>).
                </p>
                <p>So far, none of the ectoparasites recorded from Tunney’s <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> have been reported from New Guinea <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but very little is known about the parasites of<!--PageBreak--> Long-beaked echidnas. We are aware of only two ectoparasites definitively recorded from New Guinea <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The tick <italic><tp:taxon-name>Bothriocroton oudemansi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Neumann, 1910) has been reported from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> at Fakfak, and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bartoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the Central Cordillera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Beati et al. 2008</xref>). The tick <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ixodes zaglossi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kohls, 1960, was described from a specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bartoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Wissel Lakes at the western end of New Guinea’s Central Cordillera. Whether either of these ticks is the same taxon as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ixodes acanthoglossi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lucas, 1878 (regarded as an indeterminable <italic>nomen dubium</italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Beati et al. [2008])</xref>, originally described as a parasite of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the Arfak Mountains, has not been determined.
                </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Possible Aboriginal familiarity with Zaglossus in the Kimberley">
                <title>Possible Aboriginal familiarity with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the Kimberley
                </title>
                <p>The Late Quaternary occurrence of Long-beaked echidnasin northern Australia is widely accepted on the basis of a compelling Aboriginal rock art illustration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>), from an undisclosed Arnhem Land locality, that accurately depicts <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">Murray and Chaloupka 1984</xref>). This illustration, usually considered Late Pleistocene in age, has been often reproduced in reference books on Australian mammals (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Johnson 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B112">Tyndale-Biscoe 2005</xref>), and demonstrates Australian Aboriginal familiarity and interaction with Long-beaked echidnas.
                </p>
                <p>It is possible that Aboriginal Australians also interacted with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> much more recently. In 2001, years before we became aware of the Australian provenance of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen reported here, one of us (Kohen) recorded a potential example of living memory of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> while engaged in field work in the East Kimberley. His account of the experience is as follows:
                </p>
                <p><italic>While conducting faunalsurveys at Faraway Bay, I was accompanied by an Aboriginal woman in her fifties who belonged to the Miriwoong Gadjerong tribe. Their territory extends from the coast inland in the region close to the Western Australia-Northern Territory border. In this part of Australia, tribal affiliation is passed down through the female line. However, Faraway Bay is on her father’s country, and he belonged to the <tp:taxon-name>Kwini</tp:taxon-name> tribe</italic>.
                </p>
                <p><italic>While walking close to the coast, we found a scat. On asking my informant what she thought it was, she correctly identified it as an echidna scat, which she referred to as “porcupine”. As only one echidna is traditionally known from Australia, I assumed that it belonged to</italic> Tachyglossus.<italic> A few hours later we had returned to the camp and were sharing tea when she commented about the echidna scat we had found. She said that her grandmothers “used to hunt the other one”. I asked her what other one, and she said that she meant a much larger echidna. She indicated its height which I estimated to be around 40 cm</italic>.
                </p>
                <p><italic>I was intrigued, as both of her grandmothers were still alive and in their nineties. However, one had recently suffered a stroke and the other lived some distance away. When we returned to Kununurra, I had an opportunity to speak to my informant’s mother. As it happened, I had a copy of Tim Flannery’s 1990 paper</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Flannery 1990</xref>] <italic>on the extinct megafauna of Australia, which included a series of shadow illustrations of large Australian mammals. When I showed this to her, and asked her if she knew any of these animals, she identified the</italic> Zaglossus.<italic> My impression was that the animal had not been seen for a long time</italic>.
                </p>
                <p>We readily acknowledge that these kinds of informant accounts are fraught with difficulty of interpretation. However, we mention these interactions, because, like the Tunney specimen, this information from Kohen’s informants could be relevant to the survival of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the Kimberley region into the twentieth century. We suggest that future efforts to investigate the recent survival of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in remote northern Australia take into account evidence that may be derived from cultural sources such as rock art, living memories from Aboriginal cultures, and examination of vocabularies relevant to animal names in Aboriginal languages.
                </p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <sec sec-type="Specimen-based evidence of recent survival of Zaglossus in Australia">
                <title>Specimen-based evidence of recent survival of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Australia
                </title>
                <p>We are sufficiently convinced by the tags and information associated with the Tunney <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen to regard it as evidence for the survival of the long-beaked echidna in the Kimberley region into the early twentieth century. We accordingly recommend that the Western Long-beaked echidna, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, be included in future faunal compilations of the modern mammal fauna of Australia (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B116">Walton 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B117">Walton and Richardson 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Menkhorst and Knight 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B114">Van Dyck and Strahan 2005</xref>), and on the long list of mammal species that have declined to extirpation, extinction, or near extinction in Australia over the past two centuries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Johnson 2006</xref>).
                </p>
                <p>We realize that, despite our conclusions, summarized here, others may remain skeptical of this <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimen’s association with Tunney’s tags. Additional studies of this remarkable specimen might include analyses of ancient DNA, stable isotopes, and trace elements to test its origins and the context of its collection. Further targeted studies of relevant Kimberley Pleistocene and Holocene subfossil assemblages (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">O’Connor et al. [2008]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B99">Start et al. [2012]</xref>) may also shed useful light on the late survival of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in northern Australia.
                </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Quaternary and recent extinctions">
                <title>Quaternary and recent extinctions</title>
                <p>Most of Australia’s remarkable Pleistocene megafauna (gigantic marsupials, reptiles, and birds) became extinct after about 50,000 years before the present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Flannery 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">Roberts et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Miller et al. 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B93">Rule et al. 2012</xref>) following the arrival of humans to the continent. Many other mammal species declined broadly, many to the point of extinction, across their mainland Australian distributions during the Holocene (e.g., thylacine, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thylacinus</tp:taxon-name></italic>; Tasmanian devil, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sarcophilus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) or since the onset of European impacts in the mid-1800s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Flannery 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Johnson 2006</xref>). The Tunney specimen adds <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> to the list of mammal species that underwent dramatic declines in Australia during recent times.
                </p>
                <p>Anotherrather unexpected recent addition to the list of Quaternary extinctions in the Kimberley region is a fruit-bat of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Styloctenium</tp:taxon-name></italic>, identified by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">Pettigrew et al. (2008)</xref> from definitive illustrations in (Late Pleistocene?) rock art from near Kalumburu. Species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Styloctenium</tp:taxon-name></italic> are today known only from the large Indonesian island of Sulawesi (and some of its satellites) and the Philippine island of Mindoro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Bergmans and Rozendaal 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Esselstyn 2007</xref>). We also note with interest that compelling rock art images of the large, extinct carnivorous marsupial <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thylacaleo</tp:taxon-name></italic> have also recently come to light in the Kimberley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Akerman 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Akerman and Willing 2009</xref>). These discoveries point to the importance of rock art as a source of information about the past distributions in time and space of animals in northern Australian contexts.
                </p>
                <p>Both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Styloctenium</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> are largely rainforest-associated lineages that today are known only from tropical islands north of Australia. Their presence in the late Quaternary fauna of the Kimberley region doubtless reflects the former presence of extensive mesic forested habitats across much of northern Australia, with fragmentation and extinction of forest-reliant species driven by a combination of climate-change and prehistoric human impacts in recent millennia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">McKenzie et al. 1991</xref>)—a topic that so far has received much greater attention in the Wet Tropics of Queensland than in the tropical rainforests of the Kimberley region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Joseph et al. 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B119">Williams 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B94">Schneider and Moritz 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Bowman et al. 2010</xref>). Today, none of the mammal species known to occur in Kimberley rainforests are entirely dependent on rainforest habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Friend et al. 1991</xref>). However, we suggest that further critical examination of rock art depictions, and of fossil and subfossil assemblages, will likely illuminate the former presence in the Kimberley rainforests of additional taxa typical of modern Indo-Malayan or Australo-Papuan rainforest habitats.
                </p>
                <p>We hold out a small optimism that Long-beaked echidnasmight yet dig burrows and hunt invertebrates in at least one hidden corner of Australia’s north-west. Such hopes are founded on the remoteness of this little-studied expanse of the Australian continent, and on the relatively late discovery of other medium-sized Kimberley mammals including the Monjon, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Petrogale burbidgei</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Kitchener and Sanson 1978</xref>), a small rock wallaby endemic to the north-west Kimberley, and the recent rediscovery of the Scaly-tailed Possum (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Wyulda squamicaudata</tp:taxon-name></italic>) in the eastern Kimberley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Doody et al. 2012</xref>), where it had not been recorded since 1917.
                </p>
                <p>All living <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> taxa in New Guinea are considered to be critically endangered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Isaac et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Leary et al. 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">2008b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">2008c</xref>), with primary threats being subsistence hunting and habitat loss. While it is vitally and urgently important to explore whether <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> still survives in remote areas of the Kimberley, it is also important to learn more about its recent distribution and history of decline. Such studies may identify hitherto unsuspected dimensions to the adaptive breadth of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species, reveal the existing or former presence of populations with genetic diversity unrepresented in New Guinea, and possibly assist with long term conservation of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in New Guinea by illuminating important patterns of habitat occurrence and historical decline in Australia. If <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is extinct in the Kimberley region, it might also warrant consideration as a candidate for reintroduction, once more is learned of its former distribution and ecological role.
                </p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Ecology of Zaglossus bruijnii in western New Guinea and Australia">
                <title>Ecology of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> in western New Guinea and Australia
                </title>
                <p>Little is definitively recorded about diet in Long-beaked echidnas. Most information is based on anecdotes or extremely limited studies of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bartoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>, which is thought to be a specialist earthworm feeder that also feeds on subterranean arthropods including centipedes and large insect larvae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Griffiths 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Griffiths et al. 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Flannery 1995a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Opiang 2009</xref>), with no evidence for feeding on social insects such as ants and termites, the principal diet of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Abensperg-Traun and De Boer 1992</xref>). Because of the intimate cranial resemblance between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bartoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> and other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> taxa, it can be expected that the diets of these congeners are similar. However, it is possible that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> eats more social insects than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bartoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>, perhaps especially in lowland environments. One of only two comments about diet in an individual of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the firsthand account of naturalist Thomas Barbour, recounted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Allen (1912</xref>:302):
                </p>
                <p><italic>This specimen was kept alive for about a month and a few observations on its habits were made. It was absolutely nocturnal and spent the day partially buried in the deep layer of sand which was kept in its cage… At night it moved about sluggishly, often digging with motions that strongly recalled those of a turtle. It fed on ants only, which were procured by placing in a dish a considerable amount of shredded cocoanut. The ants soon swarmed in this and the whole was then placed in the Proechidna’s cage. It ate the insects by thrusting its long tongue down into the cocoanut. It took a little water or water with condensed milk, but seemed to drink very little</italic>.
                </p>
                <p>It may of course be the case that this animal only ate ants because other, more favored foods were not offered to it. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">Ripley (1942</xref>: 256-259), provided the only other (conflicting) account that references the diet of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic>, based on a captive animalat Sansapor (a settlement adjacent to the Tamrau Range), noting “The echidna is supposed to live on ants, although this one would never touch them, much preferring papaya and raw eggs.” Studies of the anatomy of the salivary glands of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> (not available for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bartoni</tp:taxon-name></italic>) show these glands to be greatly developed, as in various ant-eating animals, and very similar to those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B115">Viallanes 1880</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Allen 1912</xref>). Ants and termites would presumably constitute a reliable source of food for a large echidna in northern Australian contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Andersen and Majer 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Milewski et al. 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Barrow et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">2007</xref>), though earthworms might remain key resources especially in remnant rainforest areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">McKenzie and Dyne 1991</xref>). If <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus bruijnii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is more dependent on ants in lowland New Guinea (and Australian) habitats than other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zaglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> populations arein montane New Guinea habitats, its presence across northern Australia until recent times may shed new light on the riddle, posed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">Milewski et al. (1994)</xref>, of why, unlike other southern continents, Australia seems to have had no species larger than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyglossus</tp:taxon-name></italic> exploiting social insects as a major food resource. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Griffiths et al. (1991)</xref> similarly suggested that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Megalibgwilia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the other (and more southerly distributed) large echidna genus present in the Australian Quaternary, may also have been an insect-eater rather than an earthworm-eating specialist.<!--PageBreak-->
                </p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We thank P. Jenkins, L. Tomsett, J. Maclaine, R. How, E. Westwig, P. Sweet, D. Lunde, L. Gordon, S. Ingleby, J. Chupasko, Maharadatunkamsi, and M. Sinaga for assistance with specimens in museum collections around the world. We thank K. Aplin, G. Perri, M. Opiang, T. Flannery, M. Eldridge, C. Groves, M. Copley, E. Ward, R. How, J. Hatton, R. Roberts, R. Robbins, P. Engelbrektsson and O. Crimmen for helpful discussion. We acknowledge the very helpful assistance of M. Triffitt of the Western Australian Museum Library. We thank the Smithsonian Institution, the Natural History Museum (London), and the Australian Biological Resources Study for funding support.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Abensperg-Traun</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Boer</surname> <given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> The foraging ecology of a termite-and ant-eating specialist, the echidna <italic>Tachyglossus aculeatus</italic> (Monotremata: Tachyglossidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of Zoology (London)</source> <volume>226</volume>: <fpage>243</fpage>-<lpage>257</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-7998.1992.tb03837.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1469-7998.1992.tb03837.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Akerman</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Interaction between humans and megafauna depicted in Australian rock art? Antiquity 83(322). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.antiquity.ac.uk/projgall/akerman322/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.antiquity.ac.uk/projgall/akerman322/</ext-link></source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Akerman</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willing</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> An ancient rock painting of a marsupial lion, <italic>Thylacaleo carnifex</italic>, from the Kimberley, Western Australia. Antiquity 83(319). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.antiquity.ac.uk/projgall/akerman319/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.antiquity.ac.uk/projgall/akerman319/</ext-link></source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>)<article-title> <italic>Zaglossus</italic>.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the Museum of Comparative Zoology </source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>-<lpage>307</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname> <given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Majer</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> The structure and biogeography of rainforest ant communities in the Kimberley region of northwestern Australia.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Kimberley rainforests of Australia.</issue-title> <source>Surrey Beatty and Sons, Chipping Norton, New South Wales</source>: <fpage>333</fpage>-<lpage>346</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aplin</surname> <given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pasveer</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boles</surname> <given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Late Quaternary vertebrates from the Bird’s Head Peninsula, Irian Jaya, Indonesia, including descriptions of two previously unknown marsupial species.</article-title> <source>Records of the Western Australian Museum Supplement </source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>351</fpage>-<lpage>387</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Augee</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Short-beaked echidna, <italic>Tachyglossus aculeatus</italic> (Shaw, 1792).</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dyck</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strahan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>The mammals of Australia.</issue-title> <source>Third edition. Reed New Holland,  Sydney</source>: <fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Baillie</surname> <given-names>JEM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turvey</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waterman</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Survival of Attenborough’s long-beaked echidna <italic>Zaglossus attenboroughi</italic> in New Guinea.</article-title> <source>Oryx </source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>146</fpage>-<lpage>148</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0030605309002269" xlink:type="simple">10.1017/S0030605309002269</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrow</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parr</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohen</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Biogeography and diversity of ants in Purnululu (Bungle Bungle) National Park and Conservation Reserve, Western Australia.</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/ZO06009" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/ZO06009</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrow</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parr</surname> <given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohen</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Habitat type influences fire resilience of ant assemblages in the semi-arid tropics of northern Australia.</article-title> <source>Journal of Arid Environments </source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>80</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jaridenv.2006.08.005" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.jaridenv.2006.08.005</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Beati</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerians</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durden</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Opiang</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> <italic>Bothriocroton oudemansi</italic> (Neumann, 1910) n. comb. (Acari: Ixodida: Ixodidae), an ectoparasite of the western long-beaked echidna in Papua New Guinea: redescription of the male and first description of the female and nymph.</article-title> <source>Systematic Parasitology </source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>-<lpage>200</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11230-007-9115-5" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s11230-007-9115-5</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergmans</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rozendaal</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> Notes on collections of fruit bats from Sulawesi and some off-lying islands (Mammalia: Megachiroptera).</article-title> <source>Zoologische Verhandelingen </source> <volume>248</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolton</surname> <given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1952</year>)<source> A survey of the Kimberley pastoral industry from 1885 to present. MSc Thesis, University of Western Australia, Perth, Australia.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowman</surname> <given-names>DMJS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>GK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braby</surname> <given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crisp</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haberle</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isagi,</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McBride</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ladiges</surname> <given-names>PY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Biogeography of the Australian monsoon tropics.</article-title> <source>Journal of Biogeography </source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>-<lpage>216</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2699.2009.02210.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1365-2699.2009.02210.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chadwick</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> ‘Your obedient servant’: the John Tunney collection at the Western Australian Museum.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamby</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>The makers and making of indigenous Australian museum collections.</issue-title> <source>Melbourne University Press, Victoria</source>: <fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>280</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaloupka</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> Dreamtime or reality? Reply to Lewis.</article-title> <source>Archaeology in Oceania </source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>147</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coues</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1895</year>)<source> The genus <italic>Zaglossus</italic>. Science (n.s.) 1: 610.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Doody</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhind</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castellano</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bass</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> Rediscovery of the scaly-tailed possum (<italic>Wyulda squamicaudata</italic>) in the eastern Kimberley.</article-title> <source>Australian Mammalogy </source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>260</fpage>-<lpage>262</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/AM11039" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/AM11039</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunnet</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mardon</surname> <given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<article-title> A monograph of Australian fleas (Siphonaptera).</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Zoology Supplementary Series</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>273</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Esselstyn</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> A new species of stripe-faced fruit bat (Chiroptera: Pteropodidae: <italic>Styloctenium</italic>) from the Philippines.</article-title> <source>Journal of Mammalogy </source> <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>951</fpage>-<lpage>958</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1644/06-MAMM-A-294R.1" xlink:type="simple">10.1644/06-MAMM-A-294R.1</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> Pleistocene faunal loss: implications of the aftershock for Australia’s past and future.</article-title> <source>Archaeology in Oceania </source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<source> The Future Eaters: an ecological history of the Australasian lands and people. Reed Books, Sydney.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995a</year>)<source> Mammals of New Guinea. Revised edition. Reed Books, Chatswood, New South Wales.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995b</year>)<source> Mammals of the South-west Pacific and Moluccan Islands. Reed Books, Chatswood, New South Wales.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Groves</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> A revision of the genus <italic>Zaglossus</italic> (Monotremata, Tachyglossidae), with description of new species and subspecies.</article-title> <source>Mammalia </source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>-<lpage>396</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1515/mamm.1998.62.3.367" xlink:type="simple">10.1515/mamm.1998.62.3.367</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Forrest</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1880</year>)<source> North-West exploration: journal of expedition from DeGrey to Port Darwin. Richard Pether, Government Printer, Perth.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname> <given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yates</surname> <given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duszynski</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gannon</surname> <given-names>WL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname> <given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Designation and curatorial management of type host specimens (symbiotypes) for new parasite species.</article-title> <source>Journal of Parasitology </source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>930</fpage>-<lpage>932</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/3283335" xlink:type="simple">10.2307/3283335</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Friend</surname> <given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> The mammal fauna of Kimberley rainforests.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Kimberley rainforests of Australia.</issue-title> <source>Surrey Beatty and Sons, Chipping Norton, New South Wales</source>: <fpage>393</fpage>-<lpage>412</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gervais</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1877a</year>)<article-title> L’échidné de la Nouvelle-Guineé.</article-title> <source>Comptes Rendus des Séances de L’Académie des Sciences </source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>837</fpage>-<lpage>838</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gervais</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1877b</year>)<article-title> L’échidné de la Nouvelle-Guineé. Deuxième Note.</article-title> <source>Comptes Rendus des Séances de L’Académie des Sciences</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>990</fpage>-<lpage>991</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1877</year>)<article-title> Vertebrate zoology.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Baird</surname> <given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed.</role>). <issue-title>Annual record of science and industry for 1876.</issue-title> <source>Harper and Brothers, New York</source>: <fpage>171</fpage>-<lpage>172</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1885</year>)<article-title> The species of tachyglossids.</article-title> <source>Annual Report of the Board of Regents of the Smithsonian Institution </source> <volume>1884</volume>: <fpage>642</fpage>-<lpage>643</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Glauert</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1914</year>)<article-title> Taxonomy and detailed description of <italic>Zaglossus hacketti</italic>.</article-title> <source>Records of the Western Australian Museum </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>244</fpage>-<lpage>248</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<source> A pair of every species. In: Rothschild E (Chair) The Rothschild Archive Trust. Rothschild Archive Trust, London, 46–50.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>)<source> The biology of the monotremes. Academic Press, New York.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrie</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> Observations on the skulls of fossil and extant echidnas (Monotremata: Tachyglossidae).</article-title> <source>Australian Mammalogy </source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Groves</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Order Monotremata.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reeder</surname> <given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Mammal species of the world: a taxonomic and geographic reference, Third edition.</issue-title> <source>Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore, Maryland</source>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>2</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guglielmone</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robbins</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apanaskevich</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petney</surname> <given-names>TN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estrada-Pefia</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horak</surname> <given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Comments on controversial tick (Acari: Ixodida) species names and species described or resurrected from 2003 to 2008.</article-title> <source>Experimental and Applied Acarology </source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>311</fpage>-<lpage>327</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10493-009-9246-2" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10493-009-9246-2</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartert</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1905</year>)<article-title> List of birds collected in north-western Australia and Arnhem-Land by Mr. J.T. Tunney.</article-title> <source>Novitates Zoologicae </source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>194</fpage>-<lpage>242</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Helgen</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> A taxonomic and geographic overview of the mammals of Papua.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname> <given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beehler</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>The ecology of Papua (Ecology of Indonesia series Volume VI).</issue-title> <source>Periplus Editions, Singapore</source>: <fpage>689</fpage>-<lpage>749</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> A memoir and bibliography of Michael Roger Oldfield Thomas, F.R.S.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British Museum, Natural History (History Series) </source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Isaac</surname> <given-names>NJB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turvey</surname> <given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collen</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waterman</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baillie</surname> <given-names>JEM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> Mammals on the EDGE: conservation priorities based on threat and phylogeny. PLoS ONE 2(3): e296. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0000296." xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0000296.</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> Australia’s mammal extinctions: a 50,000 year history. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B44"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordan</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1906</year>)<article-title> A revision of the Sarcopsyllidae, a family of Siphonaptera.</article-title> <source>Thompson Yates and Johnstone Laboratories Reports </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B45"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moritz</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hugall</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> Molecular support for vicariance as a source of diversity in rainforest.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society Series B Biological Sciences</source> <volume>260</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>182</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.1995.0077" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rspb.1995.0077</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B46"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Keirans</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<article-title> The tick collection (Acarina: Ixodoidea) of the Hon. Nathaniel Charles Rothschild deposited in the Nuttall and general collections of the British Museum (Natural History).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British Museum of Natural History (Zoology) </source> <volume>42</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B47"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitchener</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanson</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>)<article-title> <italic>Petrogale burbidgei</italic> (Marsupialia, Macropodidae), a new rock wallaby from Kimberley, Western Australia.</article-title> <source>Records of the Western Australian Museum </source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>285</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B48"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohls</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1960</year>)<article-title> <italic>Ixodes (Endopalpiger) zaglossi</italic> n. sp. from the long-beaked echidna of New Guinea (Acarina, Ixodidae).</article-title> <source>Acarologia </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>-<lpage>452</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B49"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Krefft</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1868</year>)<source> On the discovery of a new and gigantic fossil species of <italic>Echidna</italic> in Australia. Annals and Magazine of Natural History (series 4) 1: 113–114.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B50"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Leary</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seri</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helgen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singadan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menzies</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aplin</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salas</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickman</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008a</year>)<source> <italic>Zaglossus attenboroughi</italic>. IUCN Red List of Threatened Species. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iucnredlist.org" xlink:type="simple">www.iucnredlist.org</ext-link> [Version 2012.2]</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B51"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Leary</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seri</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helgen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singadan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menzies</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aplin</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salas</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickman</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008b</year>)<source> <italic>Zaglossus bartoni</italic>. IIUCN Red List of Threatened Species. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iucnredlist.org" xlink:type="simple">www.iucnredlist.org</ext-link> [Version 2012.2]</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B52"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Leary</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seri</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helgen</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singadan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menzies</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aplin</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salas</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickman</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008c</year>)<source> <italic>Zaglossus bruijnii</italic>. IUCN Red List of Threatened Species. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iucnredlist.org" xlink:type="simple">www.iucnredlist.org</ext-link> [Version 2012.2]</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B53"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> ‘The dreamtime animals’: a reply.</article-title> <source>ArchaeologyinOceania </source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>140</fpage>-<lpage>145</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B54"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Archer</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hand</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<source> Prehistoric mammals of Australia and New Guinea: 100 million years of evolution. University of New South Wales Press, Sydney.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B55"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1878</year>)<article-title> Note.</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société Entomologique de France </source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B56"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahoney</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ride</surname> <given-names>WDL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>)<article-title> Index to the genera and species of fossil Mammalia described from Australia and New Guinea between 1838 and 1969.</article-title> <source>Western Australian Museum Special Publication </source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>247</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B57"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belbin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keigherry</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenneally</surname> <given-names>KF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> Kimberley rainforest communities: patterns of species composition and Holocene biogeography.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Kimberley rainforests of Australia.</issue-title> <source>Surrey Beatty and Sons, Chipping Norton, New South Wales</source>: <fpage>423</fpage>-<lpage>452</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B58"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyne</surname> <given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> Earthworms of rainforest soils in the Kimberley, Western Australia.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Kimberley rainforests of Australia.</issue-title> <source>Surrey Beatty and Sons, Chipping Norton, New South Wales</source>: <fpage>133</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B59"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname> <given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname> <given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<source> Kimberley rainforests of Australia. Surrey Beatty and Sons, Chipping Norton, New South Wales.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B60"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Menkhorst</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<source> A field guide to the mammals of Australia. Oxford University Press, South Melbourne.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B61"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Milewski</surname> <given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abensperg-Traun</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickman</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<source> Why are termite- and ant-eating mammals smaller in Australia than in southern Africa: history or ecology? Journal of Biogeography 21: 529–543. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/2845656" xlink:type="simple">10.2307/2845656</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B62"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fogel</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magee</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gagan</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Ecosystem collapse in Pleistocene Australia and a human role in megafaunal extinction. Science 309: 287–290.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B63"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978a</year>)<article-title> Late Cenozoic monotreme anteaters.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Augee</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>Monotreme biology.</issue-title> <source>Royal Zoological Society of New South Wales, Taronga Zoo, Mosman, New South Wales</source>: <fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B64"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978b</year>)<article-title> A Pleistocene spiny anteater from Tasmania (Monotremata: Tachyglossidae, <italic>Zaglossus</italic>).</article-title> <source>Papers and Proceedings of the Royal Society of Tasmania </source> <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B65"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaloupka</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> The dreamtime animals: extinct megafauna in Arnhem Land rock art.</article-title> <source>Archaeology in Oceania </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>-<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B66"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumann</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1905</year>)<article-title> Notes sur les Ixodidés—III.</article-title> <source>Archives de Parasitologie </source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>-<lpage>241</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B67"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumann</surname> <given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1910</year>)<article-title> Description de deux nouvelles espèces d’Ixodinae.</article-title> <source>Tijdschrift voor Entomologie </source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B68"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Connor</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aplin</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Results of a small salvage excavation in Windjana Gorge, Kimberley, Western Australia.</article-title> <source>Archaeology in Oceania </source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B69"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Opiang</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Home ranges, movement, and den use in long-beaked echidnas, <italic>Zaglossus bartoni</italic>, from Papua New Guinea.</article-title> <source>Journal of Mammalogy </source> <volume>90</volume>: <fpage>340</fpage>-<lpage>346</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1644/08-MAMM-A-108.1" xlink:type="simple">10.1644/08-MAMM-A-108.1</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B70"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Owen</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1884</year>)<article-title> Evidence of a large extinct monotreme (<italic>Echidna ramsayi</italic> Owen) from the Wellington Breccia Cave New South Wales.</article-title> <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London </source> <volume>185</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage>-<lpage>275</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rstl.1884.0013" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rstl.1884.0013</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B71"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1895</year>)<source> The generic names of the three-toed echidna. Science 1: 518.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B72"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doria</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1876</year>)<source> Descrizione di una nuova specie di <italic>Tachyglossus</italic> proveniente dalla Nuova Guinea settentrionale. Annali del Museo Civico Storia Naturale di Genova 9: 183–185.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B73"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettigrew</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koerner</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McPhee</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallman</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<source> An unexpected, stripe-faced flying fox in ice age rock art of Australia’s Kimberley. Antiquity 82(318). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://antiquity.ac.uk/projgall/pettigrew/index.html" xlink:type="simple">http://antiquity.ac.uk/projgall/pettigrew/index.html</ext-link></source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B74"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pledge</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Giant echidnas in South Australia.</article-title> <source>South Australian Naturalist </source> <volume>55</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B75"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Prideaux</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gully</surname> <given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Couzens</surname> <given-names>AMC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayliffe</surname> <given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jankowski</surname> <given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hellstrom</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gagan</surname> <given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatcher</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Timing and dynamics of Late Pleistocene mammal extinctions in southwestern Australia.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA </source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>22157</fpage>-<lpage>22162</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1011073107" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.1011073107</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B76"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Registrar</surname> <given-names>General</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perth</surname> <given-names></given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1902</year>)<source> Statistical register of the colony of Western Australia for 1900 and previous years. Perth, Australia: Wm. Alfred Watson, Government Printer.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B77"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripley</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1942</year>)<source> Trail of the money bird: 30,000 miles of adventure with a naturalist. Harper and Brothers, New York.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B78"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>FHS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1953</year>)<article-title> The Australian species of <italic>Aponomma</italic> and <italic>Amblyomma</italic> (Ixodoidea).</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Zoology </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/ZO9530111" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/ZO9530111</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B79"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>FHS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<article-title> Further observations on the Australian species of <italic>Aponomma</italic> and <italic>Amblyomma</italic> with descriptions of the nymphs of <italic>Amblyomma moreliae</italic> (L. Koch) and <italic>Amb. loculosum</italic> Neumann (Acarina: Ixodidae).</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Zoology </source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>288</fpage>-<lpage>313</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/ZO9640288" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/ZO9640288</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B80"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>FHS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<source> Australian ticks. CSIRO, Melbourne.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B81"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayliffe</surname> <given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshida</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olley</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prideaux</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laslett</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baynes</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> New ages for the last Australian megafauna: continent-wide extinction about 46,000 years ago.</article-title> <source>Science</source> <volume>292</volume>: <fpage>1888</fpage>-<lpage>1892</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1060264" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1060264</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B82"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1926</year>)<article-title> The genus <italic>Amblyomma</italic>.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuttall</surname> <given-names>GHF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Ticks: a monograph of the Ixodoidea.</issue-title> <source>Part IV, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge</source>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>302</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B83"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1883</year>)<source> Dear Lord Rothschild: birds, butterflies, and history. Balaban, Glenside, Pennsylvania.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B84"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1892</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of two new mammals from New Guinea.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London </source> <volume>1892</volume>: <fpage>545</fpage>-<lpage>546</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B85"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1903</year>)<source> Preliminary diagnosis of a new genus and species of kangaroo. Novitates Zoologicae10: 414.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B86"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1904</year>)<source> Note on <italic>Dendrodorcopsis woodwardi</italic>. Novitates Zoologicae 10: 543.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B87"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1905a</year>)<article-title> Notes on <italic>Zaglossus</italic> and description of a new subspecies of <italic>Echidna hystrix</italic>.</article-title> <source>Novitates Zoologicae </source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>305</fpage>-<lpage>306</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B88"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1905b</year>)<source> Note on <italic>Macropus rufus</italic> Desm. with description of a new subspecies. Novitates Zoologicae 12: 508.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B89"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1905c</year>)<article-title> Notes on two kangaroos from the “Northern Territory of South Australia” with descriptions of a new species.</article-title> <source>Novitates Zoologicae </source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>509</fpage>-<lpage>510</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B90"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1907</year>)<source> Further notes on <italic>Macropus magnus</italic>. Novitates Zoologicae 14: 333.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B91"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1913</year>)<article-title></article-title> <source>Novitates Zoologicae</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>188</fpage>-<lpage>191</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B92"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dollman</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1936</year>)<article-title> The genus <italic>Dendrolagus</italic>.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the ZoologicalSociety of London</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>477</fpage>-<lpage>551</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.1936.tb00459.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1096-3642.1936.tb00459.x</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B93"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rule</surname> <given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brook</surname> <given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haberle</surname> <given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turney</surname> <given-names>CSM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kershaw</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname> <given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> The aftermath of megafaunal extinction: ecosystem transformation in Pleistocene Australia.</article-title> <source>Science </source> <volume>335</volume>: <fpage>1483</fpage>-<lpage>1486</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1214261" xlink:type="simple">10.1126/science.1214261</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B94"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moritz</surname> <given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Rainforest refugia and Australia’s Wet Tropics.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society Series B Biological Sciences </source> <volume>266</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>-<lpage>196</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspb.1999.0621" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rspb.1999.0621</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B95"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1792</year>)<source> <italic>Myrmecophaga aculeata</italic>. The Porcupine Ant-eater. Naturalists’ Miscellany 3(36). [unnumbered]</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B96"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1799</year>)<source> <italic>Platypus anatinus</italic>. The Duck-billed Platypus. Naturalists’ Miscellany 10(118). [unnumbered]</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B97"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Speck</surname> <given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<source> Introduction and summary description of the West Kimberley area. General Report on Lands of the West Kimberley Area, WA Melbourne, CSIRO, 9–23.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B98"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Speck</surname> <given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgerald</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<source> The pasture lands of the West Kimberley area. In: General Report on Lands of the West Kimberley Area, WA Melbourne, CSIRO, 175–191.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B99"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Start</surname> <given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burbidge</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDowell</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname> <given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> The status of non-volant mammals along a rainfall gradient in the south-west Kimberley, Western Australia.</article-title> <source>Australian Mammalogy </source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>36</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/AM10026" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/AM10026</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B100"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Storr</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1966</year>)<article-title> J. T. Tunney’s itinerary in Northern Australia 1901–1903.</article-title> <source>Emu </source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/MU966059" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/MU966059</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B101"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1913</year>)<article-title> Report of the entomologist.</article-title> <source>Report of the Australian Institute of Tropical Medicine </source> <volume>1911</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B102"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1888</year>)<source> Catalogue of the Marsupialia and Monotremata in the collections of the British Museum (Natural History). British Museum (Natural History), London.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B103"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1901</year>)<article-title> On some kangaroos and bandicoots from Barrow Island, North-west Australia and the adjoining mainland.</article-title> <source>Novitates Zoologicae </source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>394</fpage>-<lpage>396</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B104"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1904a</year>)<article-title> On a collection of mammals made by Mr. J.T. Tunney in Arnhem Land, Northern Territory of South Australia.</article-title> <source>Novitates Zoologicae </source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>222</fpage>-<lpage>229</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B105"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1904b</year>)<article-title> On a new rock-wallaby from north-west Australia.</article-title> <source>Novitates Zoologicae </source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>-<lpage>366</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B106"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1904c</year>)<article-title> New species of <italic>Pteropus, Mus</italic>, and <italic>Pogonomys</italic> from the Australian region.</article-title> <source>Novitates Zoologicae </source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>597</fpage>-<lpage>600</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B107"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1907a</year>)<source> On the occurrence of <italic>Acanthoglossus</italic> in British New Guinea. Annals and Magazine of Natural History (series 7) 20: 293–294.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B108"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1907b</year>)<source> A new <italic>Acanthoglossus</italic> from the island of Salawatti. Annals and Magazine of Natural History (series 7) 20: 498–499.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B109"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1909</year>)<source> Two new mammals from N. Australia. Annals and Magazine of Natural History (series 8) 4: 197–198.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B110"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1922</year>)<source> On a new subspecies of <italic>Zaglossus</italic>, with remarks on other species of the genus. Annals and Magazine of Natural History (series 9) 10: 129–131.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B111"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Turney</surname> <given-names>CSM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fifield</surname> <given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higham</surname> <given-names>TFG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kemp</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colhoun</surname> <given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalin</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogle</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Late-surviving megafauna in Tasmania, Australia, implicate human involvement in their extinction.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA </source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>12150</fpage>-<lpage>12153</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B112"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyndale-Biscoe</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Life of marsupials. CSIRO Publishing, Collingwood, Victoria.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B113"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Deusen</surname> <given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>)<article-title> Results of the Archbold Expeditions. No. 90. Notes on the echidnas (Mammalia: Tachyglossidae) of New Guinea.</article-title> <source>American Museum Novitates </source> <volume>2383</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B114"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dyck</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strahan</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) (<year>2005</year>)<source> The mammals of Australia. Third edition. Reed New Holland, Sydney.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B115"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Viallanes</surname> <given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1880</year>)<source> Observations on the salivary glands of the echidnas. Annals and Magazine of Natural History (series 5) 5: 83–84.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B116"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Walton</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<source> Zoological catalogue of Australia, Volume 5. Mammalia. Bureau of Flora and Fauna, Canberra.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B117"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Walton</surname> <given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname> <given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<source> Fauna of Australia, Volume 1B, Mammalia. AGPS, Canberra.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B118"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Whittell</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1954</year>)<article-title> Notes on field-trips of J. T. Tunney.</article-title> <source>Emu </source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>322</fpage>-<lpage>326</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B119"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<source> Patterns of mammalian species richness in the Australian tropical rainforests: are extinctions during historical contractions of the rainforest the primary determinants of current regional patterns in biodiversity? Wildlife Research 24: 513–530.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B120"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood Jones</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1923</year>)<source> The mammals of South Australia. Part I. The monotremes and the carnivorous marsupials (the Ornithodelphia and the didactylous Didelphia). E.E. Rogers, Government Printer, Adelaide, Australia.</source></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>