<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.219.3674</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new 
                    <italic>Mylabris</italic> species from south-eastern Iran and a key to the Iranian species of the nominate subgenus (Coleoptera, Meloidae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Serri</surname>
                        <given-names>Sayeh</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:0BAC43EA-168D-4D43-92E3-B819890479C6</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Pan</surname>
                        <given-names>Zhao</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:B12882C5-E8CA-4A92-B400-42FB6CEF5A0B</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Bologna</surname>
                        <given-names>Marco A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:658304A8-DEF8-4EDF-A4BB-0472BD34BD39</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Insect Taxonomy Research Department, Iranian Research Institute of Plant Protection, Tehran, 19395-1454, Iran
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Dipartimento di Biologia Ambientale, Università Roma Tre, Viale G. Marconi 446, 00146 Roma Italy
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: W. Schawaller</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>4</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>219</issue>
            <fpage>81</fpage>
            <lpage>86</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>11</day>
                    <month>7</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Sayeh Serri, Zhao Pan, Marco A. Bologna</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:3A03FC59-3441-4500-83C7-7ED75607342F</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A new species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris</tp:taxon-name></italic> of the nominate subgenus is described and figured. This species is apparently endemic to the south-eastern Iranian province of Kerman and seems to be phenetically very distinct from all other species of this subgenus, primarily because of the unique elytral pattern. A key to the species of the nominate subgenus distributed in Iran is also presented.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Iran</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>key to the species</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The <tp:taxon-name>Meloidae</tp:taxon-name> of the Middle East remain poorly studied even though this area is one of the most interesting of the Palaearctic region from biogeographic and taxonomic points of view. Within the Middle East, the family is most speciose in Iran which har<!--PageBreak-->bours a fauna with several endemics together with many species in common with Central Asia, Anatolia and Levant, as well as some Saharo-Sindian and Arabic components in the southern provinces. The descriptions of species and faunistic records concerning the blister beetles of this area are few and highly scattered in the literature. The only synthetic works on the Iranian <tp:taxon-name>Meloidae</tp:taxon-name> were published in the last century by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Kaszab (1957</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">1968</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Mirzayans (1970)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bologna (2008)</xref>, in the Palaearctic catalogue of <tp:taxon-name>Meloidae</tp:taxon-name>, listed 194 species for this country.</p>
            <p>The Hayk Mirzayans Insect Museum (HMIM) of the Iranian Research Institute of Plant Protection and the M. Bologna collection at the University Roma Tre (CB) house several new species of Iranian <tp:taxon-name>Meloidae</tp:taxon-name> of the subfamilies <tp:taxon-name>Nemognathinae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Meloinae</tp:taxon-name>. Unresolved taxonomic problems prevent all from being described at this time. However, we are taking this opportunity to describe one very distinct new <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fabricius, 1775 belonging to the nominate subgenus. It is endemic to a narrow area of Iran and represents the southeasternmost species of the nominate subgenus except for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris quadripunctata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus, 1767) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris variabilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Pallas, 1781), which are broadly distributed from the Iberian peninsula to western China.</p>
            <p>The meloine genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris</tp:taxon-name></italic> is easily distinguished using a key published by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bologna and Pinto (2002)</xref>, and the nominate subgenus was well defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Kuzin (1954)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Pardo Alcaide (1950)</xref>. The most recent comprehensive key to the species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris</tp:taxon-name></italic> remains that published by Sumakov (1915). In order to help with the identification of the Iranian species of the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris</tp:taxon-name></italic>, we provide a key to its species recorded in Iran.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Mylabris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        (<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subgenus">Mylabris</tp:taxon-name-part>)
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">barezensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0141DDB7-3BC1-49EC-A502-776A5004B625</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Mylabris_barezensis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type specimens">
                    <title>Type specimens.</title>
                    <p>Holotype male (HMIM), and 2 males (CB) and 1 male and 2 female paratypes (HMIM), labelled “ Dehbakri, 6.5.1969, Paz.&amp; Hasch.”.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality">
                    <title>Type locality.</title>
                    <p><bold>IRAN</bold>, Dehbakri (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">29.0539°N, 57.9131°E</named-content>); an Iranian town in the Kerman province, about 55 km southwest of Bam, east of Jebal Barez mountain, at 2027 m a.s.l. This mountainous area was characterized by forest until before the second World War (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Planhol 1969</xref>) but now secondary steppe habitats are widely spread.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>A <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris</tp:taxon-name></italic> species belonging to the nominate subgenus as defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Pardo Alcaide (1950)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Kuzin (1954)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bologna (1991)</xref>. Immediately distinguishable from other species of the subgenus by the unique elytral pattern characterized by reduced brown-orange surface and the large extension of black colouration everywhere as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1 and 2</xref>. Male gonoforceps in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 7</xref>) slender. The mesosternum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>) is narrowed posteriorly and the setae on its anteriorly modified section are longer than usual.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body uniformly black, except elytra which have the following pattern: black colouration largely extended everywhere, except brown-orange as follows: at base (along the scutellum excluded), along the external margin except at apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1, 2a</xref>) (in one specimen the posterior section of the external margin is fragmented in one spot as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2b</xref>) and with two sub-oval spots, one in the middle, and another on the posterior third; in one specimen, the middle spot is fused to the brown-orange base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2c</xref>). Setation uniformly black, but ventral side of male foretibiae and foretarsi with golden setae, forming a small pad under the pro- and mesotarsomeres; setation evidently longer on venter than dorsally; setae denser on head and pronotum, sparser on elytra. Body length: 10–15 mm.</p>
                    <p>Head slightly longer than wide at temples level (excluding mandibles), wider at temples than at eyes; punctures relatively deep, large and irregular, surface among punctures shagreened, shiny on vertex, wrinkled on frons; head capsule subquadrate, temples broadly curved posteriorly and subequal in length to the longitudinal length of eye; frons flat, in the middle with one red spot more or less divided posteriorly; clypeus transverse, convex, with slightly rounded anterior and lateral margins, anteriorly depressed, fronto-clypeal suture clearly visible; labrum only slightly shorter and narrower than clypeus, anterior margin sinuate, longitudinally depressed in the middle; mandibles robust, curved, in lateral view longer than clypeus and labrum together; maxillary palpomere II with very long setae on the posterior side, last maxillary palpomere apically thickened and truncate at apex; antennae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>) extending almost to posterior margin of pronotum in male, scapus more than twice as long as pedicellus, pedicellus semi-globular; antennomere III elongate and about 1.2 times as long as IV–V together, IV and V similar in length, VI similar in length to IV and V but slightly widened apically, VIII – X progressively more elongate and apically widened, X subcylindrical, last antennomere elongate and narrowed in the last third, particularly in male.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->Pronotum slightly wider than long, narrowed anteriad, convex, without evident depressions or with a superficial rounded depression in the middle of each side, maximum width posterior to middle; punctures almost confluent on anterior and posterior third; elytral pattern as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1 and Fig. 2 (a, b, c)</xref>, elytral setation shorter and sparser than that on head and pronotum, erect on the anterior third, recumbent and shorter on the remaining surface; mesosternum longitudinally elevated in the middle, with a clearly modified anterior section (“scutum”), with a slightly depressed oval area with dense and very long setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>); mesepisterna depressed along the anterior margin, which consequently appears to be raised. Legs black, pro- and mesotibial spurs both similar in shape and pointed, the inner metatibial spur stick-like and the external one pointed; femora with mixed short and long setae, setae robust and more elongate on tibiae and tarsi; male foretibiae ventrally with mixed golden and black short and dense setae, in female with short dense black pubescence and also elongate black setae on external side; male pro- and mesotarsomeres with ventral golden setae forming tarsal pads, those of mesotarsomeres smaller.</p>
                    <p>Sternite VIII deeply emarginate at middle of posterior margin in male, rounded in female. Male genitalia as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 5–8</xref>: in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 7</xref>) the basal part of gonoforceps slender, apical lobe of gonoforceps relatively short, slightly less than half the length of total gonoforceps; in ventral view, gonoforceps as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>; aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>) with two distinct subequal hooks, both positioned far from apex and with the same inclination, the proximal one slightly longer; endophallic hook slender and curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>). The apodeme of the s<italic>piculum gastrale</italic> is variable: most males have this sclerite slender in the middle and clearly narrowed and elongate in the last portion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 8a</xref>) but in a single male it is very wide medially (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 8b</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–8.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris barezensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>1</bold> Habitus <bold>2a–c</bold> variation of elytral pattern <bold>3</bold> mesosternum and mesepisterna <bold>4</bold> male left antenna <bold>5</bold> aedeagus, lateral view <bold>6</bold> tegmen, ventral view <bold>7</bold> tegmen, lateral view <bold>8a–b</bold> variation of <italic>spiculum gastrale</italic>. Bar scales: 1 mm<bold>.</bold></p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-219-081-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>This new species is named after the Jebal Barez mountain range in Kerman Province, in the north west of which the new species was collected.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Taxonomic remarks">
                    <title>Taxonomic remarks.</title>
                    <p>The taxonomic revision of the nominate subgenus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris</tp:taxon-name></italic> as well as its phylogenetic study remain in preparation (Pan et al. unpublished). The nominate subgenus at present contains 19 species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bologna 2008</xref>), but at least another four undescribed species are recognized and will be described in a systematic study that includes both morphological and molecular data (Pan etal. unpublished).</p>
                    <p>For this reason we are unable to discuss in detail the phylogenetic relationships of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris barezensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. This species is clearly distinct from all others of the nominate subgenus by the unique elytral pattern, as well as by the mesosternal “scutum” with dense and very long setae.</p>
                    <p>Phenetically, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris barezensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is similar to two species of the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Micrabris</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Afghanistan, namely <italic>afghanica</italic> Kaszab, 1953 and <italic>marakensis badakhaskanica</italic> Kaszab, 1958 (both figured in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Kaszab 1958</xref>). Similarity is due to the extended black elytral pattern. From both species it can be easily distinguished by setose area on the mesosternum, the wider pronotum, and the shape and position of aedeagal hooks (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Kaszab 1958</xref> for comparison).</p>
                    <p>The type specimens were previously identified by Zoltán Kaszab, the late Hungarian specialist of <tp:taxon-name>Meloidae</tp:taxon-name>, as “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris biguttata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Gebler”, a species which actually belongs to the mylabrine genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hycleus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but has a similar elytral pattern.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <sec sec-type="Key to the Iranian species of Mylabris (Mylabris)">
                        <title>Key to the Iranian species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris (Mylabris)</tp:taxon-name></italic></title>
                        <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral apex with a very wide black fascia, more or less sinuate anteriorly and extended to cover ca. 1/6 of the entire surface</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral apex uniformly reddish-brown or with a narrow black colouration which sometimes extends on the sutural inner margin</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral pattern characterized by reduced orange-brown areas and a large extension of black colouration everywhere</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris (Mylabris) barezensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral pattern reduced to distinct spots or fasciae, never fused or coalescing to form an extended black network, which leaves isolated orange-brown areas</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum with a shallow anterior transverse depression. Frons without red macula (exceptions are very rare). Elytra usually with two series of spots, one anterior and one on the middle, and an apical fascia widely emarginate just before the suture (in some populations middle spots fused to form a wide fascia). Aedeagal distal hook long and curved, the proximal one very long and curved forward, longer than distal, positioned far from apex; gonostyli broadly cylindrical, suddenly narrowed apically in two long and slightly curved lobes</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris (Mylabris) quadripunctata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Linnaeus, 1767)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum without an anterior transverse depression. Frons with red macula. Elytral pattern not as above. Aedeagal distal hook short, the proximal one clearly longer than distal, both positioned close to apex and more rectilinear; gonostyli uniformly slender, cylindrical</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral pattern with two anterior oblique spots, one middle transverse incomplete and sinuate fascia, neither reaching the external margin nor the suture, and an apical small fascia sinuate on fore margin, not widely extended anteriorly. Aedeagal distal hook only slightly shorter than proximal, both hooks slightly inclined</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris (Mylabris) parumpicta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Heyden, 1883)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral pattern usually with three fasciae (anterior, middle and apical), the middle one reaching both external margin and suture, the apical one widely extended anteriorly, with fore margin slightly emarginated lateral to the suture (in some populations the anterior fascia is reduced to two spots). Aedeagal distal hook clearly shorter than proximal hook, both clearly inclined</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris (Mylabris) variabilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Pallas, 1781)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennomeres III-XI (particularly VII-XI) reddish, XI almost brownish. Black apical fascia of elytra very narrow,extended along the suture and reaching the internal margin of subapical transverse fascia</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris (Mylabris) olivieri</tp:taxon-name></italic> Billberg, 1813</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antennomeres uniformly black. Elytral pattern not as above</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytra uniformly reddish-brown with an extremely narrow black fascia on the apex</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris (Mylabris) apicenigra</tp:taxon-name></italic> Soumakov, 1915</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytra uniformly reddish-ochre</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mylabris (Mylabris) concolor</tp:taxon-name></italic> Marseul, 1870</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                        </table-wrap>
                    </sec>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bologna</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<source> <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name> Meloidae, Fauna d’Italia.</source> <publisher-name>XXVIII.Calderini</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Bologna</publisher-loc>, <lpage>541</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bologna</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> New nomenclatorial and taxonomic acts, and comments, Meloidae; family Meloidae Gyllenhal, 1810.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Löbl</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smetana</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Catalogue of Palaearctic Coleoptera 5.</issue-title> <source>Apollo Books, Stenstrup, 45–49</source>: <fpage>370</fpage>-<lpage>412</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bologna</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname> <given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> The Old World genera of Meloidae (Coleoptera): a key and synopsis.</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>2013</fpage>-<lpage>2102</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222930110062318">10.1080/00222930110062318</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaszab</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1957</year>)<article-title> Neue Meloiden aus Iran (1954) (Coleopt.).</article-title> <source>Jahreshefte des Vereins für Vaterländische Naturkunde in Württemberg</source> <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>50</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaszab</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1958</year>)<article-title> Die Meloiden Afghanistans (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Acta Zoologica Academiae Scientiarum Hungaricae </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>-<lpage>312</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaszab</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> Contribution à la faune de l’Iran, 8. Coléoptères Meloidae.</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société Entomologique de France (NS) </source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>749</fpage>-<lpage>776</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuzin</surname> <given-names>VS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1954</year>)<article-title> K posnanyju systemy narybnikov (Coleoptera, Meloidae, Mylabrini).</article-title> <source>Trudly Usesojnogo Entomologizesko Obzestva</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>336</fpage>-<lpage>379</lpage>. [In Russian]</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirzayans</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> Contribution à la connaissance de la faune des Clerides er Méloides de l’Iran.</article-title> <source>Entomologie et Phytopathologie Appliquées </source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pardo Alcaide</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1950</year>)<article-title> Estudios sobre Meloidae. II.</article-title> <source>Los Mylabrini de la peninsula Iberica, Boletin de Patólogia vegetal y de Entomologia Agricola </source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Planhol</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>)<article-title> Le déboisement de l’Iran.</article-title> <source>Annales de Géographie </source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>625</fpage>-<lpage>635</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3406/geo.1969.15948">10.3406/geo.1969.15948</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Soumacov</surname> <given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1915</year>)<article-title> Les espèces paléarctiques du genre <italic>Mylabris</italic> Fabr. (Coleoptera, Meloidae).</article-title> <source>Horae Societatis Entomologicae Rossicae </source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>