<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id  pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.182.2430</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>The genus <italic>Shirozuella</italic> Sasaji (Coleoptera, Coccinellidae, Shirozuellini) from the Chinese mainland</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Wang</surname>
                        <given-names>Xing-Min</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:9A316497-BA7A-4FEC-B9F7-8E806E495D1E</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Ge</surname>
                        <given-names>Feng</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:3CDEFC4D-F2AF-4D4F-A7C7-87642096E610</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Ren</surname>
                        <given-names>Shun-Xiang</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:3D26C274-7182-413F-8352-453BFB99437B</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, 100101 China
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Engineering Research Center of Biological Control, Ministry of Education, South China Agricultural University, Guangzhou, 510642 China
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Feng Ge (<email xlink:type="simple">gef@ioz.ac.cn</email>), Shunxiang Ren (<email xlink:type="simple">rensxcn@yahoo.com.cn</email>)
                    </p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: N. Vandenberg</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>10</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>182</issue>
            <fpage>87</fpage>
            <lpage>108</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>24</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>20</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Xing-Min Wang, Feng Ge, Shun-Xiang Ren</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:140066A4-367A-4270-9967-B2101B34E966</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sasaji, 1967 from the Chinese mainland is reviewed. Eight species are recognized, including four new species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella motuoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella tibetina</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella unciforma</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella guoyuei</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> Male genitalia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella parenthesis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella quadrimacularis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are described for the first time. All species are described and illustrated. A key and distribution map to the known species from the Chinese mainland are given.
                </p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Coleoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Coccinellidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Shirozuellini</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Shirozuella</italic>
                </kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>China</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> was established by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Sasaji (1967)</xref> with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella mirabilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Taiwan, China, as type species. It is a peculiar genus as follows: Clypeus distinctly expanded laterally, but antennal insertions not entirely hidden under the clypeus and distinctly visible in the lateral aspect, and labrum relatively long and exposed in front of the clypeus; antennae moderate in length with a distinct club; terminal maxillary palpomere <!--PageBreak-->very elongate, not distinctly broadening apically; underside of head capsule with deep furrows beside the mouth parts, for the reception of the retracted antennae. Based on these characteristics, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Sasaji (1967)</xref> established the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Shirozuellini</tp:taxon-name> for reception of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Promecopharus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sicard, 1910. Presently, <tp:taxon-name>Shirozuellini</tp:taxon-name> includes five genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Miyatake 1994</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sasaji, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Promecopharus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sicard, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Medamatento</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sasaji, 1989, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ghanius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ahmad, 1973, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sasajiella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Miyatake, 1994. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Seago et al. (2011)</xref> listed <italic><tp:taxon-name>Guillermo</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ślipiński, 2007 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Poorani</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ślipiński, 2007 as <tp:taxon-name>Shirozuellini</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Coccinellinae</tp:taxon-name>) in a table. Although this was purported to be the original placement, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Ślipiński (2007)</xref> had actually placed these genera in <tp:taxon-name>Coccidulini</tp:taxon-name>. Regardless, nothing in these recent analyses provided a justification for the inclusion of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Guillermo</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Poorani</tp:taxon-name></italic> in <tp:taxon-name>Shirozuellini</tp:taxon-name>.
            </p>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> is something of a taxonomic enigma. It is similar to <tp:taxon-name>Telsimiini</tp:taxon-name> of the <tp:taxon-name>Chilocorinae</tp:taxon-name> in having the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Chilocorus</tp:taxon-name></italic>-like clypeus, but the features of the antennae and maxillae, and the number of abdominal ventrites, as well as the structure of the head capsule are different than in the latter. A relatively close affinity with <tp:taxon-name>Sticholotidini</tp:taxon-name> is suggested by the very elongate maxillary palpi, the femora not strongly flattened, the relatively long antennae with a distinctly spindle shaped club, and the ventrally articulated labial palpi. Similarly, an affinity with <tp:taxon-name>Serangiini</tp:taxon-name> is supported by the possession of longitudinal furrows on the underside of the head, and by the nearly triangular median area of the prosternum. Based on this body of evidence, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Sasaji (1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">1968</xref>) placed <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Shirozuellini</tp:taxon-name> of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Sticholotidinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Sasaji 1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">1968</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Seago et al’s (2011)</xref> molecular analysis didn’t support Sasaji’s result, although it also failed to place <tp:taxon-name>Shirozuellini</tp:taxon-name> in any reasonable group. Instead, it adopted a two subfamily system for the family <tp:taxon-name>Coccinellidae</tp:taxon-name> as suggested by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Ślipiński (2007)</xref>, <tp:taxon-name>Microweiseinae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Coccinellinae</tp:taxon-name>, and placed <tp:taxon-name>Shirozuellini</tp:taxon-name> in <tp:taxon-name>Coccinellinae</tp:taxon-name>.
            </p>
            <p>At present, the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> includes eight species distributed in Southeast and East Asia. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Yu and Pang (1992)</xref> described the male genitalia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella mirabilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and added two new species from Taiwan, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella appendiculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella alishanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Canepari and Milanese (1997)</xref> described a new species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ghanius schawalleri</tp:taxon-name></italic>, from Nepal Himalayas which was subsequently transferred to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Yu (2000[1999])</xref>. Four species were added from the Chinese mainland, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella parenthesis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella bimaculata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella quadrim</tp:taxon-name></italic><italic>acularis</italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella nibagou</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Yu 2000[1999]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Yu et al. 2000</xref>). The male genitalia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella bimaculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> were described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Ren et al. (2009)</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>Specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> are rarely collected, and both sexes are known only for two of the eight previously described species. Most species were described based on only one or two specimens. In this paper, species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Chinese mainland are reviewed, and four species new to science are described, bringing the total to eight mainland species, and twelve species in all. Male genitalia of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella parenthesis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella quadrimacularis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are illustrated and described for the first time.
            </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
            <title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>The specimens examined were collected from China. All of them were preserved in 85% ethanol. External morphology was observed with a dissecting stereo microscope<!--PageBreak--> (SteREO Discovery V20, Zeiss). The following measurements were made with an ocular micrometer: total length, from apical margin of clypeus to apex of elytra (TL); total width, across both elytra at widest part (TW=EW); height, through the highest point of elytra to metaventrite (TH); head width, including eyes (HW); pronotal length, from the middle of anterior margin to the base of pronotum (PL); pronotal width at widest part (PW); elytral length, along the suture, from the apex to the base including the scutellum (EL). Male and female genitalia were dissected, cleared in a 10% solution of NaOH by boiling for several minutes, and examined with an Olympus BX51 compound microscope.</p>
            <p>Images were photographed with digital cameras (AxioCam HRc and Coolsnap–Pro<italic>cf</italic> &amp; CRI Micro*Color), connected to the dissecting microscope. The software AxioVision Rel. 4.8 and Image–Pro Plus 5.1 were used to capture images from both cameras, and photos were cleaned up and laid out in plates with Adobe Photoshop CS 8.0.
            </p>
            <p>Terminology follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Ślipiński (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Ślipiński and Tomaszewska (2010)</xref>.
            </p>
            <p>The specimens are deposited in: South China Agriculture University, Guangzhou (SCAU), Institute of Plant &amp; Environmental Protection, Beijing Academy of Agricultural &amp; Forestry Science, Beijing (BAAF) and in the Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing (IOZ).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Shirozuella</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Sasaji, 1967</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name><comment> Sasaji, 1967: 24. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella mirabilis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sasaji, 1967</comment>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name><comment>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Yu and Pang 1992</xref>: 37; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Miyatake 1994</xref>: 274; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Yu et al. 2000</xref>: 187.</comment>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>The tribe <tp:taxon-name>Shirozuellini</tp:taxon-name> includes five genera sharing many similar morphological characters: laterally expanded clypeus, very elongate terminal maxillary palpomere. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, however can be distinguished from others by having: prosternum with distinct grooves anteriorly to receive antennae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>) and maxillary palpi when the head is retracted; underside of head capsule with distinct grooves for reception of the retracted antennae; and antennae composed of nine antennomeres (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body small, oval, relatively elongate; dorsum weakly convex and pubescent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 12</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">29</xref>). Head moderate in size, frontal surface of capsule flattened, slightly convex; clypeus long and distinctly expanded laterally; antennae inserted laterally near the apical end of head capsule; eyes large (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Antennae relatively long, composed of nine antennomeres with a distinct club composed of three antennomeres, eighth antennomere longest and widest, terminal antennomere rather small and conical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>). Labrum relatively long. Mandible, bidentate at apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>). Maxillary palp much longer than antenna, composed of four palpomeres; terminal palpomere very elongate, and spatulate, more than twice as long as wide, with apex obliquely <!--PageBreak-->truncate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>). Labial palp composed of 3 palpomeres and distal two palpomeres elongate and nearly cylindrical. Ventral surface of head capsule with distinct grooves for reception of retracted antennae.
                    </p>
                    <p>Pronotum transverse, about twice as wide as long, strongly convex, lateral margins narrowly marginated and distinctly emarginated anteriorly. Scutellum medium-sized, triangular. Elytra elongate and weakly convex, with conspicuous swelling near humeral edge. Elytral base hardly wider than base of pronotum; elytral margins with very narrow rim, but distinctly visible from above. Hind wing well developed, with veins rather well-developed.</p>
                    <p>Prosternum short in front of coxae, distinctly grooved to receive antennae and palpi; prosternal process broad without longitudinal carinae. Mesoventrite broadly and nearly quadrate, slightly wider than long, anterior margin emarginate. Metaventrite broad, discrimen complete. Elytral epipleuron relatively narrow, nearly horizontal, not foveate, obsolete in apical third. Abdomen with six ventrites, ventrite 1 with complete postcoxal lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>). Legs relatively long; femora distinctly swollen and grooved to receive tibiae when retracted; tibiae slender and simple, tarsi composed of 3 tarsomeres (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 7</xref>).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Gansu, Hunan, Henan, Shanxi, Shaanxi, Sichuan, Taiwan, Tibet, Yunnan), Japan, Nepal.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to species of Shirozuella Sasaji from the Chinese mainland">
                    <title>Key to species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sasaji from the Chinese mainland
                    </title>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytron with a yellow or yellowish brown spot or stripe</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytron with two yellow or yellowish brown spots or stripes</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytron with a nearly rounded spot</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytron with a long and diagonal stripe</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Penis short and stout, penis guide in ventral view nearly triangular, apex pointed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 10</xref>). TL: 1.71–1.86mm, TW: 1.19–1.32mm
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella bimaculata</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Penis long and slender, penis guide in ventral view almost parallel at basal 2/3, apex truncate with a pair of small triangular projections on each side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 39</xref>). TL: 1.58–1.81mm, TW: 1.06–1.22 mm
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella motuoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral macula emarginate antero-laterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 18–19</xref>). Abdominal postcoxal line complete, reaching ½ length of ventrite 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 41</xref>). TL: 1.88mm, TW: 1.19 mm
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella nibagou</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytral macula without antero-lateral emargination Abdominal postcoxal line complete, reaching more than ½ length of ventrite 1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>5</italic>
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytra black, apex very narrowly brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 21–22</xref>). Anterior angles of pronotum black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 23</xref>). Apex of penis guide pointed, slightly curved outwardly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 46</xref>). TL: 1.68–1.75mm, TW: 1.02–1.12mm</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella tibetina</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elytra reddish brown, apical 1/10 yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 24–25</xref>). Anterior angles of pronotum yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 26</xref>). Apex of penis guide unciform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 51</xref>). TL: 1.65–1.75mm, TW: 1.12–1.29mm
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella unciforma</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each elytron with two longitudinal yellow spots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 27</xref>). Pronotum black (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 27</xref>). TL: 1.86mm, TW: 1.2mm
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella quadrimacularis</tp:taxon-name></italic><!--PageBreak-->
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Each elytron with two transverse bands. Pronotum yellow, or bicolored</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum with disk black and lateral margins yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 30</xref>). TL: 1.81–2.31mm, TW: 1.24–1.58mm
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella parenthesis</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pronotum yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 33</xref>). TL: 1.94mm, TW: 1.32mm
                                    </td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella guoyuei</tp:taxon-name></italic>
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–11.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella bimaculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu. <bold>1</bold> head, frontal view <bold>2</bold> prothorax, ventral <bold>3</bold> antenna <bold>4</bold> mandible <bold>5</bold> maxilla <bold>6</bold> abdomen <bold>7</bold> hind leg <bold>8–10</bold> male genitalia <bold>8</bold> penis <bold>9</bold> tegmen, lateral view <bold>10</bold> tegmen, ventral view <bold>11</bold> female genitalia: ovipositor. Scale bars: <bold>1–2</bold>: 0.2mm; <bold>3–10</bold>: 0.1mm.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-182-087-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">bimaculata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Shirozuella_bimaculata</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Yu, 2000</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">–14</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">68</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella bimaculata</tp:taxon-name><comment> Yu, 2000[1999]: 63; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Ren et al. 2009</xref>: 42.</comment>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species can be identified as follows: pronotum uniformly yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 12</xref>), elytron black with a large yellow spot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 12</xref>), penis short and stout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 8</xref>), and penis guide short and subtriangular (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 9–10</xref>).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>TL: 1.71–1.86mm, TW: 1.19–1.32mm, TH: 0.63–0.69mm, TL/TW: 1.41–1.44; PL/PW: 0.44–0.47; EL/EW: 1.08–1.14.</p>
                    <p>Body small, elongate oval, weakly convex, dorsum covered with relatively sparse pubescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 12–14</xref>). Head yellow with maxillary palpus dark brown. Pronotum yellow, scutellum dark brown. Elytra blackish, with two large yellow spots placed on apical half, apex narrowly yellow. Ventral surfaces uniformly dark brown, legs yellow.
                    </p>
                    <p>Head moderately large (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), 0.35× elytral width (HW/EW=2.86); frontal surface of head capsule slightly convex; punctures on frons fine and sparse, separated by about 2.0–3.0× a diameter, with sparse long setae in punctures; eyes large, narrowly separated; widest interocular distance 2× narrowest width. Pronotum relatively small, 0.74× elytral width (PW/EW=1:1.36), pronotal punctures fine, inconspicuous, smaller than those on head, separated by 3.0–4.0× a diameter. Scutellum moderately large, triangular, visible from above. Punctures on elytra moderately large, irregular, obviously larger than those on pronotum, separated by 1.0–2.0× a diameter.
                    </p>
                    <p>Surface of prosternum slightly shagreened, punctures inconspicuous, with sparse short setae. Mesoventrite shiny and glabrous, punctures inconspicuous, with several short setae. Metaventrite broad and glabrous, median part concave, with complete median discrimen; punctures sparse and large, with short sparse setae. Abdominal postcoxal line complete, v-shaped, reaching to 2/3 length of ventrite 1, or almost touching posterior margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Male genitalia: Penis short and stout, penis capsule with indistinct outer arm and short inner one (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 8</xref>); penis guide in lateral view slender, widest at base, tapering to apex, apex pointed and slightly curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 9</xref>); parameres slender, sparsely setose on apical half, about 1.65× as long as penis guide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 9</xref>); penis guide in ventral view short and stout, subtriangular, widest at base, tapering to apex, apex pointed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 10</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Female genitalia: Coxites elongate, about 3.0 times as long as wide, tapering to blunt, darker apices, styli distinct, with short terminal setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 11</xref>); spermatheca not sclerotized.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Types examined">
                    <title>Types examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype:</bold> 1♀, <bold>China, Henan:</bold> Huangshian, Laojieling, Taiping Town, Xixia County, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">33°37.53'N, 111°46.17'E</named-content>], ca 1500m, 19.vii.1998, Yu Guoyue leg. (BAAF).<!--PageBreak-->
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other specimens examined">
                    <title>Other specimens examined.</title>
                    <p>1♂1♀, <bold>China, Gansu:</bold> Maijishan Forest Park, Tianshui, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">34°20.81'N, 106°0.71'E</named-content>], ca 1500m, 10.viii.2008, Wang XM leg. (SCAU); 4♂♂, Maijishan Forest Park, Tianshui, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">34°20.81'N, 106°0.71'E</named-content>], ca 1650m, 6.viii.2009, Wang XM et al. leg. (3♂♂ SCAU; 1♂ IOZ); <bold>Henan:</bold> 2♂♂2♀♀, Longy<!--PageBreak-->uwan Forest Park, Luanchuan, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">33°41.16'N, 111°50.72'E</named-content>], ca 1400m, 11.vii.2009, Wang XM et al. Leg. (1♂1♀ SCAU, 1♂1♀ IOZ); <bold>Shaanxi:</bold> 2♂♂2♀♀, Xunyangba, Ningshan, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">33°32.87'N, 108°33.13'E</named-content>], ca 1600m, 23.vii.2009, Wang XM et al. Leg. (SCAU).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Gansu, Henan, Shaanxi).</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 12–20.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold>12–14</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella bimaculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu. <bold>12</bold> dorsal view; <bold>13</bold> lateral view <bold>14</bold> frontal view <bold>15–17</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella motuoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>15</bold> dorsal view <bold>16</bold> lateral view <bold>17</bold> frontal view <bold>18–20</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella nibagou</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu.<bold>18</bold> dorsal view <bold>19</bold> lateral view <bold>20</bold> frontal view. Scale bars: 0.5mm.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-182-087-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 21–29.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold>21–23</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella tibetina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>21</bold> dorsal view; <bold>22</bold> lateral view <bold>23</bold> frontal view <bold>24–26</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella unciforma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>24</bold> dorsal view <bold>25</bold> lateral view <bold>26</bold> frontal view <bold>27–29</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella quadrimacularis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu<bold>27</bold> dorsal view <bold>28</bold> lateral view <bold>29</bold> frontal view. Scale bars: 0.5mm.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-182-087-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 30–35.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold>30–32</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella parenthesis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu <bold>30</bold> dorsal view <bold>31</bold> lateral view <bold>32</bold> frontal view <bold>33–35</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella guoyuei</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>33</bold> dorsal view <bold>34</bold> lateral view <bold>35</bold> frontal view.Scale bars: 0.5mm.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-182-087-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">motuoensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8705EDF0-F6A7-4298-94A6-8A9F2AB90F4F</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Shirozuella_motuoensis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 15–17</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">36–40</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">68</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is close to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella bimaculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> in general appearance, but it is easily distinguished from the latter by the long and slender penis and the special shape of penis guide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 37–39</xref>).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>TL: 1.58–1.81mm, TW: 1.06–1.22mm, TH: 0.63–0.82mm, TL/TW: 1.49–1.50; PL/PW: 0.48–0.50; EL/EW: 1.14–1.31.</p>
                    <p>Body small, elongate oval, weakly convex, dorsum covered with relatively sparse pubescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 15–17</xref>). Head yellow to yellowish brown, with labrum and maxillary palpus brown. Pronotum yellowish brown, scutellum dark brown. Elytra blackish, with two large yellow spots placed on apical half, apex narrowly yellow. Prosternum dark brown, meso- and metaventrite black, elytral epipleura and legs brown.
                    </p>
                    <p>Head moderately large, 0.41× elytral width (HW/EW=2.46); frontal surface of head capsule slightly convex and rather weakly anteriorly inclined below; punctures on frons fine and sparse, inconspicuous, separated by 2.0–4.0× a diameter, with sparse long setae in punctures; eyes relatively large, narrowly separated; widest interocular distance 1.3× narrowest width. Pronotum relatively small, 0.69× elytral width (PW/EW=1: 1.45), pronotal punctures very fine and inconspicuous, smaller than those on head, separated by 3.0–4.0× a diameter. Scutellum moderately large, triangular, visible from above. Punctures on elytra moderately large, irregular, obviously larger than those on pronotum, separated by 1.0–2.5× a diameter.</p>
                    <p>Surface of prosternum mat and slightly shagreened, punctures inconspicuous, with sparse short setae. Mesoventrite slightly shagreened, punctures inconspicuous, with several short setae. Metaventrite broad and glabrous, median part concave, with complete median discrimen; punctures sparse and fine, separated by 2.0–6.0× a diameter, with short sparse setae. Abdominal postcoxal line complete, v-shaped, touching posterior margin of ventrite 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 36</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Male genitalia: Penis long and slender, strongly curved at 2/5 length, distinctly swollen at middle, penis capsule small (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 37</xref>); penis guide in lateral view slender, widest at base, tapering to apex, apex pointed and slightly curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 38</xref>); parameres slender, sparsely setose on apical half, about 2× as long as penis guide, always strongly curved at apical 2/5 length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 38</xref>); penis guide in ventral view short and stout, a<!--PageBreak-->lmost parallel at basal 2/3, then tapering to apex, apex truncated with a pair of small triangular projections on each side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 39</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Female genitalia: Coxities elongate, about 3.5× as long as wide, tapering to blunt, darker apices, styli small and distinct, with short terminal setae, apical area distinctly darkened (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 40</xref>); spermatheca not sclerotized.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Types">
                    <title>Types.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype:</bold> 1♂, <bold>China, Tibet:</bold> Hanmi, Motuo County, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">29°°21.87'N, 95°7.75'E</named-content>], ca 2100m, 13.x.2009, Wang XM leg. (SCAU). <bold>Paratypes: China, Tibet:</bold> 2♀♀, same data as holotype; 1♂, Yarang village, Motuo, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">29°17.70'N, 95°16.87'E</named-content>], ca 1000m, 24.x.2007, Wang XM leg. (SCAU).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Tibet).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific epithet refers to Motuo, the type locality of this ladybird.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">nibagou</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Shirozuella_nibagou</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Yu, 2000</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 18–20</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">41–43</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">68</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella nibagou</tp:taxon-name><comment>: Yu et al., 2000: 188.</comment>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is easily distinguished from other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> by black body and elytron with a yellowish curved spot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 18–19</xref>).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>TL: 1.88mm, TW: 1.19mm, TH: 0.76mm, TL/TW: 1.58; PL/PW: 0.56; EL/EW: 1.03.</p>
                    <p>Body small, elongate oval, weakly convex. Dorsum covered with relatively sparse pubescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 18–20</xref>). Head black. Pronotum and scutellum black. Elytron blackish, with a curved large yellowish brown spot situated between 2/5 and 4/5 elytral length to apex. Underside uniformly dark.
                    </p>
                    <p>Head moderately large, 0.36× elytral width (HW/EW=2.77); frontal surface of head capsule flattened and rather weakly anteriorly inclined below; punctures on frons fine and sparse, separated by 2.0–3.0× a diameter, with sparse long setae in punctures; eyes relatively large, narrowly separated; widest interocular distance 1.3× narrowest width. Pronotum 0.69× elytral width (PW/EW=1: 1.44), pronotal punctures very fine, inconspicuous, smaller than those on head. Scutellum moderately large, triangular, visible from above. Punctures on elytra large, irregular, obviously larger than those on head, separated by 0.2–0.5× a diameter.</p>
                    <p>Surface of prosternum slightly mat and shagreened, punctures inconspicuous, with sparse short setae. Mesoventrite shiny and glabrous, punctures inconspicuous, with several short setae. Metaventrite broad and glabrous, median part concave, with complete median discrimen; punctures sparse and fine, with short sparse setae. Abdominal postcoxal line complete, reaching to 1/2 length of ventrite 1, then recurved basally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 41</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Male genitalia: Penis short and stout, penis capsule indistinct, apex rounded by membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 42</xref>); penis guide in lateral view slender, widest at base, tapering to apex, apex pointed and slightly curved; parameres slender, sparsely setose; penis guide <!--PageBreak-->in ventral view short and stout, parallel at basal 6/7, then converging sharply to teat-like tip (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 43</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Female genitalia: Coxities elongate, tapering to blunt, darker apices, styli small and distinct, with short terminal setae; spermatheca not sclerotized.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Types examined">
                    <title>Types examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype:</bold> 1♂, <bold>China, Sichuan:</bold> Nibagou, Baoxing, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">30°41.31'N, 102°42.87'E</named-content>], ca viii.1997, Guo H. leg. (BAAF). <bold>Paratype:</bold> 1♀, same data as holotype.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Sichuan).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">tibetina</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BE699A24-2054-47FD-B1F2-D744ABBD67D0</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Shirozuella_tibetina</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 21–23</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">44–48</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">68</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is close to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella nibagou</tp:taxon-name></italic> in general appearance, but it can be distinguished from the latter as follows: posterior margin of abdominal postcoxal line reaching to 4/5 ventrite length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 44</xref>), and elytral spots are not curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 21–22</xref>). In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella nibagou</tp:taxon-name></italic>, posterior margin of abdominal postcoxal line reaching to 1/2 ventrite length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 41</xref>), and elytral spots are curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 18–19</xref>). The male genitalia are also diagnostic.
                    </p>
                    <p>This species is also similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella schawalleri</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Canepari &amp; Milanese, 1997) in general appearance, but it can be distinguished from the latter by elytra with a curved yellowish brown spot and elongated triangular coxities. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella schawalleri</tp:taxon-name></italic>, spots on elytra are straight and oblique and outer margins of coxities arcuate.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>TL: 1.68–1.75mm, TW: 1.02–1.12mm, TH: 0.66–0.76mm, TL/TW: 1.41–1.44; PL/PW: 0.51–0.52; EL/EW: 1.18–1.19.</p>
                    <p>Body small, elongate oval, weakly convex, dorsum covered with sparse pubescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 21–23</xref>). Head black with maxillary palpus brown. Pronotum black with anterior slightly brown, scutellum black. Elytron black, with a curved yellowish brown spot situated between 2/5 and 4/5 elytral length to apex. Ventral surface dark, except elytral epipleura and legs brown.
                    </p>
                    <p>Head moderately large, 0.38× elytral width (HW/EW=2.62); frontal surface of head capsule flattened and rather weakly anteriorly inclined below; punctures on frons fine, separated by 2.0–4.0× a diameter, with sparse long setae in punctures; eyes relatively large, narrowly separated; widest interocular distance about 1.5× narrowest width. Pronotum 0.68× elytral width (PW/EW=1: 1.48), pronotal punctures very fine, smaller than those on head, separated by 2.0–4.0× a diameter. Scutellum moderately large, triangular. Punctures on elytra moderately large, obviously larger than those on pronotum, separated by 1.5–2.5× a diameter.</p>
                    <p>Pro- and mesoventrite slightly shagreened, punctures inconspicuous, with sparse short setae. Metaventrite broad and glabrous, median part concave, with complete median discrimen; punctures fine and sparse, separated by about 2.0–4.0× a diameter,<!--PageBreak--> with short sparse setae. Abdominal postcoxal line complete, reaching to 4/5 length of ventrite 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 44</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Male genitalia: Penis short and stout, penis capsule distinct, apex blunt and slightly swollen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 45</xref>); penis guide in lateral view stout, widest at basal 2/5, apex pointed <!--PageBreak-->and curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 46</xref>); parameres slender, sparsely setose at apex, distinctly longer than penis guide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 46</xref>); penis guide in ventral view short and stout, parallel at basal 10/11, then converging sharply to pointed apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 47</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Female genitalia: Coxities elongate, subtriangular, about 3.5 × as long as wide, tapering to blunt, darker apices, styli small and distinct, with short terminal setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 48</xref>); spermatheca not sclerotized.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Types">
                    <title>Types.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype: China, Tibet:</bold> 1♂, Xiayadong town, Yadong, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">28°29.29'N, 97°1.36'E</named-content>], ca 2800m, 1.x.2009, Wang XM et al. leg.(SCAU). <bold>Paratypes: Tibet:</bold> 1♂6♀♀, same data as holotype (SCAU); 2♀♀, North of Chayu City, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">28°42.03'N, 97°27.77'E</named-content>], ca 2300m, 18.x.2007, Wang XM leg. (SCAU); 1♂1♀, Le Village, Cuona, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">27°48.63'N, 91°44.98'E</named-content>], ca 2400m, 3.x.2009, Wang XM et al. Leg. (SCAU).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Tibet).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific epithet is in reference to Tibet, the type locality of this ladybird.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">unciforma</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:21E76C93-6EB3-4933-820B-46F86E2E142F</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Shirozuella_unciforma</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 24–26</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">49–53</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">68</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is close to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella tibetina</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but it can be distinguished from the latter as follows: elytral apex is distinct yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 24–25</xref>), penis apex is slightly swollen and penis guide’s apex unciform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 50–51</xref>). Coxities are also diagnostic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 53</xref>).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description. </title>
                    <p>TL: 1.65–1.75mm, TW: 1.12–1.29mm, TH: 0.66–0.73mm, TL/TW: 1.36–1.47; PL/PW: 0.52–0.55; EL/EW: 1.05–1.12.</p>
                    <p>Body small, elongate oval, weakly convex, dorsum covered with relatively sparse pubescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 24–26</xref>). Head brown to black. Pronotum black with anterior corners clearly yellowish brown, scutellum black. Elytron brown to black, with an elongate oblique yellowish brown spot situated between 2/5 and 4/5 elytral length to apex. Pro- and mesoventrite brown, metaventrite black, elytral epipleura brown. Legs brown with coxae yellow.
                    </p>
                    <p>Head moderately large (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 26</xref>), about 0.31× elytral width (HW/EW=3.25); frontal surface of head capsule slightly convex and rather weakly anteriorly inclined below; punctures on frons fine, separated by 2.0–2.5× a diameter, with sparse long setae in punctures; eyes relatively large, narrowly separated; widest interocular distance about 1.5× narrowest width. Pronotum relatively small, 0.62× elytral width (PW/EW=1: 1.63), pronotal punctures very fine, smaller than those on head, separated by 1.5–3.5× a diameter. Scutellum moderately large, triangular, visible from above. Elytra rather elongate and weakly convex, with conspicuous swelling near humeral edge. Punctures on elytra moderately large, irregular, obviously larger than those on pronotum, separated by 1.5–2.5× a diameter.<!--PageBreak-->
                    </p>
                    <p>Pro- and mesoventrite slightly shagreened, punctures inconspicuous, with several short setae. Metaventrite broad and glabrous, median part concave, with complete median discrimen; punctures sparse and fine, separated by 2.5–3.0× a diameter, with short sparse setae. Abdominal postcoxal line complete, reaching to 4/5 length of ventrite 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 49</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Male genitalia: Penis short and stout, penis capsule inconspicuous, apex rounded (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 50</xref>); penis guide in lateral view stout, widest at base, gradually tapering to 4/5 length, then abruptly narrowed, apex unciform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 51</xref>); parameres slender, straight, sparsely setose at basal half, distinctly longer than penis guide; penis guide in ventral view short and stout, almost parallel at basal 4/5, then converging sharply to apex, apex slightly blunt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 52</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Female genitalia: Coxities elongate, subtriangular, about 2.5× as long as wide, tapering to blunt apices, styli very small and inconspicuous, each with short terminal setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 53</xref>); spermatheca not sclerotized.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Types">
                    <title>Types.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype:</bold> 1♂, <bold>China. Tibet:</bold> Hanmi, Motuo County, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">29°21.87'N, 95°7.75'E</named-content>], ca 2100m, 13.x.2009, Wang XM leg. (SCAU). <bold>Paratype</bold>: 1♀, same data as holotype.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Tibet).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific epithet is formed from the Latin adjective <italic>unciformus</italic>, referring to unciform apex of penis guide.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">quadrimacularis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Shirozuella_quadrimacularis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Yu, 2000</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 27–29</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">54–58</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">68</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella quadrimacularis</tp:taxon-name><comment>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Yu et al., 2000</xref>: 187; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Ren et al. 2009</xref>: 42.</comment>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species can be distinguished from other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name></italic> by elytra black with four longitudinal yellow spots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 27–28</xref>).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>TL: 1.86mm, TW: 1.2mm, TH: 0.71mm, TL/TW: 1.55; PL/PW: 0.42; EL/EW: 1.25.</p>
                    <p>Body small, elongate oval, weakly convex. Dorsum covered with relatively sparse pubescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 27–28</xref>). Head black with mouth parts brown. Pronotum black, with lateral margins and anterior corners brown. Scutellum black. Elytron blackish, with two longitudinal yellow spots, one situated at middle of elytral length, less than its width from suture, the other spot smaller, situated slightly past middle, distance to lateral margin slightly more than width of spot, elytral apex slightly yellow. Ventral surfaces uniformly black, except elytral epipleura brown. Legs brown with coxae and tarsi yellow.
                    </p>
                    <p>Head moderately large (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 29</xref>), 0.40× elytral width (HW/EW=2.50); frontal surface of head capsule slightly convex and rather weakly anteriorly inclined below; punctures on frons fine and inconspicuous, with sparse long setae in punctures; eyes <!--PageBreak-->relatively large, narrowly separated; widest interocular distance about 1.5× narrowest width. Pronotum 0.68× elytral width (PW/EW=1: 1.48), pronotal punctures extremely fine, separated by 3.0–5.0× a diameter. Scutellum moderately large, triangular. Punctures on elytra moderately large, irregular, obviously larger than those on pronotum, separated by 1.0–2.0× a diameter.
                    </p>
                    <p>Pro- and mesoventrite slightly shagreened, punctures inconspicuous, with sparse short setae. Metaventrite broad and glabrous, median part concave, with complete median discrimen; punctures sparse and fine, with short sparse setae. Abdominal postcoxal line complete, v-shaped, touching 2/3 length of ventrite 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 45</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Male genitalia: Penis short and stout, penis capsule small, apex rounded by membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 55</xref>); penis guide in lateral view stout, gradually narrowing to apex, apex pointed and curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 56</xref>); parameres slender, sparsely setose at apex, distinctly longer than penis guide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 56</xref>); penis guide in ventral view short and stout, parallel at basal 10/11, then converging sharply to pointed apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 57</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Female genitalia: Coxities elongate, about 3.5× as long as wide, tapering to blunt apices, styli small and distinct, with short terminal setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 58</xref>); spermatheca not sclerotized.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Types examined">
                    <title>Types examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype: China. Yunnan:</bold> 1♀, Lijiang, iv.1996, Yu GY leg. (BAAF).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other specimens examined">
                    <title>Other specimens examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>China, Sichuan:</bold> 1♀, Dafengding, Meigu, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">28°31.03'N, 103°18.22'E</named-content>], ca 2400m, 21.ix.2007, Wang XM leg. (SCAU); 1♂1♀, Pass 30km SW Mianning [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">28°27.87'N, 101°58.51'E</named-content>], ca 3000–3400m, 11–13.VII.2007, S. Murzin leg. (SCAU).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Sichuan, Yunnan).</p>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 36–43.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold>36–40</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella motuoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>36</bold> abdomen <bold>37–39</bold> male genitalia <bold>37</bold> penis <bold>38</bold> tegmen, lateral view <bold>39</bold> tegmen, ventral view <bold>40</bold> female genitalia: ovipositor <bold>41–43</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella nibagou</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu <bold>41</bold> abdomen <bold>42–43</bold> male genitalia <bold>42</bold> penis <bold>43</bold> tegmen, ventral view. Scale bars: 0.1 mm.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-182-087-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 44–53.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold>44–48</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella tibetina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>44</bold> abdomen <bold>45–47</bold> male genitalia <bold>45</bold> penis <bold>46</bold> tegmen, lateral view <bold>47</bold> tegmen, ventral view <bold>48</bold> female genitalia: ovipositor. <bold>49–53</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella unciforma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>49</bold> abdomen; <bold>50–52</bold> male genitalia: <bold>50</bold> penis <bold>51</bold> tegmen, lateral view <bold>52</bold> tegmen, ventral view <bold>53</bold> female genitalia: ovipositor. Scale bars: 0.1 mm.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-182-087-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">parenthesis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Shirozuella_parenthesis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Yu, 2000</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 30–32</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">59–63</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">68</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella parenthesis</tp:taxon-name><comment> Yu, 2000[1999]: 62.</comment>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis. </title>
                    <p>This species can be identified by pronotum yellowish brown, with a large quadrate black spot and black elytron with two large curved yellowish brown strips (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 30–31</xref>).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>TL: 1.81–2.31mm, TW: 1.24–1.58mm, TH: 0.82–0.89mm, TL/TW: 1.46–1.47; PL/PW: 0.51–0.52; EL/EW: 1.10–1.15.</p>
                    <p>Body small, elongate oval, weakly convex. Dorsum covered with relatively sparse pubescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 30–31</xref>). Head brown, with maxillary palpus dark brown. Pronotum yellowish brown, with a large quadrate black spot. Scutellum dark brown. Elytron black, with two large curved yellowish brown strips, one C-shaped, situated around out margin of humeral callus, connected to basal margin of elytron, another one v-shaped, situated between 2/5 and 4/5 elytral length to apex; apex of elytron narrowly yellowish brown. Ventral surfaces uniformly dark brown, except elytral epipleura and legs brown.<!--PageBreak-->
                    </p>
                    <p>Head moderately large (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 32</xref>), 0.37× elytral width (HW/EW=2.68); frontal surface of head capsule flatten and rather weakly anteriorly inclined below; punctures on frons fine and dense, separated by 1.5–2.0× a diameter, with sparse long setae in punctures; eyes relatively large, distinctly broader than interocular distance; widest interocular distance about 1.6× narrowest width. Pronotum relatively small, 0.67× elytral width (PW/EW=1: 1.50), pronotal punctures very fine, smaller than those on head, separated by 2.0–5.0× a diameter. Scutellum moderately large, triangular. Punctures on elytra moderately large, obviously larger than those on pronotum, separated by 1.0–3.0× a diameter.
                    </p>
                    <p>Pro- and mesoventrite slightly shagreened, punctures inconspicuous, with sparse short setae. Metaventrite broad and glabrous, median part flatten, with complete median discrimen; punctures on lateral area moderated large, separated by about 1.5–3.0× a diameter, with short sparse setae. Abdominal postcoxal line complete, reaching to 2/3 length of ventrite 1, then recurved basally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 59</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Male genitalia: Penis long and slender, penis capsule inconspicuous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 60</xref>); penis guide in lateral view slender, widest at base, tapering to apex, apex pointed and <!--PageBreak-->curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 61</xref>); parameres slender, sparsely setose at apical half, longer than penis guide, apex curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 61</xref>); penis guide in ventral view almost parallel at basal 3/4, then gradually narrowing to apex, apex truncated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 62</xref>).<!--PageBreak-->
                    </p>
                    <p>Female genitalia: Coxities elongate, subtriangular, about 5.3× as long as wide, tapering to blunt, darker apices, styli small and distinct, each with short terminal setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 63</xref>); spermatheca not sclerotized.
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Types examined">
                    <title>Types examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype:</bold> 1♀, <bold>China, Henan:</bold> Huangshian, Laojieling, Taiping Town, Xixia County, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">33°37.53'N, 111°46.17'E</named-content>], ca 1500m, 19.vii.1998, Yu GY leg. (BAAF).<!--PageBreak-->
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other specimens examined">
                    <title>Other specimens examined.</title>
                    <p>1♂2♀♀, <bold>China, Shanxi:</bold> Lishan National Natural Reserve, Yuanqu, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">35°28.39'N, 112°9.45'E</named-content>], ca 800–1400m, 3.viii.2011, Wang XM et al. leg. (SCAU).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Henan, Shanxi).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Shirozuella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">guoyuei</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:4A74A1CF-AAD1-4CD7-BFC9-0D275A23FB1A</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Shirozuella_guoyuei</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 33–35</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">64-</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">68</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is colse to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella parenthesis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in general appearance, but it can be distinguished from the latter by the distance between eyes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 35</xref>), yellow pronotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 33</xref>), stout penis and penis guide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 65–67</xref>).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>TL: 1.94mm, TW: 1.32mm, TH: 0.73mm, TL/TW: 1.48; PL/PW: 0.53; EL/EW: 1.15.</p>
                    <p>Body small, elongate oval, weakly convex. Dorsum covered with relatively sparse pubescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 33–34</xref>). Head brown, with terminal maxillary palpomere dark brown. Pronotum and scutellum yellow. Elytron black, with two large curved yellowish stripes, one c-shaped, situated around outer margin of humeral callus, connected to lateral margin of elytron, another one v-shaped, situated between 2/5 and 4/5 elytral <!--PageBreak-->length to apex, connected to elytral suture; apex of elytron yellow. Underside uniformly dark brown, except elytral epipleura and legs yellow.
                    </p>
                    <p>Head moderately large (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 35</xref>), 0.35× elytral width (HW/EW=2.86); frontal surface of head capsule slightly convex and rather weakly anteriorly inclined below; punctures on frons fine, separated by 0.5–1.5× a diameter, with sparse long setae in punctures; eyes relatively large, distinctly broader than interocular distance; widest interocular distance 3.2× narrowest width. Pronotum 0.66× elytral width (PW/EW=1: 1.51), pronotal punctures fine, smaller than those on head, separated by 1.0–3.0× a diameter. Scutellum moderately large, triangular. Punctures on elytra moderately large, irregular, obviously larger than those on pronotum, separated by 1.0–2.0× a diameter.
                    </p>
                    <p>Pro- and mesoventrite mat and shagreened, punctures inconspicuous, with sparse short setae. Metaventrite broad and glabrous, median part concaved, with complete median discrimen; punctures sparse and fine, separated by 2.0–3.0× a diameter, with short sparse setae. Abdominal postcoxal line complete, v-shaped, nearly reaching to posterior margin of ventrite 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 64</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Male genitalia: Penis short and stout, slightly curved, without penis capsule (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 65</xref>); penis guide in lateral view widest at base, gradually narrowed to apex, apex pointed and curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 66</xref>); parameres slender, sparsely setose at apical half, longer<!--PageBreak--> than penis guide, apex curved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 66</xref>); penis guide in ventral view almost parallel at basal 6/7, then gradually narrowing to apex, apex truncated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 67</xref>).
                    </p>
                    <p>Female genitalia: unknown.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Types">
                    <title>Types.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype:</bold> 1♂, <bold>China, Hunan:</bold> Tianpingshan, Zhangjiajie, [<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">29°43.02'N, 109°49.14'E</named-content>], ca 950m, 14.viii.2001, Peng ZQ leg. (SCAU).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>China (Hunan).
                    </p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The species is named after Dr. Yu Guoyue, an outstanding coccinellid taxonomist of China</p>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 54–63.</label>
                        <caption><p><bold>54–58</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella quadrimacularis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu <bold>54</bold> abdomen <bold>55–57</bold> male genitalia <bold>55</bold> penis <bold>56</bold> tegmen, lateral view <bold>57</bold> tegmen, ventral view <bold>58</bold> female genitalia: ovipositor <bold>59–63</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella parenthesis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu<bold>59</bold> abdomen <bold>60–62</bold> male genitalia <bold>60</bold> penis <bold>61</bold> tegmen, lateral view <bold>62</bold> tegmen, ventral view <bold>63</bold> female genitalia ovipositor. Scale bars: 0.1 mm. </p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-182-087-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 64–67.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella guoyuei</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>64</bold> abdomen <bold>65–67</bold> male genitalia <bold>65</bold> penis <bold>66</bold> tegmen, lateral view <bold>67</bold> tegmen, ventral view. Scale bars: 0.1 mm.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-182-087-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 68.</label>
                        <caption><p>Distribution map. ▲ <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella bimaculata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu ■ <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella motuoensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. ● <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella nibagou</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu  <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella tibetina</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. △ <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella unciforma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. □ <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella quadrimacularis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu ○ <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella parenthesis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Yu ◊ <italic><tp:taxon-name>Shirozuella guoyuei</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p>
                        </caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-182-087-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>The authors sincerely thank Dr. Yu Guoyue for encouragement, suggestions and support during this research work. My sincere thanks are extended to Dr. Claudio Canepari for examining specimens of <italic>S</italic>. <italic>Schawalleri</italic> and presenting two specimens of <italic>S. quadrimacularis</italic>. The research was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Nos. 2006FY120100 and 30970324).
            </p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>)<article-title> A new tribe of the family Coccinellidae (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of Entomological Research </source> <volume>62</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>449</fpage>-<lpage>452</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0007485300003989" xlink:type="simple">10.1017/S0007485300003989</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Canepari</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milanese</surname> <given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Coccinellidae (Coleoptera) from the Nepal Himalayas.</article-title> <source>Stuttgarter Beiträge zur Naturkunde, Serie A (Biologie) </source> <volume>565</volume>(<issue>65</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyatake</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> Revisional studies on Asian genera of the subfamily Sticholotidinae (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae).</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the College of Agriculture, Ehime University  </source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>-<lpage>292</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname> <given-names>SX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>XM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname> <given-names>ZQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Colored Pictorial Handbook of Ladybird Beetles in China.</source> <publisher-name>Science Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>, <lpage>336</lpage> pp.[In Chinese]</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaji</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> A revision of the Formosan Coccinellidae (I) the subfamily Sticholotinae, with an establishment of a new tribe (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Etizenia </source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaji</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of the family Coccinellidae (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Etizenia </source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaji</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Contribution to the taxonomy of the superfamily Cucujoidea (Coleoptera) of Japan and her adjacent districts, V.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the Faculty of Education, Fukui University Series II (Natural Science) </source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Seago</surname> <given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giorgi</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ślipiński</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny, classification and evolution of ladybird beetles (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae) based on simultaneous analysis of molecular and morphological data.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution </source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>-<lpage>151</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2011.03.015" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ympev.2011.03.015</ext-link></mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sicard</surname></name></person-group> (<year>1910</year>)<article-title> Espèces des variétés nouvelles de M. Andrewes (de London).</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société Entomologique de France </source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>377</fpage>-<lpage>389</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ślipiński</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> Australian ladybird beetles (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae) their biology and classification.</source> <publisher-name>ABRS</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Canberra</publisher-loc>, <lpage>286</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ślipiński</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomaszewska</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Coccinellidae Latreille, 1802.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Leschen</surname> <given-names>RAB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beutel</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Handbook of Zoology, 2, Coleoptera.</issue-title> <source>Walter de Gruyter GmbH &amp; Co KG, Berlin, New York</source>: <fpage>454</fpage>-<lpage>472</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>GY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000[1999]</year>)<article-title> Eight new species of lady beetles from Henan, China (Coleoptera, Coccinellidae).</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>XC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname> <given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>The fauna and taxonomy of insect in Henan, 4, Insects of the Mountains Funiu and Dabie Regions.</issue-title> <source>China Agricultural Science and Technology Press, Beijing</source>: <fpage>62</fpage>-<lpage>73</lpage>. [In Chinese]</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>GY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Lady Beetles (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae) from Chinese Hemlocks infested with the Hemlock Woolly Adegid, <italic>Adelges tsugae</italic> Annand (Homoptera: Adelgidae).</article-title> <source>The Coleopterists Bulletin </source> <volume>54</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>154</fpage>-<lpage>199</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1649/0010-065X(2000)054[0154:LBCCFC]2.0.CO" xlink:type="simple">10.1649/0010-065X(2000)054[0154:LBCCFC]2.0.CO</ext-link>;2</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname> <given-names>GY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname> <given-names>XF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Description of male genitalia of <italic>Shirozuella mirabilis</italic> Sasaji with two additional new species From Taiwan (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of South China Agricultural University </source> <volume>13</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>