<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.302.4962</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Three new species in the genus 
                    <italic>Wilkinsonellus</italic> (Braconidae, Microgastrinae) from the Neotropics, and the first host record for the genus</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Arias-Penna</surname>
                        <given-names>Diana Carolina</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:B382F703-9A31-4C7D-858E-7481C7FEA028</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Whitfield</surname>
                        <given-names>James B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7A98AB5F-552D-4437-8F5D-C593CA713506</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Janzen</surname>
                        <given-names>Daniel H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:4491369A-CFA6-4614-AC09-1137CCD06F9A</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Hallwachs</surname>
                        <given-names>Winnie</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:68F37FFD-B6AB-49AD-A1AD-1C84B2FB94C9</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Entomology, 320 Morrill Hall, 505 S. Goodwin Ave., University of Illinois, Urbana, IL 61801, USA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Department of Biology University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA 19104, USA
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: James B. Whitfield (<email xlink:type="simple">jwhitfie@life.illinois.edu</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: K. van Achterberg</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>20</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>302</issue>
            <fpage>79</fpage>
            <lpage>95</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>15</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2013</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>13</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2013</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Diana Carolina Arias-Penna, James B. Whitfield, Daniel H. Janzen, Winnie Hallwachs</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:FF23F6C6-D466-4863-9679-C5A781B7DDF6</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mason is a poorly sampled but widely distributed tropical genus of <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name>), parasitoid wasps that exclusively attack caterpillars (<tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name>). Currently, species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> have been described only from the Palaeotropics, but the genus was known to occur in the Neotropics. Here we describe the first three species from Central and South America: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus alexsmithi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus kogui</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>,and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus panamaensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> These species descriptions confirm that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a Pantropical genus. A dichotomous key for the three new Neotropical species is given. The first recorded host for the genus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Microthyris prolongalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name>Crambidae</tp:taxon-name>), is also reported, for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus alexsmithi</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            </abstract>
            <trans-abstract xml:lang="es">
                <label>Resumen</label>
                <p><!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> es un género tropical de microgastrinos (<tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name>) que ha sido poco muestreado aunque presenta una distribución amplia. Estas avispas parasitoides únicamente utilizan como hospederos larvas (orugas) de lepidópteros. Hasta el momento, las especies de <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> han sido descritas solo a partir de material colectado en la región Paleotropical (trópico del viejo mundo), aunque su presencia en el Neotrópico ya se conocía. En esta publicación se describen las primeras tres especies Neotropicales, dos de Centroamérica y una de Suramérica: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus alexsmithi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus kogui</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus panamaensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> Estas descripciones de especies Neotropicales confirman la distribución Pantropical del género. Una clave taxonómica para la identificación de las tres nuevas especies es propuesta. El primer hospedero para el género, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Microthyris prolongalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name>Crambidae</tp:taxon-name>), se reporta para <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus alexsmithi</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            </trans-abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Biodiversity</kwd>
                <kwd>caterpillars</kwd>
                <kwd>parasitoid wasps</kwd>
                <kwd>tropical rain forest lowlands</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> was erected by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Mason (1981)</xref> to accommodate four Palaeotropical species that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nixon (1965)</xref> included in the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles henicopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles daira</tp:taxon-name></italic> groups. The former of those two species-groups contained three species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles henicopus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (de <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Saeger 1944</xref>) from Kenya and Rwanda, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles iphitus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nixon 1965</xref>), and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles thyone</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nixon 1965</xref>) both from the Philippines, and the <italic>daira</italic>-group is monotypic, with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles daira</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nixon 1965</xref>) being from Papua New Guinea. In both species-groups, tergite I exhibits a distinctively narrow petiole, which is constricted medially and also with a deeply median groove (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nixon 1965</xref>).</p>
            <p>After its origin as a recognized genus, the frequency of additional new <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species descriptions has been spasmodic. Eleven years after its acceptance as a new genus, three new species were described from Papua New Guinea and Australia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Austin and Dangerfield 1992</xref>); the latter country was added as a new continental record of distribution. In the early twenty-first century, two more species were described, but this time from Northwest Vietnam (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Long and van Achterberg 2003</xref>). Between 2005-2007, two additional species were described, one from India (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Ahmad et al. 2005</xref>) and a further one from Vietnam (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Long 2007</xref>). The most recent descriptions are from Taiwan and Vietnam (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Long and van Achterberg 2011</xref>), when another four new species were added. Thus, the genus currently contains 15 described species, mainly from the Palaeotropics: Africa, south and Southeast Asia, Indonesia and Australia. The presence of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the Neotropics was reported more than a decade ago during the elaboration of a key to <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Whitfield 1997</xref>), published in the Manual of the New World Genera of the family <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name>. However, no Neotropical species were formally described at that time.</p>
            <p>Currently, there is no information available about which families of <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> are used by these wasps as hosts, except that newly reported here. However, they are assumed to be koinobiont endoparasitoids of caterpillars (larvae of <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name>), as are all genera of <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name>. Only one of the previously described species, <!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles daira</tp:taxon-name></italic>, has natural history data associated. It was labeled as bred from the plant <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hibiscus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <tp:taxon-name>Malvaceae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nixon 1965</xref>), which is obviously incomplete without an insect host.</p>
            <p>Three undetermined species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> were reported in Kalimantan (Indonesia: Borneo island) during a study that assessed braconid parasitoid wasps diversity after the reforestation of degraded <italic><tp:taxon-name>Imperata</tp:taxon-name></italic> grassland (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Imperata cylindrica</tp:taxon-name></italic>,<tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>) with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acacia mangium</tp:taxon-name></italic>,<tp:taxon-name>Fabaceae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Maeto et al. 2009</xref>). In that study, one undetermined species was reported in matured <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acacia</tp:taxon-name></italic> plantations (aged 5–12 years), and two other unidentified species were found in old secondary logged dipterocarp forests.</p>
            <p>The phylogenetic position of the genus within <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> is unclear. However, some authors have used comparative morphology to suggest a close relationship with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diolcogaster</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ashmead. Two <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diolcogaster</tp:taxon-name></italic> species-groups have been proposed as close relatives. One of them is the <italic>xanthaspis</italic>-group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Austin and Dangerfield 1992</xref>). As with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, this species-group is characterized by its narrow petiole of tergite I, but the petiole has more or less parallel sides, while that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nixon 1965</xref>) is constricted laterally. The other species-group is the <italic>fasciipennis</italic>-group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Mason 1981</xref>), which differs from <italic>xanthaspis</italic> only in that tergites II and III show no delimited median area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nixon 1965</xref>). At the present time, the phylogenetic position of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> within <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> remains an open question, largely due to little effort having been expended in representing all relevant groups in phylogenetic analyses.</p>
            <p>After a brief mention of Dr. Wilkinson’s contribution to the knowledge of <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name>, the first three Neotropical species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> are described. A Pantropical distribution for the genus is confirmed, along with the first host data for the genus, and we offer a key for the three new species.</p>
            <sec sec-type="Douglas Shipton Wilkinson (1890–1941) ">
                <title>Douglas Shipton Wilkinson (1890–1941)</title>
                <p>In 1981, William R. M. Mason named the genus in honor of D. S. Wilkinson, a renowned British entomologist at the Natural History Museum in London - then known as the British Museum (Natural History), who dedicated his entire career to the study of <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name>. Wilkinson was a significant contributor to <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> taxonomy. He concentrated his efforts in understanding the morphological variability of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> not only regionally, but also on a global scale. His vast knowledge of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> helped him to design a morphology-based classification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Papp 1976</xref>). He proposed six groups; each one was named with arbitrarily chosen letters [A, F, G, S, U, &amp; M] (first developed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Wilkinson 1932</xref>). This system of letter-designated groups was adopted, modified and extended from the previous four sections proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Marshall (1885)</xref> for the British <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> fauna (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nixon 1965</xref>). He was the first European entomologist to recognize the necessity of critically reviewing the classification of the Palaearctic <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. Wilkinson enlisted in the navy during World War II and was killed at sea in 1941, terminating his intention of attaining a world classification of <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Papp 1976</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Whitfield et al. 2002</xref>).</p>
                <!--PageBreak-->
                <p>Wilkinson’s later work on the Palaearctic fauna was published after his death, with the aid of Gilbert Nixon, who became his successor in studying the group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Wilkinson 1945</xref>). In this monumental work he re-described 58 European <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> species in a highly detailed way, and included nomenclatural comments and extensive information on natural history. The detailed critical analysis of host-ranges was due to his proficient collaborator Richard Laurence Edward Ford, who could replicate in the laboratory the conditions of rearing parasitoids and their hosts.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
            <title>Methods</title>
            <p>Specimens used by this revision were obtained on loan from the following institutions, which are identified in the text by their acronyms:</p>
            <p>•	Canadian National Collection of Insects (CNC). Ottawa, Canada.</p>
            <p>•	Entomological collection, Jorge Ignacio Hernández Camacho, Institute of Biological Resources Alexander von Humboldt (IAvH-E). Villa de Leyva, Colombia.</p>
            <p>•	Inventory Collection of D. H. Janzen and W. Hallwachs (DHJWH) destined for the CNC or National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C.</p>
            <p>The specimens from the IAvH–E collection are the result of the project “Insect Survey of a Megadiverse Country Phase I and II: Colombia” conducted from 2002 to 2006. More than 25 natural protected areas managed by the Colombian government were sampled (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Arias-Penna 2007</xref>). Specimens from the DHJWH collection are the result of “the caterpillar and parasitoid inventory of the Área de Conservación en Guanacaste (ACG) ” Costa Rica (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Janzen and Hallwachs 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Janzen et al. 2009</xref>), a large-scale on-going rearing project. Caterpillars were collected directly in the field and subsequently reared in laboratory conditions. Information about taxonomic identification for caterpillar, host plant and parasitoids as well as data of parasitoid eclosion is available. Each caterpillar is tagged with a voucher code: YY-SRNP-XXXX. The prefix refers to the last two digits of the year that caterpillar was discovered in the field. SRNP stands for Santa Rosa National Park, and the suffix is a unique number assigned within the year. When a parasitoid emerged from its host, the same caterpillar voucher code is assigned, but also a unique DNA wasp voucher code is assigned: DHJPARxxxxxxxx (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Janzen and Hallwachs 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Janzen et al. 2009</xref>).</p>
            <sec sec-type="Morphology and taxonomic characters">
                <title>Morphology and taxonomic characters</title>
                <p>Initial identification to genus level followed the key to the Neotropical microgastrine genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Whitfield 1997</xref>). The original <!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species descriptions from Papua New Guinea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nixon 1965</xref>), Australasian Region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Austin and Dangerfield 1992</xref>), Vietnam (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Long and Achterberg 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">2011</xref>), India (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Ahmad et al. 2005</xref>) and China (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Zeng et al. 2011</xref>) were consulted to confirm that the new species matched the generic aspects of those descriptions. The cuticular sculpturing terminology utilized in this revision follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Harris (1979)</xref>. Morphological terms for body structures as well as venation are a variation of the Comstock-Needham system that was used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Sharkey and Wharton (1997, fig. 15)</xref>. Photos were taken with a Leica DFC425 digital microscope camera mounted on a Leica M205 stereomicroscope, (Wetzlar, Germany). The LAS (Leica Application Suite) multifocus module integrated within the Leica microscope was used for taking the pictures. The stack of images at different focus positions was processed with Zerene Stacker version 1.04 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zerenesystems.com/cms/stacker" xlink:type="simple">http://zerenesystems.com/cms/stacker</ext-link>).</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Wilkinsonellus</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Mason, 1981</tp:taxon-authority>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                    <title>Type species:</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles iphitus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Nixon 1965</xref></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be differentiated from other <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> genera by the combination of the following characters: body coloration largely yellowish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, L</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>); propodeum with a median carina, spiracles surrounded by carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4H</xref>); propleuron with a posterior flange (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>); scutellum sculptured medio-posteriorly and often with subapical carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1M–N</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4H</xref>); lunulae of scutellum wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E–F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4G–H</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Long and Achterberg 2011</xref>), fore wing with second submarginal cell (“areolet”) open distally, thus vein r-m absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3J</xref>); vein 1-1A strongly curved, laying very close to posterior margin of the fore wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3J</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Long and Achterberg 2003</xref>); tergite I with petiole 4–5 times as long as its apical width, more or less constricted medially and deeply grooved almost to apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1H, Q–R</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3H</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4H–I</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Zeng et al. 2011</xref>); median longitudinal area of metasomal tergite II slightly raised, usually poorly delimited (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1G–H, Q–R</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3H, L</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4I</xref>), tergite II as long as tergite III, both smooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2G–H, Q–R</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3H, L</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4I</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Whitfield 1997</xref>); hind coxa enlarged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, I, L, Q</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A, H, L</xref>,) rarely short except in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus flavicrus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Long and Achterberg 2011</xref>); ovipositor sheaths short (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, G, J</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A, J</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Whitfield 1997</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to Neotropical Wilkinsonellus Mason">
                    <title>Key to Neotropical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mason</title>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scutellar sulcus with seven carinate foveae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4G</xref>). Axillary trough of metanotum with complete parallel carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4H</xref>). Eyes and ocelli appearing reddish in preserved specimens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4A–D</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus panamaensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scutellar sulcus with five carinate foveae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E, M–N</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref>). Axillary trough of metanotum with some incomplete parallel carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1F</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G</xref>). Eyes and ocelli silver in preserved specimens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A–C, L</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A–D, F</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fore wing and hind wing infuscate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A, J–K</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus kogui</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fore wing and hind wing not infuscate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, L</xref>)</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus alexsmithi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <!--PageBreak-->
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <sec sec-type="Descriptions of new species">
                <title>Descriptions of new species</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">alexsmithi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7D233175-9A75-4850-BB55-E314F705F906</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Wilkinsonellus_alexsmithi</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Arias-Penna &amp; Whitfield</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A–R</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Type material. Holotype, 1 female, COSTA RICA: Alajuela, Area de Conservación Guanacaste, Sector Rincon Rain Forest, Estación Llanura, lat 10.93332, long -85.25331, 135 m, 17.ix.2009, M. Moraga, 09-SRNP-75793, parasitoid voucher DHJPAR0039932. Paratypes: 2 males same data as holotype except for collecting dates and voucher codes as follow: 10.x.2009, 09-SRNP-76107, parasitoid voucher DHJPAR0039933; and 09.x.2009, 09-SRNP-76084, parasitoid voucher DHJPAR0039931. All specimens deposited in DHJWH temporarily, for later transfer to CNC.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Eyes silver mottled with gray, ocelli silver (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A–C, L</xref>). Curvature of pronotum with a deep groove that has semicircular rugae. Scutellar sulcus with five deep, carinated foveae of heterogeneous size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E–F, M–N</xref>). Axillary trough of scutellum (ATS) with several parallel carinae that are close to each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1F, M–N</xref>). Fore wing longer than body length.</p>
                        <p>Holotype female. Body length 4.56 mm, fore wing length 4.87 mm, hind wing length 3.99 mm</p>
                        <p>Coloration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A–R</xref>). General body pale yellow, except posterior half of hind coxa with an infuscated ventral band (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1I</xref>). Flagellum, trochanter, trochantellus, apex of both femur and tibia brown, hind tarsi, and tarsal claws of all legs completely brown. Scape and pedicel yellow-brown. Eyes silver mottled with gray, ocelli silver (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A–C, L</xref>). Membrane and microtrichiae of both fore and hind wings light brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, L</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1B–C</xref>). Scape longer than wide (0.26:0.17 mm); pedicel wider than long (0.12:0.10 mm), first antennal flagellomeres not sub-equal in length (0.30:0.36:0.34 mm). Antennal scrobes deep, smooth, far above middle level of eyes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>), carinated dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>); in frontal view, medial area between antennal scrobes with a sharp, short projection carrot-shaped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>), antennal scrobes in contact with inner eye margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). Face with small, sparse and homogeneous punctures, face with a median-longitudinal carina running from antennal scrobes to clypeus, fronto-clypeal suture absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). Distance between each anterior tentorial pit and closest inner compound eye margin equal to diameter of a tentorial pit (0.06:0.06 mm); anterior tentorial pits far away from each other (0.30 mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). Mandible with two teeth, inferior tooth thinner, longer than superior. Maxillary palps longer than labial palps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). Distance between a posterior ocellus and adjacent eye margin sub-equal in length equal to diameter of lateral ocellus (0.10:0.10 mm), distance between lateral ocelli shorter than diameter of lateral ocellus (0.06:0.10 mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Vertex narrow with small, sparse punctuations, but medially smooth and concave (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>).</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Mesosoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A, D–F, L–N</xref>). Mesosoma dorsoventrally convex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, D</xref>). Pronotum shiny, smooth; curvature of pronotum with a deep groove that has semicircular rugae. Mesopleuron convex, extended, smooth except margins lateral and ventro-lateral that form a L-shaped area that possesses small, homogeneous punctuations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>), mesopleuron with a deep dent just above L-shaped area, dent with elongated foveae bordering the L-shape area, mesosternum slightly flat with distinctive groove of deep, homogeneous foveae. Metepisternum and metepimeron separated by a groove with several deep foveae throughout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>), metepisternum narrower than metepimeron, metepisternum just above hindcoxa outlined by a wide and flat carina, and apical half with several short cariane. Mesoscutum as wide as head with small and homogenous punctures. Notauli clearly impressed, broad, but not reaching the transscutal articulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>). Scutellar sulcus with five deep, carinated foveae of heterogeneous size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E–F, M–N</xref>). Scutellum shiny, almost smooth with sparse, fine punctures and surrounded by a strong carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E–F, M–N</xref>). ATS with several parallel carinae which are close to each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E, N</xref>). Axillary trough of metanotum (ATM) with a few, incomplete parallel carinae, only present basally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E, N</xref>). Lunule of scutellum (L) and medioposterior band of scutellum (BS) smooth and shiny. Medioposterior band of metanotum (BM) short and crossed by a carina aligned with the median longitudinal carina of propodeum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref>). Medioanteror pit of metano<!--PageBreak-->tum (MPM) hexagonal, and delimited by a strong carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref>). Posterior rim of metanotum (PRM) thin and smooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref>). Propodeum with a complete median-longitudinal carina dividing the propodeum in two halves, plus one divergent carina at each half of propodeum, area between carinae basally shorter than apically, divergent carinae crossed by semicircular carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Wings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, L</xref>). Fore wing with vein r straight (0.30 mm) arising just beyond middle of pterostigma; vein 2RS as long as r (0.30:0.30 mm), but longer than 2M and (RS+M) b veins (0.30:0.15:0.20 mm). Hind wing with vannal lobe reduced, slightly convex; edge with sparse setae throughout. Costal and basal cell infuscate.</p>
                        <p>Legs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, I, L, O–R</xref>). Hind coxa surpassing apex of tergite III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, L, Q–R</xref>), outer dorsal surface of hind coxa delimiting an area surrounded by a strong longitudinal carina running from base to apex, but last third apically the carina turns inward (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1Q</xref>); that area with rugulose punctuations and with an extra strong basal carina inclined and reaching only the first third basally; hind tibia with outer spur half as long as inner spur (0.34:0.66 mm); inner spur more than half as long as hind basitarsus (0.66:0.90 mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1P</xref>); hind tibia and hind tarsi both with spines throughout, hind tarsal claw with a short comb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1O</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Metasoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1G–H, J–K, Q–R</xref>). Petiole of tergite I narrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1H, Q–R</xref>), length 0.56 mm, distinctly constricted at anterior half (minimum width 0.09 mm), but subapically wider (maximum width 0.25 mm) and with a few sculpturations, petiole with a deep groove extending more of two thirds tergite I length; hypopygium not protruding at apex of metasoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A, J</xref>); hypopygium plate with truncate apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1J</xref>), ovipositor sheath length 0.20 mm, glabrous, slightly protruding apex of metasoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1J</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Males (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1K–R</xref>). Males differ in coloration from the female: lateral mesonotal lobes pale or dark brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1M–N</xref>). Tergite II with a brown median area which is longer than wide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1Q–R</xref>); tergite III with a brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1Q</xref>) or yellow-brown area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1R</xref>) anteriorly narrower than posteriorly; tergites IV brown but subapically with a thin transversal yellow apical band (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1Q–R</xref>). The infuscate areas on hind legs are darker than in females (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1L</xref>). Antennae length = 5.0-5.2 mm, body length = 4.2-4.5 mm. Last antennal segment gradually narrowing at the apex. Tergite I, minimum width = 0.10 mm, maximum width = 0.22 mm, total length = 0.60-0.70 mm.</p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 1.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus alexsmithi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Arias-Penna &amp; Whitfield, <bold>A–J</bold> female &amp; <bold>K–R</bold> male <bold>A</bold> Habitus <bold>B–C</bold> Head <bold>B</bold> Frontal view <bold>C</bold> Dorsal view <bold>D–E</bold> Mesosoma <bold>D</bold> Lateral view <bold>E</bold> Dorsal view <bold>F</bold> Scutellum, metanotum &amp; propodeum, dorsal view <bold>G</bold> Last tergites, dorsal view <bold>H</bold> Petiole &amp; Tergites I-II, dorsal view <bold>I</bold> Hindcoxa, ventral view <bold>J</bold> Hypopygium &amp; ovipositor sheaths, lateral view <bold>K–R</bold> Male: <bold>K</bold> Genitalia <bold>L</bold> Habitus <bold>M–N</bold> Mesonotum, dorsal view <bold>O</bold> Claw of hind tarsus <bold>P</bold> Spines of hind tibia <bold>Q–R</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-302-079-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>This species is named in honor of Dr. M. Alex Smith of the University of Guelph, Canada, in recognition of his decade of deep intellectual, laboratory and logistic support for the DNA barcoding of the parasitoid wasps and flies of ACG.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>The species is only known from the original rain forest collection site, Sector Rincon Rain Forest, in Área de Conservación Guanacaste in northwestern Costa Rica. In 1999, ACG was inscribed as a UNESCO World Heritage site containing the best-preserved and regenerating dry forest habitats from Central America to northern Mexico.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Host">
                        <title>Host.</title>
                        <p><!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus alexsmithi</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been reared from the leaf-roller <italic><tp:taxon-name>Microthyris prolongalis</tp:taxon-name></italic>,<tp:taxon-name>Crambidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A, C–D</xref>) three times, while feeding on the rain forest leaves of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ipomoea phillomega</tp:taxon-name></italic> or sweet potatoes <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ipomoea batatas</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name>Convolvulaceae</tp:taxon-name>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://janzen.bio.upenn.edu/caterpillars/database.lasso" xlink:type="simple">http://janzen.bio.upenn.edu/caterpillars/database.lasso</ext-link>). The larva of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Microthyris prolongalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> lives inside of the leaf roll that it constructs, eating leaf tissue there. It is therefore likely that oviposition takes place through the leaf into the moth larva. The wasp cocoon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>) is lightly silked to the inner wall of the leaf roll and the larva dies at about the time that the wasp larva exits the cadaver.</p>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 2.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold>A</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Microthyris propongalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Guenée, 1854) <tp:taxon-name>Crambidae</tp:taxon-name>: Larva (07-SRNP-41608, Photo: DHJ422561) B Silk and wax cocoon of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus alexsmithi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (09-SRNP-75793, DHJPAR0039932, photo: DHJ476579) <bold>C–D</bold> Adults of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Microthyris propongalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>C</bold> Dorsal view <bold>D</bold> Ventral view (06-SRNP-41780 Photos: DHJ349728 &amp; DHJ349729).</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-302-079-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                        <title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>The last three antennal segments are missing from the holotype. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus alexsmithi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a parasitoid of a crambid leaf roller larva, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Microthyris prolongalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name>Crambidae</tp:taxon-name>). In ACG, this moth larva feeds only on <tp:taxon-name>Convolvulaceae</tp:taxon-name> (410 rearing records, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Janzen &amp; Hallwachs 2009</xref>). Within the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> besides <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, members of two other genera, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Apanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Diolcogaster</tp:taxon-name></italic>, are parasitoids only on this species of moth. The taxonomic range of insect parasitoids that use <italic><tp:taxon-name>Microthyris prolongalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> as a host entails two insect orders, <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>. Within <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name> the chalcidoid family <tp:taxon-name>Encyrtidae</tp:taxon-name> (genus not reported), and two additional subfamilies of <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Orgilinae</tp:taxon-name> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Stantonia</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and <tp:taxon-name>Agathidinae</tp:taxon-name> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Alabagrus maya</tp:taxon-name></italic>) were reported; for the <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name> parasitoids, two genera of <tp:taxon-name>Tachinidae</tp:taxon-name>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Actia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Argyrophylax</tp:taxon-name></italic> also parasitize this caterpillar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Janzen and Hallwachs 2009</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">kogui</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FC7BA3D2-3503-4DD9-B9F7-AADC34BF13CB</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Wilkinsonellus_kogui</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Arias-Penna &amp; Whitfield</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A–L</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Type material. Holotype. Male, COLOMBIA Magdalena, PNN [Parque Nacional Natural] Tayrona Pueblito, lat 11.33333, long -74.03333, 225m, Malaise, 03-22.i.2001, R. Henriquez leg. M.1212. Paratype. 1 Male, COLOMBIA Chocó, PNN [Parque Nacional Natural] Utría, Cocalito, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">6°1’N, 77°20’W</named-content>, 20m, Malaise, 26.xii.2000–01.ii.2001, J. Pérez, Leg. M.1342. Holotype and paratype deposited in IAvH-E.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Eyes and ocelli silver (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A–D, F</xref>). Scutellar sulcus with five deep, heterogeneous and carinated foveae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref>). Axillary trough of metanotum with a few striated grooves defined at least posteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G</xref>). Body longer than fore wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Holotype male. Body length 4.30 (4.30-4.55 mm), fore wing length 4.15mm, hind wing length 3.59 mm.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Coloration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A–L</xref>). General body dark yellow; all legs yellow, except hind leg: coxa infuscated at the apex forming a ventral, wide brown band; apex of trochanter, and trochantellus, base of tibia and tarsi brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Scape and pedicel brown both with thin apical yellow ring. Flagellum dark brown. Eyes and ocelli silver (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A–D, F</xref>.) Tergite IV and beyond mostly brown, but subapically and subbasally with a transverse yellow band (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3I, L</xref>). Membrane and microtrichiae of fore and hind wing infusctate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3J–K</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A–D</xref>). Scape slightly longer than wide (0.20:0.18 mm); pedicel wider than long (0.12:0.08 mm); first three flagellomeres subequal in length (0.32:0.30:0.34). Antennal scrobes smooth, dorsally carinate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>), positioned far above middle level of eyes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3C–D</xref>); median part between antennal scrobes with a short carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). Face with sparse, homogeneous and medium-sized punctures, interspaces wavy; face with a median-longitudinal carina running from antennal scrobes to fronto-clypeal suture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). Distance between each anterior tentorial pit and closest inner compound eye margin longer than diameter of tentorial pit (0.10:0.06 mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3C–D</xref>); anterior tentorial pits far away from each other (0.26 mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). Fronto-clypeal suture absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3C–D</xref>). Mandible with two teeth, inferior tooth thinner and longer than superior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). Suture malar present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). Maxillary palps longer than labial palps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). Distance between lateral ocellus and adjacent compound eye margin longer than diameter of lateral ocellus (0.11:0.08 mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>), distance between lateral ocelli equal to diameter of lateral ocellus (0.08:0.08 mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). Vertex medially smooth, but laterally with some sparse and small punctuations. Occiput slightly concave with a median short grove basally.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->Mesosoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A, E–G</xref>). Mesosoma dorsoventrally convex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A, F</xref>). Pronotum shiny, smooth, but curvature of pronotum with elongate areolae. Mesopleuron shiny, smooth medially, but margins lateral and ventro-lateral forming a L-shaped area which small, dense and homogeneous sculptures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3F</xref>); mesopleuron just above of L-shape area with a dent with some large wave-like sculpturing. Mesosternum slightly flat with a deep row of deep foveae. Metepisternum and metepimeron outlined by a groove with several deep foveae throughout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3F</xref>), metepisternum inverted triangular, smooth and narrower than metepimeron (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3F</xref>), apical margin metepisternum (above hindcoxa) delimited by a wide, flat carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3F</xref>). Mesoscutum as wide as head with small, dense, and homogenous sculptures. Notauli clearly impressed, but not reaching the transscutal articulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref>). Scutellar sulcus heterogeneous, with five deep, heterogeneous and carinated foveae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3E, G</xref>). Scutellum shiny, medially smooth, but with sparse fine punctures and surrounded by carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3E, G</xref>). Axillary trough of scutellum with several homogeneous striated grooves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G</xref>). Axillary trough of metanotum with a few striated grooves defined at least posteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G</xref>). Medioposterior band of scutellum slightly wider than lunule of scutellum both smooth and shiny (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G</xref>). Medioposterior band of metanotum hexagonal and crossed by a median carina aligned with the median longitudinal carina of propodeum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G</xref>). Medioanteror pit of metanotum pentagonal-shape surrounded by carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G</xref>). Posterior rim of metanotum thin, wavy and smooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G</xref>). Propodeum with a complete median-longitudinal carina dividing in two halves, each half with one divergent carina wider as they go away from propodeal foramen, space among all carinae intercepted by transverse semicircular carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Wings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A, J–K</xref>). Fore wing with vein r length 0.26 mm slightly curved, arising beyond middle of pterostigma, arising just beyond middle of stigma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3J</xref>); vein 2RS as same length as r (0.26:0.26 mm),but 2RS vein longer than 2M and (Rs+M) b veins (0.26:0.10:0.20 mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3J</xref>). Hind wing with vannal lobe reduced, slightly convex; edge with sparse setae throughout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3K</xref>). Costal and basal cells infuscate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3K</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Legs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A, H, L</xref>). Hind coxa very long, reaching apex of tergite III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3H</xref>), outer dorsal surface of hind coxa delimited by a strong carina, area coarsely rugulose and with a short, strong basal carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3H</xref>); hind tibia with outer spur more than half as long as inner spur (0.40:0.66 mm), inner more than half as long as hind basitarsus (0.66:0.88 mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>), hindtibia and tarsi with spines throughout.</p>
                        <p>Metasoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A, H–I, L</xref>). Petiole of tergite I narrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2H</xref>), length 0.70 mm, distinctly constricted at upper middle (minimum width 0.09 mm) and wider subapically (maximum width 0.20 mm) with sculpturations, petiole with a deep groove extending more of two third of the tergite I length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3H</xref>). Male genitalia externally visible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3I</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Female. Unknown</p>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 3.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus kogui</tp:taxon-name></italic> Arias-Penna &amp; Whitfield, male. <bold>A</bold> Habitus <bold>B–D</bold> Head <bold>B</bold> Dorsal view <bold>C</bold> Frontal view <bold>D</bold> lateral view <bold>E</bold> Mesosotum, dorsal view <bold>F</bold> Head and mesosoma, lateral view <bold>G</bold> Scutellum, metanotum &amp; propodeum, dorsal view <bold>ATM</bold>= axillary through of metanotum; <bold>ATS</bold>= axillary trough of scutellum; <bold>BM</bold>= Medioposterior band of metanotum; <bold>BS</bold>= medioposterior band of scutellum; <bold>L</bold> = Lunule, <bold>MPM</bold> = Medioanteror pit of metanotum &amp; <bold>PRM</bold> = Posterior rim of metanotum. <bold>H</bold> Tergites I-III &amp; hind coxa, dorsal view <bold>I</bold> Last tergites of metasoma, dorsal view <bold>J</bold> Fore wing veins <bold>K</bold> Hind wing cells <bold>L</bold> Metasoma, dorsal view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-302-079-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>From Kogui = jaguar in the Kogui language. The Kogui are indigenous in the Colombia Caribbean coast at the foot of the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta, the highest coastal mountains in the world and not directly attached to the Andean mountain range.</p>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Colombia, from PNN Tayrona and PNN Utría, both being marine ecosystems protected by the Colombian government and belonging to the National Natural systems. Tayrona is located on the Caribbean coast in Magdalena Department, whereas Utría is located on Colombia’s Pacific coast, in Chocó Department.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Host">
                        <title>Host.</title>
                        <p>Unknown</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comments">
                        <title>Comments.</title>
                        <p>Holotype lacks the last antennal flagellomeres. The specimens from Utría with antennae length = 4.8 mm, body length 4.3 mm. Last antennal flagellomere length = 0.35 mm, penultimate flagellomere antennae length = 0.30 mm. Male from Chocó shows hind legs with the same pattern of coloration but darker and Tergite VI and beyond with brown spots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3L</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">panamaensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:A3274FC6-02B2-4292-9A5B-B37D142516D1</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Wilkinsonellus_panamaensis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Arias-Penna &amp; Whitfield</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4A–J</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Type material. Holotype. Female, PANAMAProvincia Panamá, Distrito de Panamá, Las Cumbres. Malaise 20.i-02.ii.1982. M. Wolda. DNA Voucher CNCHYM03459. Specimen deposited in CNC.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Eyes and ocelli appearing reddish in preserved specimens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4A–D</xref>). Metasoma curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4J</xref>). Fore wing longer than body length. Vein 2M as long as (Rs+M) b. Scutellar sulcus with seven carinated foveae heterogeneous in size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4G</xref>). Axillary trough of scutellum and axillary trough of metanotum both with complete parallel carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4H</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Holotype female. Body length 4.18 mm, fore wing length 4.44 mm, hind wing length 3.43 mm.</p>
                        <p>Coloration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4A–J</xref>). General body dark yellow, except hind leg infuscated at the base and apex of tibia; hind coxa, trochanter and trochantellus with a narrow dorsal band (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4J</xref>). Hind tarsi completely brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Scape half basal brown and half apical yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). Pedicel brown with yellow apical ring (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). Flagellum brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4E</xref>), ocelli and eyes appearing reddish in preserved specimens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4A–D</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4A–D</xref>). Antenna longer than body (4.44:4.18 mm); scape longer than wide (0.22:0.16 mm); pedicel wider than large (0.12:0.10 mm); first antennal flagellomeres sub-equal in length (0.34:0.32:0.32 mm); penultimate flagellomere as same length than apical segment (0.11:0.11mm); but with flat, abruptly acute in apex. Antennal scrobes smooth, far above middle level of eyes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>) and carinate dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>), median part between antennal scrobes with a short carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>). Face with small, sparse and homogeneous punctures, face with a median-longitudinal carina running from antennal scrobes to clypeus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>), fronto-clypeal suture absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). Distance between an anterior tentorial pit and inner compound eye margin equal to diameter of a tentorial pit (0.06:0.07 mm); anterior tentorial pits far away from each other (0.24 mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). Mandible with two teeth, inferior tooth thinner and longer than superior. <!--PageBreak-->Maxillary palps longer than labial palps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). Distance between lateral ocellus and adjacent compound eye margin sub-equal in length to the diameter of the lateral ocellus (0.09:0.10 mm), distance between lateral ocelli shorter than diameter of lateral ocellus (0.06:0.10 mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). Vertex narrow, medially with a smooth area, but laterally with small and sparse punctuations. Occiput slightly concaved with a short grove medially.</p>
                        <p>Mesosoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4A–B, G–H</xref>). Mesosoma dorsoventrally convex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4A–B</xref>). Pronotum shiny, smooth, but curvature of pronotum with a deep grove. Mesopleuron convex, extended smooth except margins lateral and ventro-lateral that form a L-shaped region that possesses small, dense and homogeneous punctuations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>); mesopleuron with a deep dent just above of L-shaped area, demarcating the border of the area with elongate foveae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Mesosternum slightly flat with a median row of foveae. Metepisternum and metepimeron separated by a groove with several deep foveae throughout (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>), metepisternum smooth and narrower than metepimeron, apical margin metepisternum just above hindcoxa outlined by a wide, flat carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Mesoscutum as wide as head, with small, sparse and homogenous punctures. Notauli clearly impressed, but not reaching the transscutal articulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4G</xref>). Scutellar sulcus with seven deep, carinated foveae of heterogeneous size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4G</xref>). Scutellum shiny with fine, sparse punctures and delimited by carina. Axillary trough of scutellum and axillary trough of metanotum both with vertical parallel carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4H</xref>); space among ATM carinae wider than ATS carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4H</xref>). Lunule of scutellum and medioposterior band of scutellum smooth and shiny (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4H</xref>). Medioposterior band of metanotum and medioanterior pit of metanotum forming a pentagonal-shaped delimited by carinae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4H</xref>). Posterior rim of metanotum thin and smooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4H</xref>). Propodeum with a complete median-longitudinal carina dividing the propodeum in two halves, each half with one additional carina that does not branch basally at the same point than median-longitudinal carina (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4H–I</xref>); space between median and an additional carina wider as they become more <!--PageBreak-->distant from propodeal foramen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4H–I</xref>), and all three carinae crossed by transverse semicircular carinae, although apically less transverse carinae than basally.</p>
                        <p>Wings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Fore wing with vein r straight (0.27 mm), arising just beyond middle of stigma; vein 2RS longer than 2M and (Rs+M) b veins (0.24:0.10:0.10 mm). Hind wing with vannal lobe reduced, slightly convex; edge with sparse setae throughout. Costal and basal cell infuscate.</p>
                        <p>Legs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4A, F, I–J</xref>). Hind coxa reaching apex of tergite III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4I</xref>), outer dorsal surface of hind coxa with an area delimited by a strong longitudinal carina running from base to apex, but last third apically the carina turns inward (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4I</xref>); area surrounded by the carina with rugulose punctuations that are more visible in dorsal view, and with an additional basal carina which splits and runs only the first third basally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4I</xref>); hind tibia with outer spur half as long as inner spur (0.36:0.72 mm); inner spur more than half as long as hind basitarsus (0.72:0.92 mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4F</xref>); outer dorsal side of hind tibia moderately spinose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4F</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Metasoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4A, I–J</xref>). Petiole of tergite I narrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4I</xref>), length 0.52 mm, distinctly constricted at anterior half (minimum width 0.10 mm), but subapically wider (maximum width 0.26 mm); petiole with a deep groove extending more of two thirds tergite I length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4I</xref>); hypopygium not protruding beyond apex of metasoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4J</xref>), hypopygium plate with truncate apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4J</xref>); ovipositor sheaths length 0.36mm, glabrous, with apex rounded protruding apex of metasoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A, J</xref>)</p>
                        <p>Males. Unknown.</p>
                        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 4.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus panamaensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Arias-Penna &amp; Whitfield, female. <bold>A</bold> Habitus <bold>B</bold> Head &amp; mesosoma, lateral view <bold>C–D</bold> Head <bold>C</bold> Dorsal view <bold>D</bold> Frontal view <bold>E</bold> Antennal flagellomeres <bold>F</bold> Spines on hindtibia <bold>G</bold> Mesosoma, dorsal view <bold>H</bold> Scutellum, metanotum &amp; propodeum, dorsal view <bold>I</bold> Propodeum, Tergites I-V &amp; hindcoxa, dorsal view <bold>J</bold> Metasoma and hindcoxa, lateral view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-302-079-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The name is based on the country of Panamá, where the holotype was collected.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>The species is only known from the original collecting site in Panamá.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Host">
                        <title>Host.</title>
                        <p>Unknown.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Conclusions">
            <title>Conclusions</title>
            <p>Neotropical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> range from 4.0 to 4.8 mm in length, excluding antennae, and all specimens were collected in lowland tropical rain forest 500 m.a.s.l. or lower in elevation. Palaeotropical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> range from 2.5 to 4.8 mm in length, and occur at altitudes up to 1700 m.a.s.l.</p>
            <p><!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has not beenthe only genus within <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> that was initially believed to be confined to a specific zoogeographical region. This is also true for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrocotesia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Austin and Dangerfield and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Parapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ashmead, each of which has turned out to have a much wider distribution. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrocotesia</tp:taxon-name></italic> was erected as a new genus in 1992. In that time, it was considered restricted to Papua New Guinea and the adjacent Australian region of North Queensland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Austin and Dangerfield 1992</xref>). However, the first two species from South America–Colombia and Ecuador– were described thirteen years later (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Valerio and Whitfield 2005</xref>). Equally, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Parapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> wasoriginally recorded only from the Australian and American continents. Ashmead proposed the genus in 1900. However, after little more than a century, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Parapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> was reported in South Africa –Western Cape province, Cederberg (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Valerio et al. 2005</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrocotesia</tp:taxon-name></italic> was also reported from the Neotropics at the same time as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in a chapter on <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Whitfield 1997</xref>) included in the Manual of the New World genera of the family <tp:taxon-name>Braconidae</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>). Another genus mentioned in that manual was the Afrotropical genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Beyarslania</tp:taxon-name></italic>,formerly known as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xenogaster</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Koçak and Kemal 2009</xref>). However, those undescribed Neotropical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Beyarslania</tp:taxon-name></italic> species possibly belong to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mariapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic>,a genus recently erected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Whitfield et al. 2012</xref>). Thus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Beyarslania</tp:taxon-name></italic> is still restricted to the Afrotropical region. In brief, all the new records point suggest that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> as well as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrocotesia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Parapanteles</tp:taxon-name></italic> have a more extensively Gondwanan distribution.</p>
            <p>The new distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Wilkinsonellus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been discovered thanks to large-scale rearing projects as well as arthropod diversity surveys undertaken in recent decades in the Neotropical region. The importance of rearing projects lies in the fact the associations across more than two trophic levels are possible. The identification of parasitized larval hosts implies the use of external morphological characteristics present on the larvae combined with the food plant and microlocation, because the caterpillar host is often destroyed when the larval parasitoid emerges. In contrast, specimens collected by malaise trap contribute mainly to inventory of biological diversity, except that most ecological information is lacking. Notwithstanding the current efforts, the extreme richness of the Neotropics means that both taxonomic and biological records continue to be highly incomplete (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Whitfield et al. 2002</xref>) and more studies are considered necessary in order to improve understanding of the distribution patterns of the Neotropical <tp:taxon-name>Microgastrinae</tp:taxon-name> fauna. This situation also applies to other critical areas in the planet (i.e., Wallacea, New Guinea, Solomon Islands) that are still unexplored; consequently the understanding of the global distribution patterns remains incomplete.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>We thank the curators/collection managers of the loaning institutions outlined in the materials and methods; the staff of the Unidad Administrativa Especial del Sistema de Parques Nacionales Naturales de Colombia (UAESPNN, Colombia). This research was funded in part by NSF grants DEB 0346712 and DEB 0717402 to J.B. Whitfield, and NSF DEB 0515699 to D. H. Janzen, NSF DEB 9972024 and DEB 0205982 to Michael Sharkey and B. Brown. DCA-P would also like to thank Andrea Walker for help in photography using the Leica z-stacking system. The ACG parataxonomists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Janzen and Hallwachs 2011</xref>) found and reared the caterpillars and their parasitoids.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haider</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shujauddin</surname> <given-names></given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Discovery of the genus <italic>Wilkinsonellus</italic> Mason (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) from India. Zoos’ Print Journal 20 (3): 1804.</source> doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.11609/JoTT.ZPJ.1098.1804" xlink:type="simple">10.11609/JoTT.ZPJ.1098.1804</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Arias-Penna</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>New geographical records of the genus <italic>Urosigalphus</italic> Ashmead, 1889 (Hymenoptera: Braconidae, Helconinae) for Colombia.</article-title> <source>Boletín del Museo de Entomología de la Universidad del Valle</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dangerfield</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Synopsis of Australasian Microgastrinae (Hymenoptera: Braconidae), with a key to genera, and description of new taxa.</article-title> <source>Invertebrate Taxonomy</source> <volume>6</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/IT9920001" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/IT9920001</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname> <given-names>LY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>New records of six braconids (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) from Taiwan.</article-title> <source>Journal of Agricultural Research of China</source> <volume>48</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>64</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fahringer</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1837</year>) <source>Opuscula braconologica, Palaearktische Region, Microgasterinae- Agathiinae. Wien, Band III., Verlag F. Wagner, 1–520 + I-IX + I Tafel.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>A glossary of surface sculpturing. California Department of Food and Agriculture. Laboratory Services, Entomology.</article-title> <source>Occasional Papers in Entomology</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Dynamic database for an inventory of the macrocaterpillar fauna, and its food plants and parasitoids of Area de Conservación Guanacaste (ACG), northwestern Costa Rica (nn-SRNP-nnnnn voucher codes) &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://janzen.sas.upenn.edu" xlink:type="simple">http://janzen.sas.upenn.edu</ext-link>&gt;</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blandin</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cadiou</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chacon</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dapkey</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deans</surname> <given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Espinoza</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franclemont</surname> <given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haber</surname> <given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname> <given-names>JPW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauld</surname> <given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname> <given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hausmann</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitching</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafontaine</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landry</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemaire</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montero</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munroe</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rab</surname> <given-names>Green S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnasingham</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rawlins</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robbins</surname> <given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rougerie</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharkey</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solis</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiaucourt</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahl</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weller</surname> <given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willmott</surname> <given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodley</surname> <given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Integration of DNA barcoding into an ongoing inventory of complex tropical biodiversity. Molecular Ecology Resources 9 (Supplement 1): 1–26.</source> doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-0998.2009.02628.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1755-0998.2009.02628.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Joining inventory by parataxonomists with DNA barcoding of a large complex tropical conserved wildland in northwestern Costa Rica. PLoS ONE 6 (8): e18123.</source> doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0018123" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0018123</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Koçak</surname> <given-names>AÖ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kemal</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>A replacement name in the family Braconidae (Hymenoptera). Miscellaneous papers, Centre for Entomological Studies Ankara 147–148: 14.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Three new species of the subfamily Microgastrinae (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) from Vietnam.</article-title> <source>Tap chi sinh hoc</source> <volume>29</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Achterberg</surname> <given-names>C van</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Two new species of the genus <italic>Wilkinsonellus</italic> Mason (Hymenoptera: Braconidae: Microgastrinae) from northern Vietnam.</article-title> <source>Zoologische Mededelingen Leiden</source> <volume>77</volume> (<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>227</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname> <given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Achterberg</surname> <given-names>C van</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Review of the genus <italic>Wilkinsonellus</italic> Mason, 1981 (Hymenoptera: Braconidae, Microgastrinae) from Vietnam, with a key to species and four new species.</article-title> <source>Deutsche Entomologische Zeitschrift</source> <volume>58</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>133</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/mmnd.201100009" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/mmnd.201100009</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeto</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noerdjito</surname> <given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belokobylskij</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukuyama</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Recovery of species diversity and composition of braconid parasitic wasps after reforestation of degraded grasslands in lowland East Kalimantan.</article-title> <source>Journal of Insect Conservation</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>-<lpage>257</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10841-008-9164-3" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s10841-008-9164-3</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1885</year>) <source>Monograph of British Braconidae. Part I. Transactions of the Royal Entomological Society of London 1–280.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname> <given-names>WRM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>The polyphyletic nature of <italic>Apanteles</italic> Foerster (Hymenoptera: Braconidae): A phylogeny and reclassification of Microgastrinae.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the Entomological Society of Canada</source> <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>147</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4039/entm113115fv" xlink:type="simple">10.4039/entm113115fv</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nixon</surname> <given-names>GEJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>) <article-title>A reclassification of the tribe Microgasterini (Hymenoptera: Braconidae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Entomology, Supplement</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>284</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Papp</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>A survey of the European Species of <italic>Apanteles</italic> Först. (Hymenoptera, Braconidae: Microgasterinae) I. The species-Groups.</article-title> <source>Annales Historico-Naturales Musei Nationalis Hungarici</source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>-<lpage>274</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeger</surname> <given-names>H de</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1944</year>) <source>Microgasterinae (Hymenoptera Apocrita). Exploration du Parc National Albert Miss. de Witte, Bruxelles, 47, 342pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharkey</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wharton</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Morphology and terminology.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wharton</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharkey</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Manual of the new world genera of the family Braconidae (Hymenoptera).</issue-title> <source>The International Society of Hymenopterists, Washington DC</source>: <fpage>19</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Valerio</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Two new species of the genus <italic>Austrocotesia</italic> Austin &amp; Dangerfield (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) from the Andean region of South America.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>888</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Valerio</surname> <given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kole</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>Parapanteles rooibos</italic>, sp. n. (Hymenoptera: Braconidae: Microgastrinae): the first record of the genus from the African continent.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>855</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Microgastrinae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wharton</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname> <given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharkey</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Manual of the New World genera of the family Braconidae (Hymenoptera).</issue-title> <source>International Society of Hymenopterists. The International Society of Hymenopterists, Washington, DC</source>: <fpage>332</fpage>-<lpage>364</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mardulyn</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname> <given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowton</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships among the microgastrine braconid wasp genera based on data from the 16S, COI and 28S genes and morphology.</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>-<lpage>359</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-3113.2002.00183.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1046/j.1365-3113.2002.00183.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernández-Triana</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardina</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title><italic>Mariapanteles</italic> (Hymenoptera, Braconidae), a new genus of Neotropical microgastrine parasitoid wasp discovered through biodiversity inventory.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys</source> <volume>208</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.208.3326" xlink:type="simple">10.3897/zookeys.208.3326</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1932</year>) <article-title>A revision of the Ethiopian species of the genus <italic>Apanteles</italic> (Hym. Bracon.</article-title> <source>) Transactions of The Royal Entomological Society of London</source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>301</fpage>-<lpage>344</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2311.1932.tb03312.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1365-2311.1932.tb03312.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1945</year>) <article-title>Description of Palearctic species of <italic>Apanteles</italic> (Hymen.</article-title> <source>, Braconidae) Transactions of The Royal Entomological Society of London</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>226</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2311.1945.tb00436.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1365-2311.1945.tb00436.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname> <given-names>J-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>X-X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The genera <italic>Deuterixys</italic> Mason, 1981 and <italic>Wilkinsonellus</italic> Mason, 1981 (Hymenoptera, Braconidae, Microgastrinae) from China, with description of two new species.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys</source> <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.120.891" xlink:type="simple">10.3897/zookeys.120.891</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>