<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.184.2489</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A revision and key to the genera of Afrotropical Mantispidae (Neuropterida, Neuroptera), with the description of a new genus</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Snyman</surname>
                        <given-names>Louwtjie P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:AC76BEAC-C6E6-45E2-9B42-56D9B61B94E0</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Ohl</surname>
                        <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:878259F2-C3C6-4264-B04A-C397E01E5C8E</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Mansell</surname>
                        <given-names>Mervyn W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7BD4656A-A2E3-426B-A9B5-DBED06E28284</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Scholtz</surname>
                        <given-names>Clarke H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7BD4656A-A2E3-426B-A9B5-DBED06E28284</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Zoology and Entomology, University of Pretoria, Pretoria 0002, South Africa
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Museum für Naturkunde Berlin, Invalidenstr. 43, 10115 Berlin, Germany
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Louwtjie P. Snyman (<email xlink:type="simple">lpsnyman@zoology.up.ac.za</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: A. Contreras-Ramos</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>21</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>184</issue>
            <fpage>67</fpage>
            <lpage>93</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>5</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>10</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Louwtjie P. Snyman, Michael Ohl, Mervyn W. Mansell, Clarke H. Scholtz</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:4D618CA6-54E2-44B8-83F1-619AD443A80F</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> genera have previously been neglected and are poorly known. The genera are revised and redescribed. A new genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Snyman and Ohl is described with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>comb. n.</bold>as type species. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Handschin, 1960) is synonymised with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin, 1959. The new combinations within the genus include <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata austroafrica</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>comb. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata bequaerti</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>comb. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>comb. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata girardi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>comb. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata nubila</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>comb. n.,</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata perla</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>comb. n.,</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata pusilla</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>comb. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata similata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>comb. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata royi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>comb. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata tincta</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>comb. n. and</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata vassei</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>comb. n.</bold> An illustrated key to the genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>gen. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin, 1959, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Illiger, 1798, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin, 1959, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin, 1959, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nampista</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás, 1914, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin, 1960 is provided. The wing venation of <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> is redescribed. Similarities between the genera are discussed. Subsequent studies will focus on revising the taxonomic status of species, which are not dealt with in this study.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Mantispidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Neuroptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Afrotropical</kwd>
                <kwd>lacewings</kwd>
                <kwd>key</kwd>
<!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The superorder <tp:taxon-name>Neuropterida</tp:taxon-name> is considered to comprise a diversity of clades, many of which are characterized by a large number of plesiomorphic characters. It includes the orders <tp:taxon-name>Raphidioptera</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Megaloptera</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Neuroptera</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Aspöck 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Aspöck et al. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">Winterton et al. 2010</xref>). The latter two are well represented in the Afrotropical Region, with approximately 1200 species in 15 families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Mansell 2010</xref>).</p>
            <p>The significance of the order <tp:taxon-name>Neuroptera</tp:taxon-name> is well documented in fields other than taxonomy. All larvae are obligate predators, while adults are predacious or pollen-feeders and consequently fulfil vital roles in the functioning of natural ecosystems. The order is therefore ideal for studies in biological fields other than taxonomy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Picker 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Mansell 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Ohl 2004</xref>). Furthermore, their diverse range of habitats and life strategies make them ideal indicator species for global warming, fresh water health, and habitat fragmentation and destruction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Picker 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Mansell 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Ohl 2004</xref>). Despite their importance, some families are poorly studied with only a few groups having received any modern scientific scrutiny.</p>
            <p>The Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> are certainly one of the families that is in urgent need of revision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Ohl 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">2005</xref>). Reasons for this include the taxonomic complexity of the family and the confusing scientific legacy left by most previous authors. Adults are morphologically difficult to distinguish and the lack of comprehensive modern revisions makes the taxonomic status of most taxa difficult to interpret. They are consequently not easily accessible to other non-taxonomic research fields because of the paucity of taxonomic revisions or morphological keys to provide easy access to the group. Modern revisions and morphological keys are consequently of extreme importance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Ohl 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">2005</xref>).</p>
            <p>The <tp:taxon-name>Mantispinae</tp:taxon-name> are the only subfamily known from the Afrotropical Region, and since the Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> have received little attention, their potential impact on other fields of biology cannot be readily assessed. The positive impact of other families of <tp:taxon-name>Neuroptera</tp:taxon-name> has proven to be of great value in fields such as agriculture as biological control agents taxonomy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Picker 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">Stelzl and Devetak 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Mansell 2002</xref>). Furthermore, revisions are important for biodiversity inventories, not only for the relevant country, but also for global biodiversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Mansell 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Ohl 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">2005</xref>).</p>
            <p>This study forms part of two programmes, a southern African initiative and a global programme. The first will form part of the programme: ‘Monitoring lacewings (Insecta: <tp:taxon-name>Neuroptera</tp:taxon-name>) in southern Africa’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Mansell 2002</xref>). This initiative has five main areas of focus or operational components, namely (1) Biodiversity audit, (2) Systematic revisions and phylogenetic analysis (3) Larval biology and ecological requirements (4) Distribution patterns and predictive modelling (5) Conservation status and protective measures, which are all underpinned by a relational database of Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Neuroptera</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Mansell and Kenyon 2002</xref>). The second programme entitled, ‘Towards a global inventory of <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> - the state-of-the-art in mantispid taxonomy’ has revisions and morphological key generation as the central theme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Ohl 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">2005</xref>). The current<!--PageBreak--> study thus contributes significantly to improving both our local and international knowledge of this poorly known group.</p>
            <p>The ultimate long term aim of the study is to resolve the taxonomy of Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> in order to facilitate further research on the group. Since the Afrotropical Mantispids has never received a comparative and large scale revision, this manuscript will form the basis of long term directional research. To achieve this, generic groups was redefined on the basis of clear autapomorphies to support their monophyly, and future molecular studies will be carried out to determine whether these morphologically-defined genera are supported by DNA evidence. Current as well as subsequent studies on the taxonomy and biology of the species can be carried out within the context of these generic concepts.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Biology of Mantispinae">
            <title>Biology of Mantispinae</title>
            <p>Female <tp:taxon-name>Mantispinae</tp:taxon-name> lay large batches of stalked eggs ranging from several hundred to several thousand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). The substrate to which the eggs are attached varies and oviposition preference behaviour of females has not been investigated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Hoffman 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). It has however been hypothesised that females do select specific areas, <italic>e.g</italic>. those with high spider prevalence. Some support for this observation has been found, but has not been tested. Stalked eggs are common in <tp:taxon-name>Neuroptera</tp:taxon-name> and it has been hypothesised that this adaptation is due to the cannibalistic behaviour of the first instar larvae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Penny 1982</xref>). Mantispine larvae, however, are not generalist predators and all known species are predators of spider eggs and have been reported to only kill fellow larvae once inside an egg-sac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Hoffman 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). The reason for the evolution of stalked eggs, consequently, remains unclear.</p>
            <p>A campodeiform, triungulin larvae hatches from the stalked eggs and uses one of two strategies for locating a food source (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Hoffman and Brushwein 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Hoffman 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). Either the larvae, termed obligate egg-sac penetrators, actively move about in search of an egg-sac or those termed obligate spider boarders will board a spider (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Hoffman and Brushwein 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Hoffman 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). It is thought that larvae that use the former strategy are attracted to spider silk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod 1985</xref>). The second strategy includes phoretic behaviour. The larva is equipped with caudal suckers that are attached to a substrate. The head and thorax are then raised upwards to assume the phoretic position (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). The larva will sway back and forth with legs outstretched waiting for a spider to pass by. Once a spider has been boarded, the larva will usually wrap itself around the pedicel of the spider or it enters a book lung (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). A first instar larvae attached to the pedicel of an immature <tp:taxon-name>Clubionoidea</tp:taxon-name> spider has been recorded from Eocene Baltic amber (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Ohl 2011</xref>). Some species are known to make use of both strategies and this is termed facultative boarders/penetrators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). Once inside an egg-sac, the <!--PageBreak-->larva produces an allomone that limits the development of the spider eggs to increase the feeding time of the larva (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">Redborg 1983</xref>).</p>
            <p>The larvae undergo a unique ontological pattern. It has been proposed that the developmental pattern can be termed hypermetamorphic ontogeny but some authors do not agree (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Brauer 1869</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). The development is certainly not as complex as that of beetles in the family <tp:taxon-name>Meloidae</tp:taxon-name>, but much more complex than most known insect ontogenies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). The first-instar moults into a less mobile, less sclerotised second-instar. The second-instar is eruciform to scarabaeifrom. The final- and third-instar is grub-like, immobile and scarabaeiform (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). As in other <tp:taxon-name>Neuroptera</tp:taxon-name> larvae, the Malpighian tubules are modified into silk-producing glands that are used to produce a cocoon in the now-empty egg-sac (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Bissett and Moran 1967</xref>). When the construction of the cocoon is initiated, remaining eggs are ignored. However, if the entire batch of spider eggs is consumed spinning is initiated. It has been found that there is a direct relationship between the adult and the amount of food ingested by the third instar larva, leading to extreme variation in adult size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod 1985</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod (1985)</xref> found individuals twice the size of other individuals of the same species that could be correlated with the number of eggs consumed. The adults are generally predacious, but it has been suggested that some may be pollinators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">Tjeder 1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Hoffman 1992</xref>). The evidence is not conclusive and flowers might just be a suitable platform for ambushing prey as is manifest by some praying mantids (Mantodea) and crab spiders (<tp:taxon-name>Thomisidae</tp:taxon-name>).</p>
            <p>The mating behaviour of mantispids has received some attention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Eltringham 1932</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). The adults face each other and a series of movements are followed, probably for recognition purposes since cannibalism is common when adults encounter one another (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Eltringham 1932</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Hoffman 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). An organ termed Eltringham’s extrusible gland (EEG) is situated dorsally in the fourth and fifth abdominal segments of some male mantispids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Eltringham 1932</xref>). It is thought that the gland secretes a pheromone that has a calming effect on the female (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Eltringham 1932</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Hoffman 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Redborg 1998</xref>). The pheromone is probably distributed by short and regular bursts of ‘wing flapping’ during the mating ritual (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Hoffman 1992</xref>). Mating may take more than 24 hours and the whitish spermatophore can be seen after mating while entering the female genitalia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">Redborg and MacLeod 1985</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematic status of Afrotropical Mantispidae">
            <title>Systematic status of Afrotropical Mantispidae</title>
            <sec sec-type="Taxonomic complexity">
                <title>Taxonomic complexity</title>
                <p>The Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> are taxonomically extremely complex. Interspecific morphology differs only slightly, while marked intraspecific variation adds to the complexity. Appropriate distinguishing characters must consequently be carefully<!--PageBreak--> sought. The literature on southern African taxa is limited. Most of the species descriptions are vague and not intelligible, often lacking sufficient illustrations. This is probably because several authors were not Neuropterists and described the specimens using inappropriate characters and often overlooked important distinguishing criteria. As an example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Mansell (2010)</xref> found that Longinos Navás described over 764 Afrotropical neuropteran taxa (mostly species) of which 50% have already proven to be invalid. Museum material reveals that Navás misspelled names and misidentified several species, including type specimens, and re-described some species that he had originally described himself, often classifying the re-described species into a different genus. All Navás’ descriptions and names consequently require careful evaluation.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Previous works">
                <title>Previous works</title>
                <p>Previous authors did little comparative studies and described new taxa without conclusively capering them with similar taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Handschin 1959</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">1960a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">1963</xref>). Therefore, the main taxonomic impediment in the family appears to be synonymy. No complete, comparative revisions of the generic groups has previously been published, with only <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Poivre (1982b)</xref> appempting to compare some of the genera by using a matrix consisting of six relatively weak characters. To use the matrix for identification purposes, the specimen must be dissected and consequently destroyed. Furthermore, the matrix proved to be inadequate to identify several specimens to generic level.</p>
                <p>The most recent publications on the Afrotropical taxa were by Poivre in the early 1980’s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Poivre 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">1981a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60"> b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">1982a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62"> b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">1984a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">1985</xref>). Several new species were described and a limited revision was done on some of the West African species. Poivre’s publications are complex and his statements difficult to interpret. He frequently used anatomical morphological characters such as internal genitalic stuctures for descriptions, but did not provide comparative descriptions or keys. Several of the Poivre types (<italic>e.g</italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella ivoiriensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Poivre, 1982b and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella cachani</tp:taxon-name></italic> Poivre, 1982b) housed in MNHN are completely dissected, macerated and mounted on slides. The major concern is the loss of information from material preserved on slides. Colours and patterns, which are of extreme importance, are both difficult to communicate in articles and are lost when using slides as a method of preservation.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Nampista Navás, 1914">
                <title><tp:taxon-name>Nampista</tp:taxon-name> Navás, 1914</title>
                <p>This Palaearctic genus was recently revised by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Ohl (2009)</xref> so does not require redescription. It is incorporated into the key because <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nampista auriventris</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Guérin-Méneville), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nampista africana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Esben-Petersen) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nampista ragazziana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás) also occur in African countries (Egypt, Sudan, Eritrea, Ethiopia, Djibouti and possibly Somalia) bordering the Arabian Peninsula.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Mantispa">
                <title>Mantispa</title>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Illiger, 1798 is treated as a Palaearctic genus and is not redescribed in this study. Only a few specimens were available for this revision. Material is currently being obtained for a full comparative study of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin, 1959.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Mantispa and Perlamantispa">
                <title>Mantispa and Perlamantispa</title>
                <p>It has been suggested that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin, 1960 may be a synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Aspöck et al. 1980a</xref>). For the purposes of this study, the genera have been kept separate (see discussion below).</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p><bold><italic>Wing terminology</italic>:</bold> This study followed the wing terminology of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Lambkin (1986a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">b</xref>) with additions from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Ferris (1940)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Aspöck et al. (1980b)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Hoffman (1992)</xref>. Some minor changes to vein systems at the wing margins have been made. The changes include a different interpretation of Sc+R, Rs, M, Cu and A (anal vein system in only the hind wing) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The wing venation of <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> is complex with controversy abounding. The complexity is due to the major veins that are often fused and the relatively reduced number of minor veins. The median fused with the radius in both the forewing (FW) and the hind wing (HW) have been interpreted differently by several authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Ferris 1940</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Aspöck et al. 1980b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Lambkin 1986a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">b</xref>), the most recent being <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Machado and Rafael (2010)</xref>.</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Wing venation of <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name>. <bold>A</bold> Anal <bold>C</bold> Costa <bold>Cu</bold> Cubitus <bold>M</bold> Median <bold>Pt</bold> Pterostigma <bold>R</bold> Radius, Radial cells 1, 2, 3 and 4 <bold>Rt</bold> Radial triangle <bold>Rs</bold> Radial sector <bold>Sc</bold> Subcosta <bold>+</bold> indicates fused veins <bold><sub>p</sub></bold> posterior <bold><sub>a</sub></bold> anterior.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-184-067-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <p>In the FW Rs+M<sub>a</sub> splits into Rs and M<sub>a</sub> at the first fork (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The M<sub>a</sub> vein follows a path directly to the posterior margin. The Rs form the three radial cells and the anterior half of a hexagon-shaped cell (radial cell 4) before reaching the apical margin. In the FW <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Ferris (1940)</xref> interpreted the M<sub>a</sub> as a vein fused with Rs that separated from the Rs by forking into yet another anterior and posterior M<sub>a</sub> with the anterior M<sub>a</sub> following the fusion with the radial sector up to the first crossvein originating from the first radial cell. This interpretation (or assumption as referred to by Ferris) has been widely adopted with only Lambkin questioning the statement by explaining several different scenarios (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Lambkin 1986a</xref>). In the present study only the proximal border of the first radial cell is considered to be a fusion between M<sub>a</sub> and Rs. Consequently, no crossvein originating from a radial cell is considered to be fused with M<sub>a</sub>. The interpretations of the mantispid wing are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
            <p><bold><italic>Male genitalia</italic>:</bold> No dissections were made because it proved to be unnecessary for the delimitation of monophyletic groups. Preliminary studies indicated that internal genitalic structures might not be a necessary character for the elucidation of the Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> genera even though it is valuable for species delimitation. The only genus where the ectoprocts as well as the pseudopenis are autapomorphic for the Afrotropical genera is <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin, 1959 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4f</xref>; also see discussion below <!--PageBreak--><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin, 1959). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">Tjeder (1963)</xref> noted that the pseudopenis is not used for sperm transferal and thus wrongly termed in previous work (Flagellum in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Ferris 1940</xref>; penis/spinasternum in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Handschin (1959)</xref>; spinasternum in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Poivre 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">1981a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60"> b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">1982a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62"> b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">1984a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">1985</xref>). In all other groups, such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin 1960 there is too much genitalic variation whereas other characters proved consistent. Eltringham’s extrusible gland (EEG) is visible between the fourth and fifth abdominal tergite of some males without dissection and it was noted when the gland is present.</p>
            <p><bold><italic>Studied genera</italic>:</bold> Since the genera studied here are all distributed in the Afrotropics, the autapomorphies have not been compared to all <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> genera. The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Illiger, 1798 is not assigned an autapomorphy because of the confusion between this genus and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin, 1959 (see <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> below) that resulted in the lack of a character rather than the presence of one.</p>
            <p><bold><italic>Madagascar</italic>:</bold> The Madagascar fauna was revised by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Handschin (1963)</xref>. The two genera occurring on Madagascar are not included in this revision. The type specimens of both <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paulianella</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Handschin 1960a</xref> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Madantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fraser, 1952 should be <!--PageBreak-->in MNHN but have apparently been lost. Due to the lack of identified specimens of either of the genera in museum collections, as well as the inadequate descriptions, they are excluded from this revision. The fauna of Madagascar will only be revised once the type specimens are either located or sufficient specimens are collected.</p>
            <p>Name combinations and museums holding valuable collections were identified using LDL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Lacewing Digital Library</xref>) and the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Ohl catalogue (2004)</xref>. All specimens studied were dried pinned specimens. The collections studied are housed in the following institutions:</p>
            <p><bold>SANC</bold>	South African National Collection of Insects, Pretoria, South Africa</p>
            <p><bold>MZB</bold>	Museo de Zoologia, Barcelona, Spain</p>
            <p><bold>MRAC</bold>	Musée Royal de l’Afrique Centrale, Tervuren, Belgium</p>
            <p><bold>ZMB</bold>	Museum für Naturkunde an der Humboldt-Universität, Berlin, Germany</p>
            <p><bold>MNHN</bold>	Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris, France</p>
            <p><bold>DMNH</bold>	Ditsong Museum of Natural History (formerly Transvaal Museum of Natural History), Pretoria, South Africa</p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:23AFF0D1-4D05-4E15-8B91-79F32AE4A9D0</object-id>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Afromantispa</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Snyman &amp; Ohl</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name><comment> Snyman and Ohl gen. n. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa tenella</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Erichson, 1839: 169) comb. n., designated here.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>Both <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Handschin (1959</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">1960a</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Poivre (1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">1982b</xref>) considered the Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> to be part of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> without comparing the Afrotropical species to the type species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantis pagana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fabricius, 1775 (=<italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa styriaca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Poda, 1761)). The new genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> can easily be identified and clearly differs morphologically from the Palaearctic <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> although the two genera are possibly closely related. (see discussion below). Species complexes within this genus must be investigated, with at least one species with a distribution from South Africa to the Arabian Peninsula lacking morphological variation. Sexual dimorphism has not been formally investigated, but it appears to be absent in the genus.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Widespread throughout Africa. A few species have been collected in the Palaearctic Region sharing borders with Africa such as Spain and the Arabian Peninsula.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Prothorax granulated; granules dark (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3e</xref>). Antennae with distinct yellowish white band in the apical third (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref>). Even species with pale antennae have a few darker flagellomeres two-thirds apically from the base of the antennae and on the apex to form a yellowish-white band. The crossvein between Cu<sub>a</sub> and Cu<sub>p</sub>+A<sub>a</sub> in hind<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> wing attenuated or absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). These characteristics combined are unique to this genus and can be used to distinguish <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> species from all other genera.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p>Wing variation in the Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispinae</tp:taxon-name>. <bold>a</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella apicipennis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kolbe) <bold>b</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. <bold>c</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. <bold>d</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. <bold>e</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nampista ragazziana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás) <bold>f</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva braconidiformis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-184-067-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Head</italic>: Antennae moniliform; colour variable but all with conspicuous yellowish-white band in apical third; scape and pedicel yellow. Posterior vertex concave except for slight convex elevation directly posterior to and between antennal bases; median tubercle projection at posterior margin of vertex, vertex not visible in lateral view. Compound eyes large, each eye slightly broader medially at epistomal suture. Labrum circular. Mandible with dark apices; inner margins dark.</p>
                    <p><italic>Thorax</italic>: Pronotum narrow and elongated; prothorax longer than pterothorax; granulated; granules dark; pronotum transversely slightly wrinkled or rugulose; setae <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->present. Maculae slightly raised and inconspicuous; not pigmented in lighter coloured species, pigmented and shiny in darker species. Prozona slightly broader than base. Meso- and metathorax of similar size and distinctly separated by a deep cleft.</p>
                    <p><italic>Wings</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>): Wings always hyaline, lacking pigment except for the pterostigma. Pterostigma slightly concave in dorsal view; semi-circular and truncate appearance; pterostigma of most species with reddish appearance. Radial cell 1 and 2 of similar size with radial cell 3 smaller and narrower; a single crossvein from third radial cell to anterior margin (C). <italic>Hind wings</italic>: Crossvein between Cu<sub>a</sub> and Cu<sub>p</sub>+A<sub>a</sub> attenuated or absent; Cu<sub>a</sub> with sharp angle to and from attenuated crossvein to form inverted triangle.</p>
                    <p><italic>Legs</italic>: Median line on the anterior surface of the forecoxae never continuous from thorax to femur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref>). Mid- and hind legs differ considerably between species. Fore tarsal claw reduced to a single claw lacking arolium; Mid- and hind pretarsal claws pectinate (5 -6 teeth) with the middle tooth elongated giving the claw a sharp triangular appearance; arolium present on mid and hind tarsi.</p>
                    <p><italic>Abdomen/Genitalia</italic>: Males with ectoprocts slightly enlarged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4j</xref>). Pseudopenis visible in lateral and dorsal view. EEG present. No morphological significance regarding the female genitalia.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The new genus name is a combination of <italic>Afro</italic>- and <italic>Mantispa</italic>, which emphasises the African distribution of this <italic>Mantispa</italic>-like taxon.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Included species">
                    <title>Included species.</title>
                    <p>Besides the type species, 18 confirmed and 7 unconfirmed species names will be added in the future. These numbers are, however, certain to change. Synonyms need to be identified and new species described. A subsequent full revision of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> is currently in progress. The genus for the time being will therefore be based on the type species only.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Mantispa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Mantispa</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Illiger</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name><comment> Illiger in Kugelann 1798: 499. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantis pagana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fabricius, 1775: 278 (=<italic><tp:taxon-name>Raphidia styriaca</tp:taxon-name></italic> Poda, 1761: 101), by monotypy.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Amycla</tp:taxon-name><comment> Rafinesque, 1815: 118. Unjustified emendation of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Illiger in Kugelann 1798. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Amycla</tp:taxon-name></italic> was considered an emendation of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Illiger in Kugelann 1798, by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Neave 1939</xref>, 1: 167.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Mantispilla</tp:taxon-name><comment> Enderlein, 1910: 346 (as subgenus of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Illiger in Kugelann 1798). Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa indica</tp:taxon-name></italic> Westwood, 1852: 268, by original designation. Synonymised with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Penny 1982</xref>: 217.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>The genus was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Illiger (1798)</xref> in a single sentence more than two centuries ago with the European species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantis pagana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fabricius, 1775 (= <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa styriaca</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Poda, 1761)) as the type species. It became the best-known <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> genus probably due to the age of the genus, and several species described worldwide were incorrectly assigned to the genus. It therefore became the most speciose genus in the famil<!--PageBreak-->y <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Ohl 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Machado and Rafael 2010</xref>). More recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Hoffman (2002)</xref> proposed that revisions should focus on elucidating the true taxonomy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Newly described genera in the New World replaced the universal <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> name that is now restricted to the Old world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Hoffman 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Machado and Rafael 2010</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> might be confined to the Old World but is probably only represented by a few Palaearctic and Oriental species and not by species from the Afrotropics.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Palaearctic genus with some species records from the Afrotropical Region. These countries include Morocco and countries bordering the Arabian Peninsula.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Ectoprocts sligtly swollen/enlarged. Pterostigma elongated and dark red. Prothorax with setae and slightly transversely rugulose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3g</xref>). Fore coxae lack continuous median line on anterior surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 3.</label>
                        <caption><p>Pronotum variation in the Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispinae</tp:taxon-name> <bold>a</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella apicipennis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kolbe) <bold>b</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata hilaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás) <bold>c</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. <bold>d</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva braconidiformis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin <bold>e</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. <bold>f</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nampista ragazziana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás)<bold>g</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa mandarina</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-184-067-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 4.</label>
                        <caption><p>Apomorphic characters of the Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispinae</tp:taxon-name> <bold>a</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., antennal band and discontinuous fore-coxal line <bold>b</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., continuous line on fore-coxae <bold>c</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva braconidiformis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Handschin, Elongated antennae and light pleura <bold>d</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nampista ragazziana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás), lamellate flagella <bold>e</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella apicipennis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kolbe), black maculae and pronotal markings <bold>f</bold> Male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa perparva</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Esben-Peterson), elongated ectoprocts and pseudopenis <bold>g</bold>Male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., slightly enlarged/swollen ectoprocts <bold>h</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp., anterior scape and pedicel always yellow <bold>i</bold> Male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa perparva</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Esben-Peterson), inner femoral surface.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-184-067-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Sagittalata</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Handschin</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name><comment> Handschin, 1959: 215. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispilla hilaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás, 1925: 573 (as “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata hilaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás 1924) [sic]”), by original designation</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa</tp:taxon-name><comment> Handschin, 1960a: 191. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantis perla</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pallas, 1772: 14 (as “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa perla</tp:taxon-name></italic>”), by original designation. syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="New combinations">
                    <title>New combinations</title>
                    <p><italic>austroafrica</italic> (Poivre)</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa austroafrica</tp:taxon-name></italic> Poivre, 1984b: 642. syn. n.</p>
                    <p><italic>bequaerti</italic> (Navás)</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispilla bequaerti</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás, 1932: 279. Synonymized with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa bequaerti</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás) by Handschin, 1960a: 197.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispilla bequaerti</tp:taxon-name></italic> var. <italic>decolor</italic> Navás, 1932: 280. Synonymized with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa bequaerti</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás) by Handschin, 1960a: 197.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispilla kibumbana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás, 1936c: 355.. Synonymized with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa bequaerti</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás) by Handschin, 1960a: 197.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa bequaerti</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás). As a new combination by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Handschin 1960a</xref>: 197.syn. n.</p>
                    <p><italic>dorsalis</italic> (Erichson)</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Erichson, 1839: 168.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispilla hemichroa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás, 1931: 129.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispilla hypophoea</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás, 1932: 279.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa dorsalis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Erichson). As a new combination by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Handschin 1960a</xref>: 196.syn. n.</p>
                    <p><italic>girardi</italic> Poivre</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa girardi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Poivre, 1982a: 194.syn. n.</p>
                    <p><italic>nubila</italic> (Stitz)</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispilla nubila</tp:taxon-name></italic> Stitz, 1913: 15.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa nubila</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Stitz, 1913) syn. n.</p>
                    <p><italic>perla</italic> (Pallas)</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantis perla</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pallas, 1772: 14.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa christiana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Charpentier, 1825: 93. Synonymized with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa perla</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Erichson 1839</xref>: 167.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa flaveola</tp:taxon-name></italic> Erichson, 1839: 168.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa victorii</tp:taxon-name></italic> Guérin-Méneville, 1844: 391. Synonymized with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa perla</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Hagen 1858</xref>: 128.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa perla</tp:taxon-name></italic> var. <italic>brunnea</italic> Navás, 1906: 102.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa perla</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Pallas, 1772). As a new combination by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Handschin 1960a</xref>: 191.syn. n.</p>
                    <p><italic>pusilla</italic> (Pallas)</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantis pusilla</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pallas, 1772: 15</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantis brevicornis</tp:taxon-name></italic> De Geer, 1778: 620, pl. 46, fig. 9–10. Synonymized with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa pusilla</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Burmeister 1839</xref>: 967.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa pusilla</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Pallas, 1772) As a new combination by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Handschin 1960a</xref>: 191.syn. n.</p>
                    <p><italic>similata</italic> (Navás)</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispilla similata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás, 1922: 396.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa similata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás, 1922). Listed as valid combination in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Ohl (2004)</xref> and LDL. syn. n.</p>
                    <p><italic>royi</italic> Poivre</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa royi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Poivre, 1982a: 191. syn. n.</p>
                    <p><italic>tincta</italic> (Navás)</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispilla tincta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás, 1929: 107</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa tincta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás, 1929). As a new combination by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Handschin 1960a</xref>: 200.syn. n.</p>
                    <p><italic>vassei</italic> (Navás)</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa vassei</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás, 1909: 474.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa (Mantispilla) lineatifrons</tp:taxon-name></italic> Enderlein, 1910: 346. Synonymized with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa vassei</tp:taxon-name></italic> by Handschin, 1960a: 193.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispilla sankitana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás, 1922: 395. Synonymized with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa vassei</tp:taxon-name></italic> by Handschin, 1960a: 193.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispilla burgeoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás, 1923: 77., Probable synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa vassei</tp:taxon-name></italic> according to Handschin, 1960a: 193.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa vassei</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás, 1909) As a new combination by Handschin, 1960a: 193. syn. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>Handschin seemed to confuse the female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens and the genus he described as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic>. In his revision (1960a) he mentioned that types of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata tristis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata tristella</tp:taxon-name></italic> are both female and that he is certain they are <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp<!--PageBreak-->ecies. He mentions that the wing venation and prothorax corresponds with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However, the complete fusion between the Cu<sub>a</sub> and Cu<sub>p</sub>+A<sub>a</sub> veins in the hind wing to form a rectangle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>) occurs in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata tristis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (= <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa tristis</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata tristella</tp:taxon-name></italic> (= <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa tristella</tp:taxon-name></italic>) corresponds with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and not with the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata hilaris</tp:taxon-name></italic> or any of the other species (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata lugubris</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">Poivre 1981a</xref>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata jucunda</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">Poivre 1981a</xref>) that do conform to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The pronotum them also differs between the genera: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata tristis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata tristella</tp:taxon-name></italic> have a smooth elongated pronotum with a thin metazona, again corresponding with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and not <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata hilaris</tp:taxon-name></italic>. In addition, the colour patterns of the prozona as well as the antennae also suggest these two species should be placed with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and not <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Furthermore, the wing venation and genitalia suggest that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> species conform to all the characteristics of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata hilaris</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The only morphological difference is a subtle robustness of the pronotum. Some species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> seem to have a slightly more robust pronotum. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> is consequently relegated as a synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The difference between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> is weak as well, as explained in the systematic account above. Finding an autapomorphy proved to be difficult. The only consistent character was a continuous median longitudinal line on the anterior surface of the coxae of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. In addition to the coxal line, the presence of setae on the pronotum of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> are lacking in the Afrotropical <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However, two species did not conform to this character. The raptorial legs of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (= <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic>) <italic>dorsalis</italic> is completely black and therefore lacks the line. The second species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (= <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic>) <italic>nubila</italic> lacks the line. Both species, however, lack setae on their pronotum. The rest of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> species studied conforms to the characteristics. Distribution therefore plays an extremely important role in the delimitation of the genera. The type species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Perlamantispa perla</tp:taxon-name></italic> however, is well known in Europe and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa styriaca</tp:taxon-name></italic> occurs in Morocco. C.-k. Yang (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">Yang and Peng 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">Yang 1999</xref>) described three <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> species from China. The descriptions are unfortunately in Chinese that could not be translated and the specimens were not studied. These species probably belong to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> instead of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Except for these species the distribution patterns of the genera are quite clear with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> an Afrotropical genus and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> a Palaearctic genus. Unfortunately it might be a genus that one will identify by eliminating other genera. Ongoing studies are in progress to find the relationship between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <sec sec-type="">
                        <title></title>
                        <p>Widespread in the Afrotropical Region. Also occur in the Palaearctic and Oriental Regions</p>
                    </sec>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>An Afrotropical genus with four species currently known from the Palaearctic Region. Ectoprocts of males sligtly swollen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4g</xref>), pseudopenis visible in dorsal view. Pterostigma elongated and dark red or black. Prothorax transversly rugulose; lacks setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>). Fore coxae with continuous median line on anterior surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Head</italic>: Antennae moniliform. Flagellum dark, may end in two or three yellow flagellomeres. Anterior scape and pedicel either yellow or black; vertex flat, not visible in lateral view; frons and mouthparts vary in colour; eye margin yellow in dark species and black/dark brown in light species.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak--><italic>Thorax</italic>: Maculae inconspicuous, never pigmented in a different colour from the surrounding pronotum; pronotum lacks setae, transversely rugulose; prothorax longer than pterothorax.</p>
                    <p><italic>Wings</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>): Wings usually hyaline, may be partly or completely pigmented, pterostigma elongated and robust, always reddish or black; crossvein between radial cells 1 and 2 perpendicular to R; a single crossvein from third radial cell to anterior margin (C); <italic>Hind wings</italic>: Crossvein between Cu<sub>a</sub> and Cu<sub>p</sub>+A<sub>a</sub> attenuated, rarely absent; Cu<sub>a</sub> with sharp angle to and from attenuated crossvein to form inverted triangle shape.</p>
                    <p><italic>Legs</italic>: Raptorial legs differ in colour, coxal sulcus conspicuous, surrounding patterns never visible on sulcus; continuous line on anterior surface of fore coxae; fore tarsal claw reduced to a single claw lacking an arolium. Mid- and hind pretarsal claws pectinate (5–6 teeth); median tooth longer than surrounding teeth; pointed appearance; arolium present on mid and hind tarsi.</p>
                    <p><italic>Abdomen/Genitalia</italic>: EEG present. Ectoprocts of male slightly swollen; slightly smaller than ectoprocts of members of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic>; pseudopenis visible in dorsal view.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion">
                    <title>Discussion.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> seem to form a group with several similar aspects regarding their morphology. All three genera seem to have similar genitalic structures. In addition to the genitalia, the general wing venation is extremely similar with only the pterostigma of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> slightly different with a reddish, roundish and truncate appearance. In the hind wing, the inverted “V” shape made by the Cu<sub>a</sub> when descending towards the attenuated or absent crossvein extending to Cu<sub>p</sub>+A<sub>a</sub> and again ascending after the crossvein is prominent and easily identified in this group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2b, c</xref>). The median coxal line is not a strong autapomorphy since some of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens studied had a discontinuous line on the anterior coxa, but the geographic distribution of the genera does support separate genera. A decision to keep the genera separate has consequently been made, thereby ensuring that relevant morphological information is not lost before a conclusive result is achieved. Of significant importance is the presence of the EEG that manifests in this group only.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Cercomantispa</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Handschin</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name><comment> Handschin, 1959: 224. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa mozambica</tp:taxon-name></italic> Westwood, 1852: 269 by original designation.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> is probably the most complex of all the Afrotropical genera. This is not only because of the sexual dimorphism and the general small size, but because of the confusion in the literature and physical state of the type specimen. Males are easily recognised by their elongated ectoprocts, but females do not have conspicuous genitalia and differ morphologically from the males in terms of colour and patterns. Females were therefore described as different species from the males and placed in se<!--PageBreak-->veral other genera. In addition to the confusion between the female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic> there is a lack of clarity regarding the generic boundaries of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Necyla</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Orientispa</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Necyla</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> could be synonyms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">Tjeder 1963</xref>). The name <italic><tp:taxon-name>Necyla</tp:taxon-name></italic> inexplicably disappeared from the literature. It is thought to be a genus comprising Oriental species with the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Necyla exigua</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás being represented by a female holotype. The type species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Necyla</tp:taxon-name></italic> could not be studied and photographs studied show a specimen in poor condition and pinned with closed wings. In addition to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Necyla</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Orientispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">Poivre 1984a</xref> also have elongated ectoprocts. The literature is not sufficiently unambiguous to synonymise these genera and for the purposes of this study, the genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Necyla</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Orientispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> will remain separate until further investigation can either confirm or reject the synonymy.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Widespread throughout the Afrotropical Region</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>The flagella of the antennae are very dark with the anterior surface of the scape and pedicel always yellow, even in the very dark species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4h</xref>). Pronotum smooth, lacks setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>). The rectangular cell formed by the fusion of A<sub>2</sub> and Cu<sub>p</sub> in the hind wing is very diagnostic and no other mantispid genus has such a structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>). All wing cells lacks pigment except for the pterostigma. The mid- and hind legs yellowish-brown to yellow covered in black setae. The males have elongated ectoprocts as well as an elongated pseudopenis, both longer than the 8<sup>th</sup> tergite, and bent ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4f</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Head</italic>: Antennae long, moniliform; flagellomeres black; the apical three flagellomeres might be lighter in colour; anterior scape and pedicel always yellow, even in very dark species; vertex medially convex, clearly visible in lateral view; vertex bordered by conspicuous yellow eye margin; frons with longitudinal dark median line, not visible in very dark species <italic>(e.g. C. tristis</italic>); mandibles usually yellow or lighter than coloration of frons; black tipped with black inner margin</p>
                    <p><italic>Thorax</italic>: Pronotum smooth, lacking setae; maculae conspicuous, not always pigmented; similar in length or slightly longer than pterothorax; in most species a dark median line forms two circular dorso-lateral yellow markings on prozona; prozona much wider than metazona, metazona narrow;</p>
                    <p><italic>Wings</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>): Wing venation comparatively simple; always lacks pigmented cells; pterostigma elongated, narrow; dark brown; a single crossvein from third radial cell to anterior margin (C); a single radial sector vein extending posteriorly from each radial cell 1, 2 and 3 respectively; four or five crossveins reaching posterior wing margin from M<sub>p</sub> in hind wing; a rectangle shaped cell formed by the fusion of A<sub>a</sub>+Cu<sub>p</sub> and Cu<sub>a</sub>.</p>
                    <p><italic>Legs</italic>: Raptorial forelegs yellow; fore tarsal claw reduced to a single claw lacking an arolium; inner femoral surface dark in females; often only distal half dark in males (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4i</xref>), outer femur of both sexes with a narrow, brown latero-dorsal line; middle and hind legs yellow-brown to yellow covered in setae; most species with a narrow dark longitudinal line along femur and tibia; pretarsal claws pectinate; middle tooth projecting beyond the others giving the claw a sharp appearance.</p>
                    <p><italic>Abdomen/Genitalia: Male</italic>: Ectoprocts elongated, longer than tergite 8; slightly swollen apically; apices bent downwards; pseudopenis elongated and bent ventrally; visible between ectoprocts in ventral and dorsal view; EEG absent</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Rectinerva</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Rectinerva</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Handschin</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Handschin 1959</xref>: 215. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva braconidiformis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Handschin 1959</xref>: 221, by original designation.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a monotypic genus. Only two female specimens have been collected, one being the holotype collected in 1933 (MRAC) the other collected in 1976 (MNHN) and described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">Poivre (1985)</xref>. The male remains undiscovered and sexual dimorphism therefore unknown.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Katanga (Democratic Republic of Congo) and Cameroon</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Light red-brown. The antennal flagellae long slender and black, proximal half covered in prominent thick black setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref>). The anepimeron, anepisternum, katepimeron as well as katepisternum much lighter than the rest of the body, almost white (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref>). Three radial sector veins extending posteriad from radial cells 1–3. The wing colouration is unique among mantispids from the region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Head</italic>: Head capsule light reddish-brown except for black tipped mandibles, vertex and pedicels. Scape light reddish-brown and pedicel black; flagellum long slender, black, proximal half covered in prominent thick black setae. Vertex medially raised in convex shape, visible in lateral view; raised vertex from antennal bases to posterior margin; black. Inner mandible margins lack black pigment. Eyes small; black to dark grey.</p>
                    <p><italic>Thorax</italic>: Pronotum light reddish-brown; smooth; covered in light inconspicuous setae. Maculae inconspicuous; same colour as pronotum. Pterothorax uniform light red-brown; sutures inconspicuous and smooth; lacks deep clefts. Anepimeron, anepisternum, katepimeron as well as katepisternum lighter, almost white, conspicuous against the uniform light red-brown of the pteronota.</p>
                    <p><italic>Wings</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>): Both wings pigmented in banded formation with colours ranging from dark-brown to light red-brown. Pterostigma black and slightly concave in dorsal view. A single vein from radial cell 3 to the anterior wing margin (C). Radial cells broad, Radial cell 1 being the largest, radial cell 2 somewhat smaller and rectangular in shape with the radial cell 3 being the smallest. Lacks the hexagonal radial cell 4 found in other Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> genera. Three radial sector veins extending in posterior direction from radial cells 1–3. <italic>Hind wing</italic>: Cu<sub>a</sub> parallel with A<sub>2</sub>+Cu<sub>p</sub>. Cu<sub>a</sub> - A<sub>2</sub>+Cu<sub>p</sub> crossvein not attenuated and close to posterior margin.</p>
                    <p><italic>Legs</italic>: Raptorial legs uniformly light reddish-brown; coxal sulcus same colour and inconspicuous; tibia-tarsal joint and fist tarsal segment black; fore tarsal claw reduced to a single claw lacking an arolium. Mid- and hind pretarsal claws pectinate (5–6 teeth); median tooth longer than surrounding teeth; pointed; arolium present on mid and hind tarsi. The rest of the mid leg light red-brown. Femur of hind leg light red-brown as well as the proximal third of the tibia, distal two-thirds and tarsal segments black; pre-tarsus light red-brown with some dark brown at pretarsal-claw bases.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    <p><italic>Genitalia</italic>: At the time of this study the macerated female genitalia (prepared by Ragner Hall in 1983) were missing.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion">
                    <title>Discussion.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva</tp:taxon-name></italic> form a group because of synapomorphies. The male of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva</tp:taxon-name></italic> is not yet known, so the genitalia cannot be used as a morphological character and sexual dimorphism cannot be excluded. However, the antennae of both genera are quite long compared to other Afrotropical taxa, and the flagellomeres are black with the anterior surface of the scape and pedicel yellow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4h</xref>). Furthermore, the pronota of members of both genera are very similar in structure, smooth and narrow posterior to the maculae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3c, d</xref>). The rectangular shape of the cell formed by the fusion of A<sub>a</sub>+Cu<sub>p</sub> and Cu<sub>a</sub> is present in only <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However, the second cell between the Cu<sub>p</sub>+A<sub>a</sub> and the posterior wing margin of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva</tp:taxon-name></italic> is quite similar in shape but lacks the fusion between A<sub>a</sub>+Cu<sub>p</sub> and Cu<sub>a</sub>. In addition to these, the comparatively simple wing venation and reduced number of radial sector cross veins in both genera seems to confirm the close relationship (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2d, f</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Nampista</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Nampista</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Navás</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Nampista</tp:taxon-name><comment> Navás, 1914: 97. Type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nampista speciosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Navás, 1914: 98 (= <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa auriventris</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Guérin-Méneville 1838</xref>: 202), by monotypy</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Forciada</tp:taxon-name><comment> Kozhanchikov, 1949: 355. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Forciada relicta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kozhanchikov, 1949: 356 (= <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa auriventris</tp:taxon-name></italic> Guérin-Méneville), by monotypy</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Bucharispa</tp:taxon-name><comment> Martynov, 1936: 437. Name unavailable, no type species was assigned to the genus.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>Predominantly a Palaearctic genus In the Afrotropics the genus is found only in the countries bordering the Arabian Peninsula where it is represented by three species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Handschin 1960b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Ohl 2009</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>The only Afrotropical genus close to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nampista</tp:taxon-name></italic> is <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name></italic>. It can easily be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the following characteristics: Flagellomeres asymmetrically lamellate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>); deeply incised ventrally. Prothorax shorter than pterothorax (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f</xref>). The basal half of the forewings always pigmented; the majority of the basal half of the hind wings clear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Revised by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Ohl (2009)</xref></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Pseudoclimaciella</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Handschin</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name><comment> Handschin, 1960a: 207. Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa erichsonii</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Guérin-Méneville 1844</xref>: 391 (as “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella erichsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> [sic] (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Guérin-Méneville 1844</xref>)” on page 207, and as “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Climaciella erichsoni</tp:taxon-name></italic> [sic] <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Guérin-Méneville 1844</xref>” <!--PageBreak-->on page 210), by original designation. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa erichsonii</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a replacement name for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa grandis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Erichson, 1839: 164, which is a junior secondary homonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa grandis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Guérin-Méneville, 1831: 196.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                    <title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name></italic> can easily be recognised and confusion with other genera is unlikely. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tuberonotha</tp:taxon-name></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Handschin 1961</xref>, a genus with a Palaearctic, Oriental and Australasian distribution is similar in appearance but always lacks an apical stain on the wings. Four Afrotropical species also lack an apical stain and were assigned to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name></italic> by either Handschin (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella congensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Navás, 1936); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella coronata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Stitz, 1913)) or Poivre (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella cachani</tp:taxon-name></italic> 1982b; <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella ivoiriensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Poivre, 1982b) but all four have the characteristic elongated radial cells as well as a large number of crossveins originating from the radial cells. In addition to these, two crossveins originate from radial cell 3 and terminate at the anterior wing margin, all other Afrotropical mantispines have only one such vein. The members of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name></italic> are generally large mantispids. They may be mimics of certain <tp:taxon-name>Vespidae</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>) species, an adaptation apparently not rare in <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name>. Colour patterns on the head as well as the pronotum fades with time and older museum specimens are frequently difficult to identify. Sexual dimorphism is unknown in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution.</title>
                    <p>The genus is probably confined to woodland and forests in the Eastern Tropical Corridor. All the locality data indicate a C-shaped distribution extending from the tropical areas in western Africa such as Sierra Leone through central Africa extending down into South Africa east of the plateau, and into Madagascar.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>All members of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name></italic> are rusty reddish to brown. Basal cells of forewings always pigmented; basal cells of the hind wing always clear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Two or three veins originate from radial cell 3 and terminate at anterior wing margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>); radial cells 1–3 elongated and narrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Two yellow bands extend from pronotal maculae to ventral basal margin forming an inverted “V” shape on the dorsal side (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4e</xref>). Hind tibia rusty reddish at joints and yellow in middle.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Head</italic>: Antennae moniliform; most flagellomeres dark in colour; twice as broad as long, one to three bright yellow flagellomeres apically; scape and pedicel rusty reddish. Vertex convex, not visible in lateral view; slightly raised posteriorly; vertex always yellow or rusty reddish; epistomal suture black except in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella elisabethae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Navás 1936</xref>); mandibles black tipped with black inner margin. Eye margins rusty reddish.</p>
                    <p><italic>Thorax</italic>: Pronotal maculae conspicuous, from the pronotal maculae two yellow bands with black margins extend to ventral basal margin forming an inverted “V” shape on the dorsal side; prescutum with yellow margin forming another inverted “V” shape; prothorax longer than pterothorax, prozona relatively smooth, anterior margin of prothorax black, might be discontinuous medially; metazona with transversely rugulose, lacks setae. Postnota 2 and 3 often yellow as well as posterior abdominal margins providing a vespid wasp-like appearance.</p>
                    <p><italic>Wings</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>): Wing venation complex. Pterostigma elongated, narrow, rusty-reddish. Radial cells 1–3 elongated and narrow; of similar length; at least 8 radial sector<!--PageBreak--> veins extending in posterior direction from radial cells 1–3. Two veins from radial cell 3 extending towards anterior margin (C), (very few specimens with three such veins but only in one wing so some individual variation present). All species except for above mentioned 4 with apical pigmentation in both wings. <italic>Hind wings</italic>: Crossvein between Cu<sub>a</sub> and Cu<sub>p</sub>+A<sub>a</sub> prominent; Cu<sub>a</sub> almost parallel with basal half of Cu<sub>p</sub>+A<sub>a</sub>; inverted triangle formed by Cu<sub>a</sub> shallow.</p>
                    <p><italic>Legs</italic>: Raptorial femur, tibia and tarsi uniformly red; lacks patterns on inner femoral surface; suture in fore coxa prominent and paler; single fore tarsal claw claw lacking an arolium. Mid- and hind pretarsal claws pectinate (5–6 teeth); teeth of similar size; spoon-shaped appearance; arolium present on mid- and hind-tarsi. Proximal joint of hind tibia dark rusty-red, distal joint lighter rusty red; proximad third of tibia same dark rusty red as joint, two distal thirds of tibia yellow.</p>
                    <p><italic>Abdomen/Genitalia</italic>: Males with ectoprocts inconspicuous to slightly enlarged. Pseudopenis visible in lateral and dorsal view; continuous variation in both ectoproct size and pseudopenis size. EEG absent. No morphological significance regarding the female genitalia.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion">
                    <title>Discussion.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nampista</tp:taxon-name></italic> are quite similar in many aspects. Species of both genera are generally quite large, reddish in appearance with wings often pigmented with a similar colour. From an Afrotropical perspective, they may form a group, but with other genera such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tuberonotha</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the Oriental Region that is in most aspects identical to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name></italic>, it is likely that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nampista</tp:taxon-name></italic> is not the most closely related taxon to any of the Afrotropical genera.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <sec sec-type="Key to the genera of the Afrotropical Mantispidae">
                <title>Key to the genera of the Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name></title>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1a</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flagellomeres asymmetrical and lamellate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Nampista</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flagellomeres symmetrical and moniliform (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a, b, c, e</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2a</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crossvein between A<sub>2</sub> and Cu<sub>p</sub> in hind wing attenuated or absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b, c, f</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A<sub>2</sub> and Cu<sub>p</sub> in hind wing fused (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>) or crossvein between A<sub>2</sub> and Cu<sub>p</sub> in hind wing prominent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3a</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prothorax granulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3e</xref>), white band present in distal third of antennae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Afromantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prothorax either smooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c, d</xref>), rugulose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a, f</xref>) or covered in setae but lack granules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3g</xref>) and white band in distal third of the antenna absent</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4a</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prothorax smooth</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prothorax rugulose</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Pseudoclimaciella</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5a</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prothorax smooth and rectangle cell formed by fusion of A<sub>a</sub>+Cu<sub>p</sub> and Cu<sub>a</sub> in hind wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cercomantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prothorax smooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4c</xref>) but no fusion between A<sub>2</sub> and Cu<sub>p</sub> in hind wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva</tp:taxon-name></italic> (in part)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <!--PageBreak-->
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7a</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In the hind wing Cu<sub>p</sub> forms a sharp angle when bending towards A<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In the hind wing Cu<sub>p</sub> do not form a sharp angle towards A<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rectinerva</tp:taxon-name></italic> (in part)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8a</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median line on anterior surface of fore coxae present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref>), prothorax lacks setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>), Afrotropical distribution</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Sagittalata</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median line absent on anterior surface of fore coxae, setae present on prothorax (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3g</xref>), Palaearctic distribution</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mantispa</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="The way forward">
            <title>The way forward</title>
            <p>The taxonomic ultimate aim is to comprehensively revise the family. The present study will serve as a basis for future taxonomic research on the lower taxa of Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name>. The complexity of the <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> has consequently been arranged into smaller monophyletic groups each with at least one autapomorphy. Future studies should therefore focus on revising each genus thereby avoiding an unnecessary increase in the already confusing list of invalid names in the region.</p>
            <p>Genitalic structures may prove to be important to elucidate the species and should be thoroughly investigated. Given the diversity and complexity of the Afrotropical <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name>, molecular and behavioural studies may delimit what traditional morphological tools cannot resolve.</p>
            <p>Fundamental knowledge regarding the basic biology of <tp:taxon-name>Mantispidae</tp:taxon-name> is sparse and requires attention. Studies that aim to investigate the oviposition preference of females, larval cues used for locating food sources and host specificity should be priority. This might allow for easier collection of specimens as well as raising other important questions regarding their evolution, behaviour and ecology.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We would like to extend our gratitude to the University of Pretoria and the Scarab Research Group (University of Pretoria) for funding the project. Thanks to the various museum curators for their assistance. Personally, I would also like to thank Christian Pirk, Catherine Sole, Cornel du Toit and Werner Strümpher for their support and patience as well as the staff of the ZMB for providing me with all the images which without the study could not have been possible. Lastly I thank the reviewers for their helpful comments.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspöck</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspöck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hölzel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980a</year>)<source> Die Neuropteren Europas I.</source> <publisher-name>Eine zusammenfassende Darstellung der Systematik, Ökologie und Chorologie der Neuropteroidea (Megaloptera, Raphidioptera, Planipennia) Europas. Goecke und Evers</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Krefeld</publisher-loc>, <lpage>495</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspöck</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspöck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hölzel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980b</year>)<source> Die Neuropteren Europas II.</source> <publisher-name>Eine zusammenfassende Darstellung der Systematik, Ökologie und Chorologie der Neuropteroidea (Megaloptera, Raphidioptera, Planipennia) Europas. Goecke und Evers</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Krefeld</publisher-loc>, <lpage>355</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspöck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of the Neuropterida (Insecta: Holometabola).</article-title> <source>Zoologica Scripta </source> <volume>31</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aspöck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plant</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemeschkal</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Cladistic analysis of Neuroptera and their systematic position within Neuropterida (Insecta: Holometabola: Neuropterida: Neuroptera).</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology </source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>-<lpage>86</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-3113.2001.00136.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1046/j.1365-3113.2001.00136.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bissett</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> The life history and cocoon spinning behaviour of a South African mantispid (Neuroptera: Mantispidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of the Entomological society of southern Africa </source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>82</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1869</year>)<article-title> Beschreibung der Vervandlungsgeschichte der Mantispa styriaca Poda and Betrachtungen ¨uber die sogenannte Hypermetamorphose Fabre’s.</article-title> <source>Verhandllungen der kaiserlich-kongiglichen zoologish-botanischen Gesellschaft in Wien </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>831</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Burmeister</surname><given-names>HCC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1839</year>)<source> Handbuch der Entomologie. Zweiter [=2nd] Band. Besondere Entomologie. Zweite [=2nd] Abtheilung. Kaukerfe. Gymnognatha. (Zweite [=2nd] Hälfte; vulgo Neuroptera). Theod. Chr. Friedr. Enslin, Berlin, 757–1050.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Charpentier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1825</year>)<source> Horae entomologicae, adjectis tabulis novem coloratis. A. Gosohorsky, Wratislaviae, xvi + 255 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>De Geer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1778</year>)<source> Memoires pour servir a l’histoire des insectes. Vol. 7. P. Hesselberg, Stockholm. xii + 950 pp. Neuropterida parts: „Mante“ [a mantispid], 620–621, pl. 46, figs 9–10.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eltringham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1932</year>)<article-title> On an extrusible glandular structure in the abdomen of Mantispa styriaca Poda (Neuoptera). Trans. Entomol. Soc.</article-title> <source>London </source> <volume>80</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Enderlein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1910</year>)<article-title> Klassifikation der Mantispiden nach dem Material des Stettiner Zoologischen Museums.</article-title> <source>Stettiner Entomologische Zeitung </source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>341</fpage>-<lpage>379</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Erichson</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1839</year>)<article-title> Beiträge zu einer Monographie von Mantispa, mit einleitenden Betrachtungen über die Ordnungen der Orthopteren und Neuropteren.</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift für die Entomologie </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>147</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fabricius</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1775</year>)<source> Systema entomologiae, sistens insectorvm classes, ordines, genera, species, adiectis synonymis, locis, descriptionibvs, observationibvs. Flensbvrgi et Lipsiae, 832 pp. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.36510" xlink:type="simple">10.5962/bhl.title.36510</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1940</year>)<article-title> The morphology of Plega signata (Hagen) (Neuroptera: Mantispidae).</article-title> <source>Microentomology </source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1952</year>)<article-title> New species of Neuroptera in the Museum National d‘Histoire Naturelle, Paris.</article-title> <source>Revue Française d‘Entomologie </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guérin-Méneville</surname><given-names>FÉ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1831</year>)<source> [„1830“] Névroptères. In Duperrey LI (Ed.): Voyage autor du monde, exécuté par ordre du roi, sur la corvette de sa majesté, La Coquille, pendant les années 1822, 1823, 1824 et 1825 à par m. L. I. Duperrey, [section] Zoologie, Vol. 2, Pt. 2, div. 1. Crustacés, Arachnides et Insectes, pp. 57–302. Plate 10 with 1 neuropterid figure. [Dating: Sherborn and Woodward (1901:392). Volume 2, part 2, pp. 1–216 dated 12 Nov. 1831, title page dated 1830.] 194–197.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guérin-Méneville</surname><given-names>FÉ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1838</year>)<source> Mantispe. Mantispa. Illiger. Magasin de Zoologie, (1) 8 (text to pl 202): 1–2.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guérin-Méneville</surname><given-names>FÉ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1844</year>)<source> [“1829–1838”] Iconographie du règne animal de G.</source> <publisher-name>Cuvier, ou représentation d’après nature de l’une des espèces les plus remarquables, et souvent non encore figurées</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>de chaque genre d’animaux. Insectes. Paris</publisher-loc>, <lpage>576</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1858</year>)<article-title> Russlands Neuropteren.</article-title> <source>Stettiner Entomologische Zeitung </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>110</fpage>-<lpage>134</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Handschin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>)<article-title> Beiträge zu einer Revision der Mantispiden (Neuroptera). I Teil. Mantispiden des Musee Royal du Congo Belge, Tervuren.</article-title> <source>Revue de Zoologie et de Botanique Africaines </source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>-<lpage>227</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Handschin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1960a</year>)<article-title> Beiträge zu einer Revision der Mantispiden (Neuroptera). II Teil. Mantispiden des “Musée Royal du Congo Belge”, Tervuren.</article-title> <source>Revue de Zoologie et de Botanique Africaines </source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>-<lpage>245</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Handschin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1960b</year>)<article-title> Nampista auriventris (Guérin) 1838 (Neuropt. Planip.).</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen der Schweizerischen Entomologischen Gesellschaft </source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>-<lpage>160</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Handschin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>)<article-title> Beiträge zur Kenntnis der Gattungen Euclimacia, Climaciella und Entanoneura Enderlein 1910 im indo-australischen Faunengebiet.</article-title> <source>Nova Guinea, Zoology </source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>-<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Handschin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<article-title> [“1962”] Beitrag zur Kenntnis der Neuropterenfauna von Madagascar.</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen der Schweizerischen Entomologischen Gesellschaft </source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>-<lpage>226</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<source> Systematics of the Mantispinae (Neuroptera: Mantispidae) of North, Central, and South America.</source> <publisher-name>Unpublished Ph.D. dissertation, Clemson University, Clemson</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>South Carolina</publisher-loc>, <lpage>501</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>K[M]</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Family Mantispidae. Pp. 251–275. In N. D. Penny (Ed.): A guide to the lacewings (Neuroptera) of Costa Rica.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences </source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>-<lpage>457</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brushwein</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> Spider (Araneae) taxa associated with the immature stages of Mantispa interrupta (Neuroptera: Mantispidae).</article-title> <source>Entomological News </source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brushwein</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<source> Descriptions of the larvae and pupae of some North American Mantispinae (Neuroptera: Mantispidae) and development of a system of larval chaetotaxy for Neuroptera. Transactions of the American Entomological Society 118: 159– 196.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Illiger</surname><given-names>JKW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1798</year>)<source> Genus Mantispa. p. 499.</source> <publisher-name>In J. G. Kugelann: Verzeichnis der Käfer Preussens, entworfen von Johann Gottlieb Kugelann ausgearbeitet von Johann Karl Wilhelm Illiger. Mit einer Vorrede des Professors und Pagenhofmeisters Helwig in Braunschweig</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>und dem angehängten Versuche einer natürlichen Ordnungs- und Gattungsfolge der Insekten. Halle</publisher-loc>, <lpage>510</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozhanchikov</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1949</year>)<article-title> New Mantispidae (Neuroptera) from Tadshikistan.</article-title> <source>Entomologicheskoe Obozreni </source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>353</fpage>-<lpage>358</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacewing Digital Library (LDL). Oswald JD (chief editor)</surname></name></person-group> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lacewing.tamu.edu" xlink:type="simple">http://lacewing.tamu.edu</ext-link> [accessed 23 September 2011]<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambkin</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986a</year>)<article-title> A revision of the Australian Mantispidae (Insecta: Neuroptera) with a contribution to the classification of the family I. General and Drepanicinae.</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Zoology, Supplementary Series </source> <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
 						
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambkin</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986b</year>)<article-title> A revision of the Australian Mantispidae (Insecta: Neuroptera) with a contribution to the classification of the family II. Calomantispinae and Mantispinae.</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Zoology, Supplementary Series </source> <volume>117</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>113</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>RJP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafael</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Taxonomy of the Brazilian species previously placed in Mantispa Illiger, 1798 (Neuroptera: Mantispidae), with the description of three new species.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>2454</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansell</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Monitoring lacewings (Insecta: Neuroptera) in Southern Africa.</article-title> <source>Acta Zoologica Academiae Scientiarum Hungaricae </source> <volume>48</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>165</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansell</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Towards a catalogue of Afrotropical Lacewings and Alderflies (Neuroptera, Megaloptera).</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Devetak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipovšek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnett</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Proceedings of the Tenth International Symposium on Neuropterology.</issue-title> <source>Piran, Slovenia, 2008</source>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansell</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> The Palpares relational database: an integrated model for lacewing research.</article-title> <source>Acta Zoologica Academiae Scientiarum Hungaricae </source> <volume>48</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>185</fpage>-<lpage>195</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martynov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1936</year>)<article-title> Lacewings (Neuroptera). In: Zhivotnyi mir SSSR [= Animal kingdom of the USSR].</article-title> <source>Izdatel’stvo Akademii Nauk SSSR, Moscow-Leningrad, </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>-<lpage>438</lpage></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Navás</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1906</year>)<article-title> Notas entomológicas. XIII. Sobre una pequeña colección de Neurópteros de Italia, reunida por el profesor Felipe Silvestri, de Portici.</article-title> <source>Boletín de la [Real] Sociedad Española de Historia Natural </source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Navás</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1914</year>)<source> Mantíspidos nuevos (Segunda [II] serie). Memorias de la Real Academia de Ciencias y Artes de Barcelona (3) 11: 83–103.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Navás</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1931</year>)<article-title> Insectes du Congo Belge (Série VI).</article-title> <source>Revue de Zoologie et de Botanique Africaines </source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Navás</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1932</year>)<article-title> Insectes du Congo Belge. (Série VII).</article-title> <source>Revue de Zoologie et de Botanique Africaines </source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>290</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Navás</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1936</year>)<article-title> Insectes du Congo Belge. Série IX.</article-title> <source>Revue de Zoologie et de Botanique Africaines, </source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>-<lpage>368</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B44"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Navás</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1909</year>)<source> [“1908–1909”]. Mantíspidos nuevos [I]. Memorias de la Real Academia de Ciencias y Artes de Barcelona (3) 7: 473–485.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B45"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Navás</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1922</year>)<source> Insectos nuevos o poco conocidos [I]. Memorias de la Real Academia de Ciencias y Artes de Barcelona (3) 17: 383–400.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B46"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Navás</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1923</year>)<article-title> Estudis sobre Neuròpters (Insectes).</article-title> <source>Arxius de l’Institute [d’Estudis Catalans, Seccio] de Ciencias, Barcelona </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>203</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B47"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Navás</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1925</year>)<article-title> Névroptères nouveaux.</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société Scientifique de Bruxelles </source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>566</fpage>-<lpage>573</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B48"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Navás</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1929</year>)<article-title> Insectes du Congo Belge (Série III).</article-title> <source>Revue de Zoologie et de Botanique Africaines </source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>92</fpage>-<lpage>112</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B49"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Neave</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> <role>(Ed)</role> (<year>1939</year>)<source> Nomenclator Zoologicus. Zoological Society of London, London, Vol. 1: 957 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B50"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<source> Annotated catalog of the Mantispidae of the World (Neuroptera). Contributions on Entomology, International 5: [ii+] 131–262.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B51"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Towards a global inventory of Mantispidae – the state-of-the-art in mantispid taxonomy.</article-title> <source>Annali del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale di Ferrara </source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B52"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> A revision of the mantispid genus Nampista (Neuropterida, Mantispidae), Zoosystematics and Evolution 85 (2): 189–198. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/zoos.200900003" xlink:type="simple">10.1002/zoos.200900003</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B53"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Aboard a spider – A complex developmental strategy fossilized in amber.</article-title> <source>Naturwissenschaften </source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>-<lpage>456</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00114-011-0783-2" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/s00114-011-0783-2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B54"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pallas</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1772</year>)<source> [Genus Mantis.] In: Spicilegia zoologica, quibus novae imprimis et obscurae animalium species iconibus, descriptionibus atque commentariis illustrantur, cura P. S. Pallas. Tome 1, Fasciculus 9. Berolini. 1 plate with 2 Neuroptera figures, 12–15.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B55"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Penny</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<article-title> Review of the generic level classification of the New World Mantispidae (Neuroptera).</article-title> <source>Acta Amazonica </source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>223</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B56"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Picker</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> A new genus and species of spoon-wing lacewing (Neuroptera: Nemopteridae) from Namaqualand, South Africa.</article-title> <source>Journal of the Entomological Society of Southern Africa </source> <volume>47</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B57"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1761</year>)<source> Insecta musei Graecensis, quae in ordines, genera et species juxta systema naturae Caroli Linnaei digessit, Graecii, 127 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B58"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poivre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Nouvelle description et morphologie externe comparée de Mantispa nana Erichson (Planipennia, Mantispidae).</article-title> <source>Neuroptera International </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B59"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poivre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981a</year>)<article-title> [„1980“] Mantispides du Cameroun I. (Neuroptera, Planipennia).</article-title> <source>Neuroptera International, </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B60"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poivre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981b</year>)<article-title> Mantispides du Cameroun II. Nouvelle description et morphologie externe comparée de Sagittalata lugubris et S. jucunda (Neuroptera, Planipennia).</article-title> <source>Neuroptera International, </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B61"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poivre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982a</year>)<article-title> [„1981“] Mantispides nouveaux d‘Afrique et d‘Europe (Neuroptera, Planipennia) (1<sup>re</sup> partie).</article-title> <source>Neuroptera International </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>205</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B62"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poivre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982b</year>)<article-title> Mantispides nouveaux d’Afrique et d’Europe (Neuroptera, Planipennia) (seconde partie).</article-title> <source>Neuroptera International </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B63"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poivre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984a</year>)<article-title> Les mantispides de l’Institut Royal des Sciences Naturelles de Belgique (Insecta, Planipennia) 1re partie: especes d’Europe, d’Asie et d’Afrique.</article-title> <source>Neuroptera International </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B64"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poivre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Mantispides du Cameroun III. Nouvelledescription de Rectinerva braconidiformis (Planipennia, Mantispidae).</article-title> <source>Neuroptera International </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>77</fpage>-<lpage>89</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B65"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Poivre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984b</year>)<article-title> Les Mantispidés du Muséum d’Histoire naturelle de Genève. III. (Insecta, Planipennia).</article-title> <source>Revue Suisse de Zoologie </source> <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>635</fpage>-<lpage>646</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B66"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafinesque</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1815</year>)<source> Analyse de la natureoutableau de l‘univers et des corps organisés. Palerme, 224 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B67"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Redborg</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> A mantispid larva can preserve its spider egg prey: evidence for an aggressive allomone.</article-title> <source>Oecologia </source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>230</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF00399222" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/BF00399222</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B68"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Redborg</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> Biology of the Mantispidae.</article-title> <source>Annual Review of Entomology </source> <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>194</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ento.43.1.175" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.ento.43.1.175</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B69"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Redborg</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacLeod</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> The developmental ecology of Mantispa uhleri Banks (Neuroptera: Mantispidae).</article-title> <source>Illinois Biological Monographs </source> <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>130</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B70"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stelzl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devetak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Neuroptera in Agricultural Ecosystems.</article-title> <source>Agriculture, Ecosystems and Environment </source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>305</fpage>-<lpage>321</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0167-8809(99)00040-7" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/S0167-8809(99)00040-7</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B71"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stitz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1913</year>)<article-title> Mantispiden der Sammlung des Berliner Museums.</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen aus dem Zoologischen Museum in Berlin, </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B73"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tjeder</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<article-title> A new Necyla from Uganda (Neur. Mantispidae).</article-title> <source>Opuscula Entomologica </source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>-<lpage>126</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B74"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Westwood</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1852</year>)<article-title> On the genus Mantispa, with descriptions of various new species.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the Entomological Society of London </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>252</fpage>-<lpage>270</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B75"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Winterton</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiegmann</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> On wings of lace: phylogeny and Bayesian divergence time estimates of Neuropterida (Insecta) based on morphological and molecular data.</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology </source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>-<lpage>378</lpage> doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3113.2010.00521.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1365-3113.2010.00521.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B76"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C-k</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> Neuroptera: Mantispidae. In: Fauna of Insects. Fujian Province of China. Vol. 3, 132–140, 163–164. [Text in Chinese]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B77"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C-k</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Y-z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> A new species of genus Sagittalata from Mt. Funiu (Neuroptera: Mantispidae).</article-title> <source>Fauna and Taxonomy of Insects in Henan </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>62</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>