<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.238.3970</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>First record in the Tropical Eastern Pacific of the exotic species 
                    <italic>Ficopomatus uschakovi</italic> (Polychaeta, Serpulidae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Bastida-Zavala</surname>
                        <given-names>Rolando</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>García-Madrigal</surname>
                        <given-names>Socorro</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Laboratorio de Sistemática de Invertebrados Marinos (LABSIM), Universidad del Mar, campus Puerto Ángel, Ciudad Universitaria, Apdo. Postal 47, Puerto Ángel, Oaxaca, 70902, México
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Rolando Bastida-Zavala (<email xlink:type="simple">rolando_bastida@yahoo.com.mx</email>, <email xlink:type="simple">rolando@angel.umar.mx</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: C. Glasby</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>5</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>238</issue>
            <fpage>45</fpage>
            <lpage>55</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>7</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>1</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Rolando Bastida-Zavala, Socorro García-Madrigal</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The exotic Indo-West-Pacific species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name>Polychaeta</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Serpulidae</tp:taxon-name>) is recorded for the first time in the Tropical Eastern Pacific from two sites in La Encrucijada Biosphere Reserve, Chiapas, a coastal lagoon in the Pacific south of Mexico. The means of dispersal of this serpulid species still remains unclear, as the nearest port (Puerto Chiapas) is 70 km to the south, and there are no port installations or shrimp cultures in the lagoon. The record of this serpulid species, apparently widely distributed in this coastal lagoon, has implications regarding possible effects on the brackish-water ecosystem, since the invasion event very well may have occurred several years ago. It is recommended that an exhaustive study be carried out in the coastal lagoons of Chiapas to evaluate the real distribution and the effects of this invasive species on the ecosystem. A complete description, including photographs and drawings, is provided.</p>
            </abstract>
            <trans-abstract>
                <label>Resumen</label>
                <p>Se registra por primera vez la especie exótica del Indo-Pacífico occidental, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<tp:taxon-name>Polychaeta</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Serpulidae</tp:taxon-name>), en el Pacífico oriental tropical, en dos sitios de la reserva de la biosfera La Encrucijada, Chiapas, una laguna costera en el Pacífico sur de México. El medio de dispersión de este serpúlido no es claro, debido a que el puerto más cercano (Puerto Chiapas) está 70 km al sur de la laguna, tampoco hay instalaciones portuarias ni estanques de cultivo de camarón. El registro de esta especie de serpúlido, aparentemente bien distribuida en esta laguna costera, tiene implicaciones con respecto a posibles efectos sobre el ecosistema salobre, sobretodo considerando que el evento de invasión pudo suceder hace ya varios años. Se recomienda realizar un estudio exhaustivo en las lagunas costeras de Chiapas para evaluar la distribución real y los efectos de esta especie invasora en el ecosistema. Se incluye una descripción completa, con fotografías e ilustraciones de la especie.</p>
            </trans-abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Annelida</kwd>
                <kwd>brackish-water</kwd>
                <kwd>Chiapas</kwd>
                <kwd>fouling</kwd>
                <kwd>ecologic impacts</kwd>
                <kwd>La Encrucijada</kwd>
                <kwd>México</kwd>
                <kwd>polychaete taxo-nomy</kwd>
                <kwd>systematics</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Southern, 1921 includes five species of brackish-water serpulids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">ten Hove and Kupriyanova 2009</xref>): <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus macrodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> Southern, 1921, from India and Sri Lanka (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">ten Hove and Weerdenburg 1978</xref>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus enigmaticus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fauvel, 1923), recorded from subtropical-temperate waters worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Fauvel 1923</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">ten Hove and Weerdenburg 1978</xref>); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus miamiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Treadwell, 1934), widely distributed in the Gulf of Mexico and Caribbean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Rioja 1945</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">ten Hove and Weerdenburg 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bastida-Zavala and Salazar-Vallejo 2000</xref>, and see below); <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Pillai, 1960), from Indo-Pacific and West Africa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">ten Hove and Weerdenburg 1978</xref>); and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus talehsapensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pillai, 2008, known only from Taléh Sap, Gulf of Thailand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Pillai 2008</xref>). It should be noted that we do not follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Pillai (2008)</xref>, who reinstated the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neopomatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> for the species <italic>uschakovi</italic> on the single autapomorphy of left and right thoracic membranes joined over the thorax.</p>
            <p>On the Pacific Coast of America, no indigenous species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bastida-Zavala 2008</xref>). However, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus enigmaticus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, was recorded as an exotic species from San Francisco Bay, California (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">ten Hove and Weerdenburg 1978</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bastida-Zavala 2008</xref>), and, recently, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus miamiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> was recorded from Urías lagoon, near Mazatlán, southeast of the Gulf of California, as an exotic species related to shrimp-ponds; however, the introduction could have taken place 20 years ago, when shrimp larvae were imported from Florida (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Salgado-Barragán et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Tovar-Hernández et al. 2009</xref>).</p>
            <p>The case of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus enigmaticus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, a serpulid widely dispersed around the world and with a long historical record of invasions, is a well-known example, because it can have dramatic impacts in invaded habitats building large, reef-like colonies in some coastal lagoons that cause major changes in benthic communities, especially in the Lake of Tunis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">ten Hove and van den Hurk 1993</xref>) and the Mar Chiquita Lagoon, Argentina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Schwindt et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Luppi and Bas 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bazterrica et al. 2012</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Rioja (1943)</xref> recorded, for the first time, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus enigmaticus</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Puerto Quequén, south of Mar del Plata, and now the species is widely distributed in the Mar Chiquita Lagoon, forming annular reefs and having several effects on the ecosystem and navigation of fishing boats in this lagoon-system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Schwindt et al. 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Luppi and Bas 2002</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Schwindt et al. 2004a</xref>, b). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Borthagaray et al. (2006)</xref> analysed the potential impacts of this invasive species in other lagoons of La Plata River, especially of the Uruguay coast.</p>
            <p>The effects of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus miamiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Urías lagoon were considered to be positive in the shrimp-ponds because the population of these serpulids (densities higher than 230,000<!--PageBreak--> ind/m<sup>2</sup>) helps to clean the water and control the suspended particulates. However, the impact of the colonies attached to the mangrove roots is negative, because the serpulid competes with other fouling and filter-feeding invertebrates such as native barnacles, mussels and oysters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Tovar-Hernández et al. 2009</xref>).</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> has been recorded from the Gulf of Guinea, West Africa since the 1950’s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Hartmann-Schröder 1971</xref>). Recently, this species was recorded in north-eastern Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">de Assis et al. 2008</xref>) and Venezuela (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Liñero-Arana and Díaz-Díaz 2012</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods">
            <title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>From 19–24 September, 2011, we visited several sites to collect marine invertebrates in Chiapas, including Puerto Chiapas (or Puerto Madero, as its old name), La Encrucijada Biosphere Reserve, Chocohuital, Boca del Cielo Lagoon, Paredón (Mar Muerto Lagoon) and ending in Oaxaca, in San Dionisio del Mar (Superior Lagoon). Serpulid samples were taken from hard substrates such as rocks, mangrove roots and artificial structures (e.g. piers, submerged buildings, etc.). The preliminary examination of the specimens included only the samples from La Encrucijada Biosphere Reserve because <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> tubes were immediately identified in the field. In the other sites in Chiapas and Oaxaca the typical tubes of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> were not found. Most specimen lots were deposited in the Colección de Invertebrados Marinos, Universidad del Mar, Puerto Ángel, Oaxaca (UMAR-Poly), other samples were deposited in the collections of El Colegio de la Frontera Sur, Chetumal, Quintana Roo (ECOSUR), and in the Universidad Autónoma de Nuevo León, Monterrey, México (UANL). Topotypical specimens examined came from the Los Angeles County Museum of Natural History, Allan Hancock Foundation, Los Angeles, California, USA (LACM-AHF).</p>
            <p>The specimens were fixed with 10% formalin and preserved in 70% alcohol. The line drawings were made using camera lucida, the photographs were taken with a digital camera (Nikon Coolpix). Opercula were generally found to be covered in silt and algae, and were, therefore, cleaned with a fine brush.</p>
            <p>Standard measurements and counts were total length, measured from the most distal part of the operculum to the pygidium; thoracic length, from the apron to the base of the collar; thoracic width, measured across the collar region; the number of thoracic chaetigers, the number of radioles in each lobe of the branchial crown; opercular length, from the base of peduncle to the end plate; and opercular diameter, measured across the dorso-ventral axis of the end plate.</p>
            <p>The abbreviations used in the text were as follows: OL (opercular length), OD (opercular diameter), THL (thoracic length), THW (thoracic width), TL (total length of the body), n (sample size), r (range of data), µ (mean), and ± (standard deviation).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics">
            <title>Systematics</title>
            <sec sec-type="Class Polychaeta Grube, 1850">
                <title>Class Polychaeta Grube, 1850. Family <tp:taxon-name>Serpulidae</tp:taxon-name> Rafinesque, 1815. Genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Southern, 1921</title>
                <p><bold>Type species.</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus macrodon</tp:taxon-name></italic> Southern, 1921 by monotypy.</p>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ficopomatus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">uschakovi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Ficopomatus_uschakovi</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Pillai, 1960</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A–E</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">, 2A–I</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Neopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name><comment> Pillai, 1960: 28–32, text-figs 10H, 11A–H, 12A–H, plate I, figs 1–2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Pillai 2008</xref>: 43–49, Fig 5–6, reinstated the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neopomatus</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Neopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name><comment> var. <italic>lingayanensis</italic> Pillai, 1965: 170–172, Fig. 23A–I. Type locality: Lingayan Gulf, Luzon Island, Philippines.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Neopomatus similis</tp:taxon-name><comment> Pillai, 1960: 32–33, text-figs 12I–M, plate II, fig. 1. Type locality: Negombo Lagoon, Sri Lanka.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Neopomatus similis</tp:taxon-name><comment> var. <italic>rugosus</italic> Pillai, 1960: 33–35, plate II, fig. 2. Type locality: Negombo Lagoon, Sri Lanka.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Mercierella enigmatica</tp:taxon-name><comment> (not Fauvel, 1923): Several examples of incorrect use of this name have been studied by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">ten Hove and Weerdenburg 1978</xref>: 109–110.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name><comment>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">ten Hove and Weerdenburg 1978</xref>: 109–112, figs 2a–d, 3a, f–k, 4j–n, r, x–z, jj–mm, yy, 5d, revision; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">de Assis et al. 2008</xref>: 51–58, Fig. 2A–G, Brazil; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Liñero-Arana and Díaz-Díaz 2012</xref>: 234–237, fig. 1a–j, Venezuela.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type locality">
                        <title>Type locality.</title>
                        <p>Panadura River estuary, Madu Ganga estuary at Balapitiya and Ratgama Lake at Dodanduwa, Sri Lanka.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined. </title>
                        <p><bold>Chiapas, South Pacific of Mexico.</bold> Five specimens (ECOSUR), three specimens (UANL), more than 100 specimens (UMAR-Poly 112), La Encrucijada Biosphere Reserve, Barra San Juan, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">15°09'58"N, 92°51'12"W</named-content>, 0.5–1 m, submerged mangrove root (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhizophora mangle</tp:taxon-name></italic>), September 21, 2011, Rolando Bastida-Zavala et al. leg. Five specimens (ECOSUR), 20 specimens (UMAR-Poly 113), La Encrucijada Biosphere Reserve, Zacapulco, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">15°11'37"N, 92°53'22"W</named-content>, on rotting mangrove root and gastropod shell, 0–0.5 m, September 21, 2011, Rolando Bastida-Zavala et al. leg.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Topotypical material">
                        <title>Topotypical material.</title>
                        <p>Two specimens (LACM-AHF N10947), Panadura River estuary, Sri Lanka, brackish water (donated by T.G. Pillai), October 9, 1961.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Mass occurrence is present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A, D</xref>); however, some specimens were solitary (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2E</xref>). The tube colour varies from pink to red in live material, changing to white, brown or orange in preserved material (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D–E</xref>). They possess several prominent to shallow peristomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>) or only low growth rings (annulations, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2E</xref>), but lack longitudinal ridges and alveoli.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <p>The body is yellow; with 6–7 dark bands on the radioles (preserved material, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">, 2F</xref>). The thorax has five dark bands on the lateral side, between the notopodial bundles, although sometimes these bands are blurred. TL=6.7 mm (n=10, r:4–6.7, µ=5.2 ±1); THL=2 mm (n=10, r:1.4–2, µ=1.7 ±0.2); THW=0.7 mm (n=10, r:0.5–0.7, µ=0.6 ±0.1). The branchial crown has nine radioles (n=10, r:6–9, µ=7.4 ±0.8) on the left, and eight on the right (n=10, r:7–9, µ=8 ±0.7). Interradiolar membrane absent.</p>
                        <p>The peduncle is smooth, inserted in the left branchial lobe; lacks a constriction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D–E</xref>); OL=1.8 mm (n=9, r:1–1.9, µ=1.6 ±0.4). The operculum is spherical to oval in shape, with a slightly convex, flat or slightly concave horny plate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B–E</xref>). OD=0.6 mm (n=9, r:0.5–0.8, µ=0.6 ±0.1). The end plate bears 1–5 concentric rows of spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2H</xref>); the rows are sometimes incomplete or converge with the other rows. The spines are transparent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2I</xref>).</p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 1.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold>A–E</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, from La Encrucijada Biosphere Reserve, UMAR-Poly 112–113. <bold>A, C</bold> complete body in lateral and dorsal views; <bold>B, D–E</bold> opercula, lateral views.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-238-045-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 2.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold>A–I</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, from La Encrucijada Biosphere Reserve, UMAR-Poly 112–113. <bold>A</bold> tubes on mangrove roots <bold>B</bold> tubes on the shell of the gastropod <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thaisella kiosquiformis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>C</bold> mangroves in the collecting site <bold>D</bold> tubes forming small aggregations <bold>E</bold> large, single tube <bold>F</bold> complete specimen in dorsal view <bold>G</bold> complete specimen with mass of sperm attached to the abdomen <bold>H</bold> operculum in dorsal view <bold>I</bold> operculum in aboral view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-238-045-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <p>The collar is entire, with well-developed lobes. The collar chaetae include coarsely serrated chaetae and hooded (capillary) chaetae. The thoracic membranes are fused dorsally, ventrally forming a small apron. The thorax has six chaetigers with hooded (limbate) chaetae, and saw-shaped uncini. A short achaetous region is present between the thorax and abdomen. Most of the abdominal segments possess geniculate chaetae and rasp-shaped uncini.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Originally limited to Indo-West Pacific and Gulf of Guinea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">ten Hove and Weerdenburg 1978</xref>), the species was also recorded in some isolated areas of the tropical and subtropical Western Atlantic: Sossego Creek, Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">de Assis et al. 2008</xref>), Morocoto Creek, Venezuela (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Liñero-Arana and Díaz-Díaz 2012</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>) and<!--PageBreak--> several sites in the Northern Gulf of Mexico (Bastida-Zavala et al. in prep.). There have been new records in Chiapas coast, Southern Pacific of Mexico (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>).</p>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 3.</label>
                            <caption><p><bold>A</bold> World-wide distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Triangles denote examined material, circles literature records (data from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">ten Hove and Weerdenburg 1978</xref>) <bold>B</bold> Study area and the localities where specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> were recollected. <bold>1</bold>: Zacapulco; <bold>2</bold>: Barra San Juan; <bold>3</bold>: Las Garzas boat pier (observed by S.I. Salazar-Vallejo et al., pers. comm.).</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-238-045-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Ecology">
                        <title>Ecology.</title>
                        <p>Depth: Intertidal to 1 m. On mangrove roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A, C</xref>) and on the shell of the gastropod <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thaisella kiosquiformis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Duclos, 1832) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>); coastal lagoon with salinity ranges approximately 20–35 o/oo. On shells, stones and petiole bases of coconut leaves in the topotypical area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Pillai 1960</xref>); on submerged piece of bamboo, with salinity ranges approximately 4–11 o/oo in Brazil records (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">de Assis et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Reproductive characters">
                        <title>Reproductive characters.</title>
                        <p>Two specimens (TL=4 mm and 4.2 mm) have masses of sperm glued to the abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2G</xref>); however, eggs have not been found in the specimens studied in detail (n=10).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>The specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Chiapas are slightly bigger than the topotypical specimens (TL=4–4.2 mm, THL=1.1–1.4 mm, THW=0.7–0.8 mm, OL=1.1–1.2, OD=0.3–0.5 mm); however, the rest of the morphological characteristics are very similar.</p>
                        <p>Apart from the spines of the operculum, the main character that separates <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus enigmaticus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus miamiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the dorsally fused thoracic membranes. This autapomorphy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is regarded to be of generic level by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Pillai (2008)</xref>, but is not followed by us.</p>
                        <p>In the local community the serpulid tubes on the mangroves are called ‘broca’ (more or less ‘drill’), just like all other sessile invertebrates with calcareous covers, such as barnacles and oysters.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>The presence of a species, resembling <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, from La Encrucijada Biosphere Reserve was initially brought to the attention of the authors two years ago (S.I. Salazar-Vallejo et al. pers. comm. 2009). Previously, no other record of the species existed throughout the Tropical Eastern Pacific. However, the observations in the field show that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is widely distributed in La Encrucijada, suggesting that the invasion event of this species may have occurred several years ago.</p>
            <p>Although ballast water, sediment transport and fouling are the main means of dispersal of aquatic exotic species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Carlton and Geller 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Ruiz et al. 2000</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Okolodkov et al. 2007</xref>), the means of dispersal of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> in La Encrucijada Biosphere Reserve still remains unclear, as the nearest port (Puerto Chiapas) is 70 km to the south, and there are no port installations or any shrimp cultures in the lagoon. The local people mentioned that these serpulids had gone unnoticed until now and apparently negative effects to the ecosystem have not been detected, except the fouling of the fishing boats, which require frequent cleaning.</p>
            <p>Mass occurrence of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>), however, not to the extent of the reef-like structures, formed by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus enigmaticus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Argentina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Schwindt et al. 2004a</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">, b</xref>) and by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus miamiensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> in Mazatlán (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Tovar-Hernández et al. 2009</xref>). However, similar impacts as caused by the latter species may be expected for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Therefore, it is necessary to conduct detailed monitoring of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the sites that have been invaded. It is also recommend that an exhaustive study in the coastal lagoons of Chiapas be conducted to evaluate the real distribution and the impact generated by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ficopomatus uschakovi</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>We would like to thank Sergio Salazar-Vallejo, Luis Carrera-Parra (ECOSUR, Chetumal) and Ángel de León-González (UANL, Monterrey) for alerting us to the exis<!--PageBreak-->tence of this species in La Encrucijada. We thank Edmundo Aguilar López, Teófilo González and Candelario Girón (CONANP, Chiapas), for their support during the visit to La Encrucijada Biosphere Reserve. The help in the field of Jani Jarquín-González (INECOL, Xalapa), Carmen Méndez (CICIMAR, La Paz) and Violeta Jiménez (UNSIJ, Ixtlán) was invaluable; Esmeralda Morales (UMAR, Puerto Angel), is thanked for the fast processing of the samples. The gastropod shell was identified by Norma Barrientos (UMAR). The specimens from Sri Lanka were examined in a visit to Los Angeles in 2004, hosted kindly by Leslie Harris (LACM-AHF). We appreciated the corrections and comments of Harry ten Hove (NCB Naturalis, Leiden), one anonymous referee and Chris Glasby (as editor) to the latest version. This work is part of the study of marine exotic species made by the Mexican network of exotic species (UMAR-UANL-UABC), supported by the project Programa de Mejoramiento del Profesorado 103–5/09/1353.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Assis</surname> <given-names>JE de</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christoffersen</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> First record of <italic>Ficopomatus uschakovi</italic> (Pillai, 1960) Serpulidae (Polychaeta: Annelida) for the Western Atlantic.</article-title> <source>Revista Nordestina de Biologia </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bastida-Zavala</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<source> Serpulids (Annelida: Polychaeta) from the Eastern Pacific, including a brief mention of Hawaiian serpulids. Zootaxa 1722: 1–61. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2008/f/z01722p061f.pdf">http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2008/f/z01722p061f.pdf</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bastida-Zavala</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salazar-Vallejo</surname> <given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<source> Serpúlidos (Polychaeta: Serpulidae) del Caribe noroccidental con claves para la región del Gran Caribe: <italic>Salmacina</italic>, <italic>Ficopomatus</italic>, <italic>Pomatoceros</italic>, <italic>Pomatostegus</italic>, <italic>Protula</italic>, <italic>Pseudovermilia</italic>, <italic>Spirobranchus</italic> y <italic>Vermiliopsis</italic>. Revista de Biología Tropical 48: 807–840. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biologiatropical.ucr.ac.cr/attachments/volumes/vol48">http://www.biologiatropical.ucr.ac.cr/attachments/volumes/vol48</ext-link> –4/08_Bastida_Serpulidos.pdf</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bazterrica</surname> <given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botto</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iribarne</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> Effects of an invasive reef-building polychaete on the biomass and composition of estuarine macroalgal assemblages.</article-title> <source>Biological Invasions </source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>765</fpage>-<lpage>777</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10530-011-0115-7">10.1007/s10530-011-0115-7</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Borthagaray</surname> <given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemente</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boccardi</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brugnoli</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muniz</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Impacto potencial de invasión de <italic>Ficopomatus enigmaticus</italic> (Fauvel) (Polychaeta: Serpulidae) en la Laguna de Rocha, Uruguay.</article-title> <source>Pan-American Journal of Aquatic Sciences </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlton</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geller</surname> <given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Ecological roulette: The global transport of nonindigenous marine organisms.</article-title> <source>Science </source> <volume>261</volume>: <fpage>78</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.261.5117.78">10.1126/science.261.5117.78</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fauvel</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1923</year>)<article-title> Un nouveau serpulien d’eau saumâtre <italic>Mercierella</italic> n. g., <italic>enigmatica</italic> n. sp.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Société Zoologique de France </source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>424</fpage>-<lpage>430</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann-Schröder</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<article-title> Zur Unterscheidung von <italic>Neopomatus</italic> Pillai und <italic>Mercierella</italic> Fauvel (Serpulidae, Polychaeta). (Mit neuen Beiträgen zur Kenntnis der Ökologie und der Rohrenform von <italic>Mercierella enigmatica</italic> Fauvel).</article-title> <source>Mitteilungen aus dem Hamburgischen Zoologischen Museum und Institut </source> <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hove</surname> <given-names>HA ten</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurk</surname> <given-names>P vaх den</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> A review of Recent and fossil serpulid “reefs”; actuopaleontology and the ‘Upper Malm’ serpulid limestones in NW Germany.</article-title> <source>Geologie en Mijnbouw </source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hove</surname> <given-names>HA ten</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kupriyanova</surname> <given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Taxonomy of Serpulidae (Annelida, Polychaeta): The state of affairs.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>2036</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>126</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3853/j.0067-1975.61.2009.1489">10.3853/j.0067-1975.61.2009.1489</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hove</surname> <given-names>HA ten</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weerdenburg</surname> <given-names>JCA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>)<article-title> A generic revision of the brackish-water serpulid <italic>Ficopomatus</italic> Southern 1921 (Polychaeta: Serpulinae), including <italic>Mercierella</italic> Fauvel 1923, <italic>Sphaeropomatus</italic> Treadwell 1934, <italic>Mercierellopsis</italic> Rioja 1945 and <italic>Neopomatus</italic> Pillai 1960.</article-title> <source>Biological Bulletin </source> <volume>154</volume>: <fpage>96</fpage>-<lpage>120</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1540777">10.2307/1540777</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Liñero-Arana</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Díaz-Díaz</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> Presencia del poliqueto exótico <italic>Ficopomatus uschakovi</italic> (Polychaeta: Serpulidae) en Venezuela: descripción y comentarios sobre su distribución.</article-title> <source>Interciencia </source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>234</fpage>-<lpage>237</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Luppi</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bas</surname> <given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Rol de los arrecifes del poliqueto invasor <italic>Ficopomatus enigmaticus</italic> Fauvel 1923 (Polychaeta: Serpulidae) en el reclutamiento de <italic>Cyrtograpsus angulatus</italic> Dana 1851 (Brachyura: Grapsidae), en la laguna costera Mar Chiquita, Argentina.</article-title> <source>Ciencias Marinas </source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>330</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Okolodkov</surname> <given-names>YB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bastida-Zavala</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibáñez</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suárez-Morales</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedroche</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutiérrez-Mendieta</surname> <given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Especies acuáticas no indígenas en México.</article-title> <source>Ciencia y Mar </source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pillai</surname> <given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1960</year>)<article-title> Some marine and brackish-water serpulid polychaeta from Ceylon, including new genera and species. Journal of Science.</article-title> <source>Biological Sciences </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pillai</surname> <given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>)<article-title> Annelida Polychaeta from the Philippines and Indonesia.</article-title> <source>Journal of Science, Biological Sciences </source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>110</fpage>-<lpage>177</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pillai</surname> <given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> <italic>Ficopomatus talehsapensis</italic>, a new brackish-water species (Polychaeta: Serpulidae: Ficopomatinae) from Thailand, with discussions on the relationships of taxa constituting the subfamily, opercular insertion as a taxonomic character and their taxonomy, a key to its taxa, and zoogeography.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1967</volume>: <fpage>36</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rioja</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1943</year>)<article-title> Estudios Anelidológicos IX: La presencia de la <italic>Mercierella enigmatica</italic> Fauvel, en las costas argentinas.</article-title> <source>Anales del Instituto de Biología, UNAM </source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>547</fpage>-<lpage>551</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rioja</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1945</year>)<article-title> Estudios Anelidológicos XIII: Un nuevo género de serpúlido de agua salobre de México.</article-title> <source>Anales del Instituto de Biología, UNAM </source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>411</fpage>-<lpage>417</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fofonoff</surname> <given-names>PW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlton</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wonham</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hines</surname> <given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Invasion of coastal marine communities in North America: Apparent patterns, processes, and biases.</article-title> <source>Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics </source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>481</fpage>-<lpage>531</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.31.1.481">10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.31.1.481</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Salgado-Barragán</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Méndez</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toledano-Granados</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> <italic>Ficopomatus miamiensis</italic> (Polychaeta: Serpulidae) and <italic>Styela canopus</italic> (Ascidiacea: Styelidae), non-native species in Urías estuary, SE Gulf of California, Mexico.</article-title> <source>Cahiers de Biologie Marine </source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwindt</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bortolus</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iribarne</surname> <given-names>OO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Invasion of a reef-builder polychaetes: direct and indirect impacts on the native benthic community structure.</article-title> <source>Biological Invasions </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>137</fpage>-<lpage>149</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1014571916818">10.1023/A:1014571916818</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwindt</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Francesco</surname> <given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iribarne</surname> <given-names>OO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004a</year>)<article-title> Individual and reef growth of the invasive reef-building polychaetes <italic>Ficopomatus enigmaticus</italic> in a south-western Atlantic coastal lagoon.</article-title> <source>Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom </source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>987</fpage>-<lpage>993</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0025315404010288h">10.1017/S0025315404010288h</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwindt</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iribarne</surname> <given-names>OO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isla</surname> <given-names>FI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004b</year>)<article-title> Physical effects of an invading reef-building polychaete on an Argentinean estuarine environment.</article-title> <source>Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science </source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>-<lpage>120</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2003.06.004">10.1016/j.ecss.2003.06.004</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tovar-Hernández</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Méndez</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villalobos-Guerrero</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Fouling polychaete worms from the southern Gulf of California: Sabellidae and Serpulidae.</article-title> <source>Systematics and Biodiversity </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>336</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S1477200009990041">10.1017/S1477200009990041</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>