<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.228.3826</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Dental morphology of the Lesser Bamboo Rat, <italic>Cannomys badius</italic> (<tp:taxon-name>Rodentia</tp:taxon-name>, Spalacidae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>López-Antoñanzas</surname>
                        <given-names>Raquel</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Departamento de Paleobiología, Museo nacional de Ciencias naturales–CSIC, C/ José Gutiérrez Abascal 2, 28006 Madrid, Spain
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Raquel López-Antoñanzas (<email xlink:type="simple">ralopan@mncn.csic.es</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: K. M. Helgen</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>17</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>228</issue>
            <fpage>69</fpage>
            <lpage>75</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>13</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>10</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Raquel López-Antoñanzas</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhizomys</tp:taxon-name></italic> are the sole living genera of the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Rhizomyini</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Rhizomyinae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Spalacidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Rodentia</tp:taxon-name>), known in the fossil record since the Late Miocene. The dental morphology of fossil <tp:taxon-name>Rhizomyini</tp:taxon-name> has been described in detail but until recently such descriptions were unavailable for extant species. A detailed account of the morphology and dental wear pattern of the cheek teeth of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic> is provided here based on the examination of museum specimens. Three stages of wear are recognized. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys</tp:taxon-name></italic> shares with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhizomys</tp:taxon-name></italic> the synapomorphy of having a mesolophid that is a long continuation of the protoconid on the first lower molar. There are significant differences between these taxa, such as the much smaller size of the cheek teeth and the trilophodont dental pattern of the M2, M3, and m2 in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Rhizomyinae</kwd>
                <kwd>Rhizomyini</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Cannomys</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>dental wear pattern</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Rhizomyinae</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Spalacidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Rodentia</tp:taxon-name>) is known in the fossil record since the Oligocene. It is represented by three modern genera: the Asian bamboo rats <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhizomys</tp:taxon-name></italic> (a trispecific genus) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys</tp:taxon-name></italic> (monospecific) and the African mole rats <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyoryctes</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The latter genus is considered bispecific by some authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Missone 1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Rahm 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bucher 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Corbet and Hill 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Beolchini and Corti 2004</xref>), but this <!--PageBreak-->may be an underestimation of true diversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Allen 1939</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Ellerman 1941</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Musser and Carleton 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">2005</xref>). The Asian bamboo rats belong to the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Rhizomyini</tp:taxon-name>, whereas <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyoryctes</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the only extant representative of the <tp:taxon-name>Tachyoryctini</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Flynn 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">López-Antoñanzas et al. in press</xref>). The lesser bamboo rat <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic> ranges from eastern Nepal, through northeast India, Bhutan, southeastern Bangladesh, Myanmar, south China, northwest Vietnam, Thailand and Cambodia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Musser and Carleton 2005</xref>). It is known to live in a wide variety of habitats, from bamboo forest to cultivated land and other modified areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">IUCN 2010</xref>).</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic> was originally named as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhizomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Hodgson (1841</xref>; p. 60) on the basis of a male specimen obtained “some miles north of the great valley” of Nepal. The type specimen is BMNH 1843.1.12.61 (skin and skull) (P. Jenkins, pers. comm. 2012). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Thomas (1915a)</xref> created the new genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys</tp:taxon-name></italic> for which he took <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhizomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic> as type, but in which he also included two other species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys castaneus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Blyth 1843</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys minor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Gray 1842</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Thomas (1915b)</xref> later described another species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys pater</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and split <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys castaneus</tp:taxon-name></italic> into two subspecies (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys castaneus castaneus</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys castaneus plumbescens</tp:taxon-name></italic>). Later, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Gyldenstolpe (1916)</xref> described a new subspecies of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys minor</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys minor lönnbergi</tp:taxon-name></italic>). All these taxa are currently regarded as synonyms of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Musser and Carleton 2005</xref>).</p>
            <p>The dental morphology of all living <tp:taxon-name>Rhizomyinae</tp:taxon-name> other than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic>, has been described in detail recently (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tachyoryctes</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">López-Antoñanzas 2012</xref>) or are in the process thereof (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhizomys</tp:taxon-name></italic>). The aim of the present work is to provide an in-depth description of the dental morphology of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>All the specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic> housed in the Laboratoire de Zoologie-Mammifères et Oiseaux of the Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle, Paris, France (MNHN) and in the Institut für Systematische Zoologie-Zoologische Sammlung of the Museum für Naturkunde, Berlin, Germany (ZMB) have been examined. MNHN individuals come from Thailand and Nepal, whereas those at ZMB are from Myanmar.</p>
            <p>First, second, and third lower molars are designated as m1, m2, and m3, respectively, and first, second, and third upper molars as M1, M2, and M3, respectively. The terminology used in the tooth descriptions follows the rodent dental terminology of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Flynn (1982)</xref> with some adjustments (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Dental terminology used in this paper. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <bold>a</bold> Left upper cheek teeth <bold>b</bold> Right lower cheek teeth. Scale bar equals 5 mm.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-228-069-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <sec sec-type="Dental morphology and wear pattern">
                <title>Dental morphology and wear pattern</title>
                <p>Incisors of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic> are strongly proodont, flattened anteriorly, lack major ornamentation and have the enamel pigmented orange.</p>
                <p>The upper molars of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic> show unilateral hypsodonty, with crowns higher lingually than labially. m1 has four roots, the anterolabial one being the<!--PageBreak--> most developed. Its occlusal outline is square. In early wear (e.g., MNHN C.G. 2000-271; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>), it has four transverse lophs (anteroloph, protoloph, mesoloph, and metaloph-posteroloph) and all labial and lingual sinuses are open. In later wear (e.g., ZMB 44769 and MNHN C.G. 2000-761; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b–c</xref>), the number of lophs is reduced to three as the anteroloph and protoloph combine and join at the margin of the tooth, isolating two transversely elongated enamel lakes, whereas the lingual sinus remains open. The latter, narrow and short, is directed toward the middle enamel lake. The connection between the anterior and posterior parts of the tooth persists through wear.</p>
                <p>The occlusal outline of m2is square, with its posterior side more reduced than the anterior one. This tooth is much shorter than m1. In early wear (e.g., MNHN C.G. 1860-382; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>), it has three transverse lophs (anteroloph-protoloph, mesoloph, and metaloph-posteroloph). The sinus is directed toward the anterosinus. All reentrants remain open. After moderate wear (e.g., ZMB 44769, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>), the sinus becomes narrower and the anterosinus and posterosinus are closed-off, isolating two enamel lakes. Late in wear (e.g., MNHN C.G. 2000-761; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>), the morphology <!--PageBreak-->of M2 is quite similar to that in the previous wear stage. However, the posterior part of the tooth becomes more reduced and, even though the lingual sinus remains open, it turns out to be more anterolabially directed due to the labial displacement of the hypocone. The connection between the anterior and posterior parts of the tooth persists through wear.</p>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a reduced m3. In early wear (e.g., MNHN C.G. 1860-382; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>), it is morphologically similar to m2 but with its posterior part smaller due to the more labial position of the hypocone. This tooth is trilophodont, with anteroloph-protoloph, mesoloph, and metaloph-posteroloph. After moderate wear (e.g., ZMB 44769; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>), the anteroloph-protoloph is nearly connected to the mesoloph and the metaloph-posteroloph joins the mesoloph, isolating a labial circular enamel lake. The hypocone is much more labially displaced and the sinus much more anterolabially oriented. Therefore, the posterior part of the tooth becomes much reduced. In<!--PageBreak--> late wear (e.g., MNHN C.G. 2000-761; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>), the first and second lophs combine and the anterior enamel lake disappears. At this stage of wear only a labial enamel lake persists and the hypocone is located on the posterior margin of the tooth.</p>
                <p>The lower molars are lower crowned than the upper molars. As for the lower jaw bone, the mandibular foramen is located well caudal to the posterior margin of m3 (a little dorsal to m3, at the level of the tip of the coronoid process), whereas the mental foramen is situated rostrally to the anterior border of m1 (approximately on the midline of the dentary).</p>
                <p>The occlusal outline of m1 is triangular, with its anterior part much narrower than its posterior. In early wear (e.g., MNHN C.G. 1860-382; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>), it shows a pentalophodont dental pattern with anterolophid, metalophid, mesolophid, hypolophid, and posterolophid. The metalophid joins lingually the anterolophid and labially the protoconid, isolating a small and oval anterior enamel lake. The mesolophid is a long continuation of the protoconid. The anterior part of the tooth is isolated from the rest of the crown by a long sinusid. The latter results from the junction of the sinusid (or labial reentrant) with the mesosinusid (or middle labial reentrant). All lophids join the lingual margin of the tooth, isolating four transversely elongated enamel lakes. The m1 shows two open labial sinusids (protosinusid and sinusid). After moderate wear (e.g., ZMB 44768; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>), all reentrants are closed-off, the protosinusid disappears, and the anterior part of the tooth is deprived of any enamel lake. However, two enamel lakes persist posteriorly. In late wear (e.g., MNHN C.G. 2000-761; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>), the occlusal surface is completely flat and generally devoid of enamel lakes although a tiny and circular posterolabially located enamel lake may persist. The enamel has disappeared from the anterior border of the tooth, but it persists posteriorly.</p>
                <p>The m2 has four roots, the posterior ones being the most developed. Its occlusal outline is square and it is anteroposteriorly compressed. In early wear (e.g., MNHN C.G. 1860-382, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>); this tooth has three lophs (anterolophid-metalophid, mesolophid, and hypolophid-posterolophid). The mesolophid is short and joins labially the anterior lophid (through the protoconid) and lingually the posterior one. The sole lingual reentrant is closed-off, isolating a labial enamel lake, which is elongated. The narrow and posterolingually directed sinusid is open. After moderate wear (e.g., ZMB 44768, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>); the morphology of the tooth is similar to that of the preceding stage. In late wear (e.g., MNHN C.G. 2000-761; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>), the sinusid is closed off and the tooth shows both a labial and a lingual enamel lake. The anterior side of the tooth loses the enamel.</p>
                <p>In early wear (e.g., MNHN C.G. 1860-382; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>), m3 has three lophids (anterolophid-metalophid, mesolophid, and hypolophid-posterolophid). The first lophid joins the second one through the protoconid. The posterior lophid is isolated from the rest of the crown by a long reentrant. At this stage of wear, all reentrants are open. After moderate wear (e.g., ZMB 44768, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>), the lingual reentrants are closed-off. The tooth has an elongate anterior enamel lake and a long sinusid. In late wear (e.g., MNHN C.G. 2000-761; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>), the lingual reentrant is closed-off, isolating two enamel lakes, and the anterior enamel lake persists.</p>
                <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    <label>Figure 2.</label>
                    <caption><p>Dental wear pattern in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <bold>a–c</bold> Upper molars: <bold>a</bold> Stage of wear 1, juvenile individual, left maxilla with M1-M3 in occlusal view (MNHN C.G. 1860-382) <bold>b</bold> Stage of wear 2, left maxilla with M1-M3 (ZMB 44769) <bold>c</bold> Stage of wear 3, left maxilla with M1-M3 in occlusal view (MNHN C.G. 2000-761). <bold>d–f</bold> Lower molars: <bold>d</bold> Stage of wear 1, juvenile individual, right hemimandible with m1-m3 in occlusal view (MNHN C.G. 1860-382), <bold>e</bold> Stage of wear 2, right hemimandible with m1-m3 in occlusal (ZMB 44768) <bold>f</bold> Stage of wear 3, left hemimandible with m1-m3 in occlusal (reversed) (MNHN C.G. 2000-761). Scale bar equals 5 mm.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-228-069-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                </fig>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Conclusion">
            <title>Conclusion</title>
            <p>The examination of the cheek teeth in various specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic> has allowed determining the changes undergone by the dental pattern during wear. Three fundamental stages of wear have been recognized.</p>
            <p>As postulated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Flynn (1990)</xref>, modern and extinct rhizomyines are united by dental features that include lophodonty, high crowned teeth, a strong wear gradient decreasing from first to last molar, junction between the metalophid and the anterolophid or the protoconid on the lower molars, and isolation of enamel lakes. In addition, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys</tp:taxon-name></italic> shares with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhizomys</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the other extant representative of the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Rhizomyini</tp:taxon-name>, the synapomorphy of having on the m1 a mesolophid that is a long continuation of the protoconid. However, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cannomys badius</tp:taxon-name></italic> is much smaller than all the extant species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhizomys</tp:taxon-name></italic> and exhibits the particularity of a trilophodont dental pattern on m2, M2, and M3, whereas it is tetralophodont in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhizomys</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>I sincerely thank C. Denys (Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle, Paris) and F. Mayer and N. Lange (Museum für Naturkunde, Berlin) for making available the rhizomyine material under their care. P. Jenkins (Natural History Museum, London) kindly answered all my inquiries. L. J. Flynn (Harvard University, Cambridge MA, USA), K. P. Aplin and K. M. Helgen (Smithsonian Institution, Washington DC, USA) helped to improve various aspects of this paper. M. Furió, A. García and L. Tormo (Museo nacional de Ciencias naturales-CSIC, Madrid) kindly took the SEMs.</p>
            <p>My sojourns in Berlin and Paris were funded by the SYNTHESYS Project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.synthesys.info/">http://www.synthesys.info/</ext-link> ), which is financed by the European Community Research Infrastructure Action under the FP7 “Capacities” Program, and by the EDIT Gender Action Plan, respectively. I am currently supported by the Ramón y Cajal Program and the research project CGL2011-24829.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1939</year>)<article-title> A checklist of African mammals.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology at Harvard College </source> <volume>83</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>763</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Beolchini</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corti</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> The taxonomy of the genus <italic>Tachyoryctes</italic>: a geometric morphometric approach.</article-title> <source>Italian Journal of Zoology </source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/11250000409356548">10.1080/11250000409356548</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blyth</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1843</year>)<article-title> Mr. Blyth’s monthlyReport for December Meeting, 1842, with Addenda subsequently appended.</article-title> <source>Journal of the Asiatic Society of Bengal </source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>925</fpage>-<lpage>1011</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bucher</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<article-title> Family Rhizomyidae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Honacki</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinmam</surname> <given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koeppl</surname> <given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Mammals Species of the World, First Edition.</issue-title> <source>Association of Systematics Collections, Lawrence</source>: <fpage>477</fpage>-<lpage>478</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Corbet</surname> <given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<source> A World List of Mammalian Species, Third edition. Oxford University Press, Oxford.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellerman</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1941</year>)<source> The families and genera of living rodents. Volume II. Family Muridae. British Museum (Natural History), London.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flynn</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<article-title> Systematic revision of Siwalik Rhizomyidae (<tp:taxon-name>Rodentia</tp:taxon-name>).</article-title> <source>Geobios </source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>-<lpage>389</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0016-6995(82)80084-3">10.1016/S0016-6995(82)80084-3</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flynn</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> The natural history of rhizomyid rodents.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nevo</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reig</surname> <given-names>OA</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Evolution of subterranean Mammals at the organismal and molecular Levels.</issue-title> <source>A.R. Liss, New York</source>: <fpage>155</fpage>-<lpage>183</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flynn</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> The antiquity of <italic>Rhizomys</italic> and independent acquisition of fossorial traits in subterranean muroids.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History </source> <volume>331</volume>: <fpage>128</fpage>-<lpage>156</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1206/582-4.1">10.1206/582-4.1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyldenstolpe</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1916</year>)<article-title> Zoological Results of the Swedish Zoological Expeditions to Siam 1911–1912 &amp; 1914–1915. Mammals II.</article-title> <source>Kungliga Svenska Vetenskapsakademiens Handlingar </source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.57007">10.5962/bhl.title.57007</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1842</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of some new Genera and fifty unrecorded Species of Mammalia.</article-title> <source>Annals and Magazine of Natural History </source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>267</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/03745484209445232">10.1080/03745484209445232</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgson</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1841</year>)<article-title> New species of <italic>Rhizomys</italic> discovered in Nepal.</article-title> <source>Calcutta Journal of Natural History </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>60</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>IUCN</surname></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source> IUCN red list of threatened species. Version 2010.1. Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iucnredlist.org">www.iucnredlist.org</ext-link> </source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>López-Antoñanzas</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> Dental morphology and wear pattern in <italic>Tachyoryctes</italic> (Spalacidae, <tp:taxon-name>Rodentia</tp:taxon-name>).</article-title> <source>Mammalia </source> <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>314</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1515/mammalia-2012-0018">10.1515/mammalia-2012-0018</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>López-Antoñanzas</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flynn</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knoll</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>in press</year>)<source> A comprehensive phylogeny of extinct and extant Rhizomyinae (<tp:taxon-name>Rodentia</tp:taxon-name>): evidence for multiple intercontinental dispersals. Cladistics.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Misonne</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<article-title> Order <tp:taxon-name>Rodentia</tp:taxon-name>.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Meester</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Setzer</surname> <given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>The Mammals of Africa: an identification manual.</issue-title> <source>Smithsonian Institution Press, Washington</source>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5479/si.03629236.298.1">10.5479/si.03629236.298.1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Musser</surname> <given-names>GG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carleton</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Family Muridae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reeder</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Mammal Species of the World, Second Edition.</issue-title> <source>The Johns Hopkins University Press, Maryland</source>: <fpage>501</fpage>-<lpage>755</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Musser</surname> <given-names>GG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carleton</surname> <given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Superfamily Muroidea.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname> <given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reeder</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Mammal Species of the World, Third Edition.</issue-title> <source>The Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore</source>: <fpage>894</fpage>-<lpage>1531</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahm</surname> <given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<source> Die Afrikanische Wurzelratte <italic>Tachyoryctes</italic>. A. Ziemsen, Lutherstadt Wittenberg.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1915a</year>)<article-title> Notes on the Asiatic Bamboo-Rats (<italic>Rhizomys</italic>, etc.).</article-title> <source>Annals and Magazine of Natural History </source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>56</fpage>-<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1915b</year>)<article-title> Further notes on Asiatic Bamboo-Rats.</article-title> <source>Annals and Magazine of Natural History </source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>-<lpage>317</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222931508693719">10.1080/00222931508693719</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>