<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.191.3070</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Australian Assassins, Part II: A review of the new assassin spider genus 
                    <italic>Zephyrarchaea</italic> (Araneae, Archaeidae) from southern Australia
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Rix</surname>
                        <given-names>Michael G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:B7D4764D-B9C9–4496-A2DE-C4D16561C3B3</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Harvey</surname>
                        <given-names>Mark S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:FF5EBAF3–86E8–4B99-BE2E-A61E44AAEC2C</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Terrestrial Zoology, Western Australian Museum, Locked Bag 49, Welshpool DC, Perth, Western Australia 6986, Australia
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Research Associate, Division of Invertebrate Zoology, American Museum of Natural History, New York, NY 10024, USA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Research Associate, California Academy of Sciences, 55 Music Concourse Drive, San Francisco, CA 94118, USA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A4">
                <label>4</label>Adjunct Professor, School of Animal Biology, University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, Perth, Western Australia 6009, Australia
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Michael G. Rix (<email xlink:type="simple">michael.rix@museum.wa.gov.au</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: M. Kuntner</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>7</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>191</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>62</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>12</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>24</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Michael G. Rix, Mark S. Harvey</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:2540D0CD-28B4-4079-A63D-4A6156615B8E</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The Assassin Spiders of the family <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> from southern Australia are revised, with a new genus (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>gen. n.</bold>) and nine new species described from temperate, mesic habitats in southern Victoria, South Australia and south-western Western Australia: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> Specimens of the type species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Platnick, 1991), <bold>comb. n.</bold>, are redescribed from the Albany region of Western Australia, along with the holotype female of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Harvey, 2002) <bold>comb. n.</bold> from the Stirling Range National Park. The previously described species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Archaea hickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> Butler, 1929 from Victoria is here recognised as a <bold>nomen dubium</bold>. A key to species and multi-locus molecular phylogeny complement the species-level taxonomy, with maps, habitat photos, natural history information and conservation assessments provided for all species.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>New species</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>conservation</kwd>
                <kwd>cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase</kwd>
                <kwd>mitochondrial DNA</kwd>
                <kwd>Palpimanoidea</kwd>
                <!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Once considered among the most enigmatic and poorly known of spider families, recent research into the assassin spiders of the family <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) has revealed three diverse, highly endemic faunas from southern Africa, Madagascar and Australia, each of considerable evolutionary and conservation significance, and all the focus of modern revisionary systematic studies that have transformed our understanding of archaeid evolution and biogeography (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Platnick 1991a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">1991b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Lotz 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Harvey 2002a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Wood et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Wood 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Rix and Harvey 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">2012</xref>). Although widely known from Mesozoic and Tertiary fossil deposits on multiple continents (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Dunlop et al. 2012</xref>), the Recent archaeid fauna consists of 54 described species in three genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Platnick 2012</xref>), with numerous new species still to be described from African, Malagasy and Australian regions (H. Wood, pers. comm., M. Rix pers. obs.). These species, all remarkable for their araneophagic ecology and highly autapomorphic morphology, have highlighted the contrasting patterns of speciation and endemism that occur in Australian versus Old World taxa, and the importance of the unique archaeid carapace morphology in the evolution of the group (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Wood et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Rix and Harvey 2012</xref>). The distinctive Australian fauna, while long neglected taxonomically and once presumed to be comparatively species-poor, has recently been shown to be far more widespread and species-rich than previously expected, thanks to dedicated field surveys and significant advances in our understanding of archaeid biology, ecology and biogeography (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Rix and Harvey 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">2012</xref>).</p>
            <p>The history of the discovery and documentation of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in Australia is one of significant recent, almost exponential progress, with over 85% of currently recognised species described in the past five years, and only four valid taxa described in the eight decades since the first species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea hickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Butler, 1929) was first recorded from Victoria. The second true archaeid to be recorded from Australia, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea nodosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Forster, 1956), was described from the Lamington Plateau, south-eastern Queensland, and nearly 30 years later <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Forster and Platnick (1984)</xref> described a third species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea daviesae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Forster &amp; Platnick, 1984, from the Wet Tropics of north-eastern Queensland, further erecting the new genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> to include all of the Australian taxa. <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> were unknown from Western Australia until <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Platnick, 1991b (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E-F</xref>) was described from the Torndirrup Peninsula, near Albany (first reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Dyer and Lyon 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Main 1987a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">1987b</xref>), and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Main (1995)</xref> reported the discovery in the 1970s of six unidentified juvenile specimens from near Pemberton. The first archaeid specimen to be recorded from the Stirling Range National Park in southern Western Australia was collected in 1996 and this species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Harvey, 2002a, remained the only assassin spider to have been collected in Western Australia for a further 10 years. In 2006, living adult specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>) were discovered in wet forest near Pemberton, catalysing the first of many such discoveries in Western Aus<!--PageBreak-->tralia, and highlighting the importance of temperate coastal heathlands as a habitat for assassin spiders. Indeed, since the pioneering revisionary work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Forster and Platnick (1984)</xref>, when only eight adult archaeids had been recorded for the whole of Australia, over 500 specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> have since been found throughout Queensland, New South Wales, Victoria, South Australia and Western Australia, revealing a diverse Australian fauna, characterised by numerous new species and mostly allopatric, relictual, short-range endemic taxa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Harvey 2002b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Harvey et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Rix and Harvey 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">2012</xref>).</p>
            <p>The current paper – the second in a series revising the <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> of Australia – presents a taxonomic revision of the assassin spiders from temperate ‘southern Australia’, including those species from Victoria, South Australia and south-western Western Australia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). A new genus, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>), is described to include the type species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, along with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> and nine new species. These taxa were found to form a monophyletic and highly divergent clade in a recent molecular phylogenetic analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Rix and Harvey 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>), sister to all other species of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> from eastern Australia. This revision takes the total number of described Australian <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> to 30 species, with the remaining, unrevised archaeids from north-eastern Queensland to be described in the third and final monograph of this series.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>All taxa were described and illustrated from specimens stored in 75% or 95% ethanol. Digital images were taken using a Leica MZ16A binocular microscope and a Leica DM2500 compound microscope, with auto-montage images captured using Leica DFC500 mounted cameras with Leica Application Suite Version 3.6.0 software. Male left pedipalps were dissected prior to imaging and bulbs were aligned for standardised comparison in the retrolateral and prolateral positions illustrated; expanded pedipalps were illustrated in a retro-ventral position. Female genitalia were dissected and cleared in a 10% lactic acid plus 90% glycerol solution, prior to mounting on temporary glass slides. Illustrations were made on Utoplex tracing paper, using printed template auto-montage images. Maps were generated using ArcMap version 9.3.1 (ESRI Inc.) with Virtual Earth (Microsoft Corp.).</p>
            <p>Measurements are in millimetres (rounded to the nearest hundredth of a millimetre) and were taken using an ocular graticule on a Leica M80 binocular microscope. Left legs were removed from specimens prior to taking measurements and imaging lateral body profiles. Lateral profile images were standardised for inter-specific comparison by vertically aligning the centre of each left anterior median eye with the lower anterior margin of the carapace (above the labrum) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A</xref>). Carapace height was measured in lateral view, from the margin of the pars thoracica above coxa II to the highest point of the pars cephalica (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). Carapace length was<!--PageBreak--> measured from the lower anterior margin of the carapace (above the labrum) to the posterior margin of the pars thoracica (above the pedicel) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). ‘Neck’ width was measured in lateral view, at the narrowest point of the carapace, with total length, carapace width, abdomen length and abdomen width all measured in dorsal view. To quantify inter-specific variation in the shape of the cephalothorax and ‘head’, three morphometric ratios (the <italic>carapace height to carapace length</italic> [CH/CL] <italic>ratio</italic>; the <italic>post-ocular ratio</italic> [P.O. ratio]; and the ratio of <italic>highest point of pars cephalica</italic> [HPC] <italic>to post-ocular length ratio</italic>) were derived from lateral profile images (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8"></xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">-9</xref>) as defined and discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Rix and Harvey (2011)</xref> (see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A</xref>).</p>
            <sec sec-type="Conventions">
                <title>Conventions</title>
                <p>Specimens sequenced for the molecular analysis of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Rix and Harvey (2012)</xref> are denoted by superscript codes, which correspond to specimen codes as shown in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Rix and Harvey (2012</xref>, table 1, fig. 4). For species diagnoses, molecular autapomorphies for mitochondrial cytochrome oxidase genes (COI-COII; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Harvey et al. 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Cook et al. 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Rix and Harvey 2011</xref>) are coded according their nucleotide number (1-1609), as defined in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Rix and Harvey (2011</xref>, table 3).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Abbreviations used in the text are as follows">
                <title>Abbreviations used in the text are as follows:</title>
                <p><abbrev>AME<def><p>	Anterior median eye/s</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>C1-2	<def><p>Conductor sclerites 1–2</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>CH/CL	<def><p>Carapace height (CH) to carapace length (CL) ratio</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>F1/CL	<def><p>Femur I length (F1) to carapace length (CL) ratio</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>HPC<def><p>	Highest point of pars cephalica</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>HT 1–6<def><p>	Abdominal hump-like tubercles 1–6</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>PME<def><p>	Posterior median eye/s</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>TS 1–3<def><p>	Tegular sclerites 1–3</p></def></abbrev></p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Specimens described in this study are lodged at the following institutions">
                <title>Specimens described in this study are lodged at the following institutions:</title>
                <p><abbrev>AMNH<def><p>	American Museum of Natural History, New York (N. Platnick, L. Sorkin)</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>AMS<def><p>	Australian Museum, Sydney (G. Milledge)</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>CASENT<def><p>	California Academy of Sciences, San Francisco (C. Griswold, A. Carmichael)</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>MV<def><p>	Museum Victoria, Melbourne (P. Lillywhite)</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>QMB<def><p>	Queensland Museum, Brisbane (R. Raven, O. Seeman)</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>SAM	<def><p>South Australian Museum, Adelaide (L. Chisholm)</p></def></abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>WAM<def><p>	Western Australian Museum, Perth (MSH, J. Waldock)</p></def></abbrev></p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <sec sec-type="Family Archaeidae Koch &amp; Berendt, 1854">
                <title>Family <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> Koch &amp; Berendt, 1854</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <label>Genus</label>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:BEE3BD64-0A61-40D4-880A-2A562847A855</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zephyrarchaea</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Rix &amp; Harvey</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                        <title>Type species.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Platnick, 1991b.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The generic name is derived from the Latin ‘zephyrus’, meaning ‘west wind’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Brown 1956</xref>), in reference to the diversity of this genus in south-western Australia, and the windy, coastal habitats occupied by several species, including the type species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from all eastern Australian species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the significantly shorter carapace (CH/CL ratio &lt;&lt; 2.0) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref> cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7"> 7</xref>), by the presence of accessory setae on or adjacent to the proximal (rather than the distal) bulge of the male cheliceral paturon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref> cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>), and by the shape of the two conductor sclerites on the male pedipalp, which are hinged, unfused and moveable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref> cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>), together forming a fully articulated cradle for the unexpanded embolus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10E</xref>). Like species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the genus can be further distinguished from Malagasy and African species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Eriauchenius</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Afrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of numerous, clustered spermathecae in females (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16G</xref>) and by the presence of a long, wiry embolus on the pedipalp of males (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">16E</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Forster and Platnick 1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Wood 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Rix and Harvey 2011</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Small, haplogyne, araneomorph spiders; total length 2.5 to 4.5.</p>
                        <p><italic>Colouration</italic>: Body colouration cryptic and relatively uniform across species, usually with only subtle intraspecific variation in abdominal patterning; carapace, sternum and chelicerae tan brown to reddish-brown in males, interspersed with darker regions of granulate cuticle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5F–G</xref>), covered in highly reflective setae; legs tan-brown to darker reddish-brown, with pattern of darker annulations on distal segments; abdomen mottled with beige and variable hues of grey-brown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>), with reddish-brown sclerites, scutes and sclerotic spots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>); paler beige markings due to reflective, subcuticular guanine crystals; antero-lateral face of abdomen always with large, humeral patch of reflective guanine crystals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6A–B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">17A–B</xref>).</p>
                        <p><italic>Cephalothorax</italic>: Carapace elevated anteriorly (CH/CL ratio usually 1.55–1.75; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>), with raised, highly modified pars cephalica forming ‘neck’ and bulbous ‘head’ (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Wood 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Rix and Harvey 2011</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5A–D</xref>); ‘neck’ with concomitantly long diastema (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Schütt 2002</xref>) between cheliceral bases and anterior margin of carapace, fused along entire length with sclerotised cuticle; cheliceral bases emanating from broad, fully-enclosed cheliceral foramen situated at front of ‘head’ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5B, 5D</xref>). Carapace with densely granulate cuticular microstructure, covered in larger setose tubercles arranged in clusters or distinct rows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5F–G</xref>); each tubercle bearing single densely plumose or ciliate seta; setose tubercles largest on ‘neck’ and pars thoracica (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5C, 5F–G</xref>). Eight eyes present on anterior margin of ‘head’, in four widely separated d<!--PageBreak-->iads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5A–D</xref>); AME largest, widely separated, directed antero-laterally on rounded ocular bulge (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>); PME situated closely posterior to AME, directed obliquely on postero-lateral side of ocular bulge; lateral eyes contiguous, with shared raised bases, directed ventro-laterally on widest lateral margin of ‘head’ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5A–D</xref>). Sternum longer than wide, covered in setose tubercles; lateral margins separated from dorsal pleural sclerite extending between coxae I–IV. Labium subtriangular, not fused to sternum, directed antero-ventrally at oblique angle to sternum; labrum with pair of divergent projections on anterior surface. Maxillae large, straddling labium and labrum, converging distally; serrula a single row of teeth. Chelicerae very long, spear-like, distally divergent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5C–E</xref>), usually with proximal bulging projection in males (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5A, 5E</xref>); both sexes with oval, ectal stridulatory file adjacent to pedipalps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5E</xref>); males also with tuft (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A, 5E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18B</xref>), brush (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figs 14C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15C</xref>) and/or comb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">16C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">17C</xref>) of accessory setae on anterior face of paturon. Chelicerae armed with three rows of peg teeth; anterior (prolateral) row with two peg teeth near tip of fang; posterior (retrolateral) row with single peg tooth near tip of fang; median (prolateral) row with more than 15 peg teeth extending along inner prolateral margin of paturon to near base of fang; median row with approximately eight porrect, comb-like peg teeth adjacent to fang, several larger, flattened, spiniform peg teeth near tip of fang, and additional progressively shorter, spiniform peg teeth along inner paturon; cheliceral retromargin also with four or five true teeth and prominent cheliceral gland mound.</p>
                        <p><italic>Legs and female pedipalp</italic>: Legs (longest to shortest) 1–4–2–3, covered with short plumose setae; spines absent; patella I long, greater than one-third length of femur I. Trichobothria present on tibiae and metatarsi of legs; tibiae I–IV each with two trichobothria; metatarsi I–IV each with single trichobothrium. Tarsi shorter than metatarsi, with three claws; tarsi, metatarsi and distal tibiae of legs I–II usually with ventral and pro-ventral rows of moveable, spatulate setae. Female pedipalp with long, porrect trochanter and small tarsal claw; tibia with two dorsal trichobothria.</p>
                        <p><italic>Abdomen</italic>: Abdomen arched anteriorly, rounded-subtriangular or spherical in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6A–B</xref>), sometimes with six large hump-like tubercles on dorsal surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10A–B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11A–B</xref>); cuticle covered with short plumose setae and numerous sclerotic spots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6C–F</xref>). Epigastric region with sclerotised (setose) book lung covers and dorsal and ventral plates surrounding pedicel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6C–D</xref>) (plates fused in males); dorsal pedicel plate with transverse ridges; females with median genital plate and sclerotised lateral sigillae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>); males with broad dorsal scute fused anteriorly to epigastric sclerites, with (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>) or usually without (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>) additional paired sclerites associated with hump-like tubercles. Six spinnerets, surrounded by thickened cuticle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6F</xref>); ALS largest, PMS smallest; colulus absent. Posterior pair of divided tracheal spiracles situated closely anterior to spinnerets; males also with epiandrous gland spigots situated closely anterior to epigastric furrow.</p>
                        <p><italic>Genitalia</italic>: Female genitalia haplogyne, with sclerotised, subtriangular genital plate anterior to epigastric furrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>); internally with gonopore leading to large, membranous bursa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 13B–C</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Harvey 2002a</xref>, fig. 2) overlying two separate, radiating clusters of sclerotised, sausage-shaped anterior spermathecae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 13B–D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15G</xref>, <!--PageBreak--><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">16G</xref>). Male pedipalp with complex, expandable spherical or pyriform bulb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">16E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18D</xref>), consisting of smooth tegulum, proximal ‘subtegulum’ and associated tegular groove with basal haematodocha (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>); distal tegulum with excavate, rimmed cavity surrounding massive, inflatable haematodochal complex, incorporating distal embolus, basal embolic sclerite, two articulating conductor sclerites and three additional tegular sclerites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18D</xref>) (see below). Unexpanded pedipalp with folded, curved embolus abutting paired conductor sclerites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10E</xref>); other tegular sclerites embedded pro-distally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10F</xref>); pedipalpal expansion and haematodochal inflation (e.g. see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18D</xref>) resulting in significant conformational changes to length and orientation of embolus, and relative position of tegular sclerites.</p>
                        <p>As noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Wood (2008)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Rix and Harvey (2011)</xref>, the homology of the tegular sclerites among archaeid genera remains unclear. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Rix and Harvey (2011)</xref> used a numbering system for comparing the moveable tegular sclerites among species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> from mid-eastern Australia, identifying four separate sclerites (TS 1, 2, 2a and 3) according to their relative position within the unexpanded tegular cavity (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>). These four sclerites can be broadly homologised with the tegular sclerites of species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, although at least one sclerite appears to be absent or otherwise highly modified in the latter, with no evidence for an interlocking, differentiated TS 2–2a complex (as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref> cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). Tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) is a prominent and strongly developed process in all species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">16F</xref>), originating proventrally adjacent to the base of conductor sclerite 1. Two additional tegular sclerites (here labelled collectively TS 2–3) are closely contiguous and not easily distinguished in the unexpanded state, usually embedded pro-distally adjacent to the retro-distal rim of the tegulum. The larger of these two sclerites, presumably homologous to tegular sclerite 3 (TS 3) in species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, has a shorter and broader, more plate-like morphology relative to TS 1, and is usually (but not always) visible as a pointed projection beyond the retro-distal rim of the tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">16E</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> occur in mesic habitats throughout southern Western Australia, South Australia and Victoria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>), usually in coastal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Figs 20C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">22C</xref>), sub-coastal or montane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23">Figs 23C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">24C</xref>) temperate heathlands, but also in wet eucalypt forests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">Figs 21C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F29">29C</xref>) and temperate rainforests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F26">Figs 26C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F27">27C</xref>). In Victoria they occur along the Great Dividing Range, from Grampians National Park and the Otway Range in south-western Victoria east to the Yarra and Strzelecki Ranges east of Melbourne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F26">Figs 26</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F27"></xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F28"></xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F29">29</xref>). In South Australia they occur on Kangaroo Island, at a single known locality north of Flinders Chase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F30">Fig. 30</xref>). In south-western Western Australia they occur in the southern high rainfall and south-eastern coastal provinces (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Hopper and Gioia 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Figs 20</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21"></xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22"></xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23"></xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24"></xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F25">–25</xref>), from the Wellington and Leeuwin-Naturaliste National Parks (near Bunbury) east to Cape Le Grand National Park, with outlying populations in the Porongurup and Stirling Range National Parks.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Composition">
                        <title>Composition.</title>
                        <p>Two described species – <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Platnick, 1991b) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Harvey, 2002a) – and the nine new species from southern Australia: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic><!--PageBreak--> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. The previously described species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Archaea hickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> Butler, 1929 is here recognised as a nomen dubium.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> forms a monophyletic and highly divergent clade sister to all other <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> from mid-eastern and north-eastern Australia (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Rix and Harvey 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Three main lineages have been recognised within the genus, for species from south-eastern Australia (South Australia and Victoria), from the Stirling Range National Park and from elsewhere in south-western Western Australia (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Rix and Harvey 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). The genus is not known to occur north or east of the Australian Alps, which may be a vicariant biogeographic barrier between populations of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to the Australian species of ">
                        <title>Key to the Australian species of </title>
                        <p><bold><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic></bold></p>
                        <p>Note that males of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> are unknown; females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. are unknown.</p>
                        <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Males</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdomen with six pronounced dorsal hump-like tubercles (HT 1–6), in three pairs, HT 3–6 each with small dorsal sclerite posterior to dorsal scute (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11B</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdomen spherical, or nearly so, without pronounced hump-like tubercles and without additional sclerites posterior to dorsal scute (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1B, 1D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">16B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">17B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18A</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) with flattened, rounded apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10D–F</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Platnick, 1991b)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) with more tapered, spiniform apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11D–F</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chelicerae with proximal bulging projection bearing tuft or brush of accessory setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 12B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18B</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chelicerae without tuft of accessory setae on proximal bulging projection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 16C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">17C</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tegular sclerites 2–3 (TS 2–3) not projecting beyond retro-distal margin of tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figs 14D–E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15D–E</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tegular sclerites 2–3 (TS 2–3) projecting well beyond retro-distal margin of tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 12C–D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18C–D</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior margin of diastema adjacent to ‘neck’ almost straight, only slightly concave in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14B</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior margin of diastema adjacent to ‘neck’ curved, strongly concave in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15B</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proximal bulging projection on chelicerae strongly protuberant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12B</xref>); dorsal scute on abdomen extending posteriorly (in lateral view) to roughly in-line with epigastric furrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12A</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><!--PageBreak-->–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proximal bulging projection on chelicerae indistinct, only slightly protuberant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 18B</xref>); dorsal scute on abdomen larger, extending posteriorly (in lateral view) to beyond line of epigastric furrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 18A</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conductor sclerite 2 (C2) relatively slender, with sinuous, S-shaped proximal portion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 17D–E</xref>); anterior margin of diastema adjacent to ‘neck’ slightly convex in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17B</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conductor sclerite 2 (C2) without sinuous, S-shaped proximal portion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 16D–E</xref>); anterior margin of diastema adjacent to ‘neck’ slightly concave in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16B</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdomen with six pronounced dorsal hump-like tubercles (HT 1–6), in three pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1E–F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11A</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abdomen spherical, or nearly so, without pronounced dorsal hump-like tubercles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">16A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">17A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">19A, 19C</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‘Head’ not strongly elevated dorsally, post-ocular ratio &lt; 0.25 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9E</xref>); highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) near posterior third of ‘head’, ratio of HPC to post-ocular length ≤ 0.66 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9E</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Platnick, 1991b)*</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‘Head’ more strongly elevated dorsally, post-ocular ratio ≥ 0.25 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9F</xref>); highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching posterior quarter of ‘head’, ratio of HPC to post-ocular length &gt; 0.66 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9F</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.*</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carapace with strongly concave post-ocular depression in lateral view  (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9A–D</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carapace with shallow post-ocular depression in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9G–I</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body size small, carapace length &lt; 1.10 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>); carapace relatively short, CH/CL ratio &lt; 1.70 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">19C</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body size larger, carapace length &gt; 1.10 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>); carapace taller, CH/CL ratio ≥ 1.70 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">19A</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‘Head’ not strongly elevated dorsally, post-ocular ratio &lt; 0.25 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9C</xref>); highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching middle of ‘head’, ratio of HPC to post-ocular length &lt; 0.60 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9C</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">‘Head’ more strongly elevated dorsally, post-ocular ratio ≥ 0.25 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9A–B</xref>); highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching posterior third of ‘head’, ratio of HPC to post-ocular length &gt; 0.60 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9A–B</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n./<italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.**</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carapace relatively short, CH/CL ratio &lt; 1.70 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13A</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Harvey, 2002a)</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carapace taller, CH/CL ratio &gt; 1.70 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15A</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior margin of diastema adjacent to ‘neck’ straight, almost perpendicular in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14A</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior margin of diastema adjacent to ‘neck’ slightly curved, concave in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15A</xref>)</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
                        <p><bold>*</bold>	Females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. are very similar morphologically, with only subtle morphometric differences in the shape of the carapace; male<!--PageBreak--> specimens or nucleotide sequences are recommended to accurately identify these closely related species.</p>
                        <p><bold>**</bold>	Females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. are essentially indistinguishable morphologically, with male specimens or nucleotide sequences required to identify these closely related sister-species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="The Western Australian fauna">
                <title>The Western Australian fauna</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">mainae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zephyrarchaea_mainae</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>(Platnick, 1991b)</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E–F</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A–B, 5E</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A, 6C–D, 6F</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8G</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9E</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">20</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name><comment> Platnick, 1991b: 259, figs 1–7.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Vernacular name">
                        <p>Albany Assassin Spider</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Holotype male. Torndirrup National Park (probably near end of Eclipse Island Road), Western Australia, Australia, pitfall trap, 1–6.VI.1983, P. Dyer, J. Lyon (WAM T17683).</p>
                        <p>Paratypes. Allotype female, same data as holotype except 3–8.X.1983  (WAM T17684).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined">
                        <title>Other material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>AUSTRALIA: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Western Australia</tp:taxon-name></italic>:</bold> <bold>Torndirrup National Park:</bold> same data as holotype except 2–9.XI.1983, 1 juvenile (WAM T17682); next to carpark at end of Salmon Hole Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°06'07"S, 117°58'03"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 14.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♀, 2 juveniles (WAM T89566<sup>DNA: TO-1-J/TO-2-J</sup>); same data except 30 April 2008, 1♀ (AMNH); same data, 1♀ (QMB S91206); same data, 1 juvenile (WAM T89567<sup>DNA: TO-171-J</sup>); next to carpark at base of Isthmus Hill, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°05'55"S, 117°58'02"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter in coastal <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> and eucalypt grove, 14.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 2 juveniles (WAM T89568<sup>DNA: TO-3-J/TO-4-J</sup>). <bold>Bremer Bay:</bold> Wellstead Road, S. of Bremer Bay, near Yate Place, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°24'10"S, 119°22'42"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> grove, 19.VI.2010, M. Rix, J.D. Roberts, 1♂, 1♀ (WAM T118984); same data except 21.IV.2009, M. Rix, 1♂, 1 juvenile (WAM T97463<sup>DNA: BB-147-J</sup>); same data except 2.V.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, J. Newell, 1♀, 1 juvenile (WAM T89563<sup>DNA: BB-34-F/BB-35-J</sup>). <bold>Denmark Region:</bold> Gilge Road, 15 km SE. of Denmark, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°03'15"S, 117°28'49"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter in remnant Karri grove with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 16.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♀, 1 juvenile (WAM T89577<sup>DNA: GI-14-F/GI-15-J</sup>); Mount Hallowell, 7 km SW. of Denmark, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°00'34"S, 117°18'04"E</named-content>, beating grass clumps in Karri forest, 6.XI.2007, M. Moir, D. Jolly, 1 juvenile (WAM T78901); Mount Hallowell, 7 km SW. of Denmark, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°00'38"S, 117°17'57"E</named-content>, beating grass clump in Karri forest, 19.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1 juvenile (WAM T89590<sup>DNA: MH-30-J</sup>). <bold>Gull Rock National Park:</bold> end of Ledge Point Road, near carpark, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°00'51"S, 118°00'23"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 17.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♀, 1 juvenile (WAM T89578<sup>DNA: GR-<!--PageBreak-->16-F/GR-17-J</sup>). <bold>Mutton Bird Point:</bold> end of Mutton Bird Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°02'53"S, 117°41'42"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 19.VI.2010, M. Rix, J.D. &amp; B. Roberts, 1♂, 2♀, 2 juveniles (WAM T118983); end of Mutton Bird Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°02'52"S, 117°41'42"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 18.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♂, 3 juveniles (WAM T89582<sup>DNA: MB-21-J</sup>); end of Mutton Bird Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°02'40"S, 117°41'50"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 18.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♀ (WAM T89581<sup>DNA: MB-20-F</sup>); end of Mutton Bird Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°02'54"S, 117°42'07"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 18.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♀ (WAM T89584<sup>DNA: MB-23-F</sup>); end of Mutton Bird Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°02'42"S, 117°41'36"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 18.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1 juvenile (WAM T89579); end of Mutton Bird Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°02'43"S, 117°41'43"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 18.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1 juvenile (WAM T89580); end of Mutton Bird Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°02'58"S, 117°41'56"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 18.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1 juvenile (WAM T89583). <bold>Porongurup National Park:</bold> west of Waddy's Hut, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°40'54"S, 117°50'48"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter in unburnt Karri forest, 306 m, 20.IV.2009, M. Rix, 1♀, 1 juvenile (WAM T97465<sup>DNA: PO-166-F/PO-167-J</sup>); same data except 6 March 2010, M. Rix, L. Lopardo, 1♀ (WAM T114028<sup>DNA: PO-168-F</sup>). <bold>Torndirrup Peninsula:</bold> Albany Wind Farm, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°03'53"S, 117°47'35"E</named-content>, beating vegetation in coastal heathland, 26.IX.2007, M. Harvey, R. Ott, 3 juveniles (WAM T89557); Albany Wind Farm, off Bibbulmun Track boardwalk, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°03'57"S, 117°47'43"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Banksia praemorsa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 12.III.2007, M. Rix, M. Harvey, M. Moir, 1 juvenile (WAM T81097); Albany Wind Farm, NW. of Wind Turbine No. 2, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°03'43"S, 117°47'46"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 15.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1 juvenile (WAM T89575<sup>DNA: WF-12-J</sup>); Albany Wind Farm, NW. of Wind Turbine No. 3, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°03'44"S, 117°47'38"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 15.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1 juvenile (WAM T89576<sup>DNA: WF-13-J</sup>); Albany Wind Farm, SW. of Wind Turbine No. 5, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°03'35"S, 117°47'22"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 15.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♀ (WAM T89574<sup>DNA: WF-11-F</sup>); along Bibbulmun Track E. of Albany Wind Farm, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°04'05"S, 117°48'01"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 27.V.2011, M. Rix, M. Harvey, G. Binford, 1♂ (WAM T118982); along Bibbulmun Track E. of Albany Wind Farm, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°04'05"S, 117°48'07"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 18.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♀ (WAM T89585<sup>DNA: WF-24-F</sup>); along Bibbulmun Track E. of Albany Wind Farm, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°04'10"S, 117°48'26"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 18.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1 juvenile (WAM T89588); along Bibbulmun Track E. of Albany Wind Farm, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°04'08"S, 117°48'18"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 18.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1 juvenile (WAM T89587<sup>DNA: WF-26-J</sup>); along Bibbulmun Track E. of Albany Wind Farm, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°04'06"S, 117°48'09"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 18.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1 juvenile (WAM T89586<sup>DNA: WF-25-J</sup>); Cuthbert, W. of Roberts Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°01'59"S, 117°47'47"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 18.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♀, 2 juveniles (WAM T89589<sup>DNA: WF-28-J/WF-29-J</sup>); end of Prescott Vale Road, W. of Albany Wind Farm, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°02'57"S, 117°45'30"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 15.III.2008,<!--PageBreak--> M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♂, 3 juveniles (WAM T89569<sup>DNA: WF-5-J/WF-6-J</sup>); end of Prescott Vale Road, W. of Albany Wind Farm, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°03'10"S, 117°46'11"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 15.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1 juvenile (WAM T89573<sup>DNA: WF-10-J</sup>); end of Prescott Vale Road, W. of Albany Wind Farm, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°03'10"S, 117°45'59"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 15.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♀ (WAM T89572<sup>DNA: WF-9-F</sup>); end of Prescott Vale Road, W. of Albany Wind Farm, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°03'02"S, 117°45'28"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 15.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♀ (WAM T89570); end of Prescott Vale Road, W. of Albany Wind Farm, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°03'10"S, 117°45'43"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 15.III.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1♀ (WAM T89571<sup>DNA: WF-8-F</sup>). <bold>Walpole-Nornalup National Park:</bold> Anderson Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°59'43"S, 116°52'14"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under curly grass in Marri and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> forest, 3.V.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 2 juveniles (WAM T89564<sup>DNA: WA-36-J/WA-37-J</sup>); same data except 24.I.2010, M. Rix, J. Wojcieszek, 1♂, 2♀, 1 juvenile (WAM T114037<sup>DNA: WA-162-F</sup>). <bold>William Bay National Park:</bold> near Elephant Rock carpark, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°01'21"S, 117°14'12"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 26.VI.2010, M. Rix, 2♀ (WAM T114029<sup>DNA: WB-169-F</sup>); same data except 29.IV.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1 juvenile (WAM T89591<sup>DNA: WB-31-J</sup>); same data except 7.III.2010, M. Rix, L. Lopardo, 2 juveniles (WAM T114030<sup>DNA: WB-170-J</sup>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from other known congeners except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the presence of six dorsal, hump-like tubercles on the abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E–F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10A–B</xref>); and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the more flattened, rounded apex of tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10D–F</xref>).</p>
                        <p>This species can also be distinguished from other genotyped taxa (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) by the following two unique nucleotide substitutions for COI and COII (n = 35): A(282), T(1173).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype male</italic>: Total length 3.44; leg I femur 1.81; F1/CL ratio 1.72. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige, with reddish-brown dorsal scute and sclerites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10B</xref>). Carapace short (CH/CL ratio 1.60); 1.05 long, 1.68 high, 1.03 wide; ‘neck’ 0.60 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) near posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.67), carapace with pronounced concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ not strongly elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.24) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8G</xref>). Chelicerae with proximal tuft and additional comb of accessory setae on anterior face of paturon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5A, 5E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10C</xref>). Abdomen 1.69 long, 1.18 wide; with three pairs of dorsal hump-like tubercles (HT 1–6); dorsal scute fused anteriorly to epigastric sclerites, extending posteriorly to first pair of hump-like tubercles; HT 3–6 each covered by separate dorsal sclerites. Pedipalp fully expanded (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Platnick 1991b</xref>, figs 4–6). Unexpanded pedipalp (of WAM T89569) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10D–F</xref>) pyriform, with broad, distally curved embolus supported by conductor sclerites 1–2; tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) porrect, slightly curved in prolateral view, with flattened, rounded apex; TS 2–3 projecting beyond retro-distal rim of tegulum.</p>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic> (WAM T118983): Total length 3.31; leg I femur 1.97; F1/CL ratio 1.73. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10A</xref>). Carapace short (CH/CL ratio 1.71); 1.14 <!--PageBreak-->long, 1.95 high, 1.10 wide; ‘neck’ 0.68 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) near posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.63), carapace with pronounced concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ not strongly elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.24) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9E</xref>). Chelicerae without accessory setae on anterior face of paturon. Abdomen 2.00 long, 1.36 wide; with three pairs of dorsal hump-like tubercles (HT 1–6). Internal genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10G</xref>) with cluster of ≤ 15 sausage-shaped spermathecae either side of gonopore, clusters widely separated along midline of genital plate.</p>
                        <p><italic>Variation</italic>: Males (n = 8): total length 2.82–3.44; carapace length 1.02–1.15; carapace height 1.62–1.80; CH/CL ratio 1.56–1.64. Females (n = 23): total length 2.77–3.82; carapace length 0.94–1.21; carapace height 1.45–1.99; CH/CL ratio 1.55–1.71. Specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> from the eastern-most Bremer Bay population have significantly smaller hump-like tubercles on the abdomen compared to populations further west (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref> cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10A</xref>), and males from this Bremer Bay population also have a more distally paddle-shaped TS 1 morphology similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. from Cape Le Grand National Park. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Rix and Harvey (2012)</xref> showed that the Bremer Bay population of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is genetically distinct (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>), with no evidence of recent gene flow, indicating possible incipient speciation.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution and habitat.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known from the greater Albany region of southern Western Australia, from Walpole-Nornalup National Park (near Walpole) east to Bremer Bay and north to the Porongurup National Park, with a range centred on the Torndirrup Peninsula south of Albany (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Fig. 20</xref>). Specimens have been collected by beating and sifting sedges (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepidosperma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.), curly grass (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Empodisma gracillimum</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and low shrubs in dense coastal or near-coastal groves of Peppermint (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.), with several outlying populations also known from wet Karri (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Eucalyptus diversicolor</tp:taxon-name></italic>) forest.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                        <title>Conservation status.</title>
                        <p>Thisspecies is listed as <bold>threatened</bold> under the<italic>Western Australian Wildlife Conservation Act 1950</italic>. It is a short-range endemic taxon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Harvey 2002b</xref>), with known populations threatened by fire, dieback disease (affecting coastal heathland vegetation), land-clearing and climate change.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">janineae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3E20D50E-50A2-4D59-A2CD-565E05D4554D</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zephyrarchaea_janineae</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Rix &amp; Harvey</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1C</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8I</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9F</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">21</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name><comment> sp. Main, 1995: 153.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Vernacular name">
                        <p>Karri Forest Assassin Spider</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Holotype male: Karri Valley, ‘Karri Valley Hideaway Cottages’, off Hopgarden Road, west of Pemberton, Western Australia, Australia, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°24'59"S, 115°50'52"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter in wet Marri and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> forest, 26–28.VIII.2006, M. Rix, J. Wojcieszek (WAM T89559).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <p>Paratypes: Allotype female, same data as holotype (WAM T118981).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined">
                        <title>Other material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>AUSTRALIA: <italic>Western Australia</italic>:</bold> <bold>Karri Valley:</bold> ‘Karri Valley Hideaway Cottages’, off Hopgarden Road, west of Pemberton, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°24'57"S, 115°50'50"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter in wet Marri and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> forest, 3.V.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 2 juveniles (WAM T89565<sup>DNA: KV-38-J/KV-39-J</sup>). <bold>Greater Hawke National Park:</bold> Gloucester Road, ~360 m off Pemberton-Northcliffe Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°21'01"S, 116°01'14"E</named-content>, sifting leaf litter and beating grass-trees in very wet area, 16.X.2009, D. &amp; S. Harms, 1 juvenile (WAM T114035<sup>DNA: GL-160-J</sup>). <bold>Dombakup State Forest:</bold> Marri Road, 15.I.1979, M. Gray, 4 juveniles (AMS KS15242). <bold>Leeuwin-Naturaliste National Park:</bold> near Cape Leeuwin, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°22'00"S, 115°09'16"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter in coastal <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> forest, 15.VII.2009, M. Rix, 2♂ (WAM T94476); same data except 16.IV.2009, 1♀, 5 juveniles (WAM T97464<sup>DNA: CL-163-J/CL-164-J/CL-165-J</sup>); Sugarloaf Road, near Cape Naturaliste, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">33°33'31"S, 115°01'18"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 30.III.2008, M. Rix, 1 juvenile (WAM T89561<sup>DNA: CN-32-J</sup>); Sugarloaf Road, near Cape Naturaliste, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">33°33'29"S, 115°01'25"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, 25.IV.2008, M. Rix, 2 juveniles (WAM T89562<sup>DNA: CN-33-J</sup>). <bold>Treen Brook State Forest:</bold> side road fire track off Vasse Highway, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°26'45"S, 115°59'00"E</named-content>, sifting leaf litter and teasing low shrubs, 14.X.2009, D. &amp; S. Harms, 1 juvenile (WAM T114036<sup>DNA: TB-161-J</sup>); 8 km W. of Pemberton, 13.II.1979, M. Gray, 2 juveniles (AMS KS15341). <bold>Wellington National Park:</bold> Lennard Drive, near turnoff to Rapids Picnic Ground, 33°23’59”S, 115°57’52”E, sifting elevated leaf litter, dense Jarrah forest with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> on slope leading to Collie River, 141 m, 18.IX.2010, S. &amp; D. Harms, 1♀ (WAM T112584<sup>DNA: CO-158-F</sup>); same data except 25.IX.2010, M. Rix, J. Wojcieszek, 1 juvenile (WAM T114034<sup>DNA: CO-159-J</sup>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific epithet is a patronym in honour of Dr Janine Wojcieszek, for helping to discover the first live specimens of this species in 2006, and therefore catalysing the Western Australian Museum’s ‘archaeid project’ in the half decade since 2007.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from other known congeners except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of six dorsal, hump-like tubercles on the abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11A–B</xref>); and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the more tapered, spiniform apex of tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11D–F</xref>).</p>
                        <p>This species can also be distinguished from other genotyped taxa (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) by the following three unique nucleotide substitutions for COI (n = 11): G(87), G(132), T(609).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype male</italic>: Total length 2.92; leg I femur 1.87; F1/CL ratio 1.76. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige, with reddish-brown dorsal scute and sclerites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11B</xref>). Carapace short (CH/CL ratio 1.60); 1.06 long, 1.71 high, 1.01 wide; ‘neck’ 0.59 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) near posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.65), carapace with pronounced concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ not strongly elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.22) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8I</xref>). Chelicerae with proximal tuft and additional comb of accessory setae on anterior face of paturon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11C</xref>). Abdomen 1.54 long, 1.08 wide; with three pairs of dorsal hump-like tubercles (HT 1–6); dorsal scute fused anteriorly to epigastric scle<!--PageBreak-->rites, extending posteriorly to first pair of hump-like tubercles; HT 3–6 each covered by separate dorsal sclerites. Unexpanded pedipalp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11D–F</xref>) pyriform, with broad, distally curved embolus supported by conductor sclerites 1–2; tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) porrect, slightly curved in prolateral view, with tapered, spiniform apex; TS 2–3 projecting beyond retro-distal rim of tegulum.</p>
                        <p><italic>Allotype female</italic>: Total length 4.10; leg I femur 1.97; F1/CL ratio 1.66. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11A</xref>). Carapace short (CH/CL ratio 1.70); 1.19 long, 2.03 high, 1.15 wide; ‘neck’ 0.69 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching posterior quarter of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.70), carapace with pronounced concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ moderately elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.26) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9F</xref>). Chelicerae without accessory setae on anterior face of paturon. Abdomen 2.62 long, 2.15 wide; with three pairs of dorsal hump-like tubercles (HT 1–6). Internal genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11G</xref>) with cluster of ≤ 15 sausage-shaped spermathecae either side of gonopore, clusters widely separated along midline of genital plate.</p>
                        <p><italic>Variation</italic>: Males (n = 3): total length 2.92–3.15; carapace length 1.03–1.10; carapace height 1.67–1.82; CH/CL ratio 1.60–1.66. Females (n = 3): total length 3.03–4.10; carapace length 1.14–1.19; carapace height 1.92–2.03; CH/CL ratio 1.69–1.70.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution and habitat.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known from the high rainfall province (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Hopper and Gioia 2004</xref>) of southern Western Australia, from the Leeuwin-Naturaliste and Wellington National Parks (near Bunbury) east to Pemberton (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">Fig. 21</xref>). It is the dominant assassin spider of the south-western Karri (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Eucalyptus diversicolor</tp:taxon-name></italic>) forest and surrounding areas, and has been collected by beating and sifting elevated leaf litter in wet forested habitats and in coastal groves of Peppermint (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Agonis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.). Six juvenile specimens first collected by M. Gray in 1979 in the Treen Brook and Dombakup State Forests near Pemberton (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Main 1995</xref>) almost certainly belong to this species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                        <title>Conservation status.</title>
                        <p>This specieshas a relatively widespread distribution in several National Parks and State Forests, and is not considered to be of conservation concern.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">marki</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:8EF9792F-4867-40B9-A409-2318A03E33E8</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zephyrarchaea_marki</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Rix &amp; Harvey</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1D</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8H</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">22</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Vernacular name">
                        <p>Cape Le Grand Assassin Spider</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Holotype male: Cape Le Grand National Park, Thistle Cove, Western Australia, Australia, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">33°59'55"S, 122°11'59"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Banksia speciosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> thicket behind beach, 5.VI.2010, M. Rix (WAM T118985).</p>
                        <p>Paratypes: 1 male and 1 juvenile, same data as holotype (WAM T114033<sup>DNA: CLG-146-J</sup>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined">
                        <title>Other material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>AUSTRALIA: <italic>Western Australia</italic>:</bold> <bold>Cape Le Grand National Park:</bold> Thistle Cove, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">33°59'54"S, 122°12'01"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter,<!--PageBreak--> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Banksia speciosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> thicket behind beach, 28.VII.2009, M. Rix, M. Wojcieszek, 3 juveniles (WAM T94477<sup>DNA: CLG-144-J/CLG-145-J</sup>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific epithet is a patronym in honour of Mark Wojcieszek, for helping to discover the first specimens of this species at Cape Le Grand National Park in 2009.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the absence of dorsal hump-like tubercles on the abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12A</xref>); from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the presence of a proximal tuft of accessory setae on the male chelicerae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12B</xref>); from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the shape of tegular sclerites 2–3, which project well beyond the retro-distal rim of the tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 12C–D</xref>); and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the larger, more protuberant proximal bulge on the male chelicerae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12B</xref>).</p>
                        <p>This species can also be distinguished from other genotyped taxa (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) by the following nine unique nucleotide substitutions for COI and COII (n = 3): A(147), T(204), C(300), C(306), G(495), C(804), G(807), G(1491), A(1548).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype male</italic>: Total length 2.77; leg I femur 2.00; F1/CL ratio 1.95. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige, with reddish-brown dorsal scute and sclerites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12A</xref>). Carapace short (CH/CL ratio 1.65); 1.03 long, 1.69 high, 1.00 wide; ‘neck’ 0.56 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.62), carapace with pronounced concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ not strongly elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.21) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8H</xref>). Chelicerae with proximal tuft and additional comb of accessory setae on anterior face of paturon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12B</xref>). Abdomen 1.64 long, 1.13 wide; almost spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like tubercles but with highly recumbent mound-like vestiges; dorsal scute fused anteriorly to epigastric sclerites, extending posteriorly to cover nearly anterior two-thirds of dorsal abdomen. Unexpanded pedipalp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 12C–E</xref>) pyriform, with broad, distally curved embolus supported by conductor sclerites 1–2; tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) porrect, strongly curved in prolateral view, with flattened, broadly rounded, paddle-shaped apex; TS 2–3 projecting beyond retro-distal rim of tegulum.</p>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>: Unknown.</p>
                        <p><italic>Variation</italic>: Males (n = 2): total length 2.77–2.79; carapace length 1.03 (invariable); carapace height 1.69 (invariable); CH/CL ratio 1.64–1.65.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution and habitat.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known only from Thistle Cove at Cape Le Grand National Park, on the far south-eastern coast of Western Australia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 22</xref>). Specimens have been collected by beating and sifting elevated leaf litter in a dense coastal thicket of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Banksia speciosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                        <title>Conservation status.</title>
                        <p>This species appears to be a rare short-range endemic taxon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Harvey 2002b</xref>), with the single known population in the Cape Le Grand National Park potentially threatened by fire, dieback disease (affecting <italic><tp:taxon-name>Banksia</tp:taxon-name></italic> heathland vegetation) and climate change.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">robinsi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zephyrarchaea_robinsi</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>(Harvey, 2002a)</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9G</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23">23</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name><comment> Harvey, 2002a: 35, figs 1–4.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Vernacular name">
                        <p>Eastern Massif Assassin Spider</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Holotype female: Stirling Range National Park, Ellen Peak, Western Australia, Australia, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°21'20"S, 118°19'45"E</named-content>, pitfall trap near summit, 28.V.1996, S. Barrett (WAM T42580).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined">
                        <title>Other material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>AUSTRALIA: <italic>Western Australia</italic>: Stirling Range National Park:</bold> Ellen Peak, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°21'30"S, 118°19'57"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepidosperma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sedges in montane heathland near summit, 1007 m, 6.XI.2007, M. Rix et al., 2 juveniles (WAM T89558<sup>DNA: EP-40-J/EP-41-J</sup>); south face of Pyungoorup Peak, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°21'54"S, 118°19'44"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepidosperma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sedges along shaded creek line near waterfall, 5.VIII.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey, 1 juvenile (moulted cuticle) (WAM T94090); Bluff Knoll, summit track, 800 m SW. of summit, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°22'49"S, 118°15'01"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepidosperma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sedges in montane heathland, 897 m, 20.VI.2010, M. Rix, J.D. Roberts, 1 juvenile (WAM T114032<sup>DNA: BK-149-J</sup>); Bluff Knoll, off summit track, 900 m SW. of summit, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°22'52"S, 118°15'00"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter in eucalypt grove near creek line, 877 m, 20.VI.2010, M. Rix, J.D. Roberts, 1 juvenile (WAM T114031<sup>DNA: BK-148-J</sup>); Bluff Knoll, off summit track, 400 m SW. of summit, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°22'34"S, 118°15'15"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepidosperma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sedges in montane heathland, 1065 m, 24.V.2011, M. Rix, M. Harvey, G. Binford, 1 juvenile (WAM T118987).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the absence of dorsal hump-like tubercles on the abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13A</xref>); from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the shallow post-ocular depression in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9G</xref>); and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the much shorter carapace (CH/CL ratio &lt; 1.70) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13A</xref>).</p>
                        <p>This species can also be distinguished from other genotyped taxa (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) by the following three unique nucleotide substitutions for COI and COII (n = 4): C(162), A(531), G(1442).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype female</italic>: Total length 3.69; leg I femur 1.97; F1/CL ratio 1.60. Cephalothorax reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen variably beige-grey (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13A</xref>). Carapace short (CH/CL ratio 1.60); 1.23 long, 1.97 high, 1.13 wide; ‘neck’ 0.74 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.61), carapace with shallow concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ not strongly elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.24) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9G</xref>). Chelicerae without accessory setae on anterior face of paturon. Abdomen 2.10 long, 1.78 wide; spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like tubercles. Internal genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 13B–D</xref>) with cluster of ≤ 15 sausage-shaped spermathecae either side of gonopore, clusters widely separated along midline of genital plate.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>: Unknown.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution and habitat.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known only from Ellen Peak, Bluff Knoll and the south face of Pyungoorup Peak, on the eastern massif of the Stirling Range National Park of southern Western Australia (east of Chester Pass) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23">Fig. 23</xref>). Specimens have been collected by beating and sifting sedges (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepidosperma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.) in montane heathland habitats and along mesic, shaded creek lines.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                        <title>Conservation status.</title>
                        <p>This species is a short-range endemic taxon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Harvey 2002b</xref>), with a maximum total range of less than 10 km<sup>2</sup>, and all known populations in the eastern Stirling Range National Park <bold>potentially threatened</bold> by fire, dieback disease (affecting montane vegetation) and climate change.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">melindae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:E42EAC7F-09B8-4441-85DD-4D84F44D923C</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zephyrarchaea_melindae</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Rix &amp; Harvey</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 8E</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9H</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">24</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Vernacular name">
                        <p>Toolbrunup Assassin Spider</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Holotype male: Stirling Range National Park, Mount Hassell, Western Australia, Australia, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°22'41"S, 118°04'15"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepidosperma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sedges near summit, 726 m, 22.IV.2009, M. Rix (WAM T118986).</p>
                        <p>Paratypes: Allotype female and 1 juvenile, Toolbrunup Peak, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°23'02"S, 118°02'55"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under low herbaceous shrubs near summit, 964 m, 10.IV.2009, M. Rix, H. Wood (WAM T97468<sup>DNA: TP-152-F/TP-153-J</sup>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined">
                        <title>Other material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>AUSTRALIA: <italic>Western Australia</italic>:</bold> <bold>Stirling Range National Park:</bold> same data as holotype, 2 juveniles (WAM T97467<sup>DNA: HA-150-J/HA-151-J</sup>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific epithet is a patronym in honour of Dr Melinda Moir, in recognition of her contributions to biodiversity research, especially in the Stirling Range National Park of southern Western Australia.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the absence of dorsal hump-like tubercles on the abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figs 14A–B</xref>); from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the shape of tegular sclerites 2–3, which do not project beyond the retro-distal rim of the tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figs 14D–E</xref>); and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the shape of the anterior margin of the diastema adjacent to the ‘neck’, which is straight (in females) or only slightly concave in lateral view (in males) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figs 14A–B</xref> cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 15A–B</xref>). Females further distinguished from other known congeners by the combination of a spherical abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14A</xref>), shallow post-ocular depression in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9H</xref>), taller carapace (CH/CL ratio &gt; 1.70) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14A</xref>) and straight, almost vertical anterior margin of the diastema adjacent to the ‘neck’ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14A</xref>).</p>
                        <p>This species can also be distinguished from other genotyped taxa (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) by the following three unique nucleotide substitutions for COI and COII (n = 4): G(165), G(924), T(1533).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype male</italic>: Total length 3.15; leg I femur 2.37; F1/CL ratio 2.01. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige, with reddish-brown dorsal scute and sclerites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14B</xref>). Carapace relatively short (CH/CL ratio 1.77); 1.18 long, 2.09 high, 1.18 wide; ‘neck’ 0.68 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.62), carapace with shallow concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ not strongly elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.20) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8E</xref>). Chelicerae with proximal brush and additional comb of accessory setae on anterior face of paturon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14C</xref>). Abdomen 1.64 long, 1.23 wide; almost spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like tubercles; dorsal scute fused anteriorly to epigastric sclerites, extending posteriorly to cover anterior two-thirds of dorsal abdomen. Unexpanded pedipalp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figs 14D–F</xref>) pyriform, with broad, distally curved embolus supported by conductor sclerites 1–2; tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) strongly curved, claw-like in prolateral view, with twisted, flattened and broadly rounded apex; TS 2–3 not projecting beyond retro-distal rim of tegulum.</p>
                        <p><italic>Allotype female</italic>: Total length 3.54; leg I femur 2.50; F1/CL ratio 1.93. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14A</xref>). Carapace relatively short (CH/CL ratio 1.86); 1.29 long, 2.41 high, 1.28 wide; ‘neck’ 0.78 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching middle of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.57), carapace with shallow concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ not strongly elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.19) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9H</xref>). Chelicerae without accessory setae on anterior face of paturon. Abdomen 1.95 long, 1.51 wide; spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like tubercles. Internal genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 14G</xref>) with cluster of ≤ 15 sausage-shaped spermathecae either side of gonopore, clusters widely separated along midline of genital plate.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution and habitat.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known only from the summits of Toolbrunup Peak and nearby Mount Hassell, in the western Stirling Range National Park of southern Western Australia (west of Chester Pass) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F24">Fig. 24</xref>). Specimens have been collected by beating and sifting sedges (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepidosperma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.) and low shrubs in montane heathland habitats.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                        <title>Conservation status.</title>
                        <p>This species is a short-range endemic taxon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Harvey 2002b</xref>), with a maximum total range of less than 10 km<sup>2</sup>, and all known populations in the western Stirling Range National Park potentially threatened by fire, dieback disease (affecting montane vegetation) and climate change.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">barrettae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D01825F1-C02A-45C9-96F3-0329CA4F1308</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zephyrarchaea_barrettae</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Rix &amp; Harvey</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1B</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8F</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9I</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F25">25</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Vernacular name">
                        <p>Talyuberlup Assassin Spider</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p><bold>AUSTRALIA:</bold> Holotype male: Stirling Range National Park, Talyuberlup Peak, Western Australia, Australia, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°24'21"S, 117°57'08"E</named-content>, sifting elevated<!--PageBreak--> leaf litter under <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepidosperma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sedges near summit, 4.VIII.2008, M. Rix, M. Harvey (WAM T117055<sup>DNA: TA-154-M</sup>).</p>
                        <p>Paratypes: Allotype female and 2 juveniles, same data as holotype except 8.II.2009, M. Harvey (WAM T97466<sup>DNA: TA-156-J/TA-157-J</sup>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined">
                        <title>Other material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>AUSTRALIA: <italic>Western Australia</italic>:</bold> <bold>Stirling Range National Park:</bold> same data as holotype, 1 juvenile (WAM T94089<sup>DNA: TA-155-J</sup>); Talyuberlup Peak, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°24'20"S, 117°57'06"E</named-content>, sifting elevated and low leaf litter, montane vegetation around rocky peak, 752 m, 12 April 2009, H. Wood, 1♂, 2♀ (CASENT 9028379); same data, 1♀ (CASENT 9034515).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific epithet is a patronym in honour of Sarah Barrett, for first discovering assassin spiders in the Stirling Range National Park in 1996.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the absence of dorsal hump-like tubercles on the abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 15A–B</xref>); from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the shape of tegular sclerites 2–3, which do not project beyond the retro-distal rim of the tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 15D–E</xref>); and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the shape of the anterior margin of the diastema adjacent to the ‘neck’, which is slightly (in females) or strongly concave in lateral view (in males) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 15A–B</xref> cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figs 14A–B</xref>). Females further distinguished from other known congeners by the combination of a spherical abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15A</xref>), shallow post-ocular depression in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9I</xref>), taller carapace (CH/CL ratio &gt; 1.70) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">15A</xref>) and slightly concave anterior margin of the diastema adjacent to the ‘neck’ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15A</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype male</italic>: Total length 3.13; leg I femur 2.19; F1/CL ratio 1.92. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige, with reddish-brown dorsal scute and sclerites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15B</xref>). Carapace relatively short (CH/CL ratio 1.71); 1.14 long, 1.95 high, 1.13 wide; ‘neck’ 0.67 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.59), carapace with shallow concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ not strongly elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.21) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8F</xref>). Chelicerae with proximal brush and additional comb of accessory setae on anterior face of paturon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15C</xref>). Abdomen 1.59 long, 1.21 wide; almost spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like tubercles; dorsal scute fused anteriorly to epigastric sclerites, extending posteriorly to cover anterior two-thirds of dorsal abdomen. Unexpanded pedipalp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 15D–F</xref>) pyriform, with broad, distally curved embolus supported by conductor sclerites 1–2; tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) strongly curved, claw-like in prolateral view, with twisted, flattened and broadly rounded apex; TS 2–3 not projecting beyond retro-distal rim of tegulum.</p>
                        <p><italic>Allotype female</italic>: Total length 3.64; leg I femur 2.31; F1/CL ratio 1.77. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen variably beige-grey (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15A</xref>). Carapace relatively short (CH/CL ratio 1.78); 1.31 long, 2.33 high, 1.26 wide; ‘neck’ 0.78 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.59), carapace with shallow concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ not strongly elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.22) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9I</xref>). Chelicerae without accessory setae on anterior face of paturon. Abdomen 1.90 long, 1.69 wide; spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like <!--PageBreak-->tubercles. Internal genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15G</xref>) with cluster of ≤ 15 sausage-shaped spermathecae either side of gonopore, clusters widely separated along midline of genital plate.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution and habitat.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known only from the summit of Talyuberlup Peak, in the western Stirling Range National Park of southern Western Australia (west of Chester Pass) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F25">Fig. 25</xref>). Specimens have been collected by beating and sifting sedges (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Lepidosperma</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.) in montane heathland.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                        <title>Conservation status.</title>
                        <p>This species is a short-range endemic taxon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Harvey 2002b</xref>), with a maximum total range of less than 10 km<sup>2</sup>, and all known populations in the western Stirling Range National Park potentially threatened by fire, dieback disease (affecting montane vegetation) and climate change.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. (unidentified juvenile specimens)</tp:taxon-status>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Note">
                        <title>Note.</title>
                        <p>In the absence of adult specimens or molecular data, the following juvenile specimens from Western Australia could not be confidently identified as a known species.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>AUSTRALIA: <italic>Western Australia</italic>:</bold> <bold>Stirling Range National Park:</bold> Talyuberlup Picnic Area, gully 400 m NW. of carpark, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">34°24'42"S, 117°57'12"E</named-content>, sifting grass patches within gully, 21.VI.2011, D. &amp; S. Harms, 4 juveniles (WAM T118991).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>These specimens are the first <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> to be collected from lowland habitats in the Stirling Range National Park, and the first members of the Western Australian High Rainfall Zone Clade (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) to be discovered in the Stirling Range. All four juveniles possess paired dorsal tubercles on the abdomen, clearly aligning them with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a known distribution that extends north to the Porongurup National Park (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Fig. 20</xref>), and it is possible that the Talyuberlup Picnic Area may represent a northern extension of this range. Adult specimens or sequence data are required to confirm the identification of this population.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="The Victorian fauna">
                <title>The Victorian fauna</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Archaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">hickmani</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Butler, 1929</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">nomen dubium</tp:taxon-status>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Archaea hickmani</tp:taxon-name><comment> Butler, 1929: 46, pl. 2, figs 1–5.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Archaea hickmanni</tp:taxon-name><comment> Butler: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Canals 1934</xref>: 5, fig. 3.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea hickmani</tp:taxon-name><comment> (Butler): Forster &amp; Platnick, 1984: 23, fig. 69 (figs 40–50 show an unrelated species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> from New South Wales; see below).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Holotype juvenile (not examined): no specific locality, Victoria, Australia, ~1922 (MV K097).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined">
                        <title>Other material examined. </title>
                        <p><bold>AUSTRALIA: <italic>Victoria</italic>:</bold> no specific locality, 1936, C. Oke, 1 juvenile (AMS KS97261).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Nomenclatural remarks">
                        <title>Nomenclatural remarks.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Archaea hickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> was first described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Butler (1929)</xref> from a juvenile specimen of unspecified providence, labelled and listed by Butler simply as “Victoria”. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Forster and Platnick (1984)</xref> examined this holotype, stating that it was in rather poor condition, and noting that a second adult female (labelled as a “homotype”) accompanied the specimen, the latter apparently collected after the original description in 1929. The genitalia of this adult female specimen were illustrated in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Forster and Platnick (1984</xref>, fig. 69), the specimen was briefly described, and the species was transferred to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Forster and Platnick (1984</xref>, figs 40–50) also presented scanning electron micrographs of a juvenile archaeid from near Sydney, erroneously regarded as being conspecific or very closely related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea hickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> based on the absence of setose tubercles on the carapace. However, this specimen is clearly a juvenile of an unrelated species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, as evidenced by the abdominal tubercles (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Forster and Platnick 1984</xref>, fig. 40) and New South Wales distribution. The Australian Museum collection also has an additional juvenile specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea hickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> collected by C. Oke in 1936, similarly labelled as being from “Victoria”.</p>
                        <p>Based on the three known Victorian specimens identified by Butler as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Archaea hickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic>, the species is clearly congeneric and probably even conspecific with one of the four new Victorian species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> described in this paper. Unfortunately, given the unspecified collection locality of all three specimens, and thus the inability to unequivocally link the single adult female to the holotype or the type locality, this species must be regarded as a nomen dubium.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">vichickmani</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:ADCE3562-8F83-49BE-BB5F-F794E7FECB41</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zephyrarchaea_vichickmani</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Rix &amp; Harvey</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1A</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8B</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">16</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F26">26</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Vernacular name">
                        <p>Central Highlands Assassin Spider</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Holotype male: Yarra Ranges National Park, Acheron Gap, Victoria, Australia, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">37°40'37"S, 145°44'24"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under tree ferns, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nothofagus</tp:taxon-name></italic> rainforest, 769 m, 29.III.2010, M. Rix (MV K11578).</p>
                        <p>Paratypes: Allotype female, same data as holotype (MV K11579); 1 female and 6 juveniles, same data as holotype (WAM T112583<sup>DNA: Ar14–49-F/Ar14–133-J/Ar14–134-J</sup>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined">
                        <title>Other material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>AUSTRALIA: <italic>Victoria</italic>:</bold> <bold>Yarra Ranges National Park:</bold> Acheron Gap, Central Highlands, 6 km NE. of Mount Donna Buang, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">37°40'43"S, 145°44'20"E</named-content>, pitfall trap, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nothofagus cunninghamii</tp:taxon-name></italic> forest, 25.VI.–29.VIII.1996, G. Milledge, 1♀ (MV K5919); same data except 21.II.–23.IV.1996, 1 juvenile (MV K5920).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific epithet is a patronym in honour of the late Professor Victor Hickman, for his extraordinary contributions to arachnology and in honour of L. S. Butler’s original (1929) patronym.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from other known congeners except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the absence of a proximal tuft or brush on the male chelicerae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16C</xref>); and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the less sinuous shape of conductor sclerite 2 (C2) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 16D–E</xref>) and the more concave anterior margin of the male diastema adjacent to the ‘neck’ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16B</xref>). Females further distinguished from other known congeners except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the combination of a spherical abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16A</xref>), strongly concave post-ocular depression in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A</xref>), and moderately elevated ‘head’ dorsally (post-ocular ratio ≥ 0.25) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A</xref>).</p>
                        <p>This species can also be distinguished from other genotyped taxa (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) by the following 16 unique nucleotide substitutions for COI and COII (n = 3): C(24), G(54), G(216), G(309), A(360), A(393), C(702), G(795), T(951), A(976), A(1059), T(1063), A(1200), G(1281), C(1479), T(1596), and can be further distinguished from all other Australian <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the absence of a COII amino acid residue at positions 1441–1443.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype male</italic>: Total length 2.77; leg I femur 1.80; F1/CL ratio 1.67. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige, with reddish-brown dorsal scute and sclerites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16B</xref>). Carapace relatively short (CH/CL ratio 1.69); 1.08 long, 1.82 high, 1.01 wide; ‘neck’ 0.59 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) near posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.64), carapace with pronounced concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ moderately elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.28) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8B</xref>). Chelicerae with short comb of accessory setae on anterior face of paturon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16C</xref>). Abdomen 1.59 long, 1.10 wide; almost spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like tubercles; dorsal scute fused anteriorly to epigastric sclerites, extending posteriorly to cover anterior two-thirds of dorsal abdomen. Unexpanded pedipalp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 16D–F</xref>) bulbous, almost spherical, with gently curved, tapering embolus supported by conductor sclerites 1–2; tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) strongly curved, claw-like in prolateral view, with twisted, flattened and rounded apex; TS 2–3 projecting well beyond retro-distal rim of tegulum.</p>
                        <p><italic>Allotype female</italic>: Total length 3.90; leg I femur 2.08; F1/CL ratio 1.76. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16A</xref>). Carapace relatively short (CH/CL ratio 1.83); 1.18 long, 2.15 high, 1.12 wide; ‘neck’ 0.69 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.61), carapace with pronounced concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ moderately elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.26) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A</xref>). Chelicerae without accessory setae on anterior face of paturon. Abdomen 2.51 long, 1.92 wide; spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like tubercles. Internal genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16G</xref>) with cluster of ≤ 15 sausage-shaped spermathecae fanning out either side of gonopore, clusters widely separated along midline of genital plate; outermost (posterior) spermatheca on each side stalked, distally spherical.</p>
                        <p><italic>Variation</italic>: Females (n = 3): total length 3.44–3.90; carapace length 1.14–1.18; carapace height 2.00–2.15; CH/CL ratio 1.75–1.83.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution and habitat.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known only from temperate <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nothofagus</tp:taxon-name></italic> rainforest habitats in the Victorian Central Highlands, north-east of Melbourne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F26">Fig. 26</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                        <title>Conservation status.</title>
                        <p>This species has an imperfectly known distribution, and although potentially restricted, the abundance of protected forested habitats near the type locality would suggest that the species is unlikely to be of conservation concern.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">marae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:010F55AE-B08E-4725-8781-5157D69EDCBA</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zephyrarchaea_marae</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Rix &amp; Harvey</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4D</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C–D, 5F–G</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B, 6E</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A, 8C</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9B</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">17</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F27">27</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Vernacular name">
                        <p>West Gippsland Assassin Spider</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Holotype male: Tarra-Bulga National Park, Tarra Valley, near Tarra Valley Picnic Area, Victoria, Australia, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">38°26'51"S, 146°32'17"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under tree ferns, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nothofagus</tp:taxon-name></italic> rainforest, 368 m, 1.IV.2010, M. Rix, D. Harms (MV K11580<sup>DNA: Ar18–138-M</sup>).</p>
                        <p>Paratypes: Allotype female, Gunyah Rainforest State Reserve, Toorah Road, 2 km SSW. of Gunyah, Victoria, Australia, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">38°32'30"S, 146°19'00"E</named-content>, pitfall trap, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nothofagus cunninghamii</tp:taxon-name></italic> forest, 14.IX.–14.XI.1995, G. Milledge (MV K5921); 1 male, same data except 5.III.–7.V.1996 (MV K5923).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined">
                        <title>Other material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>AUSTRALIA: <italic>Victoria</italic>:</bold> <bold>Tarra-Bulga National Park:</bold> same data as holotype, 3 juveniles (WAM T114025<sup>DNA: Ar18–139-J/Ar18–140-J</sup>); 0.2 km W. of Tarra Valley Picnic Area, 38°27'S, 146°32'E, pitfall trap, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nothofagus cunninghamii</tp:taxon-name></italic> forest, 14.XI.1995 – 10.I.1996, G. Milledge, 1 juvenile (MV K5922). <bold>Dandenong Ranges National Park:</bold> Sherbrooke Forest, near start of Welch Track, off Nation Road, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">37°54'24"S, 145°22'10"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under tree ferns, wet Mountain Ash/tree fern forest, 28.III.2010, M. Rix, D. Harms, 1♀, 2 juveniles (WAM T114024<sup>DNA: Ar13–135-F/Ar13–136-J/Ar13–137-J</sup>). <bold>Mount Worth State Park:</bold> Giants Circuit from Moonlight Creek Picnic Area, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">38°16'54"S, 146°00'35"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter under tree fern, complex eucalypt/tree fern forest with thick understorey, 400 m, 31.III.2010, M. Rix, D. Harms, 1 juvenile (WAM T114026<sup>DNA: Ar16–141-J</sup>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific epithet is a patronym in honour of Dr Māra Blosfelds, in recognition of her love for small spiders and the Australian forests.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from other known congeners except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the absence of a proximal tuft or brush on the male chelicerae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17C</xref>); and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the more sinuous, slender, S-shaped conductor sclerite 2 (C2) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 17D–E</xref>) and the less concave, slightly convex anterior margin of the male diastema adjacent to the ‘neck’ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17B</xref>). Females further distinguished from other known congeners except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the combination of a spherical abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17A</xref>), strongly concave post-ocular depression in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9B</xref>), and moderately elevated ‘head’ dorsally (post-ocular ratio ≥ 0.25) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9B</xref>).</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak-->This species can also be distinguished from other genotyped taxa (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) by the following 12 unique nucleotide substitutions for COI and COII (n = 7): G(69), G(345), G(552), G(762), G(786), A(1026), G(1059), T(1263), G(1341), G(1512), C(1584), C(1587), and can be further distinguished from all other Australian <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the absence of a COII amino acid residue at positions 1441–1443.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype male</italic>: Total length 3.03; leg I femur 1.99; F1/CL ratio 1.80. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige, with reddish-brown dorsal scute and sclerites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17B</xref>). Carapace relatively short (CH/CL ratio 1.70); 1.10 long, 1.87 high, 1.08 wide; ‘neck’ 0.61 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) near posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.66), carapace with pronounced concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ moderately elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.25) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 8A, 8C</xref>). Chelicerae with short comb of accessory setae on anterior face of paturon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17C</xref>). Abdomen 1.64 long, 1.31 wide; almost spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like tubercles; dorsal scute fused anteriorly to epigastric sclerites, extending posteriorly to cover anterior two-thirds of dorsal abdomen. Unexpanded pedipalp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 17D–F</xref>) bulbous, almost spherical, with gently curved, tapering embolus supported by conductor sclerites 1–2 (C1–2); C2 relatively slender, sinuous, with S-shaped proximal portion; tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) strongly curved, claw-like in prolateral view, with twisted, flattened and rounded apex; TS 2–3 projecting well beyond retro-distal rim of tegulum.</p>
                        <p><italic>Allotype female</italic>: Total length 3.95; leg I femur 2.10; F1/CL ratio 1.76. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown (with paler, partially encrusted material on ‘neck’); legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen variably beige-grey (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17A</xref>). Carapace relatively short (CH/CL ratio 1.86); 1.19 long, 2.22 high, 1.17 wide; ‘neck’ 0.72 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.62), carapace with pronounced concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ moderately elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.26) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9B</xref>). Chelicerae without accessory setae on anterior face of paturon. Abdomen 2.31 long, 1.90 wide; spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like tubercles. Internal genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17G</xref>) with cluster of ≤ 15 sausage-shaped spermathecae fanning out either side of gonopore, clusters widely separated along midline of genital plate.</p>
                        <p><italic>Variation</italic>: Males (n = 2): total length 3.03–3.23; carapace length 1.09–1.10; carapace height 1.85–1.87; CH/CL ratio 1.69–1.70. Females (n = 2): total length 3.74–3.95; carapace length 1.18–1.19; carapace height 2.09–2.22; CH/CL ratio 1.77–1.86.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution and habitat.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known only from temperate rainforest and mesic closed forest habitats in the Dandenong and Strzelecki Ranges of West Gippsland, east and south-east of Melbourne, Victoria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F27">Fig. 27</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                        <title>Conservation status.</title>
                        <p>This specieshas a relatively widespread distribution in several National Parks and State Forests, and is not considered to be of conservation concern.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">porchi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3005E6AB-024D-4559-BAE7-78E3D47CE5E0</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zephyrarchaea_porchi</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Rix &amp; Harvey</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 8D</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">18</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F28">28</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Vernacular name">
                        <p>Otway Range Assassin Spider</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Holotype male: Bimbi Park, 2.2 km N. of Cape Otway Lighthouse, Victoria, Australia, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">38°50'13"S, 143°30'55"E</named-content>, dry pitfall trap, grassy edge of bracken-rich dry sclerophyll forest, 2–5.XI.2011, N. Porch &amp; Deakin University Wildlife Field Studies students (MV K11581).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific epithet is a patronym in honour of Dr Nicholas Porch, for first discovering this species in the Otway Range.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and  <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the absence of dorsal hump-like tubercles on the abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 18A</xref>); from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the presence of a proximal tuft of accessory setae on the male chelicerae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 18B</xref>); from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the shape of tegular sclerites 2–3, which project well beyond the retro-distal rim of the tegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 18C–D</xref>); and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the smaller, less protuberant proximal bulge on the male chelicerae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 18B</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype male</italic>: Total length 2.77; leg I femur 1.97; F1/CL ratio 1.86. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige, with reddish-brown dorsal scute and sclerites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 18A</xref>). Carapace relatively short (CH/CL ratio 1.70); 1.06 long, 1.81 high, 1.00 wide; ‘neck’ 0.58 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) near posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.69), carapace with pronounced concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ moderately elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.27) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8D</xref>). Chelicerae with proximal tuft and additional comb of accessory setae on anterior face of paturon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 18B</xref>). Abdomen 1.59 long, 1.08 wide; almost spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like tubercles; dorsal scute fused anteriorly to epigastric sclerites, extending posteriorly to cover anterior two-thirds of dorsal abdomen. Partially expanded pedipalp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 18C–E</xref>) bulbous-pyriform, with gently curved, tapering embolus adjacent to conductor sclerites 1–2; tegular sclerite 1 (TS 1) porrect, slightly curved in prolateral view, with flattened, rounded apex; TS 2–3 projecting well beyond retro-distal rim of tegulum.</p>
                        <p><italic>Female</italic>: Unknown.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution and habitat.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known only from north of Cape Otway, in the Otway Range of southern Victoria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F28">Fig. 28</xref>). The single known specimen was collected in a dry vertebrate pitfall trap in eucalypt forest with a dense bracken fern understorey.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                        <title>Conservation status.</title>
                        <p>This species has an imperfectly known distribution, and although potentially restricted, the abundance of protected forested habitats near the type locality would suggest that the species is unlikely to be of conservation concern.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">grayi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B449FA7D-B159-42D5-8F8F-74639C04575E</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zephyrarchaea_grayi</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Rix &amp; Harvey</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9C</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">19A–B</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F29">29</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Vernacular name">
                        <p>Grampians Assassin Spider</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Holotype female: Grampians National Park, Delley’s Dell, Silverband Road, Victoria, Australia, sweeping at night, 26.III.1974, M. Gray (AMS KS109448).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific epithet is a patronym in honour of Dr Mike Gray, for his contributions to arachnology and for first discovering this species in the Grampians National Park.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the absence of dorsal hump-like tubercles on the abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19A</xref>); from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the strongly concave post-ocular depression in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9C</xref>); from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. by the larger body size (carapace length &gt; 1.10) and taller carapace (CH/CL ratio ≥ 1.70) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">19A</xref>); and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the shape of the ‘head’, which is less elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio &lt; 0.25) and with the highest point of the pars cephalica (HPC) closer to the middle of the head (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length &lt; 0.60) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9C</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype female</italic>: Total length 3.36; leg I femur 1.95; F1/CL ratio 1.73. Cephalothorax dark reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19A</xref>). Carapace relatively short (CH/CL ratio 1.72); 1.13 long, 1.94 high, 1.03 wide; ‘neck’ 0.63 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) approaching middle of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.57), carapace with pronounced concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ not strongly elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.23) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9C</xref>). Chelicerae without accessory setae on anterior face of paturon. Abdomen 1.85 long, 1.36 wide; spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like tubercles. Internal genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19B</xref>) with cluster of ≤ 15 sausage-shaped spermathecae fanning out either side of gonopore, clusters widely separated along midline of genital plate; outermost (posterior) spermathecae bulbous distally.</p>
                        <p><italic>Male</italic>: Unknown.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution and habitat.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known only from wet eucalypt forest at Delley’s Dell, in the Grampians National Park of western Victoria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F29">Fig. 29</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                        <title>Conservation status.</title>
                        <p>This species appears to be a rare short-range endemic taxon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Harvey 2002b</xref>), with the single known population in the Grampians National Park potentially threatened by fire and climate change. Targeted searching at the type locality in March 2010 failed to reveal new specimens of this species, and the site had been recently burnt.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="The South Australian fauna">
                <title>The South Australian fauna</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">austini</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9571EBAF-A9E3-4053-9549-D36E06806DBE</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Zephyrarchaea_austini</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Rix &amp; Harvey</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9D</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">19C-D</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F30">30</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Vernacular name">
                        <p>Kangaroo Island Assassin Spider</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material">
                        <title>Type material.</title>
                        <p>Holotype female: Kangaroo Island, Western River Wilderness Protection Area, Waterfall Creek walking trail, near waterfall, South Australia, Australia, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">35°41'44"S, 136°54'37"E</named-content>, sifting elevated leaf litter, open eucalypt woodland with complex understorey of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Xanthorrhoea</tp:taxon-name></italic> and low shrubs, 9-10.V.2010, M. Rix, D. Harms (SAM NN28000<sup>DNA:</sup> <sup>Ar77-50-F</sup>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined">
                        <title>Other material examined.</title>
                        <p><bold>AUSTRALIA: <italic>South Australia</italic>:</bold> <bold>Western River Wilderness Protection Area:</bold> same data as holotype, 3 juveniles (WAM T114027<sup>DNA: Ar77-142-J/Ar77-143-J</sup>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific epithet is a patronym in honour of Professor Andy Austin, in recognition of his contributions to biodiversity research.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the absence of dorsal hump-like tubercles on the abdomen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19C</xref>); from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the strongly concave post-ocular depression in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9D</xref>); and from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the smaller body size (carapace length &lt; 1.10) and shorter carapace (CH/CL ratio &lt; 1.70) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">19C</xref>).</p>
                        <p>This species can also be distinguished from other genotyped taxa (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) by the following 45 unique nucleotide substitutions for COI and COII (n = 3): T(42), A(45), C(130), T(132), G(222), A(243), G(291), A(354), G(360), T(372), A(453), A(504), G(567), G(648), A(690), A(702), C(717), C(721), G(756), C(852), A(858), A(891), G(901), A(910), G(962), C(971), G(1050), G(1165), G(1197), A(1198), T(1233), G(1234), C(1235), T(1236), G(1317), A(1374), A(1403), T(1404), G(1416), G(1418), A(1419), A(1449), T(1530), G(1574), G(1585).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><italic>Holotype female</italic>: Total length 2.77; leg I femur 1.80; F1/CL ratio 1.80. Cephalothorax pale reddish-brown; legs tan brown with darker annulations; abdomen mottled grey-brown and beige (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19C</xref>). Carapace short (CH/CL ratio 1.58); 1.00 long, 1.58 high, 0.92 wide; ‘neck’ 0.55 wide; highest point of pars cephalica (HPC) near posterior third of ‘head’ (ratio of HPC to post-ocular length 0.67), carapace with pronounced concave depression anterior to HPC; ‘head’ not strongly elevated dorsally (post-ocular ratio 0.23) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9D</xref>). Chelicerae without accessory setae on anterior face of paturon. Abdomen 1.49 long, 1.13 wide; almost spherical in lateral profile, without dorsal hump-like tubercles. Internal genitalia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19D</xref>) with cluster of ≤ 15 sausage-shaped spermathecae fanning out either side of gonopore, clusters widely separated along midline of genital plate.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak--><italic>Male</italic>: Unknown.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution and habitat.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known only from eucalypt woodland and associated heathland habitats near ‘Billy Goat Falls’, in the Western River Wilderness Protection Area of Kangaroo Island, South Australia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F30">Fig. 30</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Conservation status">
                        <title>Conservation status.</title>
                        <p>This species appears to be a rare short-range endemic taxon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Harvey 2002b</xref>), with the single known population on Kangaroo Island potentially threatened by fire, dieback disease (affecting heathland vegetation) and climate change.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>This research was made possible by an Australian Biological Resources Study (ABRS) taxonomy research grant to M. Harvey and M. Rix (Grant No. 209-09), with critical initial support provided by Roy Teale (Biota Environmental Sciences) and significant additional funding provided by Cliffs Natural Resources and Verve Energy. Specimens of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> were loaned by various curators, and the authors would like to especially thank Peter Lillywhite (Museum Victoria), Graham Milledge (Australian Museum) and Leslie Chisholm (South Australian Museum) for their curatorial assistance throughout this study. Numerous friends, family and colleagues assisted in the collection of assassin spiders in the field, including Greta Binford, Sarah Comer, Alan Danks, Volker Framenau, Danilo Harms, Stephanie Harms, Lara Lopardo, Melinda Moir, Janet Newell, Ricardo Ott, Dale Roberts, Beverley Roberts, Roy Teale, Janine Wojcieszek and Hannah Wood. Thanks also to Nicholas Porch and the Deakin University Wildlife Field Studies students for first discovering archaeids in the Otway Range and making the holotype specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> available to MGR prior to the completion of this revision. Specimens were collected under permit throughout Victoria (Permit No. 10005193), South Australia (Permit No. W25803) and Western Australia (Permit Nos. SF005357, SF005814, SF006247, SF006821). Finally, thanks to Hannah Wood and Charles Griswold for providing data on Australian specimens housed at the California Academy of Sciences (CAS), and for assisting MGR and MSH during their visit to the CAS in 2011.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1956</year>)<source> Composition of Scientific Words: A Manual of Methods and a Lexicon of Materials for the Practice of Logotechnics.</source> <publisher-name>Smithsonian Books</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc>, <lpage>882</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>LSG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1929</year>)<article-title> Studies in Australian spiders, No. 1.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria </source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Canals</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1934</year>)<source> Estudios aracnologicos. IV. Las arañas de la familia Archaeidae y su distribucion geografica actual. Buenos Aires, 8 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crisp</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<source> Need morphology always be required for new species descriptions? Invertebrate Systematics 24: 322–326. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/IS10011" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/IS10011</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunlop</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penney</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jekel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> A summary list of fossil spiders and their relatives. In: Platnick NI (Ed) The World Spider Catalog, Version 12.5. American Museum of Natural History, New York. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://research.amnh.org/iz/spiders/catalog/Fossils_12.5.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://research.amnh.org/iz/spiders/catalog/Fossils_12.5.pdf</ext-link> [accessed 29.II.2012]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<source> The Effect of Fire Induced Successional Changes on Invertebrate Populations in Western Australian Coastal Heathland. Unpublished (draft) preliminary report for the National Parks Authority, 12 pp.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1956</year>)<article-title> A new spider of the genus <italic>Archaea</italic> from Australia.</article-title> <source>Memoirs of the Queensland Museum </source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> A review of the archaeid spiders and their relatives, with notes on the limits of the superfamily Palpimanoidea (Arachnida, Araneae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History </source> <volume>178</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002a</year>)<article-title> A new species of <italic>Austrarchaea</italic> (Araneae: Archaeidae) from Western Australia.</article-title> <source>Records of the Western Australian Museum </source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002b</year>)<article-title> Short-range endemism among the Australian fauna: some examples from non-marine environments.</article-title> <source>Invertebrate Systematics </source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>-<lpage>570</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/IS02009" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/IS02009</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edward</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Molecular and morphological systematics of hypogean schizomids (Schizomida: Hubbardiidae) in semiarid Australia.</article-title> <source>Invertebrate Systematics </source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>194</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/IS07026" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/IS07026</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rix</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Framenau</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teale</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Protecting the innocent: studying short-range endemic taxa enhances conservation outcomes.</article-title> <source>Invertebrate Systematics </source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/IS11011" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/IS11011</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gioia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> The Southwest Australian Floristic Region: evolution and conservation of a global hot spot of biodiversity.</article-title> <source>Annual Review of Ecology, Evolution and Systematics </source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>623</fpage>-<lpage>650</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.35.112202.130201" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.35.112202.130201</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berendt</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1854</year>)<source> Die im Bernstein befindlichen Crustaceen, Myriapoden, Arachniden und Apteren der Vorweld. In: Berendt GC (Ed) Die im Bernstein befindlichen Organischen Reste der Vorweld, Berlin, 1–124.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lotz</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> Afrotropical Archaeidae (Araneae): 1. New species of <italic>Afrarchaea</italic> with notes on <italic>Afrarchaea godfreyi</italic> (Hewitt, 1919).</article-title> <source>Navorsinge van die Nasionale Museum, Bloemfontein </source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>-<lpage>160</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lotz</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Afrotropical Archaeidae: 2. New species of the genera <italic>Archaea</italic> and <italic>Afrarchaea</italic> (Arachnida: Araneae).</article-title> <source>Navorsinge van die Nasionale Museum, Bloemfontein </source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>240</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lotz</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Afrotropical Archaeidae: 3. The female of <italic>Eriauchenius cornutus</italic> and new species of <italic>Afrarchaea</italic> (Arachnida: Araneae) from South Africa.</article-title> <source>Navorsinge van die Nasionale Museum, Bloemfontein </source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>-<lpage>127</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Main</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987a</year>)<article-title> Persistence of invertebrates in small areas: case studies of trapdoor spiders in Western Australia.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burbidge</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Nature Conservation: The Role of Remnants of Native Vegetation.</issue-title> <source>Surrey Beatty &amp; Sons, Chipping Norton, N.S.W. in association with CSIRO Division of Wildlife &amp; Rangelands Research and W.A. Department of Conservation &amp; Land Management, W.A. Wildlife Research Centre</source>: <fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Main</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987b</year>)<article-title> Ecological disturbance and conservation of spiders: implications for geographic relics in southwestern Australia.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Majer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>The Role of Invertebrates in Conservation and Biological Survey.</issue-title> <source>Western Australian Department of Conservation and Land Management Report, Perth</source>: <fpage>89</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Main</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> Additional records of the Gondwanan spider <italic>Austrarchaea</italic> from southwestern Australia.</article-title> <source>Western Australian Naturalist </source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991a</year>)<article-title> On Malagasy <italic>Archaea</italic> (Araneae, Archaeidae).</article-title> <source>Journal of African Zoology </source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>-<lpage>140</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991b</year>)<article-title> On Western Australian <italic>Austrarchaea</italic> (Araneae, Archaeidae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British Arachnological Society </source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>-<lpage>261</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> The World Spider Catalog, Version 12.5. American Museum of Natural History, New York. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://research.amnh.org/entomology/spiders/catalog/" xlink:type="simple">http://research.amnh.org/entomology/spiders/catalog/</ext-link> [accessed 20.II.2012]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rix</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Australian Assassins, Part I: a review of the assassin spiders (Araneae, Archaeidae) of mid-eastern Australia.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys </source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>100</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.123.1448" xlink:type="simple">10.3897/zookeys.123.1448</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rix</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny and historical biogeography of ancient assassin spiders (Araneae: Archaeidae) in the Australian mesic zone: evidence for Miocene speciation within Tertiary refugia.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution </source> <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>-<lpage>396</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2011.10.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ympev.2011.10.009</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schütt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<source> The limits and phylogeny of the Araneoidea (Arachnida, Araneae). PhD thesis, Berlin, Germany: Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> A revision of the assassin spiders of the <italic>Eriauchenius</italic> gracilicollis group, a clade of spiders endemic to Madagascar (Araneae: Archaeidae).</article-title> <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society </source> <volume>152</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>296</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.2007.00359.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1096-3642.2007.00359.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griswold</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spicer</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Phylogenetic relationships within an endemic group of Malagasy ‘assassin spiders’ (Araneae, Archaeidae): ancestral character reconstruction, convergent evolution and biogeography.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution  </source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>612</fpage>-<lpage>619</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2007.07.012" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.ympev.2007.07.012</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
        <sec sec-type="Figures">
            <title>Figures</title>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Habitus images of live <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> from southern Australia: <bold>A</bold> paratype female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. from Acheron Gap, Central Highlands, Victoria; <bold>B</bold> holotype male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. from Talyuberlup Peak, Stirling Range National Park, Western Australia; <bold>C</bold> paratype female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. from Karri Valley, Western Australia; <bold>D</bold> male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. from Thistle Cove, Cape Le Grand National Park, Western Australia; <bold>E</bold> female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Platnick) from William Bay National Park, Western Australia; <bold>F</bold> female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Bremer Bay, Western Australia. </p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 2.</label>
                <caption><p>Map showing the known distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in Australia, with locality records for species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted in black. Note the disjunct distribution of the genus in south-eastern and south-western mainland Australia.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 3.</label>
                <caption><p>Phylogeny of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> species from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Rix and Harvey (2012)</xref>, showing results from a combined, gene-partitioned Bayesian analysis of that study’s multi-gene dataset (2591 bp: COI, COII, tRNA-K, tRNA-D, ATP8, ATP6, H3). Clades with &gt;95% posterior probability support are denoted by thickened branches, with lower individual clade support values shown above nodes. Note the presence of three main regional clades, each illustrated with an exemplar species (highlighted*). The Victorian species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. were not able to be sequenced for this study (shown as black dots on inset map).</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 4.</label>
                <caption><p>Diagnostic characters of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> Forster &amp; Platnick. <bold>A–B</bold>, Cephalothorax, lateral view, showing differences in carapace height and the position of accessory setae on male chelicerae: <bold>A</bold>, male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea harmsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Rix &amp; Harvey; <bold>B</bold>, male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>C–D</bold>, Expanded male pedipalps, retro-ventral view, showing differences in the articulation and fusion of the conductor sclerites: <bold>C</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea helenae</tp:taxon-name></italic> Rix &amp; Harvey; <bold>D</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. bH = basal haematodocha; C = conductor; C1–2 = conductor sclerites 1–2; Cy = cymbium; E = embolus; Es = embolic sclerite; H = distal haematodocha; T = tegulum; (TS)1–3 = tegular sclerites 1–3. Scale bars: C–D = 0.2 mm.&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 5.</label>
                <caption><p>Carapace morphology of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. <bold>A–B</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Platnick): <bold>A</bold>, male pars cephalica, dorso-lateral view, showing accessory setae (AS) on and adjacent to proximal cheliceral bulge; <bold>B</bold>, female pars cephalica, antero-lateral view, showing cheliceral foramen (CF) and ocular bulge (OB). <bold>C–D</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.: <bold>C</bold>, male cephalothorax, antero-lateral view; <bold>D</bold>, male pars cephalica and chelicerae, frontal view, showing dorsal ‘head’ region and cheliceral foramen (CF). <bold>E</bold>, Cheliceraeof male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, lateral view, showing proximal accessory setae (AS) and ectal stridulatory file (SF). <bold>F–G</bold>, Detail of carapace of male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, lateral view, showing granulate cuticle and setose tubercles (sT).&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 6.</label>
                <caption><p>Abdominal morphology of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. <bold>A–B</bold>, Male abdomens, dorso-lateral view, showing dorsal scutes (S) and additional dorsal sclerites (ds) on hump-like tubercles: <bold>A</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Platnick); <bold>B</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>C</bold>, Female epigastric region of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ventral view, showing setose book lung covers (BL) and median genital plate (GP). <bold>D</bold>, Male epigastric region of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ventral view, showing fusion of epigastric sclerites. <bold>E</bold>, Abdominal cuticle of male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, lateral view, showing sclerotic spots (ss) surrounded by short setae. <bold>F</bold>, Spinnerets of female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, posterior view (ventral side uppermost), showing anterior lateral (ALS) and posterior lateral (PLS) spinnerets anterior to anal tubercle (AT), and the absence of a colulus.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 7.</label>
                <caption><p>Graphs depicting the relationship between carapace length (CL) and carapace height (CH) for species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Smaller grey dots denote species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Austrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Rix and Harvey 2011</xref>); boxes denote the three lineages of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Victoria/South Australia, the Stirling Range and elsewhere in southern Western Australia.&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 8.</label>
                <caption><p>Lateral ‘head’ profiles of males of species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, showing variation in carapace shape as quantified by the post-ocular ratio (P.O. Ratio) and ratio of highest point of carapace relative to post-ocular length (HPC Ratio): <bold>A</bold>, holotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., showing the derivation of morphometric ratios; <bold>B</bold>, holotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <bold>C</bold>, holotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <bold>D</bold>, holotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <bold>E</bold>, holotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <bold>F</bold>, holotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <bold>G</bold>, holotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Platnick, 1991b); <bold>H</bold>, holotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <bold>I</bold>, holotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 9.</label>
                <caption><p>Lateral ‘head’ profiles of females of species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, showing variation in carapace shape as quantified by the post-ocular ratio (P.O. Ratio) and ratio of highest point of carapace relative to post-ocular length (HPC Ratio) (see Fig. 8): <bold>A</bold>, allotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <bold>B</bold>, allotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <bold>C</bold>, holotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <bold>D</bold>, holotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <bold>E</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Platnick, 1991b); <bold>F</bold>, allotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <bold>G</bold>, holotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Harvey, 2002a); <bold>H</bold>, allotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.; <bold>I</bold>, allotype <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 10.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Platnick, 1991b). <bold>A–B</bold>, Cephalothorax and abdomen, lateral view: <bold>A</bold>, female (WAM T118983) from Mutton Bird Point, Western Australia; <bold>B</bold>, holotype male (WAM T17683) from Torndirrup National Park, Western Australia. <bold>C</bold>, Holotype male chelicerae, lateral view, showing accessory setae. <bold>D–F</bold>, Male (WAM T89569) pedipalp: <bold>D–E</bold>, bulb, retrolateral view; <bold>F</bold>, detail of distal tegular sclerites, prolateral view. <bold>G</bold>, Female (WAM T118983) internal genitalia, dorsal view. C1–2 = conductor sclerites 1–2; E = embolus; GP = genital plate; T = tegulum; (TS)1–3 = tegular sclerites 1–3. Scale bars: A–B = 1.0 mm; E = 0.2 mm.&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 11.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A–B</bold>, Cephalothorax and abdomen, lateral view: <bold>A</bold>, allotype female (WAM T118981) from Karri Valley, Western Australia; <bold>B</bold>, holotype male (WAM T89559) from Karri Valley, Western Australia. <bold>C</bold>, Holotype male chelicerae, lateral view, showing accessory setae. <bold>D–F</bold>, Holotype male pedipalp: <bold>D–E</bold>, bulb, retrolateral view; <bold>F</bold>, detail of distal tegular sclerites, prolateral view. <bold>G</bold>, Allotype female internal genitalia, dorsal view. C1–2 = conductor sclerites 1–2; E = embolus;  GP = genital plate; T = tegulum; (TS)1–3 = tegular sclerites 1–3. Scale bars: A–B = 1.0 mm; E = 0.2 mm.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F12" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 12.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A–E</bold>, Holotype male (WAM T118985) from Thistle Cove, Cape Le Grand National Park, Western Australia: <bold>A</bold>, cephalothorax and abdomen, lateral view; <bold>B</bold>, chelicerae, lateral view, showing accessory setae; <bold>C–D</bold>, pedipalpal bulb, retrolateral view; <bold>E</bold>, detail of distal tegular sclerites, prolateral view. C1–2 = conductor sclerites 1–2; E = embolus; T = tegulum; (TS)1–3 = tegular sclerites 1–3. Scale bars: A = 1.0 mm; D = 0.2 mm.&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g012.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F13" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 13.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Harvey, 2002a). <bold>A–D</bold>, Holotype female (WAM T42580) from Ellen Peak, Stirling Range National Park, Western Australia: <bold>A</bold>, cephalothorax and abdomen, lateral view; <bold>B–D</bold>, internal genitalia, dorsal view; <bold>C–D</bold>, illustrations (from Harvey 2002a) of internal genitalia, dorsal view, showing shape of membranous bursa and underlying spermathecae. B = bursa; GP = genital plate; Sp = spermathecae. Scale bar: A = 1.0 mm.&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g013.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F14" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 14.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A–B</bold>, Cephalothorax and abdomen, lateral view: <bold>A</bold>, allotype female (WAM T97468) from Toolbrunup Peak, Stirling Range National Park, Western Australia; <bold>B</bold>, holotype male (WAM T118986) from Mount Hassell, Stirling Range National Park, Western Australia. <bold>C</bold>, Holotype male chelicerae, lateral view, showing accessory setae. <bold>D–F</bold>, Holotype male pedipalp: <bold>D–E</bold>, bulb, retrolateral view, with inset showing twisted apex of tegular sclerite 1 in retroventral view; <bold>F</bold>, detail of distal tegular sclerites, prolateral view. <bold>G</bold>, Allotype female internal genitalia, dorsal view. C1–2 = conductor sclerites 1–2; E = embolus; GP = genital plate; T = tegulum; (TS)1 = tegular sclerite 1. Scale bars: A–B = 1.0 mm; E = 0.2 mm.&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g014.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F15" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 15.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A–B</bold>, Cephalothorax and abdomen, lateral view: <bold>A</bold>, allotype female (WAM T97466) from Talyuberlup Peak, Stirling Range National Park, Western Australia; <bold>B</bold>, holotype male (WAM T117055) from Talyuberlup Peak, Stirling Range National Park, Western Australia. <bold>C</bold>, Holotype male chelicerae, lateral view, showing accessory setae. <bold>D–F</bold>, Holotype male pedipalp: <bold>D–E</bold>, bulb, retrolateral view, with inset showing twisted apex of tegular sclerite 1 in retroventral view; <bold>F</bold>, detail of distal tegular sclerites, prolateral view. <bold>G</bold>, Allotype female internal genitalia, dorsal view. C1–2 = conductor sclerites 1–2; E = embolus; GP = genital plate; H = distal haematodocha; T = tegulum; (TS)1 = tegular sclerite 1. Scale bars: A–B = 1.0 mm; E = 0.2 mm.&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g015.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F16" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 16.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A–B</bold>, Cephalothorax and abdomen, lateral view: <bold>A</bold>, allotype female (MV K11579) from Acheron Gap, Victoria; <bold>B</bold>, holotype male (MV K11578) from Acheron Gap, Victoria. <bold>C</bold>, Holotype male chelicerae, lateral view, showing accessory setae. <bold>D–F</bold>, Holotype male pedipalp: <bold>D–E</bold>, bulb, retrolateral view, with inset showing twisted apex of tegular sclerite 1 in retroventral view; <bold>F</bold>, detail of distal tegular sclerites, prolateral view. <bold>G</bold>, Allotype female internal genitalia, dorsal view. C1–2 = conductor sclerites 1–2; E = embolus; GP = genital plate; T = tegulum; (TS)1–3 = tegular sclerites 1–3. Scale bars: A–B = 1.0 mm; E = 0.2 mm.&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g016.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F17" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 17.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A–B</bold>, Cephalothorax and abdomen, lateral view: <bold>A</bold>, allotype female (MV K5921) from Gunyah Rainforest State Reserve, Victoria; <bold>B</bold>, holotype male (MV K11580) from Tarra-Bulga National Park, Victoria. <bold>C</bold>, Holotype male chelicerae, lateral view, showing accessory setae. <bold>D–F</bold>, Holotype male pedipalp: <bold>D–E</bold>, bulb, retrolateral view, with inset showing twisted apex of tegular sclerite 1 in retroventral view; <bold>F</bold>, detail of distal tegular sclerites, prolateral view. <bold>G</bold>, Allotype female internal genitalia, dorsal view. C1–2 = conductor sclerites 1–2; E = embolus; GP = genital plate; T = tegulum; (TS)1–3 = tegular sclerites 1–3. Scale bars: A–B = 1.0 mm; E = 0.2 mm.&lt;br/&gt; </p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g017.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F18" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 18.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A–E</bold>, Holotype male (MV K11581) from Bimbi Park, Otway Range, Victoria: <bold>A</bold>, cephalothorax and abdomen, lateral view; <bold>B</bold>, chelicerae, lateral view, showing accessory setae; <bold>C–D</bold>, pedipalpal bulb (partially expanded), retrolateral view; <bold>E</bold>, detail of distal tegular sclerites, prolateral view. C1–2 = conductor sclerites 1–2; E = embolus; eH = embolic (distal) haematodocha; T = tegulum; (TS)1–3 = tegular sclerites 1–3. Scale bars: A = 1.0 mm; D = 0.2 mm.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g018.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F19" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 19.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. <bold>A–B</bold>, holotype female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. (AMS KS109448) from Delley’s Dell, Grampians National Park, Victoria: <bold>A</bold>, cephalothorax and abdomen, lateral view; <bold>B</bold>, internal genitalia, antero-dorsal view. <bold>C–D</bold>, holotype female <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SAM NN28000) from Western River Wilderness Protection Area, Kangaroo Island, South Australia: <bold>C</bold>, cephalothorax and abdomen, lateral view; <bold>D</bold>, internal genitalia, antero-dorsal view. GP = genital plate. Scale bars: A, C = 1.0 mm.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g019.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F20" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 20.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Platnick, 1991b), distribution and habitat: <bold>A</bold>, topographic map showing the known distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in south-western Western Australia, with collection localities for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea mainae</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted in yellow (red highlighted localities denote juvenile specimens of tentative identification; see <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. unidentified juvenile specimens, above); <bold>B</bold>, satellite image showing detail of inset (A); <bold>C</bold>, temperate coastal heathland near the type locality – Albany Wind Farm, Torndirrup Peninsula, Western Australia (March 2008). Image (C) by M. Rix.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g020.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F21" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 21.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., distribution and habitat: <bold>A</bold>, topographic map showing the known distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in south-western Western Australia, with collection localities for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea janineae</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted in yellow; <bold>B</bold>, satellite image showing detail of inset (A); <bold>C</bold>, wet eucalypt forest at the type locality – Karri Valley, Western Australia (August 2006). Image (C) by M. Rix.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g021.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F22" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 22.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., distribution and habitat: <bold>A</bold>, topographic map showing the known distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in south-western Western Australia, with collection localities for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marki</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted in yellow; <bold>B</bold>, satellite image showing detail of inset (A); <bold>C</bold>, temperate coastal heathland at the type locality – Thistle Cove, Cape Le Grand National Park, Western Australia (June 2010). Image (C) by M. Rix.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g022.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F23" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 23.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Harvey, 2002a), distribution and habitat: <bold>A</bold>, topographic map showing the known distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in south-western Western Australia, with collection localities for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted in yellow; <bold>B</bold>, satellite image showing detail of inset (A); <bold>C</bold>, montane heathland at the type locality – Ellen Peak, Stirling Range National Park, Western Australia (November 2007), with Bluff Knoll visible in the distance. Image (C) by M. Rix.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g023.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F24" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 24.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., distribution and habitat: <bold>A</bold>, topographic map showing the known distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in south-western Western Australia, with collection localities for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted in yellow; <bold>B</bold>, satellite image showing detail of inset (A); <bold>C</bold>, view from the summit of Bluff Knoll across the western Stirling Range National Park, showing collection localities for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> (i.e. Toolbrunup Peak, Mount Hassell) highlighted in bold (June 2010). Note the Chester Pass lowlands, separating populations of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea melindae</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea robinsi</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and Talyuberlup Peak in the distance, home to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Image (C) by M. Rix.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g024.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F25" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 25.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., distribution and habitat: <bold>A</bold>, topographic map showing the known distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in south-western Western Australia, with collection localities for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea barrettae</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted in yellow; <bold>B</bold>, satellite image showing detail of inset (A); <bold>C</bold>, view from Stirling Range Drive showing the type locality – Talyuberlup Peak, Stirling Range National Park (August 2008). Image (C) by M. Rix.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g025.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F26" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 26.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., distribution and habitat: <bold>A</bold>, topographic map showing the known distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in Victoria and South Australia, with collection localities for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea vichickmani</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted in yellow; <bold>B</bold>, satellite image showing detail of inset (A); <bold>C</bold>, cool-temperate <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nothofagus</tp:taxon-name></italic> rainforest at the type locality – Acheron Gap, Yarra Ranges National Park, Victoria (March 2010). Image (C) by M. Rix.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g026.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F27" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 27.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., distribution and habitat: <bold>A</bold>, topographic map showing the known distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in Victoria and South Australia, with collection localities for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea marae</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted in yellow; <bold>B</bold>, satellite image showing detail of inset (A); <bold>C</bold>, cool-temperate <italic><tp:taxon-name>Nothofagus</tp:taxon-name></italic> rainforest at the type locality – Tarra Valley, Tarra-Bulga National Park, Victoria (April 2010). Image (C) by M. Rix.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g027.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F28" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 28.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., distribution and habitat: <bold>A</bold>, topographic map showing the known distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in Victoria and South Australia, with collection localities for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea porchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted in yellow; <bold>B</bold>, satellite image showing detail of inset (A); <bold>C</bold>, bracken-rich eucalypt forest at the type locality – Bimbi Park, Otway Range, Victoria (March 2012). Image (C) by N. Porch, used with permission.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g028.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F29" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 29.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., distribution and habitat: <bold>A</bold>, topographic map showing the known distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in Victoria and South Australia, with collection localities for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea grayi</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted in yellow; <bold>B</bold>, satellite image showing detail of inset (A); <bold>C</bold>, wet sclerophyll forest at the type locality – Delley’s Dell, Grampians National Park, Victoria (March 2010). Image (C) by M. Rix.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g029.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <fig id="F30" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 30.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., distribution and habitat: <bold>A</bold>, topographic map showing the known distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Archaeidae</tp:taxon-name> in Victoria and South Australia, with collection localities for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Zephyrarchaea austini</tp:taxon-name></italic> highlighted in yellow; <bold>B</bold>, satellite image showing detail of inset (A); <bold>C</bold>, open eucalypt woodland and heathland at the type locality – near Billy Goat Falls, Western River Wilderness Protection Area, Kangaroo Island, South Australia (May 2010). Image (<bold>C</bold>) by M. Rix.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-191-001-g030.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
        </sec>
    </back>
</article>