<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.90.1136</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>The larva of Eustra (Coleoptera, Paussinae, Ozaenini):a facultative associate of ants</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Moore</surname>
                        <given-names>Wendy</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Song</surname>
                        <given-names>Xiao-bin</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Di Giulio</surname>
                        <given-names>Andrea</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>1</label><italic>Department of Entomology, University of Arizona, Tucson, Arizona 85721-0036, USA</italic></aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>2</label><italic>Shanghai, P.R. China</italic></aff>
                    <aff id="A3"><label>3</label><italic>Dipartimento di Biologia Ambientale, Università “Roma Tre” Viale G. Marconi 446, I-00146 Rome, Italy</italic></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Wendy Moore (<email xlink:type="simple">wmoore@email.arizona.edu</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Terry Erwin</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
            	    <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>14</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>90</issue>
            <fpage>63</fpage>
            <lpage>82</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>16</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>1</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Wendy Moore, Xiao-bin Song, Andrea Di Giulio</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Larvae of the ground beetle genus <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> Schmidt-Goebel are described and illustrated for the first time and some biological notes are reported. One specimen of an unknown <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> species was collected while excavating a nest of the ant <tp:taxon-name>Pachycondyla javana</tp:taxon-name> Mayr, in Taiwan, which is the first report of a paussine associated with a member of the ant subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Ponerinae</tp:taxon-name>. Several larvae and adults of a second species, <tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> Bänninger, were collected in Shanghai under bark with no association with ants. First instar larvae of the latter species were also reared in the lab. The occurrence of larvae of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> both inside and outside ant nests, together with a report of adults collected inside a nest in Taiwan, suggests that members of this genus may be facultative predators or facultative symbionts of ants, an attribute that has never been reported for this genus. The larvae of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> show several unique features, including a peculiar bidentate mandibular apex, an extremely long galea, one of two tarsal claws greatly reduced, abdominal setae (including those of terminal disk) elongate and clavate at apex, urogomphi wide and flattened, and inflated sensilla S-I. Larvae were studied by both optical and scanning electron microscopy, their morphological features are compared with those of other described <tp:taxon-name>Paussinae</tp:taxon-name> larvae, and their potential phylogenetic and functional significance are discussed.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>flanged bombardier beetles</kwd>
                <kwd>myrmecophily</kwd>
                <kwd>systematics</kwd>
                <kwd>larvae</kwd>
                <kwd>Southeast Asia</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> Schmidt-Goebel is an ozaenine genus (<tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Paussinae</tp:taxon-name>) containing twenty-two species (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Deuve 2001</xref>). Adults in this Southeast Asian genus have the smallest body size of all members of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Paussinae</tp:taxon-name>. Many <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> species live in caves and exhibit typical structural adaptations to a troglobitic life, including loss of pigmentation, loss of eyes, and long, delicate appendages. Other species are not cave-dwelling, but rather they have been collected in microhabitats typical of other ozaenines including under rocks and under bark. Recently larvae of two species of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> were collected in the field. Both adults and larvae of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> Bänninger were collected in Shanghai while they were hibernating in rotting wood and a single larva of an unidentified species of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> was collected during the excavation of nests of the ant <tp:taxon-name>Pachycondyla javana</tp:taxon-name> Mayr in Taiwan, suggesting for the first time that at least some species of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> are facultatively associated with ants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Moore 2006</xref>).</p>
            <p>Many different animals, especially arthropods, profit from a facultative or obligate association with ants (myrmecophily), bypassing the behavioral and chemical defenses of the hosts and adapting to the peculiar environmental conditions of the nests. Since myrmecophiles are rare and live in concealed environments, our knowledge of their behavior is sparse, and most of the information we do have has been inferred from structural features of adults and larvae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Di Giulio and Moore 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Di Giulio et al. 2011</xref>). The <tp:taxon-name>Paussinae</tp:taxon-name>, commonly known as flanged bombardier beetles, are a good model taxon to study the evolution of myrmecophily in beetles, since members of this ground beetle subfamily have different degrees of associations with ants, ranging from apparently none to obligate myrmecophiles (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Geiselhardt et al. 2007</xref> and references therein). As far as we know all members of the tribes <tp:taxon-name>Protopaussini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Paussini</tp:taxon-name> are myrmecophilous, at least during the larval stage, and their associations with ants have either been directly observed in the field or deduced from their remarkable structural adaptations. Most of these species associate with members of the ant subfamilies <tp:taxon-name>Formicinae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Myrmicinae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p>In general, very little is known about the behaviour of the ozaenines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Di Giulio and Vigna Taglianti 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Moore and Di Giulio 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Moore 2008</xref>). Like most ground beetles, they are usually found under stones, bark, and rotting wood and they are night-active predators on other arthropods. Ozaenine larvae are known for only nine species in four genera (<tp:taxon-name>Itamus</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Sphaerostylus</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Pachyteles</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Physea</tp:taxon-name>) (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Di Giulio and Moore 2004</xref>). They all have a terminal disk composed of modified abdominal tergites and urogomphi, which is a synapomorphy for the subfamily (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bousquet 1986</xref>). Unlike the physogastric myrmecophilous larvae of the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Paussini</tp:taxon-name> which use their round terminal disk as a glandular symphilous organ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Oberprieler 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bousquet 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Luna de Carvalho 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Di Giulio and Moore 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Di Giulio et al. 2011</xref>), free-living larvae of <tp:taxon-name>Metriini</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Mystropomini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Ozaenini</tp:taxon-name> use their terminal disk as a door to close the galleries they construct in rotten wood, humid earth or sandy riverbanks, and they use the moveable components of the terminal disk to trap their prey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Costa et al. 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Di Giulio and Vigna Taglianti 2001</xref>), seizing them with their sharp mandibles through a<!--PageBreak--> backward spring-like movement. This specialized feeding strategy allows these delicate larvae to feed on fast moving invertebrates and to occasionally feed on ants. It is likely that many non-myrmecophilous members of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Paussinae</tp:taxon-name> facultatively feed on ants, as has been demonstrated in the tribe <tp:taxon-name>Metriini</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Moore and Di Giulio 2008</xref>). We hypothesize that myrmecophagy may be a preadaptation for myrmecophily.</p>
            <p>Members of the ozaenine genus <tp:taxon-name>Physea</tp:taxon-name> Brullé are known to live inside the nests of the Neotropical leafcutting ants, <tp:taxon-name>Atta</tp:taxon-name>, and both larvae and adults have structural adaptations for this lifestyle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Eidmann 1937</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Di Giulio et al. 2003</xref>). Recently adults of other ozaenine species have been found inside <tp:taxon-name>Atta</tp:taxon-name> nests including adults of <tp:taxon-name>Tachypeles moretianus</tp:taxon-name> Deuve and <tp:taxon-name>Serratozaena paraphysea</tp:taxon-name> Deuve (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Moore 2008</xref>). Based on structural features of adults, myrmecophily has also been hypothesized for the Southeast Asian species <tp:taxon-name>Dhanya mulu</tp:taxon-name> Stork (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Stork 1985</xref>), and the South and Central American genera <tp:taxon-name>Ozaena</tp:taxon-name> Olivier and <tp:taxon-name>Platycerozaena</tp:taxon-name> Bänninger (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Ball and McCleve 1990</xref>). Larval specimens of the Malagasy species <tp:taxon-name>Sphaerostylus goryi</tp:taxon-name> (Laporte de Castelnau) were recently collected both in rotten wood with ants and in leaf litter without apparent association with ants (WM, personal observations). The discovery of an <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> larva inside a <tp:taxon-name>Pachycondyla javana</tp:taxon-name> nest in Taiwan is the only report of a paussine associated with a member of the ant subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Ponerinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Moore 2006</xref>). That <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> larvae have been collected both inside and outside of ant nests suggests the possibility that they are at least facultatively associated with ants. In addition, a report of adults of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> sp. collected inside an ant nest in Taiwan was posted on the Internet (http://nc.kl.edu.tw/bbs/showthread.php?t=653&amp;page=9). These findings suggest that more ozaenine taxa may be facultative or obligate myrmecophiles, even those without evident structural adaptations, and they suggest that myrmecophily has evolved multiple times during the evolution of in <tp:taxon-name>Paussinae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Moore 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Moore et al. 2010</xref>).</p>
            <p>In this paper we: (1) present biological information about the habitats and behaviors of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> and the <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> species from Taiwan observed in nature and in captivity; (2) describe and illustrate these larvae; (3) discuss the functional significance of several unique characteristics of the genus; and (4) compare them to other described paussine larvae.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
            <sec sec-type="Material described"><title>Material described</title>
                <p>(1) <tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> Bänninger, 1949. Twenty-five adults and several larvae were collected in Shanghai on February 9, 2009 and April 6, 2008. They were found hibernating together in the soft, rotten wood of bristly locust (<tp:taxon-name>Robinia hispida</tp:taxon-name> Linnaeus,1767) and weeping willow (<tp:taxon-name>Salix babylonica</tp:taxon-name> Linnaeus,1753). Adults and larvae can be found in Shanghai throughout the year. They overwinter as both adults and larvae (all larval instars), from November to April. Presumably, while these larvae are overwintering they do not feed. In captivity, a third instar larva overwintered without food for more <!--PageBreak-->than six months. During this time they did not close the opening of their galleries with their terminal disks, as they do to facilitate feeding during the spring and summer (as described for other ozaenine larvae, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Costa et al. 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Di Giulio and Vigna Taglianti 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Moore and Di Giulio 2006</xref>).</p>
                <p>(2) <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> sp. A single third instar larva was collected in northern Taiwan (Shan-shya [sic]) by Gustav Tzh-wei Chen on 9.IX.2003 while excavating a nest of <tp:taxon-name>Pachycondyla javana</tp:taxon-name> Mayr (<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Formicidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Ponerinae</tp:taxon-name>). The specimen was identified as belonging to the genus <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name>, by a phylogenetic analysis of molecular sequence data obtained from this specimen and from sixty other members of the subfamily <tp:taxon-name>Paussinae</tp:taxon-name>, including other members of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Rearing conditions"><title>Rearing conditions</title>
                <p>Larvae of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> were reared in captivity, where ambient conditions (<italic>e.g.</italic>, temperature, light and humidity) were similar to natural conditions outdoors. Five larvae of each instar were reared in 2 ml centrifuge tubes. Other larvae were reared in a plastic box (18 cm × 11 cm × 12 cm) with the field-collected rotten wood. All larvae were fed springtails once a month.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Morphological analysis"><title>Morphological analysis</title>
                <p>Prior to preparing them for microscopy, larvae were drawn by a stereomicroscope Olympus SZX16 equipped with drawing tube. One specimen of each instar of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name>, and the single specimen from Taiwan were rehydrated, cleared in 10% KOH, transferred in hot lactic acid, dehydrated through a series of EtOH baths of increasing concentration (10-20-50-70-90-95-100%), left overnight in a clove oil bath, and mounted on slides with Canada balsam. These specimens were studied and illustrated by using a light microscope Olympus BX51 equipped with drawing tube. Another first instar specimen was dehydrated through a series of EtOH baths of increasing concentration (70-80-90-95-100%), critical point dried (Bal-Tec CPD 030), mounted on a stub (by using self adhesive carbon disks), sputtered with gold (Emitech k550 sputter coater), and observed with Philips XL30 scanning electron microscope and FEI Dualbeam FIB/SEM Helios Nanolab (L.I.M.E. laboratory, University ‘Roma Tre’, Rome). In this paper, the general terminology of larval structures follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Lawrence (1991)</xref>. Notation of primary setae and pores follows the system of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bousquet and Goulet (1984)</xref>, modified for <tp:taxon-name>Metrius contractus</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bousquet 1986</xref>). Because some of the sensilla on the abdomen and terminal disk of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> are homologous to those recognized in <tp:taxon-name>Metrius contractus</tp:taxon-name> (sensilla S-I to S-V) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bousquet 1986</xref>), <tp:taxon-name>Pachyteles</tp:taxon-name> spp. (sensilla S-I to S-VII) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Di Giulio et al. 2000</xref>), and <tp:taxon-name>Arthropterus</tp:taxon-name> sp. (sensilla S-I to S-VIII) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Di Giulio and Moore 2004</xref>), we adopt here the same nomenclature used by these authors. Notation of microsculpture follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Harris (1979)</xref>. An asterisk (*) following a coded<!--PageBreak--> seta indicates that the homology between the structure on the <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> larvae and the corresponding code is questionable.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results"><title>Results</title>
            <sec sec-type="Eustra larval morphology"><title>Eustra larval morphology</title>
                <p><bold>Generic diagnosis.</bold> Body length very small as compared with other <tp:taxon-name>Paussinae</tp:taxon-name> (1.75mm, first instars); antenna 3-jointed (II+III fused); mandible apically bidentate, with sub-basal retinaculum, ental margin of retinaculum with additional small sub-basal tooth; galea extremely long and apically sharp, distinctly longer than maxillary palp and lacinia; maxillary palpomere 3-jointed (II+III fused); claws of very different size, smaller claw obsolescent; hypopleurite VI with ventrolateral, elongate digitiform protuberance, tipped by strong spine-like seta; most sternal and pleural setae of the abdomen elongate and clavate at apex; lateral plates of terminal disk thin and wing-like, pointed at apex, with dorsal margin straight and ventral margin curved; urogomphi flattened, wider and longer than dorsal plates, composed by 7 short triangular lobes, acute at apex, separated by V-shaped incisures of different depths; lobe X present between C and E2; lobe E1 divided into E1a and E1b; peculiar mushroom-like inflated sensilla S-I of different length present on surface of plates and urogomphi; sensilla S-II of two different types, alternate on dorsal plates and urogomphi: (1) very long and stick-like, pointed at apex; (2) short and clavate at tip; terminal disk covered with peculiar hairy microsculpture.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Eustrachinensis first instar larva"><title>Eustrachinensis first instar larva</title>
                <p><bold>Habitus and coloration.</bold> Body soft, whitish, weakly sclerotized, not physogastric; abdomen flattened, bellows-like, contracted dorsally elevating the large terminal disk; terminal disk, cephalic capsule and mouthparts well sclerotized, yellowish to light brown; mandibles, laciniae, anterior margin of frontal sclerite, egg-bursters and claws thickly sclerotized and reddish brown.</p>
                <p><bold>Microsculpture.</bold> Cephalic capsule, mouthparts, thoracic tergites and legs smooth, without or with only sparse, pointed microsculpture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a, 5b</xref>); anterior margin of frontoclypeolabrale to adnasalia strongly denticulate at sides of median prominence, resulting in a serrate anterior edge (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>); anterior frontal keel smooth; basal third of prementum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1f</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3f</xref>) and stipes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1e</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3f</xref>) with pointed microsculpture on dorsal surface; membranous areas of the body and sclerites of the abdomen rugulose to rugose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5a, 5c-f</xref>), with pointed or multi-pointed sculpticells, sparse near the setae, longer on epipleurites I-VII; dorsal surface of dorsal plates, basal part of lateral plates and ventral surface of urogomphi covered by transverse rows of 2-6 spines (2-3 µm long), regularly spaced every 3-6 µm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7d</xref>); surface of terminal disk <!--PageBreak-->(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>) thickly covered by a peculiar hairy microsculpture; pygidium, with pointed to multi-pointed microsculpture.</p>
                <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Figure 1.</label>
                    <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> first instar larva: line drawings of <bold>a</bold> head, dorsal view <bold>b</bold> head, ventral view <bold>c</bold> left antenna, dorsal view <bold>d</bold> left mandible, dorsal view <bold>e</bold> left maxilla, dorsal view <bold>f</bold> labium, dorsal view. Scale bars: 0.1 mm.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-090-063-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <p><bold>Chaetotaxy.</bold> Frontoclypeolabrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a-c</xref>) without additional setae; FR1-4,6-9 easily distinguished (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>); medial prominence of frontoclypeolabrum with 2 minute spine-like setae on dorsal surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>); FRb absent; several minute  filiform sensilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>) expanded at apex present on anterior part of frontale (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2e-f</xref>). Parietale (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2c</xref>) with several small additional setae irregularly positioned mesodorsally, and longer additional setae placed ventrally; some setae of parietale possibly homologous to the ancestral pattern are tentatively assigned in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>. Antennomere I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2c</xref>)<!--PageBreak--> with 5 dorsolateral additional setae; ANa,b absent; III with AN1 and ANf displaced apically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>). Mandibles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d</xref>) with two large additional pores mesodorsally. Setal group gMX on stipes composed of about 10 setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1e</xref>); MX6 very small, dorsal and subbasal on lacinia; galeomere II with one additional seta on ental side and a subapical, dorsal sensorial area (composed of 3 dome-like and 1 longer medial sensilla) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>); maxillary palpomere IV with 1 small additional seta on ental side, 2 longitudinal subapical digitiform sensilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3e</xref>) and apical sensorial area composed of several papillae. Prementum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1f</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3f</xref>) with about 10 additional setae on lateral and dorsal surface, LA3, 4, 5 not clearly identifiable; seta LA1 close to the midline; LAa absent, LAc subapical; labial palpomere II with 2 additional setae, 1 dorsal, medially directed and 1 small ventrolateral, 2 longitudinal subapical digitiform sensilla and apical sensorial area composed of several papillae. Pro-, meso- and metanotum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref>) with about 25 setae each (identification not possible). Coxa with about 20 setae; trochanter with spiniform setae present mostly on ventral side, including a long TR4; TR8 about as long as TR4 but thinner and more flexible. Meso- and metasternum with MS4 long. Abdominal tergites I-VII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref>) with 4 setae on each side. Tergal side of dorsal and lateral plates of terminal disk (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7b</xref>) with stiff pointed setae (sensilla S-VII) of various sizes, with cylindrical bases protruding from the plates: about 14 on each dorsal plate (epipleurite IX + tergite VIII) and about 3 on each lateral plate (epipleurite VIII); distal margin of each dorsal plate with about 12 elongated, straight and deeply corrugated sensilla S-II, of two different sizes and shapes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6a</xref>) alternately placed: type 1 extremely long (about double than type 2), stick-like, with sharp tip; type 2 thinner than 1 and distinctly clavate at apex; inner edge of each dorsal plate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6a</xref>) with 2-3 S-II type 2 obliquely directed, increasing in size from base to apex; margin of each lateral plate with 8 sensilla S-II, 5 of type 1; caudal side of the terminal disk with numerous sensilla S-I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6a</xref>) sparsely distributed: 25-30 S-I on each dorsal plate and about 1-4 on each lateral plate. Epipleurites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs. 4c-d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5c-d</xref>) of abdominal segment I without setae, II-V with one elongate sensillum S-II (type 2) each, VI-VII with several setae and S-II type 2. Sternal area of segment I with small simple setae, II-VI with elongate sensilla S-II type 2, VII with simple elongate setae (except for one, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>). Urogomphi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7a, c</xref>) with many S-I (about 40), mainly on dorsal surface and at margins of branches; branches A, C, X and E1b with S-II type 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7a</xref>), B, E2, E1a with apical long S-II type 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7a, f</xref>). Pygidium without setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7a</xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Figure 2.</label>
                    <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> first instar larva: SEM micrographs of <bold>a</bold> head, dorsal view <bold>b</bold> head, frontal view <bold>c</bold> head, dorsolateral oblique view <bold>d</bold> left egg-burster, right dorsolateral oblique view <bold>e</bold> basal setae of frontoclypeolabrale, with filiform sensilla, dorsal view <bold>f</bold> close-up of a filiform sensillum of frontoclypeolabrale. Scale bars: <bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> = 100 µm; <bold>d</bold> = 20 µm; <bold>e</bold> = 10 µm; <bold>f</bold> = 1 µm.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-090-063-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Figure 3.</label>
                    <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> first instar larva: SEM micrographs of <bold>a</bold> apex of left antenna, dorsal view <bold>b</bold> apex of left mandible, lateral view <bold>c</bold> apex of left galea, dorsal view <bold>d</bold> right lacinia, dorsal view <bold>e</bold> digitiform sensillum of maxillary palpomere IV, lateral view <bold>f</bold> labium, dorsal view. Scale bars: <bold>a</bold> = 20 µm; <bold>b</bold>, <bold>f</bold> = 25 µm; <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold> = 10 µm; <bold>e</bold> = 2 µm.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-090-063-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Figure 4.</label>
                    <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> first instar larva: line drawings of <bold>a</bold> pro- and meso-notum, dorsal view <bold>b</bold> left foreleg, anterior view <bold>c</bold> right side of abdomen, dorsal view <bold>d</bold> right side of abdomen, ventral view (right urogomphus not drawn). a- = abdominal segment; e- = epipleurite; t- = tergum; Scale bars: 0.1 mm.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-090-063-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Figure 5.</label>
                    <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> first instar larva: SEM micrographs of <bold>a</bold> pro- and meso-notum, dorsal view <bold>b</bold> apex of left hind-leg, anterior view <bold>c</bold> abdominal sensilla on left pleurae, dorsal view <bold>d</bold> abdominal sensilla on left pleurae, dorsal view <bold>e</bold> right metathoracic spiracle <bold>f</bold> abdominal spiracle I. Scale bars: <bold>a</bold> = 100 µm; <bold>b</bold> = 30 µm; <bold>c</bold> = 10 µm; <bold>d</bold> = 50 µm; <bold>e</bold> = 5 µm; <bold>f</bold> = 4 µm.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-090-063-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Figure 6.</label>
                    <caption><p>Terminal disks of: <bold>a</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> first instar <bold>b</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> sp. Taiwanthird instar <bold>c</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Goniotropis kuntzeni</tp:taxon-name> first instar <bold>d</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Paussus favieri</tp:taxon-name> first instar. DP = dorsal plate; LP = lateral plate; UG = urogomphus; PY = pygidium. Scale bars: a = 0.25 mm; b= 0.5 mm.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-090-063-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Figure 7.</label>
                    <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> first instar larva: SEM micrographs of <bold>a</bold> right urogomphus, dorsal view <bold>b</bold> left dorsal plate, dorsal view <bold>c</bold> right urogomphus, left dorso-lateral view <bold>d</bold> left lateral plate, dorsal view <bold>e</bold> sensillum S-I on X lobe, lateral view <bold>f</bold> right urogomphus, lobe A, dorso-lateral view. Scale bars: <bold>a</bold> = 100 µm; <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold> = 50 µm; <bold>e</bold> = 10 µm; <bold>f</bold> = 20 µm.</p></caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-090-063-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                </fig>
                <p><bold>Head.</bold> Cephalic capsule (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1a-b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a-c</xref>) strongly transverse (width/length ratio = 1.86), hyperprognathous, rounded laterally, regularly tapered at basal half into a distinct neck; maximum width at antennal insertions about twice as wide as occipital foramen. Frontoclypeolabrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a,c</xref>) strongly transverse (width/length ratio = 1.64), with surface medially convex and anterolaterally concave; basal stem of epicranial suture short, anterior frontal arms only slightly sinuate; egg-bursters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>) composed of two longitudinal, multispinulate carinae, each consisting of about 20 forwardly directed teeth; carinae parallel, about one third the length of frontoclypeolabrum, widely separated, placed between FR1 and FR3. Anterior margin of frontoclypeolabrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a-b</xref>) double-edged: dorsal edge smooth, slightly convex, form<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->ing a transverse keel (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Di Giulio et al. 2003</xref> and Di Giulio and Moore, 2004 for a discussion on the homology) extended to the adnasalia, ventral edge strongly serrate laterally, medially produced into a wide subrectangular labral tooth (labral spine <italic>sensu</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Beutel 1992</xref>); adnasalia slightly rounded and slightly protruding. Parietale (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1a-b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2c</xref>) without stemmata; ocular and cervical grooves absent; ventral walls of parietale medially fused into a complete gular suture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). Antennae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>) strongly directed mesad, 3-jointed; antennomere I (first joint) about as long as II+III (second joint) and twice as long as IV (third joint); sensorial appendage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3a</xref>) elongate, bullet-like, slightly shorter than IV, laterally positioned at apex of III. Mandibles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b</xref>) stout, sickle-shaped, about 2 times as long as wide at base, regularly curved along lateral margin; apex sharply bidentate, lower tooth smaller than upper and distinctly divergent; penicillus absent; terebra slightly convex beyond retinaculum, then concave to apex; retinaculum small sub-triangular, sub-basal in position, postero-medially directed; anterior margin rounded and convex, posterior margin straight, with sub-basal tooth. Maxilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1e</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3c</xref>) with undivided cardo, subrectangular stipes, 3-jointed palp, 2-jointed galea and 1-jointed lacinia. Stipes distinctly curved inward, about 3 times as long as wide at base; small tooth-like protuberance present subbasally on the ental side of stipes. Maxillary palpi short; palpomere I wide and subconical, medially fused with basal galeomere; II fused with III forming a unique second joint; IV (third joint) elongate, digitiform, about as long as II+III combined. Galea very long, distinctly longer than palpus; galeomere I short, stout; II elongate, hook-like, apically sharp and inward directed, about two times as long as I; galea+palpus distinctly up-curved. Lacinia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1e</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3d</xref>) very short and slender, almost straight, strongly sclerotized, basally fused with stipe. Labium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1f</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3f</xref>) with slightly sclerotized prementum and 2-jointed palpi; prementum subrectangular, distinctly decreasing in width from base to apex; small setal notches present on dorsal surface and sides; ligula very short, dome-like, sub-dorsal; labial palpomere I cylindrical, slightly shorter and wider than II; II digitiform, slightly compressed apically.</p>
                <p><bold>Thorax.</bold> Tergites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref>) scarcely sclerotized, sternum not sclerotized. Pronotum wider than meso- and metanotum, transverse, about two times wider than long. Meso- and metanotum widely transverse, about two and a half times wider than long; longitudinal ecdysial line well marked on pro- and mesonotum, less evident, but present, on metanotum.</p>
                <p><bold>Spiracles.</bold> Thoracic and abdominal spiracles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5e, f</xref>) annular-uniphorous; mesothoracic spiracles dome-like, anterolateral on mesopleura, more than twice the size of the abdominal spiracle I. Abdominal spiracles rounded, plate-like, not protruding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5f</xref>), placed dorsolaterally between tergites and epipleurites.</p>
                <p><bold>Legs.</bold> Legs well developed, 5-jointed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref>), forelegs slightly shorter than others, mid and hind legs subequal. Coxa cylindrical, very long, about as long as trochanter and femur combined; trochanter elongate, obliquely truncate and fused apically to femur, about as long as femur and tibia combined; femur about as long as tibia and tarsus combined; tibia very short, cylindrical, slightly shorter than tarsus; tarsus more slender than tibia, conical, tapered from base to apex, with 2 sharp unequal claws (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5b</xref>)<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->: anterior claw elongate and strong, slightly longer than tarsus, apically curved; posterior claw very small and somewhat obsolescent.</p>
                <p><bold>Abdomen.</bold> Abdominal segments I-VII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4c, d</xref>) not sclerotized, bellows-like, usually up-curved, keeping the abdominal apex in an elevated position. Abdominal sclerites barely discernable, recognised by reduction of multipointed microsculpture around setae or sensilla S-II; segments progressively wider from I to VIII. Each segment dorsally flattened, with swollen, setiferous pleural and sternal areas. Hypopleurites setiferous, slightly protruding; hypopleurite VI with ventrolateral, elongate digitiform protuberance, tipped by strong spine-like seta. Epipleurites conical, distinctly protruding, gradually more developed from segment I to VIII; epipleurites of segment VIII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4c-d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7d</xref>) flattened and enlarged into two sclerotized lateral plates, smaller than the dorsal plates; lateral plates slender, triangular, about two times longer than wide at base; epipleurites of segment IX greatly enlarged and fused with tergum of segment VIII into two rectangular, sclerotized plates (dorsal plates), slightly enlarged from base to apex and widely separated in the middle by a deep V-shaped notch (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4c-d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6a</xref>); lateral plates widely separated from dorsal plates; lateral plates, dorsal plates and urogomphi forming a terminal disk articulated at base by membranes, dorsal and lateral plates move against urogomphi. Urogomphi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7a,c</xref>) wide, flattened, each composed of 7 pointed lobes: A, B, C, X, E2, E1b, E1a (respectively from the inner to the outer); A much shorter than B; pygidium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7a</xref>) protruding, medioventrally positioned between the urogomphal insertions.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Eustrachinensis, second and third instar larvae"><title>Eustrachinensis, second and third instar larvae</title>
                <p>General morphology very similar to that described above for the first instar, except for: progressive increasing of relative dimensions (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>); presence of secondary setae on antennomere II (2 setae); sensorial appendage much shorter than antennomere IV; <!--PageBreak-->retinaculum progressively longer and more falcate; stipe with wider and sharp sub-basal protuberance; labial palpomere I wider than II; tibia subequal to tarsus; pronotum about as wide as meso- and metanotum; dorsal plates of terminal disk slightly longer; lobes of urogomphi relatively longer and more slender; lobe E1a slightly longer than E1b.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                    <label>Table 1.</label>
                    <caption><p>Measurements (mm) of three instars (L1, L2, L3) of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> and the third instar (L3) of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> sp.Taiwan. BL = body length (from tip of mandibles to the apex of terminal disk); HW = cephalic capsule maximum width (at the base of the antennae); HL = cephalic capsule medial length (mesodorsally, from occipital foramen to anterior margin of frontoclypeolabrum); PW = prothorax maximum width; PL = prothorax medial length; TDW = terminal disk maximum width (at the level of lateral plates); DPL = dorsal plates length (from base, near articulation, to the medial apex). </p></caption>
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> L1</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> L2</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name> L3</th>
                                <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> sp. L3</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BL</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HW</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HL</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PW</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PL</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDW</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPL</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Eustra sp. Taiwan, third instar larva"><title>Eustra sp. Taiwan, third instar larva</title>
                <p>Unfortunately, the specimen is damaged and portions of its head and legs are missing. Only basal part of head capsule, basal half of a mandible, thorax, basal part of legs, entire abdomen and terminal disk are intact. However, there is one low-resolution image of the entire specimen, which provides only limited information of some structural details.</p>
                <p>General larval structure and most characters of the terminal disk (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6b</xref>) are very similar to those described above, especially as compared with the third instar of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name>, except for the following minor differences:<!--PageBreak--></p>
                <p>(1) lobe A of urogomphi about as long as B (A much shorter than B in <tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name>); (2) E1a thinner and more elongate than E1b (subequal or only slightly longer to E1b in <tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name>); (3) lobes A very close medially, almost touching (distinctly separated medially in <tp:taxon-name>Eustra chinensis</tp:taxon-name>).</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> larvae are highly modified compared with the other known larvae of <tp:taxon-name>Ozaenini</tp:taxon-name>, and have several unique structures that make their identification easy. These include:</p>
            <p>1. Antennae 3-jointed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2c</xref>). <tp:taxon-name>Paussinae</tp:taxon-name> larvae generally show 4-jointed antennae, a condition typical for adephagans. The reduction to 3 joints in <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> is clearly due to the fusion of antennomeres II and III.</p>
            <p>2. Mandible apically bidentate with sub-basal retinaculum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b</xref>). A bidentate mandibular apex is also present in all known myrmecophilous <tp:taxon-name>Paussini</tp:taxon-name> larvae except <tp:taxon-name>Arthropterus</tp:taxon-name>, but in this tribe the second tooth is thought to be a subapically displaced retinaculum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Di Giulio and Moore 2004</xref>). In addition to the bidentate apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>), a small subtriangular and basally directed retinaculum is present in <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> first instars, and it becomes longer and more falcate in later instars.</p>
            <p>3. Ental margin of retinaculum with additional small sub-basal tooth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d</xref>). This margin is straight only in <tp:taxon-name>Physea</tp:taxon-name>, while it is more or less sinuate (basal half convex, distal half concave) in all other known ozaenine genera. The presence of a sub-basal tooth on the ental margin in <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> may be an adaptation for piercing and holding their prey.</p>
            <p>4. Maxillary palp 3-jointed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1e</xref>). The reduction of the palpomeres from 4 to 3 is a common feature of known <tp:taxon-name>Paussini</tp:taxon-name> larvae except for <tp:taxon-name>Platyrhopalopsis</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Arthropterus</tp:taxon-name>. In the genus <tp:taxon-name>Paussus</tp:taxon-name> the reduction is due to the fusion of basal palpomere with the stipe. In <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> the basal palpomere is only partially fused with stipe but still recognizable, and the actual reduction is due to the fusion of palpomeres II+III.</p>
            <p>5. Galea extremely long and apically sharp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1e</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3c</xref>). The galea of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> is two-jointed as is typical of ozaenines but it is highly modified: it is very strong, up-curved, and almost two times longer than the maxillary palp and almost three times longer than the lacinia. The apex is hook-like and unusually sharp, which would provide an effective tool for capturing and holding prey.</p>
            <p>6. Strongly asymmetric tarsal claws (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5b</xref>). All <tp:taxon-name>Metriini</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Mystropomini</tp:taxon-name>, and <tp:taxon-name>Ozaenini</tp:taxon-name> larvae have legs with two tarsal claws of unequal size, the anterior distinctly longer than posterior, while myrmecophilous <tp:taxon-name>Paussini</tp:taxon-name> larvae have only a single claw (presumably the anterior). In <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> the posterior tarsal claw is extremely small and almost obsolescent.</p>
            <p>7. Hypopleurite VI with ventrolateral, elongate digitiform protuberance, tipped by strong spine-like seta (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5d</xref>). This peculiar sensorial structure is unique to the genus <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <p>8. Most sternal and pleural setae of the abdomen elongate and clavate at apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4c-d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5c-d</xref>). Clavate sensilla have been described in the myrmecophilous genus <tp:taxon-name>Arthropterus</tp:taxon-name> (sensilla S-VIII possibly homolog to S-II, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Di Giulio and Moore 2004</xref>), which surround the terminal disk, and are also present on the thorax and cephalic capsule. In <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name>, a clavate modification affects most abdominal mechanoreceptors as well as most sensilla of the terminal disk (see below). In particular, the terminal disk has two types of sensilla, often alternate (i.e. dorsal plates): type 1 is very long, stick-like, and pointed at the apex; type 2 is short and clavate at the tip.</p>
            <p>9. Lateral plates of terminal disk transverse, subtriangular and pointed at apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6a-b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7d</xref>), with straight margins. The lateral plates of the <tp:taxon-name>Metriini</tp:taxon-name>, Mystropomin<!--PageBreak-->i and other <tp:taxon-name>Ozaenini</tp:taxon-name> are wide and broadly rounded. Lateral plates of <tp:taxon-name>Goniotropis</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Ozaenini</tp:taxon-name>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6c</xref>) are transverse and widely separated from dorsal plates similar to those of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p>10. Urogomphi flattened, wider and longer than dorsal plates, composed by 7 short triangular lobes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6a-b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7a</xref>), acute or bidentate at apex, separated by V-shaped notches of different depths, very shallowas compared to other <tp:taxon-name>Ozaenini</tp:taxon-name>. The flattening and widening of the urogomphi and the reduction (<tp:taxon-name>Physea</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Ozaenini</tp:taxon-name>) or absence (all <tp:taxon-name>Paussini</tp:taxon-name>, see for example <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6d</xref>) of branches is a typical feature of myrmecophilous larvae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Di Giulio et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Di Giulio and Moore 2004</xref>).</p>
            <p>11. Absence of urogomphal lobe D and presence of the additional urogomphal lobe X (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 6a-b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7a</xref>). The lobes of urogomphi were coded first in <tp:taxon-name>Metrius</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Bousquet (1986)</xref> and his notation was later slightly modified for ozaenines to include the partial or total bipartition of lobes B (B1+B2) and E (E1+E2) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Vigna Taglianti et al. 1998</xref>). This notation works for all described ozaenine larvae except for <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name>, which do not have a lobe D, but rather have an additional lobe (here named “lobe X”) located between lobes C and E2. Lobe X may be interpreted as: (1) a unique lobe (X = F); (2) D-lobe distally displaced to the margin (X = D); or (3) an additional subdivision of lobe E (X = E3). <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> larvae also have a unique subdivision of E1 (E1a, E1b).</p>
            <p>12. Peculiar inflated sensilla S-I (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7a,c,e</xref>) of different lengths present on surface of plates and urogomphi. Inflated sensilla S-I have been described in larvae of <tp:taxon-name>Platyrhopalopsis</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Paussini</tp:taxon-name>) and <tp:taxon-name>Physea</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Ozaenini</tp:taxon-name>) and have been considered as an adaptation to the myrmecophilous lifestyle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Di Giulio et al. 2003</xref>). The sensilla S-I of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> are very different from the homologous structures of the aforementioned taxa since these are mushroom-shaped, composed of an elongate basal stem, which emerges from a cuticular protuberance, and an apical irregular inflation.</p>
            <p>Like in the other ozaenine genera, larvae of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> live in galleries that they dig in humid soil or rotten wood and close off with their terminal disk, which they use to trap prey. However, the larvae of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> are so specialized and modified that it is not possible to find clear synapomorphies with larvae of any of the other known ozaenine genera. Some of the peculiar adaptations discussed above are similar to, but not necessary homologous to, characteristics described for the myrmecophilous larvae of <tp:taxon-name>Paussini</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Physea</tp:taxon-name> (See <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Since the <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> larva from Taiwan was found inside a nest of <tp:taxon-name>Pachycondyla javana</tp:taxon-name>,it is possible that some of these traits are adaptations to a myrmecophilous lifestyle. However, we think that it is more likely that these minute larvae feed on very small invertebrates like collembolans and <tp:taxon-name>Drosophila</tp:taxon-name>, which first instar ozaenine larvae consistently consume in the lab (Moore and Di Giulio, pers. obs.), than it is that they feed on <tp:taxon-name>Pachycondlya</tp:taxon-name>, which are relatively large-bodied ants. Instead, many of the unusual characters observed in these larvae could facilitate feeding on fast moving prey, including the very long radial mechanoreceptors (sensilla S-II) of the terminal disk which would sense the approach of fast collembolans, and modified mouthparts including the bidentate <!--PageBreak-->mandibular apex, second tooth of retinaculum, and hook-like galea which would help the larva hold onto motile prey. Other characters, such as the flattening and widening of the urogomphi, could be related to the miniaturization of the larval body. In the future, we hope to discover the larvae of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Dhanya</tp:taxon-name>, and compare its morphological structures with <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> since they are hypothesized to be sister genera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Jeannel 1946</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Stork 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Deuve 2001</xref>), as well as larvae of the species formerly classified in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Ozaenaphenops</tp:taxon-name> to search for support of its synonymy with <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Deuve 2001</xref>).<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
            <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                <label>Table 2.</label>
                <caption><p>Characteristics of <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> larvae that are similar to those found in mymecophilous larvae. </p></caption>
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="2"><tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name>+<tp:taxon-name>Physea</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">galea elongate (but in a completely different way: in <tp:taxon-name>Physea</tp:taxon-name> galeomere I long, II short and truncate at apex; in <tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name> I short and II very long and sharp)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lacinia reduced</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">prementum elongate and tapered from base to apex</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">labral spine wide</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ligula absent</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">urogomphal lobes partially fused</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">head short and transverse</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">frontoclypeolabrale wide and transverse</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">coronal suture short</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">anterior arms of frontal sutures only slightly sinuate</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">stemmata absent</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">retinaculum in first instar triangular, inward directed</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">sensilla S-I inflated</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="2"><tp:taxon-name>Eustra</tp:taxon-name>+<tp:taxon-name>Paussini</tp:taxon-name></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mandibles apically bidentate</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">number of maxillary palp articles reduced (but in a completely different way, see Discussion)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">second tarsal claw reduced (in <tp:taxon-name>Paussini</tp:taxon-name> second claw is absent)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">sensilla clavate or inflated (only in <tp:taxon-name>Arthropterus</tp:taxon-name> clavate sensilla S-II, inflated S-I in <tp:taxon-name>Platyrhopalopsis</tp:taxon-name>)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">urogomphal lobes short rather then strongly branched</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">urogomphi flat and wide</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">antennae short and strongly directed medially</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">stemmata absent</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">sensorial appendage elongate</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">head shortened and distinctly transverse</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>The authors wish to thank Gustav Tzh-wei Chen for collecting a mysterious paussine larva while excavating a nest of <tp:taxon-name>Pachycondyla javana</tp:taxon-name> and sending a leg to WM for molecular identification in 2003, and Brian Fisher (California Academy of Sciences) for his help tracking down the voucher specimen many years later. We also thank David Kavanaugh and one anonymous reviewer for helpful comments that improved this paper. This project was partially funded by NSF grant DEB-0908187 to WM.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCleve</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> The Middle American genera of the tribe Ozaenini with notes about the species in southwestern United States and selected species from Mexico.</article-title> <source>Quaestiones Entomologicae</source> <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>-<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Beutel</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Study on the systematic position of Metriini based on characters of the larval head (Coleoptera: Carabidae).</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology</source> <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>-<lpage>218</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bousquet</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> Description of first-instar larva of <italic>Metrius contractus</italic> (Coleoptera: Carabidae) with remarks about phylogenetic relationships and ranking of the genus <italic>Metrius</italic>.</article-title> <source>The Canadian Entomologist</source> <volume>118</volume>:<fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>388</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bousquet</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goulet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Notation of primary setae and pores on larvae of Carabidae (Coleoptera: Adephaga).</article-title> <source>Canadian Journal of Zoology</source> <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>573</fpage>-<lpage>588</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casari-Chen</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<source> Larvas de Coleptera do Brasil</source>. <publisher-name>Museu de Zoologia, Sao Paulo: Universidade de Sao Paulo</publisher-name>, <lpage>282</lpage> pp. + 165 pls.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Deuve</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Le genre <italic>Eustra</italic> Schmidt-Goebel, 1846, insectes (Coleoptera, Paussidae, Ozaeninae) à genitalia femelles orthotopiques.</article-title> <source>Zoosystema</source> <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>547</fpage>-<lpage>578</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Giulio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fausto</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taddei</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigna Taglianti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> The terminal disk of <italic>Pachyteles</italic> larvae (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Paussinae): a morphological study</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandmayr</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lövei</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zetto Brandmayr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigna Taglianti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Natural History and Applied Ecology of Carabid Beetles, Proceedings of the IX European Carabidologists Meeting (26–31 July, 1998, Camigliatello, Cosenza, Italy)</source>. <publisher-name>Pensoft</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Sofia-Moscow</publisher-loc>, <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Giulio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> The first-instar larva of the genus <italic>Arthropterus</italic> (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Paussinae): implications for evolution of myrmecophily and phylogenetic relationships within the subfamily.</article-title> <source>Invertebrate Systematics</source> <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>115</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Giulio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigna Taglianti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Biological observations on <italic>Pachyteles</italic> larvae (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Paussinae).</article-title> <source>Tropical Zoology</source> <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Giulio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fattorini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaupp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigna Taglianti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> Review of competing hypotheses of phylogenetic relationships of <italic>Paussinae</italic> (Coleoptera: Carabidae) based on larval characters.</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology</source> <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>509</fpage>-<lpage>537</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Giulio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurizi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hlaváč</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> The long-awaited first instar larva of <italic>Paussus favieri</italic> (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Paussini).</article-title> <source>European Journal of Entomology</source> <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Eidmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1937</year>)<article-title> Die Gäste und Gastverhältnisse der Blattschneiderameise Atta sexdens L.</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift fuer Morphologie und Oekologie der Tiere</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>391</fpage>-<lpage>462</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Geiselhardt</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peschke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> A review of myrmecophily in ant nest beetles (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Paussinae): linking early observations with recent findings.</article-title> <source>Naturwissenschaften</source> <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>871</fpage>-<lpage>894</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> A glossary of surface sculpturing.</article-title> <source>Occasional Papers in Entomology</source> <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeannel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1946</year>)<article-title> Coléoptères Carabiques de la Région Malgache (première partie).</article-title> <source>Faune de l’Empire français</source> <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>372</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> Order Coleoptera</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stehr</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>) <source>Immature insects</source>, Vol. <volume>2</volume>, <publisher-name>Kendall/Hunt Publishing Company</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dubuque, Iowa</publisher-loc>, <fpage>144</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Luna de Carvalho</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Essay monographique des Coléoptèteres Protopaussines et Paussines</article-title>. <source>Memorias do Institudo de Investigaçao Científica Tropical, (segunda série)</source>, <publisher-name>Lisboa</publisher-name>, <volume>70</volume>, (1987), <lpage>1028</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> Molecular phylogenetics, systematics, and natural history of the flanged bombardier beetles (Coleoptera: Adephaga: Carabidae: Paussinae). PhD thesis</source>, <publisher-loc>Tucson, Arizona, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The University of Arizona</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny of the Western Hemisphere Ozaenini (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Paussinae) based in DNA sequence data.</article-title> <source>Annals of the Carnegie Museum</source> <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Giulio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> Description and behaviour of <italic>Goniotropis kuntzeni</italic> larvae (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Paussinae: Ozaenini) and a key to genera of Paussinae larvae.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>111</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Giulio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> <italic>Metrius</italic> Eschscholtz (Carabidae: Paussinae) is not a millipede specialist.</article-title> <source>The Pan-Pacific Entomologist</source> <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Giulio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Paussinae (Coleoptera: Carabidae) larvae recently discovered in Asia and Madagascar. In: Fikacek M, Skuhrovec J, Sipek P (Eds) Abstracts of the Immature Beetles Meeting 2009, October 1 2, Prague, Czech Republic.</article-title> <source>Acta Entomologica Musei Nationalis Pragae</source> <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>-<lpage>342</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberprieler</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Paussidae</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholtz</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Insects of Southern Africa</source>, <publisher-name>Butterworth Publishers (Pty) Ltd.</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Durban</publisher-loc>, <fpage>196</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stork</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> <italic>Dhanya</italic>, a South-east Asian genus of ozaenine ground beetles.</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History</source> <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1113</fpage>-<lpage>1138</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigna Taglianti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santarelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Giulio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliverio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> Phylogenetic implications of larval morphology in the tribe Ozaenini (Coleoptera, Carabidae)</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigna Taglianti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Phylogeny and classification of Caraboidea (Coleoptera: Adephaga), Proceedings of a Symposium (28 August, 1996, Florence, Italy), XX International Congress of Entomology</source>, <publisher-name>Museo Regionale di Scienze Naturali</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Torino, Atti</publisher-loc>, <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>