<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.148.1278</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new genus and species of mandibulate nasute termite (Isoptera, Termitidae, Syntermitinae) from Brazil</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Rocha</surname>
                        <given-names>Mauricio M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:20D55322-12A8-4877-8A3E-330384C6B067</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Cancello</surname>
                        <given-names>Eliana M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:54294942-D86D-4B6B-ABA3-4FD16C5DC0CB</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Cuezzo</surname>
                        <given-names>Carolina</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:92FE9862-BBE2-480B-8FB6-23FE61EDDEA1</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de São Paulo, Cx. Postal 42.494, 04218-970 São Paulo, SP, Brasil
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label> CONICET- Instituto Superior de Entomología “Dr A. Willink”, Facultad de Ciencias Naturales e Instituto Miguel Lillo, UNT, Miguel Lillo 205, T4000JFE, San Miguel de Tucumán, Argentina
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Mauricio Martins Rocha (<email xlink:type="simple">mrocha@usp.br</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Michael Engel</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>21</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>148</issue>
            <fpage>125</fpage>
            <lpage>134</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>19</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>19</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Mauricio M. Rocha, Eliana M. Cancello, Carolina Cuezzo</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:AFC4AD1B-B5A3-428D-9916-D5AC1DA3C3C2</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes krishnai</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>gen. et sp. n.</bold>, is described here, based on soldiers and workers collected in Brazil. Some characteristics suggest a close kinship with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cancello &amp; Myles, and both genera share the following traits absent in all other <tp:taxon-name>Syntermitinae</tp:taxon-name>: the microsculpturing on the soldier head capsule surface with internal granulations; the piercing mandibles with a single very reduced marginal tooth and the worker very similar in both genera. The most conspicuous differences between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> are the shape of the soldier head, the frontal tube and pronotum. The shape of the soldier head in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> is unusual, with a very broad and short frontal tube, four conspicuous protuberances like sharp corners at the rear, while in the new genus the posterior contour of the head is devoid of these protuberances. The frontal tube of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> is elongate and conical, while in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> it is short and very broad. The pronotum of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> is saddle-shaped as is usual in other <tp:taxon-name>Syntermitinae</tp:taxon-name>, while it is aberrant in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Termite</kwd>
                <kwd><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic></kwd>
                <kwd><tp:taxon-name>Syntermitinae</tp:taxon-name></kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The “mandibulate nasutes” comprise a group of termite genera endemic to the Neotropical region. Fourteen genera are recognized within this group (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Armitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wasmann, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cahuallitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Constantino, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cornitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wasmann, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Curvitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Holmgren, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyrilliotermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fontes, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Embiratermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fontes, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Fontes, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Labiotermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Holmgren, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Macuxitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cancello and Bandeira, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Cancello and Myles, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paracurvitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Constantino and Carvalho, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Procornitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Emerson, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhynchotermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Holmgren and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Syntermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> Holmgren), ranging from south of Mexico (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Cahuallitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>) to northern Argentina (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Procornitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Syntermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>). The group is morphologically characterized by having soldiers with a large frontal gland opening, situated at the frontal tube apex, and functional mandibles.</p>
            <p>In the past, the mandibulate nasutes were considered an ancestral group of <tp:taxon-name>Nasutitermitinae</tp:taxon-name> but recent studies highlighted an evolutionary history independent of true nasutes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Noirot 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Ohkuma et al. 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Inward et al. 2007</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Engel and Krishna (2004)</xref> proposed <tp:taxon-name>Syntermitinae</tp:taxon-name> as a subfamily of <tp:taxon-name>Termitidae</tp:taxon-name> including four of the thirteen genera of mandibulate nasutes, and they affirm that the other mandibulate genera of <tp:taxon-name>Nasutitermitinae</tp:taxon-name> “may eventually be included” in the subfamily.</p>
            <p>In this work we describe a new monotypic termite genus that seems to be closely related to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Both genera share traits absent in all other <tp:taxon-name>Syntermitinae</tp:taxon-name>: the microsculpturing on the soldier head capsule surface with internal granulations; the piercing mandibles upturned, with a single reduced marginal tooth; and the worker almost identical in both genera.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
            <title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>The studied samples, including the holotype and paratypes, are in the Museum of Zoology of the University of São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil (MZUSP). All comparisons with other syntermitine genera where based on data from taxonomic reviews or original descriptions [<italic><tp:taxon-name>Armitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Rocha 2011</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cahuallitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Constantino 1994</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Labiotermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Constantino et al., 2006), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Macuxitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Cancello and Bandeira 1992</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Constantino 1997</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Cancello and Myles 2000</xref>), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paracurvitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Constantino and Carvalho 2011</xref>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Syntermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Constantino 1995</xref>)] and examination of material in the MZUSP collection, that has specimens of all type species of syntermitine genera.</p>
            <p>Terms used for pilosity are comparative: bristles are long erect setae with well-marked bases; hairs are shorter than bristles, less rigid and with inconspicuous bases; microscopic hairs are very short and visible only under at least 50 × magnification (not illustrated in the figures). Gut terminology follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Noirot (2001)</xref>.</p>
            <p>The morphometric characters used here and their correspondence with Roonwal’s system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Roonwal 1970</xref>) are indicated in parentheses as follows: length of head capsule, LH (9); width of head capsule, WH (18); length of frontal tube, LFT (28); length of left hind tibia, LT (85). All measurements were taken with a micrometric reticle.<!--PageBreak--></p>
            <p>Line drawings were made with a camera lucida, soldier photographs were obtained with a digital camera coupled to a stereomicroscope Leica M205C, and images of different depth of focus were further processed and merged with software. Worker mandibles were dissected and prepared for scanning electron microscopy. The worker enteric valve was mounted on Entellan (Merck) and photographed under an optic microscope. Scales are indicted in each illustration.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomic treatment">
            <title>Taxonomic treatment</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Acangaobitermes</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:B72916A1-CF82-4685-BA8C-F48677C2A9B2</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Acangaobitermes</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species">
                    <title>Type species.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes krishnai</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>From Tupi, indigenous South American language, <italic>acangaobi</italic> meaning funneled head and the Latin <italic>termes</italic> meaning termite, in reference to soldier head capsule shape in profile. The name is masculine.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Imago.</bold> Unknown.</p>
                    <p><bold>Soldier.</bold> Monomorphic. Head capsule sub-quadrangular with almost parallel lateral margins and two very discrete saliencies on the latero-posterior corners (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 7</xref>, arrows). Surface of head capsule covered with numerous minute and closely set points of about equal diameter, forming a conspicuous and characteristic microsculpture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 7</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">8</xref>). Frontal tube conical and upturned, in profile, apex with a relatively wide aperture surrounded by a white membrane. Antennae with 14 articles. Piercing slender mandibles; blade strongly curved inwards and upturned; a very small tooth at the base of the blade and a molar plate/prominence fully developed with no ridges. Clypeus very reduced. Labrum with a rounded and flat hyaline tip. Posmentum sub-rectangular with antero-lateral margins slightly concave. Coxae with a keel shape projection, pointing outwards and situated at distal antero-lateral margins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>, arrow). Tibial spurs 2:2:2.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–4.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes krishnai</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. et sp. n. <bold>1</bold> soldier head and pronotum in dorsal and profile view <bold>2</bold> soldier coxa in frontal view (arrow: keel shape projection) <bold>3</bold> worker mandibles <bold>4</bold> worker digestive tube <italic>in situ</italic>, a: dorsal view, b: right view, c: ventral view, d: left view and e: paunch in left view. MT= Mesenteric tongue; P1= first proctodeal segment (ileum); P3a and b = third proctodeal segment (paunch); P4a= first part of fourth proctodeal segment (colon).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-148-125-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <p><bold>Worker.</bold> Monomorphic. Head capsule rounded. Postclypeusinflated. Antennae with 14 articles. Left mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>): apical tooth larger than M1+2, margin between M1+2 and M3 sinuate, M3 distinct and smaller than M1+2, molar tooth conspicuous, partially hidden by molar prominence; molar prominence concave without ridges. Right mandible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3</xref>, 5): apical tooth larger than marginal teeth, M1 and M2 clearly distinct, molar plate concave without ridges (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>). Coxae smooth without projections. Body slender and elongated, digestive tube visible through abdominal sclerites. Tibial spurs 2:2:2.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 5–6.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes krishnai</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. et sp. n. <bold>5</bold> worker molar plate <bold>6</bold> enteric valve armature.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-148-125-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <p>Worker digestive tube. Crop asymmetrical, without any constriction separating it from gizzard. Cuticular armature of gizzard with 24 visible folds, six of first order, six of second and 12 of third; ratio between columnar and pulvillar belt approximately equal to one; pulvilli without armature or ornamentation. Mesenteron tubular. Short mixed seg<!--PageBreak-->ment present. Mesenteric tongue on the external side of the mesenteric arch, slightly strangled proximally. Two pairs of Malpighian tubules attached at the mesenteron-proctodeum junction, one internal side to the mesenteric arch and the other external. First proctodeal segment (P1), diagonal to body axis, more enlarged than mesenteron with about same size of proximal portion of paunch (P3a); distal end of P1 narrowed, forming a short neck prior to the attachment to P3. Enteric valve (P2) at the left side of the body. P3 slightly constricted between P3a and P3b. Dorsal torsion well-developed. P3 joined to colon (P4) on left side, isthmus short and parallel to body length. P4a dilated, U-Turn and P4b tubular.</p>
                    <sec sec-type="Comparisons with other genera of Syntermitinae">
                        <title>Comparisons with other genera of <tp:taxon-name>Syntermitinae</tp:taxon-name></title>
                        <p>Soldiers of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Syntermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cornitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Labiotermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Procornitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> have a short frontal tube, not exceeding the labrum; a well-developed hyaline tip to the labrum; straighter cutting mandibles, with well-developed marginal teeth; and a larger body size. Soldiers of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cahuallitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> have straighter cutting mandibles, with well-developed marginal teeth; a well-developed hyaline tip to the labrum; and a larger body size. Soldiers of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Embiratermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> have a larger body size, straighter and large mandibles, with well-developed marginal teeth in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Embiratermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> or totally absent in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Soldiers of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyrilliotermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Curvitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> have aberrant mandibles, with a molar plate, molar prominence and marginal teeth very similar to their corresponding worker mandibles; apical tooth fish-hooked in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Curvitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, reduced in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyrilliotermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>; and the frontal tube cylindrical and elongate in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyrilliotermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (see more details of these two genera, including the dissected soldier mandibles, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Mathews 1997</xref>, page 226). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Paracurvitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> has a broader head capsule with well developed conical and shorter frontal tube than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobiermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>; the mandibles are much longer, less curved with triangular teeth, very different from the new genus. The soldiers of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rynchotermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> have strongly curved mandibles; a very long frontal tube; procoxae with a spine-like lateral projection; and a much larger body size. Soldiers of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Armitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> have the pronotum, mesonotum, and metanotum with serrate lateral margins; mandibles with well-developed marginal teeth; and a larger body size (see Rocha, 2011, for a redescription and new illustrations of the genus). Lastly, the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Macuxitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> has dimorphic soldiers, with an aberrant head shape; pronotum, mesonotum and metanotum with serrate lateral margins; and mandibles with well-developed marginal teeth.</p>
                        <p>Despite differences in the shape of the soldier head, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> shares many exclusive traits with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The worker of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> is very similar to that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, with same mandibular pattern, body size and shape (elongate), labrum and digestive tract, including the enteric valve armature. The worker differences between both genera are: the inner margin of apical teeth in left and right mandibles are much more concave in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> than in the new genus; the M3 in left mandibleand M2 in right mandible both are larger in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>; and the insertion of the enteric valve is in the body axis, while in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> it is perpendicular to the body axis.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <p>The soldiers of both species have the same microsculpturing on the head capsule surface and the internal granulations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 8</xref>), that are otherwise absent in all other species of <tp:taxon-name>Syntermitinae</tp:taxon-name>. The piercing, upturned mandibles, with a single marginal tooth reduced are nearly identical in both genera, while in all other <tp:taxon-name>Syntermitinae</tp:taxon-name> the marginal teeth are well-developed (or completely absent in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ibitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>). The two occipital saliencies are present in both genera and in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Macuxitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but are much more discrete in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 7</xref>, arrows).</p>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 7.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes krishnai</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. et sp. n. Soldier head in dorsal view (Arrows: saliencies on latero-posterior margins).</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-148-125-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <p>The most conspicuous differences between the new genus and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> are the shapes of the soldier head and pronotum. The pronotum is aberrant in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> and saddle-shaped in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, as is usual for otherSyntermitinae. The shape of the soldier head in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> is unusual, with a very broad frontal tube and two protuberances like sharp corners at the rear, while in the new genus the frontal tube is elongate and conical, similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Armitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and the posterior rear part of the head is devoid of conspicuous projections.</p>
                    </sec>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Acangaobitermes</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">krishnai</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D82B4A68-0687-45E3-8275-AA24B9D4BFF3</object-id>
                    		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Acangaobitermes_krishnai</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"></xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">9</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype">
                    <title>Holotype.</title>
                    <p>Soldier. Part of the lot MZUSP 13167, labeled “Parque Nac. Emas, GO, 22.iv.2004. Ninho 212, D. Costa col.” Kept separately in the same vial with paratypes.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type-locality">
                    <title>Type-locality.</title>
                    <p>BRAZIL. Goiás: Parque Nacional das Emas (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">18°01.49'S; 52°57.87'W</named-content>, 850 m).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes">
                    <title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p>Soldiers and workers of MZUSP 13167 with same data as holotype. Goiás: Parque Estadual da Serra de Caldas Novas (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">17°44.7'S; 48°37.5'W</named-content>, 1000 m), 23.iii.2008, D. E. Oliveira coll. (MZUSP 13168). Minas Gerais: Serra de São José (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">21°4.98'S; 44°10.02'W</named-content>, 1250m), 11.iv.2007, E.M. Cancello coll. (MZUSP 11956). Rondônia: UHE Santo Antônio (<named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°50.63'S; 64°3.75'W</named-content>, 100 m), 22.ix.2010, T. Carrijo &amp; R. Santos coll. (MZUSP 13670).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>As for the genus (<italic>vide supra</italic>).</p>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 8.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes krishnai</tp:taxon-name></italic> gen. et sp. n. Detail of the microsculputure of the soldier head capsule.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-148-125-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named in honor of Dr Kumar Krishna, for his important contributions to termite taxonomy.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><bold>Imago.</bold> Unknown.</p>
                    <p><bold>Soldier.</bold> Shape of head, frontal tube, labrum, mandibles, pronotum under generic description. Antennae with 14 articles, 2nd half size of 1st, 3rd half of 2nd, 4th half of 3rd, 5th twice the size of 4th, subsequent articles sub-equal and similar to third. Scattered bristles, short hairs and microscopic hairs on top and lateral sides of head capsule, few bristles at rear portion. Frontal tube with microscopic hairs along its length and hairs around aperture of frontal tube. Pronotum with bristles on margins, plus two pairs of bristles at middle of anterior lobe. Mesonotum and metanotum with a row of bristles on posterior margins. Abdominal tergites and sternites with short hairs over <!--PageBreak-->surfaces and bristles on posterior margins. Head orange, mandibles ferruginous, body pale-yellow. Measurements, in millimeters, of four soldiers including the holotype: LH: 1.26–1.52; WH: 0.62–0.70; LFT: 0.56–0.74; LT: 0.64–0.66.</p>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 9.</label>
                        <caption><p>Geographic distribution of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes krishnai</tp:taxon-name></italic>, gen. et sp. n.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-148-125-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <p><bold>Worker.</bold> External morphology under generic description. Head capsule with scattered bristles, antennae with some short hairs and sparse bristles, pronotum with bristles on margins and over surface of anterior lobe, mesonotum and metanotum with bristles on posterior margins. Abdominal tergites and sternites with short hairs over surfaces and bristles on posterior margins.</p>
                    <p>Digestive tube (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 4a–4e</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">6</xref>). Coiling gut pattern and gizzard armature under generic description. P2 armature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>) with three longitudinal equidistant cushions covered with strong and erect spines oriented perpendicular to gut contents flow,<!--PageBreak--> among the cushions minor spines settled at different orientations. P3 internally ornamented with long cuticular filaments (as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Noirot 2001</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Biology. All the samples were collected in the soil or in nests of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cornitermes cumulans</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Kollar) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Armitermes euamignathus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Silvestri, in areas of openformation. The <!--PageBreak-->specimens from state of Goiás are collected in a Cerrado formation. From the state of Rondônia in a border line between primary forest and pasture. From Minas Gerais state in a “Campo rupestre”, a characteristic altitudinal field, with granitic outcrops and composed by xeric vegetation.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>Relationships among the mandibulate nasute genera are not yet clear, despite considerable evidence that they are a monophyletic group (e.g., Inward et al., 2007). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Rocha (2011)</xref> conducted a taxonomic revision and a phylogenetic analysis of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Armitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, including all type species of the genera of <tp:taxon-name>Syntermitinae</tp:taxon-name>. This analysis supports the hypothesis that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Macuxitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acangaobitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Noirotitermes</tp:taxon-name></italic> form a monophyletic group and that the last two are most closely related, with the occipital saliencies and the type of folds and their arrangement on the enteric valve as synapomorphies for the three genera.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We wish to thank our colleagues from MZUSP for their help with the images and the text in this manuscript: R. Feitosa, S. Policena Rosa, R. Kawada, L. Pires do Prado and T. Carrijo. We thank M.S. Engel, who kindly corrected the English manuscript. This work was supported by a doctoral scholarship from <italic>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior</italic>, CAPES, Brazil, to M.M.R.; a grant from <italic>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico</italic> (Proc. CNPq No. 304765/2007-4), Brazil, to E.M.C.; and a doctoral scholarship from CONICET, Argentina, to C.C.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cancello</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandeira</surname> <given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> <italic>Macuxitermes triceratops</italic> (Isoptera, Termitidae, Nasutitermitinae), a new genus and species from Island of Maracá, Roraima.</article-title> <source>Papéis Avulsos de Zoologia (São Paulo) </source> <volume>38</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cancello</surname> <given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myles</surname> <given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> <italic>Noirotitermes noiroti</italic> (Isoptera, Termitidae, Nasutitermitinae): a new genus and new species from northeastern Brazil.</article-title> <source>Sociobiology</source> <volume>36</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>531</fpage>-<lpage>546</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Constantino</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> A new genus of Nasutitermitinae with mandibulate soldiers from tropical North America (Isoptera: Termitidae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology </source> <volume>25</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>285</fpage>-<lpage>294</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Constantino</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<article-title> Revision of the neotropical termite genus <italic>Syntermes</italic> Holmgren (Isoptera: Termitidae).</article-title> <source>The University of Kansas Science Bulletin</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>455</fpage>-<lpage>518</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Constantino</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Morphology of the digestive tube of <italic>Macuxitermes</italic> and its phylogenetic significance (Isoptera: Termitidae: Nasutitermitinae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology </source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>-<lpage>230</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Constantino</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acioli</surname> <given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuezzo</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasconcellos</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> A taxonomic revision of the Neotropical termite genera <italic>Labiotermes</italic> Holmgren and <italic>Paracornitermes</italic> Emerson (Isoptera: Termitidae: Nasutitermitinae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1340</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Constantino</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname> <given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> <italic>Paracurvitermes</italic>, a new genus of Syntermitinae (Isoptera: Termitidae).</article-title> <source>Sociobiology </source> <volume>57</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>377</fpage>-<lpage>388</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Engel</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krishna</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Family-group names for termites.</article-title> <source>American Museum Novitates </source> <volume>3432</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Inward</surname> <given-names>DJG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogler</surname> <given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eggleton</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> A comprehensive phylogenetic analysis of termites (Isoptera) illuminates key aspects of their evolutionary biology.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution </source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>953</fpage>-<lpage>967</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2007.05.014">10.1016/j.ympev.2007.05.014</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathews</surname> <given-names>AGA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>)<source> Studies on termites from Mato Grosso State, Brazil.</source> <publisher-name>Academia Brasileira de Ciências</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Rio de Janeiro</publisher-loc>, <lpage>267</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Noirot</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> The gut of termites (Isoptera) comparative anatomy, systematics, phylogeny. II - Higher termites (Termitinae).</article-title> <source>Annales de la Société Entomologique de France </source> <volume>37</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>431</fpage>-<lpage>471</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohkuma</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuzawa</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amornsak</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sornnuwat</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takematsu</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vongkaluang</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarnthoy</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirtibutr</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noparatnaraporn</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kudo</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Molecular phylogeny of Asian termites (Isoptera) of the families Termitidae and Rhinotermitidae based on mitochondrial COII sequences.</article-title> <source>Molecular phylogenetics and evolution </source> <volume>31</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>701</fpage>-<lpage>710</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2003.09.009">10.1016/j.ympev.2003.09.009</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname> <given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> Revisão e análise filogenética de <italic>Armitermes</italic> Wasmann, 1897 (Isoptera, Termitidae, Nasutitermitinae), PhD thesis, São Paulo, Brasil: Universidade de São Paulo. [Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.teses.usp.br/teses/disponiveis/41/41133/tde-08022011-192936/en.php">http://www.teses.usp.br/teses/disponiveis/41/41133/tde-08022011-192936/en.php</ext-link>]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Roonwal</surname> <given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>)<article-title> Measurement of termites (Isoptera) for taxonomic purposes.</article-title> <source>Journal of Zoological Society of India </source> <volume>21</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>