	<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.153.2110</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Revision of the pseudo-orbweavers of the genus 
                    <italic>Fecenia</italic> Simon, 1887 (Araneae, Psechridae), with emphasis on their pre-epigyne</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Bayer</surname>
                        <given-names>Steffen</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Senckenberg Research Institute, Senckenberganlage 25, 60325 Frankfurt am Main, Germany
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Steffen Bayer (<email xlink:type="simple">bayer@senckenberg.de</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: D. Logunov</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>9</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>153</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>56</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>16</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>1</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Steffen Bayer</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>The present paper provides a taxonomic revision of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> with emphasis on the characteristics of the pre-epigynes which are integrated for the first time into an identification key. As a result, one species is revalidated, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thorell, 1891, <bold>stat. n.</bold>, and two new junior synonyms for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> are recognised: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia sumatrana</tp:taxon-name></italic> Kulczyński, 1908, <bold>syn. n.</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia nicobarensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Tikader, 1977), <bold>syn. n</bold>. New records are reported: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Doleschall, 1859)from Malaysian Borneo, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Simon, 1885) from Sumatra, Indonesia, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Thailand and Malaysia, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pocock, 1899 from Sri Lanka and Thailand, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thorell, 1895 from Thailand and Laos. Additional information on the biology of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> is provided and the validity of characters for identifying <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species is discussed.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>copulatory organs</kwd>
                <kwd>spination</kwd>
                <kwd>distribution</kwd>
                <kwd>South-East Asia</kwd>
                <kwd>pseudo-orbweb</kwd>
                <kwd>enrolled leaf</kwd>
                <kwd>predatory behaviour</kwd>
                <kwd>mating behaviour</kwd>
                <kwd>moult</kwd>
                <kwd>identification key</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Representatives of the spider genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> are distributed from southern India to the Solomon Islands. They are not known beyond the latitudes of 25°N and 15°S. To date (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Platnick 2011</xref>) this genus comprises five valid species. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species possess relatively long and prograde legs. The first two pairs are directed anteriorly whereas the third and <!--PageBreak-->fourth leg pairs are directed posteriorly. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species have a flat carapace and a slender body shape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Thorell 1881</xref>). Their chelicerae are short and strong and bear a distinct condyle latero-proximally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi 1982</xref>). Adults build a vertical web, which is similar to the typical orbwebs of (most) <tp:taxon-name>Araneidae</tp:taxon-name> and related families like <tp:taxon-name>Tetragnathidae</tp:taxon-name>, respectively. Thus representatives of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> are here called ‘pseudo-orbweavers'. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Simon (1892)</xref> described their web as more irregular than the webs of <tp:taxon-name>Araneidae</tp:taxon-name>. Furthermore he stated that it contains an enrolled leaf as a retreat in the centre. Despite this somewhat similar web style, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> is not closely related to the <tp:taxon-name>Araneidae</tp:taxon-name> and does not belong to the Orbiculariae either (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Coddington 1990</xref>). Together with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thorell, 1878, this genus belongs to the <tp:taxon-name>Psechridae</tp:taxon-name> Simon, 1890 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Simon 1892</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Griswold 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Griswold et al. 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Platnick 2011</xref>). Previously the pseudo-orbweavers were revised twice. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi (1982)</xref> provided a worldwide revision and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Wang and Yin (2001)</xref> covered Chinese representatives. In the study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen (1967)</xref> several <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species were synonymised. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi (1982)</xref> matched a female of a different species with the male of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Simon, 1885). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Murphy (1986)</xref> recognised this mistake and described the female of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> for the first time. At present, further taxonomic ambiguities still persist. Some of these were caused by descriptions of new species using subadult females (which only possess pre-epigynes) as type specimens.</p>
            <p>Pre-epigynes do not occur in all entelegyne spiders, but seem to be common within the families supposed to be related to <tp:taxon-name>Psechridae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Griswold 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Griswold et al. 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">2005</xref>), e.g. <tp:taxon-name>Pisauridae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Lycosidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Stiphidiidae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Zoropsidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Ctenidae</tp:taxon-name>. Up to now pre-epigynes were mostly disregarded in arachnological studies. There are some first descriptions where pre-epigynes had been erroneously regarded as epigynes (e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus mimus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Chamberlin, 1924, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Heteropoda shillongensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Sethi and Tikader, 1988, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus ghecuanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thorell, 1897). A study on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Agelena labyrinthica</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Clerck, 1757) noted the presence of a primordial copulatory organ in females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Strand 1906</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Jäger and Ono (2000)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Jäger (2008)</xref> as well as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Jäger and Bayer (2009)</xref> illustrated pre-epigynes of a few particular species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Olios</tp:taxon-name></italic> Walckenaer, 1837 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Heteropoda</tp:taxon-name></italic> Latreille, 1804 respectively. Several differently developed primordial copulatory organs in different stages of immature females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cupiennius salei</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Keyserling, 1877) were documented in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Lachmuth et al. (1985)</xref>. In <tp:taxon-name>Psechridae</tp:taxon-name> pre-epigynes were illustrated for the first time by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi (1982)</xref>. However, he studied only a few species in this regard. Moreover, in the case of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus himalayanus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Simon, 1906, he regarded a pre-epigyne as an adult epigyne. This led to misunderstandings in species determination and characterisation. As an ongoing revision shows (Bayer unpubl. data), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Griswold (1993)</xref> examined a subadult female of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus marsyandi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Levi, 1982, identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus himalayanus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, as the female representative of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in his study on the phylogeny of <tp:taxon-name>Lycosoidea</tp:taxon-name>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Wang and Yin (2001)</xref> showed the pre-epigyne of one species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus rani</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wang and Yin, 2001, and compared it with features of the conspecific adult female. A fairly complete investigation on the pisaurid genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Thalassius</tp:taxon-name></italic> Simon, 1885 was carried out by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Sierwald (1987)</xref> where most species concerned were characterised by their pre-epigyne II (penultimate instars) and some even by their pre-epigyne I (antepenultimate instars). An even more detailed study on American <tp:taxon-name>Pisauridae</tp:taxon-name> described changes in the<!--PageBreak--> development of pre-epigynes of different stages via very detailed illustrations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Sierwald 1989</xref>). Nevertheless, no study to date has examined variation within pre-epigynes of penultimate instar females within a species, nor has there been any attempt to integrate the pre-epigyne and pre-vulva- features into an identification key. In this context, the intention of this paper is to provide a thorough taxonomic revision of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> including some remarks on their biology and above all the character states of pre-epigynes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="material|methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Part of the spider material was collected by hand during an expedition in Thailand and Laos from October-December 2009. Further material was obtained from colleagues, who collected specimens in different regions of SE Asia. Most of the material examined in the present study was borrowed from several natural history museums, which are listed below. Examinations and illustrations were made using a Leica MZ 165 C stereomicroscope with a drawing mirror. Photos of living spiders were taken with a Canon EOS 500D (equipped with a Sigma 105 macro lens and a Canon ringlite). Photos of preserved spiders and copulatory organs were taken with a Sony DSC W70 compact camera via the ocular of the stereomicroscope. The material was preserved in 70% denatured ethanol. Female copulatory organs were cleared from surrounding hairs and dissected. The opaque tissue surrounding the vulva was removed. Vulvae were cleared in 96% DL-lactic acid (C<sub>3</sub>H<sub>6</sub>O<sub>3</sub>). As the cuticle surrounding the epigyne may curl and structures may get shifted in the course of applying lactic acid, this method could not be applied to every specimen. In males, hairs along the margin of the cymbium were removed to give a clear view of the bulb structures.</p>
            <p>All measurements are in millimetres (mm). Leg formula (from longest to shortest leg) and leg spination pattern follow those in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bayer and Jäger (2010)</xref>. In leg/palp spination the femur, patella, tibia and metatarsus (tarsus in palp) are listed in exactly this sequence. First, all spines on the prolateral surface of the respective limb article are counted and listed, then the ones on the dorsal, then retrolateral and finally the ventral surface. Thus the resulting number is generally one of 4-digits. Some limb articles, e.g. the femur and patella, always lack ventral spines, so here the number is of 3-digits. If a spination pattern from a certain limb article differs between the left and right sides, the pattern for the right article is listed in parenthesis behind, without a blank. Palp and leg lengths are listed as: total (femur, patella, tibia, metatarsus, tarsus).</p>
            <p>Abbreviations used in the text: ALE – Anterior lateral eye. AME – Anterior median eye. AML – Anterior margin of lateral lobe. AS – Anterior part of median septum. bEA – Basal embolus apophysis. BL – Borderline between SSI and TSI. C – Conductor. CA – Cymbium alveolus. CO – Copulatory opening. DRTA – Dorso–retrolateral tibial apophysis. E – Embolus. EF – Epigynal field. EM – Epigynal muscle sigilla. FD – Fertilisation duct. juv. – Juvenile (convention in the present work: juveniles are immature specimens of instars where no sex determination is possible, otherwise called juvenile male or juvenile female). LL – Lateral lobe. MA – Median apophysis. MP – Membra<!--PageBreak-->nous process of tegulum. PLE – Posterior lateral eye. PME – Posterior median eye. PS – Posterior part of median septum. p.s.a. – Pre-subadult. RPA – Retrolateral patellar apophysis. RTA – Retrolateral tibial apophysis. s.a. – Subadult. SB – Serial individual numbers of <tp:taxon-name>Psechridae</tp:taxon-name> examined by the author. SH – Spermathecal head. SO – Slit sense organ. SSI – Strongly sclerotised section of internal duct system. T – Tegulum. TR – Transverse edge/ridge of median septum. TSI – Transparent section of internal duct system. VPA – Ventral patellar apophysis.</p>
            <p>Terminology of structures belonging to the copulatory organs is given as follows:</p>
            <p>The female epigyne consists of two slits, which separate the lateral lobes (LL) from the median septum. The latter is folded transversely, resulting in a transverse edge or ridge (TR) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 79</xref>). Consequently, an anterior part of the septum (AS) and a posterior part (PS) can be distinguished (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 79</xref>). Anteriorly, each of the LL exhibits a more or less sclerotised margin (anterior margin of lateral lobe, AML). The entire epigyne is surrounded by an epigynal field (EF), which is a sclerotised area. It is not as intensively sclerotised as the median septum or the LL and is distinguished from the adjacent areas of the ventral opisthosoma by a darker colour. The following structures certainly do not belong to the epigyne, but they may be of additional taxonomic information, so they are illustrated and described here, too. Namely the two muscle sigilla (epigynal muscle sigilla, EM) in front of EF (sometimes they are integrated into the epigynal field) and the slit sense organs (SO) near the epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 79</xref>). The vulva consists of an internal duct system (more precisely a folded slit system, cf. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Sierwald 1987</xref>). It is divided into an initial, rather transparent section (TSI), a strongly sclerotised section (SSI) and the fertilisation duct (FD) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 83</xref>). The border line (BL) between TSI and SSI is clearly visible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 83</xref>). The initial section of SSI features a wide area with pores leading to associated glands. As this area is presumably homologous to the spermathecal head in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (for location of the spermathecal head see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Wang and Yin 2001</xref> or <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bayer and Jäger 2010</xref>) the term spermathecal head (SH) is used here for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> too, despite its different shape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 83</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Griswold (1993</xref>: p. 21) even denominated the entire SSI as “head of spermatheca”, which is not followed here. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> it is very difficult to locate the receptaculum. It is not clear where the functional copulatory duct actually ends. Moreover, nobody has ever observed how far a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> embolus penetrates within the internal duct system or where the sperm are finally stored.</p>
            <p>Apart from structures of a male palp that are well known in arachnology, e.g. conductor, sperm duct or RTA, the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> palp shows a retrolateral patellar apophysis (RPA), a ventral patellar apophysis (VPA) and a membranous process (MP) close to the embolus base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>). In one species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, an additional large apophysis arises dorso-retrolaterally from the tibia (dorso-retrolateral tibial apophysis, DRTA, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 53</xref>). Presently it cannot be clarified whether this apophysis is just the dorsal branch of an extended RTA or an additional apophysis. In either case, the DRTA can be regarded as an autapomorphy of this species.</p>
            <p>Symbols/styles used in the illustrations: Regular solid lines indicate edges/margins/rims of structures as recognised in the respective view; Weak solid lines indicate edges of fine structures, e.g. membranous structures, or wrinkles in the area of the epigyne; Dashed lines indicate inner walls of ducts and/or slits; Dotted lines (wide) indicate<!--PageBreak--> structures shining through the cuticule (e.g. parts of vulva shining through epigynal cuticula). Dotted lines (fine) indicate clear colour differences (e.g. border of epigynal field). In schematic illustrations showing the course of the internal duct system the spermathecal head area is marked with several “T” marks, the copulatory opening with a circle and the end of the fertilisation duct in the direction of the uterus externus with an arrow (see e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>). When a copulatory opening comprises an elongated slit/area, the circle is put at the central position of that slit/area. Arising points and/or directions of tegular appendages in males are described as clock-positions of the left palp in ventral view. This refers also to directions of some structures of the female vulva. As a convention in this latter case: In every species only the right vulva half is considered.</p>
            <p>Museum collections (with curators): AMS – Australian Museum, Sydney (G. Milledge). CAS – California Academy of Sciences, San Francisco (C. E. Griswold, A. Carmichael). HBI – Hunan Biological Research Institute, Hunan Normal University, Changsha (X. J. Peng, L. Ping). IRSN – Institut Royal des Sciences Naturelles de Belgique, Brussels (L. Baert, B. Goddeeris). MCSN – Museo Civico di Storia Naturale, Genoa (M. Tavano). MCZ – Harvard University, Museum of Comparative Zoology, Cambridge, Massachusetts (G. Giribet, L. Leibensperger). MHNG – Muséum d'histoire naturelle, Geneva, Switzerland (P. Schwendinger). MIZ – Museum and Institute of Zoology, Warszawa (D. Mierzwa). MNHN – Muséum National de Histoire Naturelle, Paris (C. Rollard, E. Leguin). NHM – Natural History Museum, London (J. Beccaloni). NHMW – Naturhistorisches Museum Wien, Vienna (J. Gruber, C. Hörweg). NRS – Naturhistoriska Riksmuseet, Stockholm (G. Lindberg). NZSI – Zoological Survey of India, National Zoological Collection, Calcutta. RMNH – Nationaal Natuurhistorisch Museum Naturalis, Leiden, Netherlands (J. Miller, I. J. Smit). SJPC – Sunil Jose Private Collection, Kottayam, India (S. Jose). SMF – Senckenberg Museum, Frankfurt am Main, Germany (P. Jäger, J. Altmann). USNM – National Museum of Natural History, Washington D.C. (J. Coddington). ZMA – Zoologisch Museum Amsterdam (B. Brugge). ZMB – Museum für Naturkunde, Berlin (J. Dunlop, B. Nitsche). ZMH – Zoologisches Institut und Zoologisches Museum, Hamburg (H. Dastych). ZMUC – Zoological Museum of the University of Copenhagen (N. Scharff).</p>
            <p>In the species descriptions the spider material is listed as follows: localities are listed from North to South, then from West to East; countries, provinces and towns/villages are listed as far as possible by their presently valid names.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results">
            <title>Results</title>
            <sec sec-type="Characteristics of pre-epigynes">
                <title>Characteristics of pre-epigynes</title>
                <p><bold>Distinction of pre-epigyne from adult epigyne.</bold> Pre-epigynes are considerably smaller than epigynes. If there is no adult female available to compare the size of the epigyne with that of the pre-epigyne of a subadult female the slit sense organs (SO) and epigynal muscle sigillae (EM) in front of the pre-epigyne can help. The distance between <!--PageBreak-->the SO from left to right side is about twice as long as the width of a pre-epigyne, but only slightly longer than the width of an adult epigyne. Furthermore, the pre-epigyne is only slightly longer than one EM. The adult epigyne, in contrast, is at least twice as long as EM. Moreover, the pre-epigyne exhibits either no epigynal field or the latter does not reach SO and/or EM.</p>
                <p><bold>Ontogeny of the epigyne.</bold> Pre-epigynes from four pseudo-orbweaverspecies were examined and found to exhibit apparently species-specific characteristics. Basic structures of adult epigynes can be recognised as primordial structures in the pre-epigynes. The following general ontogenetic process apparently leads from the primordial to the adult female copulatory organ: The anterior part of median septum (AS) and the anterior margins of lateral lobes (AML) extend strongly anterio-laterally.</p>
                <p>In the subadult female of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thorell, 1891 the transverse ridge/edge of the median septum (TR) is clearly recognisable as a broad “W”-shaped edge (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 69</xref>). In addition to the changes that happen from the subadult to adult stage described above, the median section of TR becomes strongly notched, together with a distinct median folding of AS. The result is the characteristic adult epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 55</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">108</xref>).</p>
                <p>In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thorell, 1895, AML run at more or less a right angle anteriorly and face each other. This can be recognised overall in pre-subadult, subadult and adult females (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 79–82</xref>). A clearly developed TR is only present in subadult females and adults. In pre-subadult females the TR is at best only slightly indicated (dotted line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 82</xref>).</p>
                <p>In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Doleschall, 1859), it is easy to identify corresponding structures of subadult females and adults, because the pre-epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–21</xref>) already strongly resembles the adult one (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 19</xref>). TR is present in subadult females. As on both sides TR is strongly curved anteriorly the characteristic broad-“nose-like” AS, like in adults (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 19</xref>), is already recognisable. By contrast, in pre-subadult females TR is at best very weakly developed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 22</xref>).</p>
                <p>In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pocock, 1899, the situation is very similar to that in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, although its pre-epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 74</xref>) slightly differs from that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 58</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">69</xref>) (see respective species descriptions).</p>
                <p><bold>Different developmental stages of pre-epigynes.</bold> Epigynes of adult females within the same species are similarly shaped (this is the reason why they can serve as an identification tool). In general this applies to the pre-epigynes, too. Yet, in one out of fifteen subadult females of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> the pre-epigyne was larger and somewhat differently shaped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 80</xref>) than generally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 81</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">94</xref>). It gives the impression that it may be further developed than the others. This phenomenon of a differing character state of the pre-epigyne does not mean that identification via the pre-epigyne is not possible. Because if the respective pre-epigyne is interpreted accurately, it is noticeable that it tends to fall along a developmental continuum together with the “regularly” shaped pre-epigynes, the pre-pre-epigynes of p.s.a. ♀♀ and the adult epigynes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 79–82</xref>). The s.a. ♀ of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 80</xref> is already more similar to the adult (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 79</xref>). Its pre-vulva already exhibits a clear division into a<!--PageBreak--> transparent section of internal duct system (TSI) and a strongly sclerotised one (SSI) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 86</xref>). Hence, it is clearly recognised as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                <p>In summary, pre-epigynes are easily distinguished from adult epigynes and apparently exhibit species-specific characters (note that one species pair <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>/<italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> is difficult to distinguish, but this is not surprising as it applies to the adults too; see respective species descriptions). In rare cases, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> pre-epigynes of particular subadult females may differ from the general type. But by the means of an accurate interpretation of those pre-epigynes the respective subadult females can be recognised as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, anyway. So, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> the pre-epigynes can be used as an identification tool. Here they are integrated in an identification key for the first time.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <sec sec-type="Psechridae Simon, 1890">
                <title><tp:taxon-name>Psechridae</tp:taxon-name> Simon, 1890</title>
                <p>In combination, the following characters are diagnostic for <tp:taxon-name>Psechridae</tp:taxon-name>: cribellum and calamistrum present; claw tufts distally on the 3-clawed tarsi; rectangular calamistrum comprising at least 3 rows of setae; indirect eyes with grate shaped tapetum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Simon 1892</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Homann 1950</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi 1982</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Griswold et al. 2005</xref>).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Key to genera">
                <title>Key to genera</title>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AME smaller than or as large as other eyes; opisthosoma ventrally mostly with white or beige median line; clypeus at least twice as high as diameter of AME; legs II and IV almost equal in length; build horizontal, dome-shaped sheet webs</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AME larger than all other eyes; opisthosoma ventrally mostly with pair of white or beige patches, never with light median line; clypeus not or just slightly higher than diameter of AME; leg IV shorter than leg II; adults build vertical pseudo-orbwebs</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Fecenia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        		<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Fecenia</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Simon, 1887</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Mezentia</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Thorell 1881</xref>: 203 (Type species: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mezentia angustata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Thorell, 1881); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Simon 1885</xref>: 451.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Simon 1887</xref>: 194 (homonym recognised, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mezentia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Stål, 1878 [<tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name>], replacement name established); Simon 1890: 80; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Simon 1892</xref>: 226; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234, 383 (syn. of type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia angustata</tp:taxon-name></italic> with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi 1982</xref>: 131; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Coddington 1990</xref>: 7; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Murphy and Murphy 2000</xref>: 264; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Griswold et al. 2005</xref>: 38.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species differ from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic> in the following characters: AME larger than all other eyes (in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, AME smaller or at most as large as other eyes); ventral side of opisthosoma centrally with pair of two white or beige patches, never with light median line like in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic>; clypeus flatter than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, not or just slightly higher than diameter of AME, hence cephalic part of carapace rather flat; leg IV always shorter than leg II (in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, leg IV slightly longer or as long as leg II); in contrast to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, males with RTA, RPA, VPA and MA; females with clearly divided median septum of epigyne, vulva always lacking spherical spermathecal heads (in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic> females, median septum simple and spherical spermathecal heads generally present).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>Medium sized to large <tp:taxon-name>Psechridae</tp:taxon-name>, body length in males: 7.2–13.2 mm; females: 7.7–20.2 mm. Cephalic part of carapace not distinctly narrower than broadest (thoracic) section. Anterior eye row recurved, posterior row straight (or at least almost straight). Chelicerae strong, shorter than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, basal article at most 2.5 times longer than broad. Cheliceral furrow with three promarginal and four retromarginal teeth. Basal article of chelicerae ventrally with long field of short, transverse striae. Ventral surface of former distally with semicircular lobe with long, curved hairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 6</xref>). Labium slightly longer than broad (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>). Gnathocoxae ca. twice as long as broad, distal section slightly broader than basal one (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>). Serrula with ca. 130–170 (size-dependant) very small, dark, apically blunt teeth, very densely arranged. Sternum slightly longer than broad, with pointed posterior ending and broad-angled (160°) anterior ending (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>). Pedipalp in females with single claw (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 51</xref>) containing 8–12 teeth. Legs extremely long in males (metatarsus I ca. three times longer than carapace (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">Fig. 117</xref>), relatively long in females (metatarsus I ca. 1.5–2 times longer than carapace, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 119</xref>). Leg formula 1243. Coxae of legs I, II broader than III, IV. Calamistrum dorso-retrolaterally on metatarsus IV consisting of 3–4 rows of setae (inner rows irregular). Spination of palp and legs: Highly variable within each species. Therefore, no species-specific and no common genus-specific spination pattern could be found. Consequently the spination will only be listed for the primary type specimen in the species descriptions. At the following positions spines are always absent: All patellae, dorsal surface of all tibiae and all metatarsi. Palpal femur spination varies from 000, 010, 110, 120, 130, which are the most common ones, to 141. Palpal patella, tibia and tarsus mostly without spines, if present, then very small, the most common patterns in this case are: patella 110, tibia 0100, tarsus 1004. Femora of legs I and II with even more variable spination, e.g. 100, 110, 210, 300, 310, 312, 320, 401, 412, 501, or 613. The most common one is 310. The same for those of legs III and IV, but here the number of spines is lower on average, most common is 010. The tibial spination pattern in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> includes a characteristic aspect: Legs I and II: retrolateral spines absent; legs III and IV: prolateral ones absent. At each opposite side the number of spines varies from 0 to 4, with legs I and II mostly having one to two spines more than III and IV. Ventrally at tibiae I and II there are mostly 6, at tibiae III and IV mostly 4 spines (paired spines at all tibiae). The spination of metatarsi is more conservative: I–II 2015, III 1025 or 1015, IV 1015 (ventrally the four proximal<!--PageBreak--> spines are paired). But there are exceptions, too. Colouration: Chelicerae, carapace and sternum yellowish brown to dark brown. In rare cases specimens exhibiting a darker carapace margin and a median longitudinal band. Sternum unicoloured. Legs from yellowish brown or light brown to brown, may be annulated. Tibiae I and II in some cases darker than other limbs/legs. Femora at distal third often with dark, annulated patches. Opisthosoma dorsally greyish-brown with yellowish patches. Heart region with darker lanceolate patch with light centre (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 119</xref>). Distal half of opisthosoma dorsally with two converging rows of dark brown spots. Lateral surface of opisthosoma is covered with 3–4 larger yellowish patches running diagonally. Opisthosoma ventrally dark brown to black, centrally with a pair of white to beige patches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Figs 116</xref>, 118), which differ intraspecifically in size and shape. In some cases those patches are fused, in extremely rare cases absent. Additionally, with white to beige transverse patch in front of spinnerets/cribellum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 116</xref>). The whole body is covered with grey hairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 116</xref>). Spinnerets are relatively short and conical, except for median ones, which are distinctly smaller, slender and cylindrical. Bipartite character clearly visible in posterior spinnerets. Copulatory organs: Male palp with almost round tegulum (T). Embolus (E) filiform, arising in prolateral half of tegulum (T) and at least twice as long as conductor (C). The latter membranous, mostly arising centrally on upper half of T (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>) and mostly shorter than median apophysis (MA). T next to E-base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>) with membranous process (MP). MA relatively large with general retrolateral direction (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 89</xref>). Cymbium distinctly broader than palpal tibia and patella (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 62</xref>). RTA differently shaped among the particular species, DRTA only present in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Simon, 1885) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 53–54</xref>). VPA often slightly bent anteriorly (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 87</xref>). RPA mostly small and inconspicuous. Palpal femur modifications, e.g. ventral bulge as present in some <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species, absent in all <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. Scopula dorsally on cymbium present in the same form in all <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Figs 99–101</xref>), but less distinct than in most <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. Female epigyne generally broader than long, with folded median septum (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 55</xref>). Anterior part of median septum (AS) larger than posterior part (PS). Anterior margins of lateral lobes (AML) iin some species strongly sclerotised (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">Fig. 108</xref>). Vulva simple, with internal duct system divided in three sections: Transversal section (TSI), strongly sclerotised section (SSI) and fertilisation duct (FD) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 83</xref>). Borderline (BL) between TSI and SSI clearly recognisable and often of taxonomic importance.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biological notes">
                        <title>Biological notes.</title>
                        <p>The pseudo-orbweavers are found in shrubs and trees, and also in the canopy (Deeleman, pers. comm.). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> suspends its vertical pseudo-orbweb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 120</xref>) in the vegetation, mostly between twigs. The web possesses an enrolled leaf at the hub serving as a retreat. This is true for adults and later instar juveniles of all <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. Earlier instars build an elongate cone-shaped tube as a retreat, which is disguised with small prey remains and soil- and leaf-particles. The very early instars do not even build a pseudo-orbweb, but a rather conical or dome-shaped web with the retreat at the top of the cone. This web can be found in the herb layer too (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Robinson and Lubin 1979</xref>). The pseudo-orbweb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 120</xref>) is more irregular than the webs of <!--PageBreak-->araneids and related families building orb-webs. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> there is no regular spiral of capturing thread(s) as in araneids etc. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, one cannot speak of a real spiral as the distance between the threads and their orientation differs. The irregularity applies to the radii too. In many cases they are not continuous.</p>
                        <p>Predatory behaviour was observed in the lab using several <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> specimens. In each case the spider was transferred to a large cylindrical glass (30 cm high, diameter 20 cm) with a leaf, already partly enrolled, placed at the bottom. The next day the leaf was suspended by threads in the middle of the glass, a day later it was already fixed at the top. The pseudo-orbweb was completed another day later. After placing a house fly into the lower area of the web it took a few seconds until the spider stretched its two forelegs out of the retreat, and after ca. 1 minute it came out. The fly was grabbed with the chelicerae and immediately dragged into the retreat. A few centimetres before the leaf entrance the spider turned and crawled backwards into the retreat. In the case of larger prey items like crickets, the spider was extremely shy and careful. It took two or three attempts of coming out of the leaf and escaping back into it, sometimes interrupted by 5–15 minutes within the retreat. During the last attempt the cricket was bitten for about 7 minutes at the capturing site of the web before it was dragged to the retreat. Binding behaviour, as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Robinson and Lubin (1979)</xref>, was observed after providing an even larger cricket. But in addition to their observations I could recognise that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> took threads out of the web, too, in order to bind its prey. An attack-wrapping behaviour like in <tp:taxon-name>Araneidae</tp:taxon-name> does not exist.</p>
                        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Robinson and Lubin (1979)</xref> observed the mating behaviour of a male <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (however in their publication identified as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp.) approaching the female retreat, which I corroborate observing (raised) <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Champasak Province, Laos (males SB 509, 510 and females SB 486–487, 511, 514, see list in description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, additional material examined). These were maintained in cylindrical glasses (see above) and fed on house flies and crickets. A few days after one male's final moult its web was reduced to a few frame threads. In two corners of that thread-framework sperm webs were found (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23">Fig. 123</xref>). The bulb filling procedure was not observed. A female was transferred into a terrarium (30 cm high, diameter 20 cm) and offered a small “cone” of transparent film as retreat, which was accepted and later on integrated in the new web. In the respective trial the male was placed into the female's terrarium. After a while it approached the retreat from the top of the terrarium by roping down onto it. There it tapped and stroked the retreat carefully (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23">Fig. 121</xref>). Later on it moved to the margin of the opening of the leaf retreat and repeated this behaviour. After some more repeats it stayed there motionless. Unfortunately, neither the moment of entering the retreat nor the copulation itself could be observed. The next day the male was sitting within the leaf retreat, together with the female (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23">Fig. 122</xref>). In another trial a raised <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> male from Flores (SB 196, see description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, list of additional material examined) was transferred to a terrarium with an already adult conspecific female from Bali. The behaviour was the same as described above, but in this case the next day saw the<!--PageBreak--> male half digested lying at the bottom underneath the retreat, which means it had been attacked and killed by the female. In one further trial a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> male was put into the terrarium of a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> female<italic>.</italic> The approaching behaviour upon the leaf was executed up to the point when the male reached the leaf opening. Here he turned and disappeared to an upper corner of the terrarium and stayed there motionless for more than one day.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Key to species">
                <title>Key to species:</title>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male (that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> unknown)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female (subadult one of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> unknown)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRTA absent, MA prominent, in some species massive</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prominent DRTA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 53–54</xref>) present, MA slender and rather inconspicuous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 53</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTA short, at most ½ the width of palpal tibia, MA shorter than width of T</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTA at least as long as width of palpal tibia, MA large and massive, at least as long as width of T (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTA knobbed, almost as broad as long, E without bEA, VPA arising proximally on patella (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 60–61</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RTA rather slender, longer than broad, E with distinct, pointed bEA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 89</xref>), VPA arising centrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 87–88</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AML distinctly visible, AS with similar colour as surrounding parts of epigyne</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AML hardly visible, posterior half of AS distinctly darker than surrounding parts of epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 48</xref>, 114)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AML converging anteriorly and surrounding epigynal pit partly, pre-epigyne with TR running completely from left to right AML, in pre-vulva distance between centres of pre-receptacula &gt; 3 x diameter of one pre-receptaculum</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AML diverging anteriorly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), in pre-epigyne gaps between TR and AML (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–21</xref>), in pre-vulva distance between centres of pre-receptacula &lt; 3 x diameter of one pre-receptaculum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 23–24</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AS with longitudinal folding, the latter mostly anteriorly pointed (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 55</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">76</xref>), TR with distinct notch, pre-epigyne with double curved TR, the latter broadly W-shaped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 69</xref>), in general appearance pre-epigyne looking crown-shaped, pre-receptaculum bulbous/spherical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figs 67–68</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AS flat (at least anteriorly), without longitudinal folding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 79</xref>), TR without notch, pre-epigyne with continuous TR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 81</xref>), the latter slightly curved, pre-receptaculum with lateral extension (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 85</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In vulva BL running almost longitudinal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 77</xref>), lateral prongs of the “crown” in pre-epigyne narrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 74</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">In vulva BL running +/- transversal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 56</xref>), lateral prongs of the “crown” in pre-epigyne not distinctly narrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 58</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">69</xref>)</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"></td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Fecenia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">ochracea</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Fecenia_ochracea</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>(Doleschall, 1859)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">–47</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">96</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">102–104</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">118</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Tegenaria ochracea</tp:taxon-name><comment> Doleschall, 1859: 50, pl. 8, fig. 8 (Description of ♀), [Holotype ♀ (SB 94) from INDONESIA: Maluku Prov.: Ambon Isl.; C. L. Doleschall leg. 1855–1858; NHMW 12∙389, examined]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">Thorell 1878</xref>: 302 (sub <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tegenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> [?]); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Thorell 1881</xref>: 694 (sub <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tegenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> [?]).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Mezentia angustata</tp:taxon-name><comment> Thorell, 1881: 204 (Description of ♀), [Holotype ♀ (SB 460) from INDONESIA: Maluku Utara Prov.: Ternate Isl. next to Halmahera; Prof. O. Beccari leg. 1872–1877; MCSN, examined]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Simon 1885</xref>: 451.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Mezentia ochracea</tp:taxon-name><comment> - <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Simon 1885</xref>: 451 (Transfer from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tegenaria</tp:taxon-name></italic>).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name><comment> - <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Simon 1887</xref>: 194 (Formal transfer from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mezentia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, preoccupied by Stål, 1878 in <tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name>, replacement name <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic>); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Simon 1892</xref>: 226; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">Simon 1906</xref>: 287, fig. 1B (Illustration of ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kulczyński 1908</xref>: 570; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Reimoser 1936</xref>: 407; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi 1982</xref>: 133, figs 68–79, 90 (Illustration of ♂ and ♀♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Murphy 1986</xref>: 65; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Griswold 1993</xref>: 7; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Murphy and Murphy 2000</xref>: plate 21, fig. 5 (Photo of ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Song et al. 2002</xref>: 373 (listed as fauna element of Singapore; doubtful!, to date no records from Singapore).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia angustata</tp:taxon-name><comment> - <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Simon 1887</xref>: 194 (Formal transfer from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mezentia</tp:taxon-name></italic>); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Simon 1892</xref>: 226; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Pocock 1900</xref>: 212; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kulczyński 1908</xref>: 570; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Petrunkevitch 1928</xref>: 90; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Reimoser 1936</xref>: 407; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Chrysanthus 1967</xref>: 102, figs 55–57, 60–64 (Description of ♂, illustration of ♂ and ♀♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234 (Synonymy).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia maforensis</tp:taxon-name><comment> Simon, 1906: 287, fig. 1A (Description of ♀), [Holotype ♀ (SB 464) from INDONESIA: Irian Jaya Barat Prov.: Numfor Isl., formerly Mafor; A. Raffray leg.; MNHN AR185, examined]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kulczyński 1908</xref>: 570; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Strand 1915</xref>: 191 (Description of ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Reimoser 1936</xref>: 407; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Chrysanthus 1967</xref>: 104, fig. 65 (Illustration of ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234 (Synonymy).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia montana</tp:taxon-name><comment> Kulczyński, 1910: 389, pl. 17, fig. 1 (Description of ♀), [Holotype ♀ (SB 461) from PAPUA NEW GUINEA: East New Britain Prov.: Baining Mountains; K. Rechinger leg. 1906; NHMW 12∙388, examined], <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Reimoser 1936</xref>: 407, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234 (Synonymy).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia oblonga</tp:taxon-name><comment> Rainbow, 1913: 7, fig. 5 (Description of ♀), [Holotype ♀ from SOLOMON ISLANDS: Western Prov., Shortland Island Group, Island of Howla; W. W. Froggatt leg. ca. 1900; AMS, lost (Milledge, AMS, pers. comm.), thus not examined]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Reimoser 1936</xref>: 407; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234 (Synonymy).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cinerea</tp:taxon-name><comment> Hogg, 1914: 56 (Description of ♀), [Holotype ♀ (SB 404) from INDONESIA: Papua Prov.: Possibly near Mount Utakwa; A.F.R. Wollaston leg. 1912–1913 (Wollaston Expedition in Dutch New Guinea); NHM 1921·3·24·9, examined]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Hogg 1915</xref>: 437, fig. 23 (Illustration of ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Reimoser 1936</xref>: 407; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234 (Synonymy).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia buruana</tp:taxon-name><comment> Reimoser, 1936: 406, fig. 1 (Description of ♂ ♀), [Lectotype ♀ (SB 418), paralectotype ♂ (SB 417) by designation of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi (1982</xref>: 134), both from<!--PageBreak--> INDONESIA: Maluku Prov.: Buru Isl., station 1; L.J. Toxopeus leg. 1921; ZMA, examined]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Chrysanthus 1967</xref>: 104, figs 66–67 (Illustration of ♂ and ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234 (Synonymy).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Note on the holotype of Tegenaria ochracea">
                        <title>Note on the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tegenaria ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</title>
                        <p>The first description of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Doleschall (1859)</xref> lacks any remarks concerning deposition of the type specimen. Generally, material recorded by naturalists of the “Natuurkundige Vereeniging in Nederlandsch Indie” has been deposited either in RMNH or in ZMA. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen (1967)</xref> stated that the type deposition was unknown (to him). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi (1982)</xref> mentioned a personal communication from Van der Hammen, the curator of the arachnid collection in RMNH at that time, who stated that the type was lost. At present, the colleagues of the arachnid collection of RMNH still cannot find any type material of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tegenaria ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic> there (K. van Dorp and J. Miller, RMNH, pers. comm.). In the arachnid collection of ZMA there is also <!--PageBreak-->no type specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tegenaria ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (B. Brugge, pers. comm.). During a stay at the natural history museum in Vienna in April 2009 I recognised a syntype specimen of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus argentatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Doleschall, 1857). Both <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen (1967)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi (1982)</xref> believed that the syntypes of this species had been lost. However, for this latter species found on Ambon, too, and recorded and described by the same author just two years before, it is evident that at least a part of the original syntype series was once deposited in RMNH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Van Hasselt 1877</xref>). After consulting Jürgen Gruber and Verena Stagl (both NHMW) I learned that Doleschall sent only a part of his spider- and insect material collected on Ambon to the museum in Leiden; a large part of the material was sent to the museum in Vienna (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Stagl 1999</xref>). In the spider collection of NHMW I found a <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> female (SB 94), which was labelled “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> - Insel Ambon” (oldest label). According to Gruber (pers. comm.) the handwriting is that of E. Reimoser, the curator of NHMW from 1923–1940. It is well known that Reimoser often discarded old labels and substituted them with new ones (Gruber pers. comm.). It is most likely that in this case the same had happened. Assuming that the handwriting on the original label from Doleschall was unclear, it is likely that Reimoser discarded that label, determined the female as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> and just added the locality on the new label. Anyway, it is evident that before 1950 nobody other than Doleschall sent spider material from the island Ambon to the natural history museum in Vienna (Gruber pers. comm.). Hence, the female SB 94 (see synonymy list above) can be considered the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tegenaria ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Additional material examined">
                        <title>Additional material examined.</title>
                        <p>(4 ♂♂, 73 ♀♀, 4 s.a. ♂♂, 7 s.a. ♀♀, 2 p.s.a. ♀♀, 11 juvenile specimens)<bold>. PHILIPPINES:</bold> Luzon: Laguna Prov.: Los Baños; Baker leg.; 1 ♀ (SB 153), MCZ 82529. <bold>MALAYSIA:</bold> <bold>Borneo: Sabah Prov.:</bold> Kinabalu N.P., Poring Hot Springs, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">5°02'N, 116°42'E</named-content>, 600–700 m, primary forest; A. Floren leg. 03.III.1996 by canopy fogging “ridge”; 1 ♀ (SB 518), Deeleman Coll. in RMNH. <bold>INDONESIA:</bold> <bold>Sumatra: Nanggroe Aceh Darussalam Prov.:</bold> Ketambe, Gunung Leuser N.P., <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">3°51'N, 97°37'E</named-content>, ca. 1300 m, primary forest, from leaves; S. Djojosudharmo leg. 03.V.1986; 1 ♀ (SB 127), Deeleman Coll. in RMNH. <bold>Halmahera: Maluku Utara Prov.:</bold> Jailolo Distr., Kampung Pasir Putih, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">0°53'N, 127°41'E</named-content>; A.C. Messer, P.M. Taylor leg. 1981; 1 ♂ (SB 187), USNM. <bold>Maluku Utara Prov.:</bold> Ternate Isl.; A. Raffray leg.; 1 s.a. ♂ (SB 465), MNHN. <bold>Maluku Prov.:</bold> Buru Isl., station 1; L. J. Toxopeus leg. 1921; 1 ♀ (SB 419), ZMA. Ceram Isl.; 6 ♀♀ (SB 470–473, 475–476), 1 s.a. ♂ (SB 467), 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 469), 1 juv. (SB 468), MNHN AR193. Ambon Isl.; 1 ♀ (SB 474), MNHN AR193. Aru Isls; 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 80), Roewer Coll. 1819 in SMF. <bold>Irian Jaya Barat Prov.:</bold> Manokwari, Dorey; A. Raffray leg.; 1 ♀ (SB 466), MNHN. <bold>Papua Prov.:</bold> Sentani; leg. IV. 1903; 1 ♀ (SB 661), MIZ. Mindiptana; B. Monulf leg. 1958-1965; 3 ♀♀ (SB 96-98) Coll.-No. 8474, 1 ♂ (SB 95), 1 ♀ (SB 442) Coll.-No. 8476, all RMNH. Merauke; B. Monulf leg. 1956-1957; 16 ♀♀ (SB 426-441) Coll.-No. 8475, 8 ♀♀ (SB 443-447, 450, 452-453), 1 s.a. ♂ (SB 444) Coll.-No. 8477, 4 ♀♀ (SB 99-102) Coll.-No. 8478, all RMNH. <bold>Java: Jawa Barat Prov.:</bold> Gunung Gedeh N.P., Cibodas Nature Reserve, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">6°44'S, 107°00'E</named-content>, 1450 m; S. Djojosudharmo leg. 06.XII.1986; 1 ♂ (SB 120), Deeleman Coll. in RMNH. <bold>PAPUA NEW GUINEA:</bold> <bold>West Sepik Prov.:</bold> Aitape, Seleo; 1 ♀ (SB 662), MIZ. <bold>Morobe Prov.:</bold> Wau, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">7°20'S, 146°43'E</named-content>; M. Robinson leg. 10–15.IV.1977, 5 ♀♀<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--> (SB 163–166, 484), 2 juvs (SB 482–483); H. Levi, Y. Lubin, M. Robinson leg. 07.–12.III.1979, MCZ 82521, 5 ♀♀ (SB 156–157, 162, 479–480), 1 s.a. ♀ (SB158), MCZ 82533, J.E. Carico leg. 22.–29.VI.1982, 2 ♀♀ (SB 154–155), 1 p.s.a. ♀ (SB 478), 1 juv. (SB 477), MCZ 82531. Wau; <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">7°20'S, 146°43'E</named-content>; J.E. Carico leg. 05.–06.VII.1982; 1 ♂ (SB 180), USNM. Wau, Ecology Center; E.I. Schlinger leg. 17.II.1978; ♀ (SB 947), CAS 9032225. <bold>East New Britain Prov.:</bold> “Putie Bucht”, South coast; Dr G. Ducker leg. 05.-19.II.1909, Hamburg Südsee Exp., No. 300; 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 896), ZMH. Jacquinot Bay, ca. <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">5°34'S, 151°26'E</named-content>; Dr G. Duncker leg. 19.-20.XII.1908, Hamburg Südsee Exp., No. 261; 2 ♀♀ (SB 892-893), ZMH. Keravat, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">4°21'S, 152°07'E</named-content>, 300 m, lowland tropical rain forest; I. Agnarsson leg. 03.–07.IV.2009; 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 540), 1 juv. (SB 541), SMF. Keravat, Laes; Y.D. Lubin leg. 01.VII.1980; 1 ♀ (SB 167), MCZ 82525. Kokopo, Ralum, ca. <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">4°20'S, 152°15'E</named-content>, ca. 50 m; F. Dahl leg. 12.X.1896; 1 ♀ (SB 801), 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 794), 4 juvs (SB 795–800), ZMB 15472, 19244–19248. “Dörper Spitze, S.O. Bucht”: Dr G. Duncker leg. 14.V.1909, Hamburg Südsee Exp., No. 534; 2 ♀♀ (SB 894-895), ZMH. <bold>New Ireland Prov.:</bold> New Ireland, Lemkamin; Nocna Dan Exp. 1961-1962; 1 ♀ (SB 887), ZMUC 5728. Feni Isls, Ambitle Isl. (Anir); E. Wolf leg. 04.V.1909; 1 ♀ (SB 86), SMF 2769/1. <bold>Papua New Guinea [no other locality data]:</bold> L. Biro leg.; 1 ♀ (SB 668), 1 p.s.a. ♀ (SB 669), 2 juvs (SB 670-671), MIZ 46/51U. <bold>SOLOMON ISLANDS:</bold> New Georgia Group; J.F. P. leg. 1965; 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 392), NHM. Auki; W.M. Mann leg. 1916; 3 ♀♀ (SB 159–161), MCZ 82524.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Distinguished from other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species by the epigyne with diverging anterior margins of lateral lobes (AML) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Males differ from all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species by RTA at least as long as width of palpal tibia, MA large and massive, at least as long as width of tegulum (T) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>MALE:Body and eye measurements. Carapace length 4.2–4.7, carapace width 2.8–3.4, anterior width of carapace 1.7–2.1, opisthosoma length 4.8–7.1, opisthosoma width 2.0–3.3. Eyes: AME 0.28–0.33, ALE 0.20–0.23, PME 0.20–0.23, PLE 0.20–0.22, AME–AME 0.17–0.28, AME–ALE 0.06–0.13, PME–PME 0.22–0.28, PME–PLE 0.28–0.42, AME–PME 0.14–0.17, ALE–PLE 0.11–0.17, clypeus height at AME 0.28–0.42, at ALE 0.21–0.34. Measurements of palp and legs. Palp 5.2–6.1 [2.0–2.4, 0.8–1.1, 0.7–0.8, 1.3–1.8], I 46.6–55.9 [12.6–15.6, 1.9–2.2, 12.3–15.5, 13.4–16.9, 5.2–5.7], II 21.7–26.8 [5.8–6.7, 1.5–1.8, 6.0–7.6, 6.0–7.0, 2.4–3.0], III 12.1–14.2 [3.4–4.1, 1.1–1.4, 3.0–3.6, 3.1, 1.4–1.7], IV 20.6–24.0 [5.4–6.8, 1.4, 5.4–6.5, 6.2–6.5, 2.2–2.6]. Leg formula: 1243. Copulatory organ: Ventral patellar apophysis (VPA) arising in basal third of palpal patella (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 11</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">18</xref>), retrolateral patellar apophysis (RPA) mostly inconspicuous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">17</xref>). RTA distally not or just slightly broader than basally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>). MA ventrally in basal third with distinct bulge (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 8–9</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">96</xref>). Distal part of MA bent prolaterally. General direction of MA 1:00 or 1:30-o'clock. Embolus (E) arising in ca. 9-o'clock-position on T, at most as long as width of T (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–10</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">96</xref>). T with corner-like lobe ventrally in prolateral half, T slightly longer than broad. MP with differing lengths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–10</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">96</xref>). Conductor (C) small, arising centrally in upper third of T.</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->FEMALE(Measurements of holotype (SB 94) first, those of other specimens given as ranges in parentheses; Holotype misses both legs I as well as all limbs of legs IV from tibia on): Body and eye measurements. Carapace length 6.4 (3.2–6.9), carapace width 4.2 (2.2–4.3), anterior width of carapace 3.0 (1.7–3.1), opisthosoma length 9.1 (4.5–9.3), opisthosoma width 4.8 (2.2–5.2). Eyes: AME 0.33 (0.20–0.33), ALE 0.23 (0.15–0.23), PME 0.23 (0.15–0.23), PLE 0.25 (0.15–0.25), AME–AME 0.29 (0.22–0.29), AME–ALE 0.17 (0.09–0.17), PME–PME 0.36 (0.24–0.36), PME–PLE 0.48 (0.33–0.48), AME–PME 0.30 (0.15–0.30), ALE–PLE 0.24 (0.14–0.24), clypeus height at AME 0.44 (0.27–0.44), at ALE 0.42 (0.20–0.42). Measurements of palp and legs. Palp 6.3 (3.5–6.7) [2.2 (1.3–2.4), 1.1 (0.5–1.1), 1.2 (0.7–1.3), 1.8 (1.0–2.0)], I 17.2–40.7 [4.6–10.8, 1.3–2.9, 4.7.7–11.3, 4.5–11.4, 2.1–4.3], II 23.5 (10.8–24.5) [6.4 (3.0–6.6), 2.2 (1.1–2.2), 6.4 (2.9–6.8), 5.9 (2.50–6.2), 2.6 (1.3–2.7)], III 13.6 (6.6–14.6) [4.0 (1.9–4.3), 1.6 (0.8–1.7), 3.3 (1.5–3.5), 3.2 (1.5–3.4), 1.5 (0.9–1.7)], IV 10.0–21.4 [5.7 (2.7–5.8), 2.0 (1.0–2.1), 2.6–5.8, 2.5–5.3, 1.2–2.4]. Leg formula: 1243. Palpal claw with 10 (8–11) teeth. Spination (holotype from Ambon [except for leg I as well as tibia and metatarsus of leg IV, which are lost in holotype: spination of SB 474 from Ambon is listed instead]). Palp: 110, 000, 0000, 0000; legs: femur I 533(423), II 313, III 213, IV 111; patella I–IV 000; tibia I 3008, II 3006, III 0025, IV 2024; metatarsus I 2025, II 2025, III 1025, IV 1026. Copulatory organ: Anterior part of median septum (AS) of epigyne broad-“nose-like”, slightly broader than its posterior part (PS). Lateral lobes massive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">102</xref>). Epigynal muscle sigillae (EM) mostly integrated in epigynal field (EF). Slit sense organs (SO) mostly outside EF. Vulva with relatively short and narrow transparent section of internal duct system (TSI). Strongly sclerotised section (SSI) compact, duct with two curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2–3</xref>), apex of first one directed posterio-medially, of second anterio-laterally. Primordial copulatory organs: Pre-epigyne: Already strongly resembling the adult epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–21</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">104</xref>). All major structures present in adult epigyne are recognizable in the pre-epigyne, too (of course much smaller). Epigynal field not or only poorly developed, EM far outside epigynal field (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 21</xref>). Pre-pre-epigyne (antepenultimate instar): AML far shorter than in pre-epigyne and transversal ridge/edge of median septum (TR) hardly recognisable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 22</xref>, fine dotted line). Pre-vulva: Pre-receptacula bulbous/spherical and relatively close to each other. Distance between centres of pre-receptacula less than 3 times of diameter of one pre-receptaculum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 23–24</xref>). Colouration: Male and female: As described for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> in general, but white to beige patch in front of spinnerets may be rather unclear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">Fig. 118</xref>), smaller or even absent. In one (SB 98, from Mindiptana, Eastern Papua Province, Indonesia) out of 103 specimens the light patches ventrally on opisthosoma are absent. Variation of copulatory organs: Among male specimens examined, cymbium differing at most slightly in length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 11–18</xref>). In some specimens MA may be more massive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 10</xref>) or T slightly broader (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9–10</xref>) than in others. Shape of prolatero-ventral lobe variable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–10</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">96</xref>). One specimen differing slightly more from the paralectotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia buruana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 8</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">16</xref>) from Buru island (which is the closest male record to the type locality, Ambon) than the others. This is SB 95 from Mindiptana, Easter<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->n Papua Province of Indonesia: MA directed to 2:30-o'clock position (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 9</xref>), embolus (E) slightly longer than in the other males examined, RTA broadest distally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 9</xref>). Additionally, T protruding a bit more out of cymbium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 13</xref>) than in the other specimens. In females intraspecific variation is higher. The shape of AS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">27</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">–33</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">102</xref>) as well as the course of AML are highly variable. Number of SO varying among specimens without geographical dependence. Vulvae of the specimens examined show less variation than epigynes. The initial part of SSI may be slightly more prominent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 38</xref>). Further on, the position of SSI seems slightly shifted in some specimens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 25</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">34</xref>). Pre-epigynes also differing in shape of AS and in course of AML (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 20–21</xref>). Based on almost 80 females examined, all the variation described so far is neither geographically fixed, nor are there distinct forms of variants which recur here and there. In some cases females from exactly the same recording site show clear differences. And on the other hand females which are recorded in different localities, partly hundreds of km away from each other, look strikingly similar. Anyway, the following ‘form of females' has to be discussed separately (see remark below).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>The vulvae of the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cinerea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 404) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 40</xref>) and the specimens recorded from Mindiptana, Eastern Papua Province of Indonesia (SB 96–98, 442) (SB 98 illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 44</xref>) differ from all other females examined. The duct of SSI is somewhat longer, especially the second curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 40</xref>, 44). Consequently, the course of the internal duct system of these specimens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 41</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">45</xref>) differs from the remaining <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic> females (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">35, 37, 39</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">43, 47</xref>). However, the vulvae of the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cinerea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 404) and female SB 98 do not correspond completely. In SB 404 the second curve of SSI protrudes more strongly in a lateral direction. In one specimen (SB 97, not illustrated) from Mindiptana the second curve of SSI is a bit shorter than in the others from this locality. The epigynes of SB 96-98, 404 and 442 differ in shape (SB 404: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 28</xref>; SB 98: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 32</xref>; others not illustrated). According to the differences in the shape of the vulvae (see above) it may be justified to revalidate <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cinerea</tp:taxon-name></italic> Hogg, 1914. However, the difference is little (second curve of SSI slightly longer than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and thus does not provide evidence for a clear species delimitation; especially considering that in one specimen from Mindiptana the second curve is again slightly shorter. In addition, if the females from Mindiptana should be regarded as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cinerea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, then the male (SB 95, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">17</xref>), which was recorded from exactly the same locality, should be placed here, too. However, as discussed above, the palp structures of this male only slightly differ from the ones of other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic> males (though these differences are worth mentioning as intraspecific variation). Moreover, no males have been recorded from the type locality of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cinerea</tp:taxon-name></italic> so far. Consequently, I refrain from changing the taxonomic status of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cinerea</tp:taxon-name></italic>. More material from the type locality of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cinerea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, especially males may enlighten this “problematic case”.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Disribution">
                        <title>Disribution.</title>
                        <p>Philippines, Malaysia [Borneo], Indonesia [Sumatra, Borneo, Moluccas, West Papua, Java], Papua New Guinea, Solomon Islands, Australia [Northern Queensland].</p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 1–6.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ holotype (SB 94) from Ambon, Indonesia <bold>1</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>2</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>3</bold> Schematic course of internal duct system, dorsal view <bold>4</bold> Sternum, ventral view <bold>5</bold> Labium and gnathocoxae, ventral view. <bold>6</bold> Right chelicere, ventral view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 7–10.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, left ♂ palp, ventral view <bold>7</bold> SB 120 from Java, Indonesia <bold>8</bold> Paralectotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia buruana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 417) from Buru, Indonesia <bold>9</bold> SB 95 from Mindiptana, Indonesia <bold>10</bold> SB 180 from Wau, Papua New Guinea. Remark on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref> Embolus slipped behind conductor. C = Conductor; CA = Cymbium alveolus; E = Embolus; MA = Median apophysis; MP = Membranous process of tegulum; RPA = Retrolateral patellar apophysis; RTA = Retrolateral tibial apophysis; T = Tegulum; VPA = Ventral patellar apophysis.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 11–14.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, left ♂ palp, prolateral view <bold>11</bold> SB 120 from Java, Indonesia <bold>12</bold> Paralectotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia buruana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 417) from Buru, Indonesia <bold>13</bold> SB 95 from Mindiptana, Indonesia <bold>14</bold> SB 180 from Wau, Papua New Guinea.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 15–18.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, left ♂ palp, retrolateral view <bold>15</bold> SB 120 from Java, Indonesia <bold>16</bold> Paralectotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia buruana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 417) from Buru, Indonesia. <bold>17</bold> SB 95 from Mindiptana, Indonesia <bold>18</bold> SB 180 from Wau, Papua New Guinea.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 19–26.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ copulatory organ/primordial copulatory organ <bold>19, 25–26</bold> Holotype ♀ of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia montana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 461) from East New Britain <bold>20, 23</bold> s.a. ♀ SB 540 from East New Britain <bold>21, 24</bold> s.a. ♀ SB 158 from Wau, Papua New Guinea <bold>22</bold> p.s.a. ♀ SB 669 from New Guinea <bold>19</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>20–21</bold> Pre-epigyne, ventral view <bold>22</bold> Pre-pre-epigyne, ventral view <bold>23–24</bold> Pre-vulva, dorsal view <bold>25</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>26</bold> Course of internal duct system.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Fecenia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">macilenta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Fecenia_macilenta</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>(Simon, 1885)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 48–54</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">95, 101</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">114–115</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Mezentia macilenta</tp:taxon-name><comment> Simon, 1885: 451, pl. 10, fig. 17 (Description and illustration of ♂), [Holotype ♂ (SB 395) from MALAYSIA: Perak Prov. (Malacca): Region of Ipoh, Kinta river valley; M.J. de Morgan leg. 1884; MNHN AR5164, examined].</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name><comment> - <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Simon 1887</xref>: 194 (Formal transfer from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mezentia</tp:taxon-name></italic>, preoccupied by Stål, 1878 in <tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name>, replacement name <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic>); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Simon 1892</xref>: 223, figs 171–172 (Illustration of ♂); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kulczyński 1908</xref>: 570; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Reimoser 1936</xref>: 406; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi 1982</xref>: 136, figs 83–87, ad part, figs 84–85 (Illustration of ♂), figs 83, 86–87 misidentified; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Murphy 1986</xref>: 65, figs 1–2 (Description and illustration of ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Coddington 1990</xref>: 10, fig. 18 (Illustration of ♂); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Murphy and Murphy 2000</xref>: plate 21, fig. 6 (photo of ♀).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Additional material examined">
                        <title>Additional material examined.</title>
                        <p>(1 ♂, 2 ♀♀). <bold>MALAYSIA:</bold> <bold>Selangor Prov.:</bold> Banting; W. Corley leg. VIII. 1981; 1 ♂ (SB389), 1 ♀ (SB 390), NHM. <bold>INDONESIA:</bold> <bold>Sumatra: Sumatera Barat Prov.:</bold> Panti (Road to Lubuk Sikaping &amp; Bukittinggi), Rimba Panti Nature Reserve, primary rainforest; C. Deeleman leg.; 1 ♀ (SB 124), Deeleman Coll. in RMNH.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Males differ from other species by prominent dorso-retrolateral tibial apophysis (DRTA) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 53–54</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">95</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">101</xref>) and slender and rather inconspicuous median apophysis (MA) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 53</xref>). Furthermore, ventral patellar apophysis (VPA) larger and retrolateral patellar apophysis (RPA) extending more clearly than in all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 53–54</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">95</xref>). Females distinguished from other species by epigyne with anterior margins of lateral lobes (AML) hardly visible and by posterior half of anterior part of median septum (AS) being distinctly darker than surrounding parts of epigyne (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">Fig. 114</xref>). Moreover, AS with permanent semicircular posterior half (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 48</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">114</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>MALE(Holotype (SB 395) is the largest of the males examined; consequently its measurements appear as maximum in each range. Eye measurements differ only insignificantly, so only those of the Holotype are listed): Body and eye measurements. Carapace length 5.4–5.8, carapace width 3.5–4.1, anterior width of carapace 2.3–2.7, opisthosoma length 5.4–7.4, opisthosoma width 2.8–3.2. Eyes: AME 0.47, ALE 0.34, PME 0.31, PLE 0.29, AME–AME 0.27, AME–ALE 0.08, PME–PME 0.35, PME–PLE 0.40, AME–PME 0.15, ALE–PLE 0.19, clypeus height at AME 0.67, at ALE 0.54. Measurements of palp and legs. Palp 7.3–8.5 [2.8–3.3, 1.2–1.4, 1.1–1.3, 2.2–2.5], I 53.5–67.4 [14.7–18.8, 2.3, 15.3–19.2, 16.7–19.9, 4.5–7.2], II 27.9–35.0 [7.5–9.4, 1.9–2.2, 7.7–9.7, 7.7–9.9, 3.1–3.8], III 15.9–19.4 [4.6–5.6, 1.5–1.7, 3.8–4.8, 4.1–4.9, 1.9–2.4], IV 25.1–30.9 [6.8–8.3, 1.7–2.0, 6.4–8.2, 7.4–8.9, 2.8–3.5]. Leg formula: 1243. Male chelicerae differing from general appearance of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic>: Basal limb ca. 4 times longer than broad. Spination (holotype from Kinta river, Malaysia). Palp: without any spines; legs: femur I 410(300), II 100, III 010, IV 001; patella I–IV 000; tibia I–II 2004, III 0000(0001), IV 001<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->3; metatarsus I 3014(1014), II 1015, III 1015(1014), IV 1015. Copulatory organ: Ventral patellar apophysis (VPA) arising centrally on palpal patella (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 52, 54</xref>), RTA small, less than 1/3 of the length of the massive DRTA. Median apophysis (MA) distally slightly bent. General direction of MA is 12:30 or 1:00-o'clock. Embolus (E) arising in ca. 6:30-o'clock-position on tegulum (T), broader than in all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species and almost twice as long as width of T. The latter slightly longer than broad. Membranous process (MP) of tegulum directed proximally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 53</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">95</xref>). Conductor (C) longer than MA, arising centrally in upper third of T.</p>
                        <p>FEMALE (The two females examined differ not or only marginally in almost all measurements, so only those of SB 390 are listed, except for opisthosoma measurements [ranges, SB 390 from Banting, Malaysia first]): Body and eye measurements. Carapace length 5.3, carapace width 3.7, anterior width of carapace 3.0, opisthosoma length 7.6–8.3, opisthosoma width 4.5–4.9. Eyes: AME 0.34, ALE 0.27, PME 0.27, PLE 0.22, AME–AME 0.26, AME–ALE 0.12, PME–PME 0.34, PME–PLE 0.46, AME–PME 0.22, ALE–PLE 0.24, clypeus height at AME 0.44, at ALE 0.41. Measurements of palp and legs. Palp 5.9 [2.0, 1.0, 1.0, 1.9], I 30.2 [8.1, 2.3, 8.5, 7.9, 3.4], II 19.7 [5.4, 1.9, 5.3, 4.7, 2.4], III 12.4 [3.6, 1.5, 2.9, 2.8, 1.6], IV 17.7 [4.9, 1.7, 4.6, 4.4, 2.1]. Leg formula: 1243. Palpal claw with 12 teeth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 51</xref>). Copulatory organ: Anterior part of median septum (AS) of epigyne “nose-like”, broader than posterior part (PS) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 48</xref>). Lateral lobes voluminous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 48</xref>, 114). Epigynal muscle sigilla (EM) integrated in epigynal field. Slit sense organs (SO) outside epigynal field. Vulva with voluminous sclerotised section of internal duct system (SSI) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 49</xref>) and short and narrow transparent section (TSI), which is in dorsal view partly covered by SSI. The latter almost in contact with each other. Duct of SSI with three curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 50</xref>). Fertilisation duct (FD) narrow. Colouration: Male and female: As described for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> in general, but white to beige patch in front of spinnerets in one female rather unclear and smaller. Variation of copulatory organs: Males varying only insignificantly. Females: In female from Banting, Malaysia (SB 390) dark section of AS reaching further anteriorly (dotted line within AS in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 48</xref>) than in SB 124 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">Fig. 114</xref>). Number of SO among specimens varies from two to four. Distance between SSI slightly longer in SB 124 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">Fig. 115</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Disribution">
                        <title>Disribution.</title>
                        <p>Malaysia, Indonesia [Sumatra].</p>
                        <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 27–28.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ epigyne, ventral view <bold>27</bold> Holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia maforensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 464) from Northwestern Irian Jaya, Indonesia <bold>28</bold> Holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cinerea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 404) from Southern Papua Prov., Indonesia.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 29-30. </label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> ochracea, ♀ epigyne, ventral view <bold>29</bold> Holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia angustata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 460) from Ternate, Indonesia <bold>30</bold> Lectotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia buruana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 418) from Buru, Indonesia.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 31–33.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ epigyne, ventral view <bold>31</bold> SB 430 from Southeastern Papua Prov., Indonesia <bold>32</bold> SB 98 from Mindiptana, Southeastern Papua Prov., Indonesia <bold>33</bold> SB 127 from Northern Sumatra, Indonesia.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 34–41.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ vulva, dorsal view <bold>(34, 36, 38, 40)</bold> with course of internal duct system <bold>(35, 37, 39, 41). 34–35</bold> Holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia angustata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 460) from Ternate, Indonesia. <bold>36–37</bold> Lectotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia buruana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 418) from Buru, Indonesia. <bold>38–39</bold> Holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia maforensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 464) from Northwestern Irian Jaya, Indonesia. <bold>40–41</bold> Holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cinerea</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 404) from Southern Papua Prov., Indonesia.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 42–47.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ vulva, dorsal view <bold>(42, 44, 46)</bold> with course of internal duct system <bold>(43, 45, 47). 42–43</bold> SB 430 from Southeastern Papua Prov., Indonesia. <bold>44–45</bold> SB 98 from Mindiptana, Southeastern Papua Prov., Indonesia. <bold>46–47</bold> SB 127 from Northern Sumatra, Indonesia.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Fecenia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">protensa</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Fecenia_protensa</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Thorell, 1891,</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">stat. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 55</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">–70</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">98–99</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">108–110</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">119</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name><comment> Thorell, 1891: 31 (Description of immature ♀), [Holotype s.a. ♀ (SB 620) from INDIA: Nicobar Islands: Nancowry; Bille, Kjellerup, Behn and Reinhardt leg. 1845–1847, Galathea Expedition; ZMUC 13091, examined]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kulczyński 1908</xref>: 570; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Reimoser 1936</xref>: 406; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi 1982</xref>: 136 (Synonymy with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, rejected); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Murphy 1986</xref>: 65 (Statement concerning synonymy with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia sumatrana</tp:taxon-name><comment> Kulczyński, 1908: 568, pl. 23, fig. 20 (Description of ♀), [Holotype ♀ (SB 357) from INDONESIA: Sumatra: Lampung Prov.: Palembang; Dr S. Libelt leg.; MIZ 212∙322, examined]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Reimoser 1929</xref>: 132 (Listing of first record from Mentawai islands); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Reimoser 1936</xref>: 407; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234 (Synonymy with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, rejected by subsequent author); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Murphy 1986</xref>: 65 (Synonymy with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic>, rejected). Syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus nicobarensis</tp:taxon-name><comment> Tikader, 1977: 208, fig. 27A–E (Description and illustration of ♂ and ♀), [Holotype ♀ as well as 8 ♀♀ paratypes and 2 ♂♂ paratypes from INDIA: West Bengal Province: Nicobar Islands, Car-Nicobar Isl., Kakana village; B.K. Tikader leg. 9.III.1970; NZSI, not available on request, thus not examined]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Jose and Sebastian 2001</xref>: 304 (genus name misapplied). Syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia nicobarensis</tp:taxon-name><comment> - <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi 1982</xref>: 138 (Transfer from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic>).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name><comment> - <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi 1982</xref>: 136, figs 83–87, ad part, figs 83, 86–87 misidentified (figs 83 and 87: Illustration of s.a. ♀ and ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Koh 1989</xref>: 76, fig. embedded in text, misidentified (Illustration of ♀).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus alticeps</tp:taxon-name><comment> - <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Jose and Sebastian 2001</xref>: 304, fig. 1, misidentified. Note: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Jose and Sebastian (2001)</xref> copied the illustrations of fig. 27 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Tikader (1977)</xref>, pasted them in their fig. 1 and partly modified them. In their fig. 1a they changed the eye arrangement and colour pattern of the carapace as well as the colour pattern of the opisthosoma “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic>”-like. Their figs 1b and 1g show the female and male copulatory organs of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> after Tikader (1977, there sub <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus nicobarensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>). Their fig. 1f is a misinterpretation and definitely shows neither the vulva of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> nor the one of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus alticeps</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pocock, 1899, which is a junior synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus torvus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1869) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi 1982</xref>).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Additional material">
                        <title>Additional material.</title>
                        <p>(6 ♂♂, 38 ♀♀, 2 s.a. ♂♂, 5 s.a. ♀♀, 10 juvenile specimens). <bold>THAILAND:</bold> <bold>Nakhon Nayok Prov.:</bold> Khao Yai N.P. located ca. 120 km North-East of Bangkok, evergreen tropical rainforest, ca. 150 m; P. Hillyard leg. 12.III.1984; 1 ♀ (SB 393), NHM. Khao Yai N.P., forests surrounding Park Headquarters, 800-900 m; P. Dankittipakul leg. 15.XI.2006; 1 ♂ (SB 218), MHNG. <bold>Nakhon Ratchasima Prov.:</bold> Khao Yai N.P., rainforest; C.L. and P.R. Deeleman leg. 28.XII.1988; 1 ♂ (SB 128, died directly after adult moult), Deeleman Coll. in RMNH. <bold>Chantaburi Prov.:</bold> Chantaburi Distr.: Nam Tok Phliu N.P., 50 m; P. Schwendinger leg. 11.IX.1993; 1 ♂ (SB 136), MHNG. <bold>Trat Prov.:</bold> Koh Chang Isl.: Khlong Chao Luam, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">12°06'30"N, 102°17'49"E</named-content>, 30–150 m, secondary forest along stream, in shrubs; P. Jäger and S. Bayer leg. 3.XI.2009; 1 ♂ (SB 512), 1 ♀ (SB 458), 2 juvs (SB 328, 350), SMF. <bold>Surat Thani Prov.:</bold> Khao Nan N.P.; P. Dankittipakul leg. 17.VIII.2006; 1 ♀ (SB 202), MHNG; P. Dankittipakul leg. 27.X.2006; 1 ♀ (SB 206), SMF. <bold>Krabi Prov.:</bold> Krabi Distr.: Thab Khaek, Hang Nak Hill Nature Trail, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°05'43"N, 98°45'11"E</named-content>, 300 m, semi-evergreen rainforest; P. Schwendinger leg. 6.VI.2009; 1 ♀ (SB 195), SMF. <bold>Phuket Prov.:</bold> Phuket, Ton Sai Waterfall, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°01'N, 98°25'E</named-content>, 150–200 m; M. Andersen, O. Martin and N. Scharff leg. 12.X.1991; 3 ♀♀ (SB 888–890), 1 s.a. ♂ (SB 891), ZMUC 4536. <bold>Song Khla Prov.:</bold> Khao Khor Hong, a small mountainous area behind Prince of Song Khla University campus; B. Phongsee leg. 15.IX.2005; 1 ♀ (SB 215), 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 216), 3 juvs (SB 782–784), MHNG. <bold>MALAYSIA:</bold> <bold>Pahang Prov.:</bold> Cameron Highlands at Tanah Rata, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">4°28'N, 101°23'E</named-content>; V. and B. Roth leg. 14.-20.IV.1990; 1 ♀ (SB 184), 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 185), USNM, 1 ♀ (SB 949), CAS ENT9032226. <bold>Selangor Prov.:</bold> Gombak, field station, forest; C.L. Deeleman leg. 6.VII.1992; 1 ♀ (SB 117); C.L. Deeleman and J.C. van Kempen leg. 2.VII.1992, by night; 1 ♀ (SB 112), both <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->Deeleman Coll. in RMNH. <bold>Borneo: Sarawak Prov.:</bold> Northern Sarawak; P. Nabawi leg.; [ex Coll. Wunderlich]; 1 ♀ (SB 1142), SMF. Gunong Mulu N.P., Environs Camp I, 1150 m, shrubs; F. Wanless leg. by net sweeping, R.G.S. Mulu Exped. 1977–78; 1 ♀ (SB 391), NHM. Gunong Mulu N.P., rain forest; C.L. and P.R. Deeleman leg. 4.X.2003; 1 ♀ (SB 131), s.a. ♀ (SB 897), 1 juv. (SB 898), Deeleman Coll. in RMNH. Kuching: Matang Reserve, primary forest, big old tree in clearing; C.L. and P.R. Deeleman leg. 25.III.1986; 2 ♀♀ (SB 107–108), 1 s.a. ♂ (SB 899), 3 juvs (SB 900–902), Deeleman Coll. in RMNH. <bold>Sabah Prov.:</bold> Kinabalu N.P., Poring Hot Springs, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">5°02'N, 116°42'E</named-content>, 600–700 m, primary forest; A. Floren leg. 3.III.1996 by canopy fogging “Ridge”; 1 ♀ (SB 519), Deeleman Coll. in RMNH. <bold>SINGAPORE:</bold> Singapore (no further details); H.N. Ridley leg.; 7 ♀♀ (SB 408–414), 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 407), NHM. Singapore: Sime Road: secondary forest; J. Koh leg. 1998; 1 ♀ (SB 186), USNM. <bold>INDONESIA:</bold> <bold>Sumatra: Nanggroe Aceh Darussalam Prov.:</bold> Simeulue Isl.; E. Jacobson leg.; 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 462), NHMW 12387. <bold>Sumatera Barat Prov.:</bold> Lubuk Sikaping, Panti Reserve; C.L. and P.R. Deeleman leg. 14.VIII.1982; 1 ♀ (SB 125), Deeleman Coll. in RMNH. <bold>Borneo: Kalimantan Timur Prov.:</bold> 40 km NNW of Balikpapan, Sepaku, isolated stand of rainforest; C.L. and P.R. Deeleman leg. 5.VIII.1980; 1 ♀ (SB 126), Deeleman Coll. in RMNH. <bold>Bali Prov.:</bold> Air Terjung Waterfall, c/o Munduk, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°15'27.8"S, 115°04'14.1"E</named-content>, ca. 1000 m; S. Huber leg. 11.IV.2011; 5 ♀♀ (SB 1013–1017), SMF. Ubud, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°29'51"S, 115°15'18.4"E</named-content>, ca. 330 m; S. Huber leg. 30.III.2011; 1 ♀ (SB 1028), SMF. Candi Dasa, creek forest, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°30'13"S, 115°33'47"E</named-content>; S. Huber leg. 16.–20.III.2009; 1 ♂ (SB 137), 2 ♀♀ (SB 196, 256), 1 juv. (SB 906), SMF. <bold>Nusa Tenggara Barat Prov.:</bold> Flores Isl., East of Labuan Bajo, rainforest, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">8°33'60"S, 120°00'02"E</named-content>; S. Huber leg. 24.III.2009; 1 ♂ (SB 196, only left palp and a few body parts remained), SMF.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Females distinguished from other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> by having anterior margins of lateral lobes (AML) anteriorly more or less converging and surrounding epigynal pit partly and the anterior part of median septum (AS) comprising a longitudinal, anteriorly pointed folding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 55</xref>); moreover, by having a notched transversal edge (TR) of median septum. Distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> by borderline (BL) between strongly sclerotised section of internal duct system (SSI) and transparent section (TSI) running almost transversal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 56</xref>). In males RTA short, at most ½ the width of palpal tibia, and knobbed, almost as broad as long (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 62–63</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">98</xref>). Median apophysis (MA) almost semicircular and shorter than width of tegulum (T) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 62</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">98</xref>). In contrast to the similar male of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> embolus (E) without basal apophysis (bEA) and ventral patellar apophysis (VPA) arising proximally on patella (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 60–61</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">99</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>MALE:Body and eye measurements. Carapace length 3.1–4.4, carapace width 2.1–3.0, anterior width of carapace 1.4–1.9, opisthosoma length 4.1–6.4, opisthosoma width 1.6–2.6. Eyes: AME 0.25–0.27, ALE 0.17–0.18, PME 0.18–0.19, PLE 0.17–0.19, AME–AME 0.14–0.22, AME–ALE 0.07–0.19, PME–PME 0.18–0.25, PME–PLE 0.25–0.34, AME–PME 0.13–0.19, ALE–PLE 0.10–0.18, <!--PageBreak-->clypeus height at AME 0.29–0.35, at ALE 0.21–0.26. Measurements of palp and legs. Palp 4.0–5.2 [1.5–2.1, 0.7–0.9, 0.5–0.7, 1.3–1.6], I 34.7–52.5 [9.1–14.2, 1.4–2.1, 9.5–14.6, 10.6–16.2, 4.1–5.4], II 16.3–25.1 [4.3–6.7, 1.2–1.6, 4.5–7.0, 4.3–7.0, 2.0–2.8], III 9.2–14.0 [2.6–4.0, 0.9–1.3, 2.2–3.6, 2.3–3.4, 1.2–1.7], IV 15.5–23.1 [4.1–6.3, 1.1–1.6, 4.1–6.2, 4.4–6.5, 1.8–2.5]. Leg formula: 1243. Copulatory organ. Retrolateral patellar apophysis (RPA) rather inconspicuous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 61–63</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">98–99</xref>). Median apophysis (MA) with tip in ca. 1:00-o'clock-position (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 62</xref>) and in retrolateral <!--PageBreak-->view almost straight (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 61</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">99</xref>). Embolus (E) arising in ca. 7:30-o'clock-position on tegulum (T), distally thicker than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> and at most as long as width of T. The latter almost round. Membranous process of tegulum (MP) reaches far up, mostly 10:00–10:30-o'clock-position. Conductor (C) small, size and shape similar like in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, arises medially in upper third of T.</p>
                        <p>FEMALE: Body and eye measurements. Carapace length 3.3–4.7, carapace width 1.9–3.1, anterior width of carapace 1.6–2.3, opisthosoma length 5.5–8.1, opisthosoma width 2.4–4.2. Eyes: AME 0.22–0.28, ALE 0.15–0.21, PME 0.17–0.22, PLE 0.16–0.19, AME–AME 0.19–0.26, AME–ALE 0.10–0.14, PME–PME 0.23–0.29, PME–PLE 0.29–0.40, AME–PME 0.23–0.24, ALE–PLE 0.16–0.19, clypeus height at AME 0.33–0.41, at ALE 0.29–0.38. Measurements of palp and legs. Palp 3.5–5.1 [1.2–1.7, 0.6–0.9, 0.6–1.0, 1.1–1.5], I 19.2–26.8 [4.8–7.0, 1.5–2.0, 5.4–7.8, 5.1–7.2, 2.4–2.8], II 11.3–16.5 [3.0–4.3, 1.1–1.6, 3.1–4.7, 2.7–4.0, 1.4–1.9], III 7.1–10.6 [2.1–3.1, 0.8–1.3, 1.8–2.6, 1.5–2.3, 0.9–1.3], IV 10.7–16.0 [2.8–4.4, 1.1–1.7, 3.1–4.6, 2.5–3.6, 1.2–1.7]. Leg formula: 1243. Palpal claw with 8–11 teeth. Spination (immature holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Nicobar Islands in poor condition! spination of holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia sumatrana</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Palembang, Sumatra listed instead). Palp: 110, 110, 0100, 1004 (spines on patella, tibia and tarsus with only half the size as those of femur!); legs: femur I 310, II 320, III 011, IV 020; patella I–IV 000; tibia I–II 3006, III 0023, IV 0024; metatarsus I 2025, II–III 2015, IV 1015. Copulatory organ: Epigyne in general appearance characteristically rounded-“W”-shaped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 55</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">108</xref>). AML mostly strongly sclerotised, converging anteriorly and surrounding epigynal pit partly. AS clearly broader than PS. Epigynal muscle sigilla (EM) integrated in epigynal field or at least located very close by, same for slit sense organs (SO) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 55</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">64</xref>). Vulva with medium sized (longer than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic>, shorter than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and broad TSI (56, 65, 109). SSI more slender than in all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species, duct with 2–3 curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 57</xref>). Primordial copulatory organ: Pre-epigyne: “Crown”-like (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 58</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">66, 69</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">110</xref>). Primordium of AS already recognisable, broad “W”-like. Epigynal field not or only poorly developed, EM far outside epigynal field (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 69</xref>). Pre-pre-epigyne: Prongs of the “crown” small (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 70</xref>). Pre-vulva: Pre-receptacula bulbous/spherical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 59</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">67–68</xref>). Distance between centres of pre-receptacula more than three times diameter of one pre-receptaculum. Variation of copulatory organs: Cymbium length of male palp differing slightly among specimens examined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Figs 60–63</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">98–99</xref>), MA may be extending further beyond retrolateral cymbium margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 63</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">98</xref>). T in some specimens slightly broader (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Fig. 98</xref>) than in others. RPA may be slightly larger (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 63</xref>) than in general. In females the shape of AS may vary, e.g. the posterior notch is larger and the anteriorly pointed longitudinal folding is as such hardly recognisable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 64</xref>). Number of SO among specimens varying without geographical dependence. TSI varying in length (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 56</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">65</xref>). In dorsal view BL direction of vulva varies from 8:30 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 65</xref>) to almost 9:30-o'clock-position (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 56</xref>). Pre-epigynes differing in shape of TR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 58</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">66</xref>). The most frequent shape seems to be the one of SB 216 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 69</xref>) and holotype SB 620 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 58</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">110</xref>). Number of SO varying strongly.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <p>Pre-vulva may be slightly more structured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Fig. 67</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>The reasons for revalidation of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and the synonymy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia sumatrana</tp:taxon-name></italic> with the former are as follows: In Thailand, Malaysia, Singapore and on Bali at several localities subadult <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> females were collected together with adult females respectively, which showed the characteristic rounded-“W”-shaped epigyne. The pre-epigyne of the subadult female holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 620) matches the ones of the subadult females mentioned above. In <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">1908 Kulczyński</xref> described <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia sumatrana.</tp:taxon-name></italic> The (adult) female holotype of this species exhibits the characteristic rounded-“W”-shaped epigyne. The adult females mentioned above match the holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia sumatrana</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the oldest name available and hence the valid name for this taxonomical species. It is distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the BL of the vulva running almost transversal. Consequently, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia sumatrana</tp:taxon-name></italic> is not a junior synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> as postulated in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Murphy (1986)</xref>, but a junior synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Both, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> are regarded as valid species (see also remarks sub species description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic>).</p>
                        <p>Reason for synonymy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia nicobarensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>: Although the types of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus nicobarensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> were not available on request it became obvious that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Tikader (1977)</xref> dealt with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The drawing of the female epigyne in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Tikader (1977</xref>: 208, fig. 27B) is not very informative, however, the rounded-“W”-shaped character of the epigyne is very clear. His fig. 27E of the right male palp is more detailed. However, the proportions probably do not reflect the real situation. Additionally, this illustration does not represent an exact ventral view of the palp. If the left palps of the males examined herein (SB 128, 136, 137, 218, 219, 512) were arranged in the same way/position, they would match the (mirrored) drawing in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">Tikader (1977)</xref>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Disribution">
                        <title>Disribution.</title>
                        <p>India [Nicobar Islands], Thailand, Malaysia, Singapore, Indonesia [Sumatra, Borneo, Bali].</p>
                        <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 48–54.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <bold>48–51</bold> ♀ (SB 390) from Selangor Prov., Malaysia. <bold>52–54</bold> Holotype ♂ (SB 395) from Perak Prov., Malaysia. <bold>48</bold> Epigyne, ventral view. <bold>49</bold> Vulva, dorsal view. <bold>50</bold> Course of internal duct system. <bold>51</bold> Left palpal claw, retrolateral view. <bold>52–54</bold> left palp, prolateral <bold>(52)</bold>, ventral <bold>(53)</bold> and retrolateral <bold>(54)</bold> view. DRTA = Dorso-retrolateral tibial apophysis; RPA = Retrolateral patellar apophysis; RTA = Retrolateral tibial apophysis.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F12" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 55–59.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ copulatory organ/primordial copulatory organ <bold>55–57</bold> Holotype ♀ of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia sumatrana</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 357) from Southern Sumatra, Indonesia <bold>58–59</bold> Holotype s.a. ♀ (SB 620) of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Nicobar Islands, India <bold>55</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>56</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>57</bold> Course of internal duct system <bold>58</bold> Pre-epigyne, ventral view <bold>59</bold> Pre-vulva, dorsal view. TR = Transversal edge/ridge of median septum (<bold>55</bold> in epigyne, <bold>58</bold> corresponding structure in pre-epigyne).</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g012.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F13" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 60–63.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♂ palp <bold>60–62</bold> SB 218 from Nakhon Ratchasima Prov., Thailand <bold>63</bold> SB 137 from Bali, Indonesia <bold>60</bold> Prolateral view. <bold>61</bold> Retrolateral view <bold>62–63</bold> Ventral view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g013.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F14" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 64–70.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ copulatory organ/primordial copulatory organ <bold>64–65</bold> ♀ SB 410 from Singapore <bold>66–67</bold> s.a. ♀ SB 185 from Pahang Prov., Malaysia <bold>68–69</bold> s.a. ♀ SB 216 from Songkhla Prov., Thailand <bold>70</bold> p.s.a. ♀ SB 897 from Sarawak Prov., Malaysia <bold>64</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>65</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>66, 69</bold> Pre-epigyne, ventral view <bold>67–68</bold> Pre-vulva, dorsal view <bold>70</bold> Pre-pre-epigyne, ventral view. TR = Transverse edge/ridge of (in this case primordial) median septum.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g014.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F15" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 71–78.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ copulatory organ/primordial copulatory organ <bold>71–73</bold> ♀ SB 118 <bold>74–75</bold> s.a. ♀ SB 119, both from Erawan, Kanchanaburi Prov., Thailand <bold>76–78</bold> Holotype ♀ (SB 403) from Kerala Prov., India <bold>71, 76</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>72, 77</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>73, 78</bold> Course of internal duct system <bold>74</bold> Pre-epigyne, ventral view. <bold>75</bold> Pre-vulva, dorsal view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g015.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Fecenia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">travancoria</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Fecenia_travancoria</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Pocock, 1899</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 71–78</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">111–113</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name><comment> Pocock, 1899: 750 (Description of ♀), [Holotype ♀ (SB 403) from INDIA: Kerala Prov.: Madatory; H. Ferguson leg. III.1896; NHM 99·1·17·36, examined]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kulczyński 1908</xref>: 570; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Reimoser 1936</xref>: 406; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234 (Synonymy with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Murphy 1986</xref>: 65 (Removed from synonymy with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Jose and Sebastian 2001</xref>: 304; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sebastian and Peter 2009</xref>: 277 (Description of ♀).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name><comment> - <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi 1982</xref>: 136, figs 83–87, ad part, figs 83, 86–87 misidentified (fig 86: Illustration of ♀).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Additional material examined">
                        <title>Additional material examined.</title>
                        <p>(3 ♀♀, 2 s.a. ♀♀, 2 juvenile specimens). <bold>INDIA:</bold> <bold>Kerala Prov.:</bold> Ernakulam; K. S. Jose leg. 23.III.2001; 1 ♀ (SB 863, checked via photo of entire specimen, ventral view, kindly provided by K. S. Jose), SJPC. <bold>SRI LANKA:</bold> <bold>Sabaragamuwa Prov.:</bold> Ratnapura, peak wilderness area; W. Sedgwick leg. 11.VIII.1979; 1 juv. (SB 481), MCZ 82528. Pitadeniya, Sinharaja Nature Reserve, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">6°21'40.2"N, 80°29'03.6"E</named-content>, ca. 300 m, primary forest, in palm, 1.5 m above ground; V. Hartmann leg. 16.I.2011 as immature, raised in laboratory, adult 05.IV.2011; 1 ♀ (SB 982, from this specimen the exuviae of the subadult instar, thus its pre-epigyne, was kept and preserved), SMF. <bold>THAILAND:</bold> <bold>Kanchanaburi Prov.:</bold> Erawan Waterfall in Erawan N.P., evergreen rainforest; C.L. &amp; P.R. Deeleman leg. 15.III.1986; 1 ♀ (SB 118), 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 119), 2 juvs (SB 903–904), Deeleman Coll. in RMNH.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Females distinguished from other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> by having anterior margins of lateral lobes (AML) anteriorly more or less converging and surrounding epigynal pit partly and the anterior part of median septum (AS) comprising a longitudinal, anteriorly pointed folding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 76</xref>); moreover, by having a notched transversal edge (TR) of median septum. Females are distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the almost longitudinal borderline (BL) between strongly sclerotised section (SSI) and the transparent section of internal duct system (TSI) in vulva (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 77</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p>MALE: unknown.</p>
                        <p>FEMALE(measurements of holotype first, those of other females in parentheses): Body and eye measurements. Carapace length 5.9 (4.4–5.2) , carapace width 4.0 (3.0–3.3), anterior width of carapace 2.9 (2.2–2.5), opisthosoma length 7.8 (7.2–12.3), opisthosoma width 4.3 (4.0–5.4). Eyes: AME 0.36 (0.23–0.28), ALE 0.20 (0.12–0.18), PME 0.24 (0.14–0.21), PLE 0.23 (0.14–0.20), AME–AME 0.37 (0.22–0.31), AME–ALE 0.15 (0.09–0.13), PME–PME 0.47 (0.26–0.39), PME–PLE 0.48 (0.39–0.43), AME–PME 0.37 (0.22–0.30), ALE–PLE 0.26 (0.21–0.24), clypeus height at AME 0.43 (0.36–0.40), at ALE 0.39 (0.32–0.34). Measurements of palp and legs. Palp 6.2 (4.5–5.7) [2.1 (1.5–1.9), 1.1 (0.8–1.0), 1.1 (0.8–1.0), 1.9 (1.4–1.8)], I 33.3 (24.4–29.7) [8.8 (6.4–7.9), 2.4 (1.9–2.1), 9.0 (7.1–8.0), 9.2 (6.2–8.1), 3.9 (2.8–3.6)], II 21.3 (15.0–18.9) [5.9 (4.0–5.1), 2.0 (1.5–1.9), 5.7 (4.1–5.0), 5.2 (3.5–4.6), 2.5 (1.9–2.3)], III 13.1 (9.8–11.8) [3.9 (2.8–3.4), 1.6 (1.3–1.5), 3.1 (2.4–2.8), 2.9 (2.1–2.7), 1.6 (1.2–1.4)], IV 19.8 (14.5–17.9) [5.5 (4.0–4.9), 2.0 (1.5–1.7), 5.2 (4.1–4.8), 4.8 (3.3–4.5), 2.3 (1.6–2.0)]. Leg formula: 1243. Palpal claw with 9 (9–10) teeth. Spination (holotype from Madatory, India). Palp: 110, 000, 0000, 0000; legs: femur I 412, II 312, III 113, IV 011; patella I–IV 000; tibia I 2006, II 3004, III 0013, IV 0013; metatarsus I–II 2015, III 1015, IV 1014. Colouration: As described for the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Sebastian and Peter (2009</xref>, plate 94) show a photo of female habitus. Copulatory organ: In epigyne AS clearly broader than PS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 76</xref>, 111). AML strongly sclerotised. Epigynal muscle sigilla (EM) integrated in epigynal field. Female holotype with four slit sense organs (SO) on each side outside the epigynal field (EF) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 76</xref>), ♀ SB 982 from Sri Lanka with three SO on each side, all in EF and ♀ SB 118 from Thailand with one on each side outside EF (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 71</xref>). In contrast to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, folding of AS may be extending further anteriorly than AML (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 76</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">111</xref>), but not always. Vulva with short (shorter than in all <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species but <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>) an<!--PageBreak-->d broad TSI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 77</xref>). SSI may be darker than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and with ca. 2 curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figs 78</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">112</xref>). Primordial copulatory organ: Pre-epigyne: Very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, but lateral prongs of the “crown” narrower (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 74</xref>, in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">Fig. 113</xref> hard to recognise). Pre-vulva: Very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> in having bulbous/spherical pre-receptacula (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figs 59</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">67–68</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">75</xref>), with centres of the latter being rather far away (more than three times the diameter of one pre-receptaculum). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> is hard to distinguish from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the characters of the pre-vulva. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> the receptacula are rather oval in shape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 75</xref>), in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> round. Variation of copulatory organs: In ♀ SB 118 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 71</xref>) from Erawan, Thailand the distance between AS and AML is shorter than in holotype. In ♀ SB 118 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 71</xref>) and in ♀ SB 982 from Sri Lanka the folding of AS extending not as far anteriorly than in holotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 76</xref>). The vulvae of the ♀♀ examined as well as the primordial copulatory organs of the s.a. ♀♀ showed no significant variation.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p>This species is very similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>. There are only fine differences in characters of the vulva (see diagnosis). Up to now, no intermediate forms concerning the shape of vulva have been found. Though it cannot be fully excluded, it seems rather unlikely that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> is a junior synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Generally, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species the vulva shows less intraspecific variation than the epigyne. By now I consider <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> as valid species. But with more material from the southern Provinces of India, especially males, it may be possible to clarify this ‘difficult taxonomic case'.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Disribution">
                        <title>Disribution.</title>
                        <p>India [Kerala Prov.], Sri Lanka, Thailand.</p>
                        <fig id="F16" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 79–82.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ epigyne/primordial epigyne, ventral view <bold>79</bold> ♀ SB 919 <bold>81</bold> s.a. ♀ SB 911, both from Bago Prov., Myanmar <bold>80</bold> s.a. ♀ SB535 from Champasak Prov., Laos <bold>82</bold> p.s.a. ♀ SB 937 from Luang Prabang Prov., Laos <bold>79</bold> Epigyne <bold>80–81</bold> Pre-epigyne <bold>82</bold> Pre-pre-epigyne. AML = Anterior margin of lateral lobe; AS = Anterior part of median septum; CO = Copulatory opening; EF = Epigynal field; EM = Epigynal muscle sigilla; LL = Lateral lobe; PS = Posterior part of median septum; SO = Slit sense organ; TR = Transversal edge/ridge of median septum.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g016.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F17" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 83–86.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ vulva/pre-vulva, dorsal view <bold>83–84</bold> ♀ SB 919 <bold>85</bold> s.a. ♀ SB 911, both from Bago Prov., Myanmar <bold>86</bold> s.a. ♀ SB535 from Champasak Prov., Laos <bold>83</bold> Vulva <bold>84</bold> Course of internal duct system <bold>85–86</bold> Pre-vulva. BL = Borderline between SSI and TSI; FD = Fertilisation duct; SH = Spermathecal head; SSI = Strongly sclerotised section of internal duct system; TSI = Transparent section of internal duct system.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g017.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F18" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 87–90.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♂ palp <bold>87–89</bold> SB 928 from Bago Prov., Myanmar <bold>90</bold> SB 111 from Hainan, China <bold>87</bold> Prolateral view <bold>88</bold> Retrolateral view <bold>89–90</bold> Ventral view. Remark on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 90</xref>: Details omitted, embolus slipped behind conductor. bEA = Basal embolus apophysis.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g018.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F19" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 91–94.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ copulatory organ/primordial copulatory organ <bold>91–92</bold> ♀SB 110 from Hainan, China <bold>93–94</bold> s.a. ♀SB 921 from Bago Prov., Myanmar <bold>91</bold> Epigyne, ventral view <bold>92</bold> Vulva, dorsal view <bold>93</bold> Pre-vulva, dorsal view. <bold>94</bold> Pre-epigyne, ventral view. Remark on Figs <bold>91–92</bold>: Details omitted. Asterisk indicates the folding, which divides the anterior from the posterior part of AS.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g019.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F20" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 95–101.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp., male palp <bold>95, 101</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>96</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>97, 100</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>98–99</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>95, 101</bold> SB 389 from Selangor Prov., Malaysia <bold>96</bold> SB 187 from Halmahera, Indonesia <bold>97</bold> SB 510 from Champasak Prov., Laos <bold>100</bold> SB 204 from Chaiyaphoom Prov., Thailand <bold>98–99</bold> SB 512 from Koh Chang, Thailand <bold>95–98</bold> ventral view <bold>99–101</bold> retrolateral view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g020.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Fecenia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">cylindrata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Fecenia_cylindrata</object-id>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Thorell, 1895</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 79</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18"></xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">–94</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">97, 100</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">105–107</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F22">116–117</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F23">120–123</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name><comment> Thorell, 1895: 64 (Description of juveniles), [2 syntypes: juvenile syntype (SB 281, neither penultimate nor antepenultimate instar, thus sex unknown) from MYANMAR: Bago Prov.: Delta near Tharrawaddy (ca. 100 km NW of Yangon); 1884–1887, ded. E.W. Oates; NRS Thorell-Coll.-No. 70a., examined; other juvenile syntype from MYANMAR: Tanintharyi Prov.: Dawei, “on an island in Tavoy river”; 1884–1887, ded. E.W. Oates; type deposition unknown, maybe lost, thus not examined]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Thorell 1897</xref>: 263 (Description of ♂ and ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Pocock 1900</xref>: 212 (Description of ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Kulczyński 1908</xref>: 570; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Reimoser 1936</xref>: 406; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>: 234, figs 472–473 (Illustration of carapace, illustration of ♂); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi 1982</xref>: 136, figs 80–82 (Illustration of ♂ and ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Murphy 1986</xref>: 65; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">Yang and Wang 1993</xref>: 29, figs 1–4 (Illustration of ♂ and ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Song et al. 1999</xref>: 397, figs 231O–Q (Illustration of ♂ and ♀); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Wang and Yin 2001</xref>: 332, figs 1–4 (Illustration of ♂ and ♀).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia hainanensis</tp:taxon-name><comment> Wang, 1990: 257, figs 1–3 (Description of ♀), [Holotype ♀ from CHINA: Hainan Province: Tongqian city, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">18°30'N, 109°45'E</named-content>; Liu leg. 01.VII.1984; HBI, not available on request, thus not examined, examined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Wang and Yin (2001)</xref>]; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Wang and Yin 2001</xref>: 332 (Synonymy).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                            <!--PageBreak-->
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Additional material examined">
                        <title>Additional material examined.</title>
                        <p>(10 ♂♂, 35 ♀♀, 5 s.a. ♂♂, 15 s.a. ♀♀, 1 p.s.a. ♀, 12 juvenile specimens). <bold>CHINA:</bold> <bold>Hainan Prov.:</bold> Mount Jainfeng; 20.IV.1990, ded. D.X. Song; 1 ♂ (SB 111), 1 ♀ (SB 110), Deeleman Coll. in RMNH. <bold>MYANMAR:</bold> <bold>Sagaing Prov.:</bold> Chattin Wildlife Sanctuary, Takontaing camp, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">22°37'20"N, 95°31'52"E</named-content>; J. Coddington &amp; R.L.C. Baptista leg. 7–12.X.1998 by night; 2 ♀♀ (SB 182, 188), USNM. <bold>Bago Prov.:</bold> Palon; L. Fea leg. 1885–1889, “Viaggio in Birmania”; T. Thorell det. 20.X.1896; 2 ♂♂ (SB 289–290), 5 ♀♀ (SB 282–286), 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 287), 1 s.a. ♂ (SB 288), NRS Thorell-Coll.-No. 70b; 5 ♀♀ (SB 915–919), 3 s.a. ♀♀ (SB 910–912), 2 s.a. ♂♂ (SB 913–914), ZMH; 1 ♂ (SB 928), 4 ♀♀ (SB 929–932), 8 s.a. ♀♀ (SB 920–927), 2 s.a. ♂♂ (SB 933–934), 1 juv. (SB 935), ZMUC 5772. The following material has the same dates as above, but was checked via photos of copulatory organs kindly provided by P. Dankittipakul: 2 ♂♂ (SB 827–828), 5 ♀♀ (SB 822–826), MCSN. <bold>THAILAND:</bold> <bold>Chiang Mai Prov.:</bold> Doi Suthep N.P.; P. Dankittipakul leg.; 1 ♀ (SB 205), MHNG. Lamphun Prov.: Mae Tha Distr.: Doi Khuntan N.P., 800 m; P. Schwendinger leg. 22.IX.1994; 1 ♀ (SB 135), MHNG. <bold>Loei Prov.:</bold> Na-Haeo, field research station; J. Constant, K. Smets &amp; P. Frootaart leg.15.–19.V.2003; 1 ♀ (SB 11), IRSN. <bold>Chaiyaphoom Prov.:</bold> Phu Kradung N.P., 1200-1300 m, flat plateau with mixed deciduous + pine + evergreen forest; P. Dankittipakul leg. 15.VIII.2006; 1 ♂ (SB 204), MHNG. <bold>LAOS:</bold> <bold>Luang Prabang Prov.:</bold> near Luang Prabang: Tham Sieng Mang, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">19°54'09"N, 102°08'32"E</named-content>, 270 m, sunny + dry area, low shrubs; P. Jäger &amp; S. Bayer leg. 15.XI.2009; 1 ♀ (SB 485), SMF. Luang Prabang: Phou Si, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">19°53'23"N, 102°08'04"E</named-content>, 300 m, dr<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->y secondary forest in town, in shrubs; P. Jäger &amp; V. Vedel leg. 12.XI.2004; 3 juvs (SB 938–940); P. Jäger leg. 25.III.2007; 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 62), 1 p.s.a. ♀ (SB 937); P. Jäger &amp; S. Bayer leg. 14.XI.2009; 1 ♂ (SB 488, deformed, died during adult moult), all SMF. SE of Luang Prabang: Nam Khan, Xieng Ngeun Distr., Ban Keng Koung, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">19°40'963"N, 102°18'442"E</named-content>, ca. 370 m, along river bank; P. Jäger leg. 24.II.2008; 1 juv. (SB 936), SMF. <bold>Champasak Prov.:</bold> Muang Bachieng: That Paxuam, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">15°10'35"N, 105°55'21"E</named-content>, 200 m, secondary forest; P. Jäger &amp; S. Bayer leg. 25.XI.2009; 1 ♀ (SB 318), 2 juvs (SB 40–401), SMF. Ban Lak 38, That Fane, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">15°11'03"N, 106°07'37"E</named-content>, 950 m, coffee plantation; P. Jäger leg. 11.–16.III.2010; 1 ♀ (SB 528), 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 535), 3 juvs (SB 527, 532–533), SMF. Near Pakse: Ban Ke, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">15°07'57"N, 105°48'54"E</named-content>, 100 m, dry shrubs; P. Jäger &amp; S. Bayer leg. 27.XI.2009, by night; 1 juv. (SB 351), SMF. Muang Pathoumphone: Vat Phou Salao, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">15°05'39"N, 105°48'35"E</named-content>, 150 m, dry bed of stream, dry shrubs; P. Jäger &amp; S. Bayer leg. 24.XI.2009, by night; 3 ♀♀ (SB 48–487, 514), 3 juvs (SB 349, 398, 526), SMF. Ban Nog Hoy, N slope of Phou Malong, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">15°03'14"N, 105°49'07"E</named-content>, 115 m, dry bed of stream, dry shrubs; P. Jäger leg. 23.XI.2009; 2 ♂♂ (SB 50–510), 1 ♀ (SB 511), 1 s.a. ♀ (SB 420), 2 juvs (SB 39–397), SMF. Ban Tha Hou, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">14°46'10"N, 105°59'35"E</named-content>, 130 m, dry forest, near summit of a prominent hill; P. Jäger &amp; S. Bayer leg. 22.XI.2009; 2 ♀♀ (SB 513, 525), SMF.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>Females distinguished from other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> by having anteriorly converging anterior margins of lateral lobes (AML) <!--PageBreak-->partly surrounding epigynal pit; distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> by the even and unfolded anterior part of median septum (AS) and by transverse edge of median septum (TR) lacking distinct notch (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 79</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">105</xref>). In vulva transparent section of internal duct system (TSI) larger than strongly sclerotised section (SSI) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 83</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">92</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">106</xref>). Males distinguished from other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species except <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> by having short (at most half as long as width of palpal tibia) RTA; distinguished from <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> in having RTA, which is longer than broad, and ventral patellar apophysis (VPA) arising centrally on patella (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 88</xref>). Median apophysis (MA) running almost in transversal plane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 87–88</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">100</xref>). Embolus (E) with pointed basal apophysis (bEA) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 89</xref>).<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <p><bold>D</bold></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="escription">
                        <title>escription.</title>
                        <p>MALE:Body and eye measurements. Carapace length 3.6–4.4, carapace width 2.2–2.8, anterior width of carapace 1.6–1.9, opisthosoma length 4.8–6.5, opisthosoma width 1.9–2.5. Eyes: AME 0.23–0.29, ALE 0.17–0.22, PME 0.17–0.22, PLE 0.18–0.21, AME–AME 0.16–0.23, AME–ALE 0.09–0.14, PME–PME 0.17–0.25, PME–PLE 0.28–0.35, AME–PME 0.12–0.16, ALE–PLE 0.10–0.15, clypeus height at AME 0.30–0.41, at ALE 0.24–0.35. Measurements of palp and legs. Palp 4.0–5.0 [1.6–2.0, 0.6–0.7, 0.4–0.5, 1.4–1.8], I 35.1–48.3 [9.5–12.9, 1.5–2.1, 9.3–13.6, 10.5–14.9, 4.3–4.8], II 16.6–22.0 [4.3–5.9, 1.3–1.6, 4.6–6.4, 4.3–5.6, 2.1–2.5], III 8.7–11.8 [2.5–3.4, 1.0–1.2, 2.0–2.9, 2.1–2.8, 1.1–1.5], IV 15.0–20.2 [4.2–5.4, 1.2–1.6, 3.8–5.6, 4.0–5.4, 1.8–2.2]. Leg formula: 1243. Copulatory organ: Retrolateral patellar apophysis (RPA) mostly more clearly visible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 89</xref>) than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Tip of MA in ca. 2:30–3:00-o'clock-position, MA shorter than width of tegulum (T) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 89–90</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">97</xref>) and in pro- and retrolateral view curved distally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 87–88</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">100</xref>). E very slim, especially distally, arising in ca. 7:30-o'clock-position on T and clearly longer than width of T (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Figs 89–90</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">97</xref>). The latter almost round. Membra<!--PageBreak-->nous process of tegulum (MP) reaches at most to 8:30-o'clock-position (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 89–90</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">97</xref>). Conductor (C) longer than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, shorter than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, arises medially (or slightly shifted retrolaterally) in upper third of T (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 89–90</xref>). Cymbium in relation a bit longer than in all other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 87–88</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">97, 100</xref>). Scopula dorsally on cymbium slightly less developed than in other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species.</p>
                        <p>FEMALE: Body and eye measurements. Carapace length 3.7–7.2, carapace width 2.2–4.2, anterior width of carapace 1.7–3.2, opisthosoma length 7.3–13.0, opisthosoma width 3.5–6.0. Eyes: AME 0.20–0.27, ALE 0.15–0.24, PME 0.16–0.22, PLE 0.16–0.22, AME–AME 0.18–0.34, AME–ALE 0.07–0.18, PME–PME 0.20–0.29, PME–PLE 0.33–0.54, AME–PME 0.14–0.27, ALE–PLE 0.12–0.27, clypeus height at AME 0.27–0.54, at ALE 0.25–0.48. Measurements of palp and legs. Palp 3.8–6.5 [1.3–2.3, 0.6–1.1, 0.7–1.1, 1.2–2.0], I 22.7–39.3 [6.0–10.8, 1.6–2.9, 6.3–10.8, 6.1–10.7, 2.7–4.1], II 13.1–23.7 [3.3–6.4, 0.9–2.3, 3.7–6.8, 3.1–5.7, 1.6–2.5], III 7.5–14.1 [2.2–4.1, 0.9–1.9, 1.8–3.4, 1.6–3.1, 1.0–1.6], IV 12.3–21.4 [3.3–5.9, 1.2–2.3, 3.5–6.2, 2.9–4.9, 1.4–2.1]. Leg formula: 1243. Palpal claw with 8–11 teeth. Spination (remaining immature syntype from Tharrawaddy in poor condition! Spination of female SB 285 from Palon, Birma (Myanmar) listed instead). Palp: 110, 000, 0100, 2004 (spines on tibia and tarsus with only half the size as those of femur!); legs: femur I 300(200), II 210, III 221(111), IV 010; patella I–IV 000; tibia I 0006(1005), II 2004(3005), III–IV 0024; metatarsus I 2015(2016), II–III 2015, IV 1018. Copulatory organ: Anterior part of AS divided from posterior part of AS by a differently developed folding (asterisk in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 91</xref>). AS broader than PS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 79</xref>). Epigynal muscle sigilla (EM) clearly outside epigynal field (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 79</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">91</xref>). Slit sense organs (SO) outside epigynal field. Vulva with large and broad TSI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 83</xref>), mostly larger than SSI. The latter with longer duct than in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, with 3–4 curves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 84</xref>). Border line (BL) between TSI and SSI of vulva in ca. 7:00-8:00 o' clock position (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 83</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">92</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">106</xref>). Primordial copulatory organs: Pre-epigyne: TR continuous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 81</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">107</xref>), slightly recurved. AML anteriorly bent sharply, running medially and (almost) meeting each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 81</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19"> 94</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">107</xref>). Epigynal field not or only poorly developed, EM far outside epigynal field. Pre-pre-epigyne: AML similar to pre-epigyne, TR hardly recognisable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 82</xref>). Pre-vulva: Pre-receptacula with lateral extension (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 85</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">93</xref>). Distance between centres of pre-receptacula more than three times the diameter of one pre-receptaculum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 85</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">93</xref>). Variation of copulatory organs: In males position of VPA may shift retrolaterally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 90</xref>). Direction of MA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 89, 90</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">97</xref>) may vary. Anterio-medial section of C differs among specimens examined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Figs 89, 90</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">97</xref>). RTA in some specimens basally broader (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 90</xref>). In females the folding which divides (or partly divides) the anterior from the posterior part of AS differently developed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 79</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">91</xref>). TR rarely with a very small, flat and indistinct notch (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 91</xref>). AS and PS in some specimens less broad than in others. Number of SO among specimens varying without geographical dependence. Anterio-lateral section of SSI may differ in shape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 83</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">92</xref>). Pre-epigynes differing in length and direction of AML (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 81</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">94</xref>), further in shape of TR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 81</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">94</xref>). The most frequent pre-epigyne type is the one of SB 911 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 81</xref>). Number of SO varying strongly. SB 535 from Champasak Province, Laos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 80</xref>) is an exception, which is discussed explicitly (see discussion below).<!--PageBreak--></p>
                        <p>The pre-vulvae differ only slightly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Figs 85</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">93</xref>). SB 535 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 86</xref>) is an exception, which is discussed explicitly (see discussion below).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks">
                        <title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">Thorell (1895)</xref> described this species based on juvenile types. Two years later Thorell himself redescribed this species based on ♂♂ and ♀♀ recorded just ca. 70 km away from type locality Tharrawaddy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">Thorell 1897</xref>). This material is deposited in NRS, ZMH and MCSN and was examined (see material list above). Moreover, to date no other <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species than the one described above had been found in Myanmar. For that reason there are no doubts about the identiy of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                        <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia hainanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wang, 1990 was synonymised with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Wang and Yin (2001)</xref>. The female holotype from Tonqian, Hainan Province, China was not available on request. According to the illustrations in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">Wang (1990)</xref>, which are not very detailed, it is more likely that his <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia hainanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> was in fact conspecific with <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The specimens from Hainan checked in the present study are considered belonging to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, though there are slight differences (see variation of copulatory organs in the description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>). More material from Hainan and also from regions of South East China and Northern Vietnam is necessary to assess the consistency of those slight differences among the different specimens. At the moment <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia hainanensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> is regarded as junior synonym of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>China, Myanmar, Laos, Thailand.</p>
                        <fig id="F21" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 102–115.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp., female copulatory organs/primordial copulatory organs <bold>102–104</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>105–107</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>108–110</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>111–113</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>114–115</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia macilenta</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>102–103</bold> ♀ SB 668 from New Guinea <bold>104</bold> s.a. ♀ SB 540 from New Britain, Papua New Guinea <bold>105–106</bold> ♀ from Loei Prov., Thailand <bold>107</bold> s.a. ♀ from Palon, Bago Prov., Myanmar <bold>108–109</bold> ♀ SB 215 from Songkhla Prov., Thailand <bold>110</bold> s.a. ♀ holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 620) from Nicobar Islands. <bold>111</bold> ♀ holotype of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia travancoria</tp:taxon-name></italic> (SB 403) from Kerala Prov., India <bold>112–113</bold> ♀ SB 982 from Sri Lanka (remark on 113: photo of exuviae of subadult instar of same specimen as in 112) <bold>114–115</bold> ♀ SB 124 from Sumatera Barat Prov., Indonesia <bold>102, 105, 108, 111, 114</bold> ♀ epigyne, ventral view <bold>103, 106, 109, 112, 115</bold> ♀ vulva, dorsal view <bold>104, 107, 110, 113</bold> pre-epigyne of s.a. ♀.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g021.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F22" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 116–120.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> spp., habitus, web <bold>116–117, 120</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ SB 486 (<bold>116</bold>), ♂ SB 509 (<bold>117</bold>) from Champasak Prov., Laos, web (<bold>120</bold>) from Xishuangbanna, China <bold>118</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ SB 161 from Auki, Solomon Islands <bold>119</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia protensa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♀ SB 256 from Bali, Indonesia <bold>116, 118</bold> Habitus, ventral view <bold>117</bold> Habitus, dorso-lateral view <bold>119</bold> Habitus, dorsal view <bold>116–117, 119</bold> Photos by Peter Jäger <bold>120</bold> Photo by Jeremy Miller.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g022.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F23" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 121–123.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>, ♂ (SB 510) and ♀ (SB 487) from Champasak Prov., Laos, mating behaviour, sperm web <bold>121</bold> ♂ stroking behaviour upon the retreat of the female <bold>122</bold> ♂ and ♀ together in the retreat <bold>123</bold> ♂ sperm webs (SB 510) <bold>123</bold> Photo by Peter Jäger.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-153-001-g023.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <sec sec-type="Characteristics of the pre-epigyne">
                <title>Characteristics of the pre-epigyne</title>
                <p>The pre-pre-epigyne (antepenultimate instar), although hardly useful for species determination, may bear important information. In some <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> species both pre-subadult and subadult females were available for examination. A continuous developmental trend from pre-pre-epigyne (p.s.a. ♀♀) to the epigyne of adults can be traced (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 19–22</xref> for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Figs 79–82</xref> for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Sierwald (1989)</xref> showed that in most of the American <tp:taxon-name>Pisauridae</tp:taxon-name> even more primordial epigyne stages exist. In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pisaurina mira</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Walckenaer, 1837) up to five stages with differently developed primordial copulatory organs (which Sierwald denominated as “anlagen”) occur. Gradually from earlier to later stages the anlagen resemble more and more the adult. The changes from penultimate instar to adult constitute the largest developmental step as the shapes of pre-epigynes and adult epigynes differ the most. The number of primordial stages in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pisaurina mira</tp:taxon-name></italic> varies between three and five (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Sierwald 1989</xref>). Interestingly, in specimens with only three primordial stages, the anlagen of the antepenultimate and penultimate instars were less developed and differentiated. Anyway, these specimens moult following their third anlage to “normal” mature females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Sierwald 1989</xref>). The total number of juvenile stages varies in <tp:taxon-name>Pisauridae</tp:taxon-name>. For example in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dolomedes triton</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Walckenaer, 1837) the number ranges from 10 to 15 in males and 9 to 15 in females (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Zimmermann and Spence 1998</xref>).</p>
                <p>The present study reveals the occurrence of a different developmental stage of the pre-epigyne (penultimate instar) in the pseudo-orbweaver <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 80</xref>). The following preliminary considerations may explain this phenomenon:</p>
                <p>In insects a juvenile hormone (JH) regulates the development of the larva throughout the several moults up to the imago. Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Wigglesworth (1952)</xref>, a controlled hormone balance between JH and prothoracotrope hormone is essential for regular development of the bug <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhodnius prolixus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Stål, 1859. From 1<sup>st</sup> to 4<sup>th</sup> stage larva the concentration of JH decreases more or less continuously, but from the 4<sup>th</sup> to 5<sup>th</sup> stage the decrease is much stronger and from 5<sup>th</sup> stage to imago JH is completely absent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">Wigglesworth 1952</xref>). It is likely that JH exists in spiders, too (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">Webber 2005</xref>). Prothoracotrope hormone does not exist in spiders, but instead of this it is possible, that another, equivalent hormone exists.</p>
                <p>On the other hand it is known from spiders that the number of moults, and thus the number of instars, to reach maturity may differ, for example in <tp:taxon-name>Pisauridae</tp:taxon-name> (see above). In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Latrodectus mactans</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Fabricius, 1775) the number of instars varies from 7 to 9 depending on food supply (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Deevey 1949</xref>). From particular species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Stegodyphus</tp:taxon-name></italic> Simon, 1873 it is also known that maturity is reached after different numbers of moults in different specimens examined, irrespective of their sex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Kullmann et al. 1972</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Kraus and Kraus 1988</xref>). Furthermore, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Kraus and Kraus (1988)</xref> state that the enormous size variation in species of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Stegodyphus</tp:taxon-name></italic> seems to be caused mainly by this flexibility. At least in the species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic>,the size variation is high. This becomes obvious by their carapace-length size ranges (see respective descriptions). It is possible that in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> the number of moults required to reach maturity differs intraspecifically, too. Considering that the number of stages of immature females with differently developed primordial copulatory organs varies in <tp:taxon-name>Pisauridae</tp:taxon-name> (see above), a family also belonging to the <tp:taxon-name>Lycosoidea</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Griswold et al. 2005</xref>), it is not unlikely that this applies to the pseudo-orbweavers too. A pre-epigyne of a s.a. ♀ of the 6<sup>th</sup> instar would then most likely differ from the one of an 8<sup>th </sup>instar.</p>
                <p>In <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> it seems to be rare, that the pre-epigyne of a particular subadult female differs from the ones of the others belonging to the same species. But, anyway, as the example of the subadult female of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 80</xref>) shows, this phenomenon may appear. In such a case additional consideration concerning the identification of subadults is necessary. Does the respective subadult female fit into a conceivable developmental continuum for the species in question? This is, of course, much easier if several “regularly” developed s.a. ♀♀ and/or p.s.a. ♀♀ are available. As the pre-epigyne of a “further developed” s.a. ♀ most likely resembles more an adult epigyne than a “regularly developed” one does, it should not be too difficult to identify it. Thus, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> the pre-epigynal characters apparently are species-specific (pre-epigynes, take notice; this must not inevitably mean that this applies also to the pre-pre-epigynes or other primordial epigynes of instars below subadult females!). Following the studies of (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Sierwald (1987</xref>, 1989) the pre-epigynes of the <tp:taxon-name>Pisauridae</tp:taxon-name> species examined seem to be specific, too. Hence, it is justified to use the pre-epigyne as a tool for identification.<!--PageBreak--></p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Validity of characters in Fecenia">
                <title>Validity of characters in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</title>
                <p>Somatic characters are not useful for species determination in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Colouration and spination, for example, are highly variable intraspecifically. Figures 69 and 82 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Levi (1982)</xref> suggest that species discrimination between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia ochracea</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia cylindrata</tp:taxon-name></italic> via colouration of the ventral surface of the opisthosoma is possible. According to the present study, this cannot be confirmed. Species identification is only possible by checking the copulatory organs.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Remarks on spination">
                <title>Remarks on spination</title>
                <p>In the description of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> above a characteristic aspect of the spination pattern on the tibiae is mentioned. This may be explained by the life style of the pseudo-orbweavers. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> is the only spider genus in which all representatives spend at least 95% of their lifetime in a very narrow enrolled-leaf retreat or cone retreat in early juveniles. In <tp:taxon-name>Araneidae</tp:taxon-name> there are several genera including species, that have similar lifestyles, e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acusilas</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyclosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neoscona</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Araneus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Cyrtophora</tp:taxon-name></italic>, also in <tp:taxon-name>Theridiidae</tp:taxon-name>, e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Parasteatoda simulans</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Thorell, 1875). In any case, there is no genus in which all representatives use enrolled leaves as a retreat. Furthermore, in representatives of the families mentioned above the leaf-retreat is never as narrow (in relation to body size) as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic>. A pseudo-orbweaver enters its retreat always with its opisthosoma first. The patellae and tibiae have the most intensive contact with the inner walls of the leaf retreat. As the legs are prograde with leg pairs I–II held anteriorly and III–IV posteriorly it becomes obvious that in the first two leg pairs the retrolateral and in the last two leg pairs the prolateral spines on the tibiae would be an impediment while moving inside the retreat. Perhaps in the course of the evolution of this genus, specimens with shorter spines or even no more spines at these respective positions were preferred? Like in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Psechrus</tp:taxon-name></italic> the patellae completely lack spines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Lehtinen 1967</xref>). This characteristic aspect of the tibial spination pattern in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Fecenia</tp:taxon-name></italic> may be an adaptation to this special life style. It would be interesting to check if the tibial spination pattern of species from the <tp:taxon-name>Araneidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Theridiidae</tp:taxon-name> genera listed above using enrolled leaves, differ from the ones with different lifestyles. But in contrast to <tp:taxon-name>Psechridae</tp:taxon-name> in <tp:taxon-name>Araneidae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Theridiidae</tp:taxon-name> the spines are in any case not so prominent in comparison to leg diameter.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>Many thanks to Peter Jäger (SMF, Frankfurt), who collected and provided numerous spider material important for this study, provided photos, gave fruitful advice, helpful comments on this manuscript, and provided a workplace at Senckenberg Research Institute as scientific mentor for my Ph.D.-thesis. Michael Tür<!--PageBreak-->kay (SMF &amp; University, Frankfurt) supported my Ph.D.-study as the scientific supervisor. The following colleagues provided freshly collected spider material, which was important for this study and/or for the study on Psechridae in general, and are thanked very much: Christa Deeleman (Ossendrecht), Siegfried Huber (Oberuhldingen), Peter Schwendinger (Geneva), Pakawin Dankittipakul (provided also photos of copulatory organs) (Auckland), Volker Hartmann (Koblenz), Ingi Agnarsson (Puerto Rico), Nikolaj Scharff (Copenhagen), Hirotsugu Ono (Tokyo), Cor Vink (Christchurch), Brian Mike Fitzgerald (Wellington), Robert Raven (Brisbane), Mark Harvey (Perth), I-Min Tso &amp; Ren-Chun Cheng (Tunghai), Joachim Haupt (Berlin), Helmut Steiner (Hanau), Booppa Ponksee (Thailand) and Xiang Xu (Changsha). The following curators loaned (type) material of <italic>Fecenia</italic>: Jeremy Miller (is also thanked for providing photos), Karen van Dorp &amp; I. Jaques Smit (RMNH, Leiden), Leon Baert &amp; B. Goddeeris (IRSN, Brussels), Maria Tavano (MCSN, Genoa), Gonzalo Giribet &amp; Laura Leibensperger (MCZ, Cambridge), Peter Schwendinger (MHNG, Geneva), Dominika Mierzwa (MIZ, Warsaw), Christine Rollard &amp; Elise-Anne Leguin (MNHN, Paris), Janet Beccaloni (NHM, London), Jürgen Gruber &amp; Christoph Hörweg (NHMW, Vienna), Gunvi Lindberg (NRS, Stockholm), Peter Jäger &amp; Julia Altmann (SMF, Frankfurt am Main), Jonathan Coddington (USNM, Washington), Ben Brugge (ZMA, Amsterdam, kindly translated dutch labels, too), Jason Dunlop, Anja Friederichs &amp; Benjamin Nitsche (ZMB, Berlin), Hieronymus Dastych (ZMH, Hamburg), Nicolaj Scharff (ZMUC, Copenhagen), Charles Griswold &amp; Anthea Carmichael (CAS, San Francisco). G. Milledge (AMS, Sydney) and Liu Ping (HBI, Changsha) gave information on spider material deposited in their museums. Charles Griswold (San Francisco) and Shuqiang Li (Beijing) provided arachnological literature. Sunil Jose (Kottayam) provided photos of a <italic>Fecenia</italic> specimen from his private collection. Jürgen Gruber &amp; Verena Stagel (Vienna) gave important information concerning the type specimen of <italic>Tegenaria ochracea</italic>. Julia Altmann (Frankfurt) helped in assigning old (colonial) locality terms to recent localities and in deciphering handwriting on old labels. Three research stays at natural history museums in Europe were financially supported via SYNTHESYS project “Worldwide revision of the spider family Psechridae (Arachnida: Araneae) with an emphasis on SE-Asian Representatives”, granted to the author by the European Community Research Infrastructure Action under the FP6 “Structuring the European Research Area” Programme. The German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD) financially supported a research stay at an arachnological congress and a visit of a natural history museum in Poland. The Senckenberg Research Institute and Natural History Museum, Frankfurt am Main financially supported a research travel to/field excursion in Thailand and Laos. Many thanks to Jason Dunlop (ZMB, Berlin) for the English proofreading. Many thanks to Norman Platnick (New York), Martin Ramirez (Buenos Aires), Yuri Marusik (Magadan), Dimitri Logunov (Manchester), Jeremy Miller (Leiden) and an anonymous referee for fruitful comments on this manuscript.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jäger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Expectedspecies richness in the genus <italic>Psechrus</italic> in Laos (Araneae: Psechridae).</article-title> <source>Revue suisse de Zoologie</source> <volume>117</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>57</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage><italic>.</italic></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamberlin</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1924</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of new American and Chinese spiders, with notes on other Chinese species.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the United States National Museum </source> <volume>63</volume> (<issue>13</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5479/si.00963801.63-2481.1" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.5479/si.00963801.63-2481.1</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chrysanthus</surname><given-names>OFM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<source> Spiders from South New Guinea IX. Tijdschrift voor Entomologie110(afl. 1): 89–105.
</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Coddington</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> Ontogeny and homology in the male palpus of orb-weaving spiders and their relatives, with comments on phylogeny (Araneoclada: Araneoidea, Deinopoidea).</article-title> <source>Smithsonian Contributions to zoology </source> <volume>496</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5479/si.00810282.496" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.5479/si.00810282.496</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Deevey</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1949</year>)<article-title> The developmental history of <italic>Latrodectus mactans</italic> at different rates of feeding.</article-title> <source>The American Midland Naturalist </source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>-<lpage>219</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/2421795" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.2307/2421795</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Doleschall</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1859</year>)<article-title> Tweede Bijdrage tot de Kennis der Arachniden van den Indischen Archipel.</article-title> <source>Verhandelingen der Natuurkundige Vereeniging in Nederlandsch Indie </source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Griswold</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Investigations into the phylogeny of the Lycosid spiders and their kin (Arachnida: Araneae: Lycosoidea).</article-title> <source>Smithsonian contributions to zoology </source> <volume>539</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5479/si.00810282.539" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.5479/si.00810282.539</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Griswold</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coddington</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Towards a phylogeny of entelegyne spiders (Araneae, Araneomorphae, Entelegynae).</article-title> <source>The Journal of Arachnology </source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Griswold</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramírez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coddington</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> Atlas of phylogenetic data for entelegyne spiders (Araneae: Araneomorphae: Entelegynae) with comments on their phylogeny. Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences 56(Suppl. II): 1–324.
</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasselt van</surname><given-names>AWM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1877</year>)<article-title> Araneae exoticae, quas quondam in India Orientali (praesertim insula Amboina) collegit Cel. Dr. C. L. Doleschall, AC, pro Museo Lugdunensi.</article-title> <source>Tijdschrift voor Entomologie </source> <volume>20</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1914</year>)<article-title> Spiders collected by the Wollaston and British Ornithological Union Expeditions in Dutch New Guinea.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London (Series C Abstracts) </source> <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>56</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1915</year>)<article-title> Report on the spiders collected by the British Ornithologists' Union Expedition and the Wollaston Expedition in Dutch New Guinea.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the Zoological Society of London </source> <volume>20</volume> (<issue>14</issue>): <fpage>425</fpage>-<lpage>484</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Homann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1950</year>)<article-title> Die Nebenaugen der Araneen.</article-title> <source>Zoologische Jahrbücher, Abteilung für Anatomie und Ontogenie der Tiere </source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>56</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jäger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Revision of the huntsman spider genus <italic>Heteropoda</italic> Latreille 1804: species with exceptional male palpal conformations from Southeast Asia and Australia (Arachnida, Araneae, Sparassidae, Heteropodinae).</article-title> <source>Senckenbergiana biologica </source> <volume>88</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>239</fpage>-<lpage>310</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jäger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> The male of <italic>Heteropoda ocyalina</italic> (Simon, 1887) (Araneae: Sparassidae: Heteropodinae).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British Arachnological Society </source> <volume>14</volume> (<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>368</fpage>-<lpage>370</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jäger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Sparassidae of Japan. I. New Species of <italic>Olios</italic>, <italic>Heteropoda</italic>, and <italic>Sinopoda</italic>, with Notes on Some Known Species (Araneae: Sparassidae: Sparassinae and Heteropodinae).</article-title> <source>Acta Arachnologica </source> <volume>49</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2476/asjaa.49.41" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.2476/asjaa.49.41</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jose</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sebastian</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Occurrence of <italic>Psechrus alticeps</italic> Pocock (Araneae: Psechridae) in Western Ghats, Kerala with a redescription and notes on its habit and habitat.</article-title> <source>Journal, Bombay Natural History Society </source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>304</fpage>-<lpage>306</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>JKH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<source> A guide to common Singapore spiders. Singapore Science Centre. Singapore, 160 pp.
</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> The genus Stegodyphus (Arachnida, Araneae). Sibling species, species groups, and parallel origin of social living.</article-title> <source>Verhandlungen des Naturwissenschaftlichen Vereins in Hamburg </source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>254</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulczyński</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1908</year>)<article-title> Symbola ad faunam Aranearum Javae et Sumatrae cognoscendam. I. Mygalomorphae et Cribellatae.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de l'academie des sciences de Cracovie </source> <volume>6</volume> (<issue>1908</issue>): <fpage>527</fpage>-<lpage>581</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulczyński</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1910</year>)<article-title> Botanische und zoologische Ergebnisse einer wissenschaftlichen Forschungreise nach den Samoainseln, dem Neuguinea-Archipel und den Salomonsinseln von März bis Dezember 1905 von Dr Karl Rechinger. IV. Araneae et Arachnoidea Arthrogastra.</article-title> <source>Denkschriften der mathematisch-naturwissenschaftlichen Klasse der kaiserlichen Akademie der Wissenschaften, Wien </source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>389</fpage>-<lpage>411</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kullmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawabi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Neue Ergebnisse zur Brutbiologie cribellater Spinnen aus Afghanistan und der Serengeti (Araneae, Eresidae).</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift des Kölner Zoos </source> <volume>14</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lachmuth</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grasshoff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<source> Taxonomische Revision der Gattung <italic>Cupiennius</italic> SIMON 1891 (Arachnida: Araneae: Ctenidae). Senckenbergiana biologica 65(3/6): 329–372.
</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehtinen</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>)<article-title> Classification of the Cribellate Spiders and some allied families, with notes on the evolution of the suborder Araneomorpha.</article-title> <source>Annales Zoologici Fennici </source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>468</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>)<article-title> The spider genera <italic>Psechrus</italic> and <italic>Fecenia</italic> (Araneae: Psechridae).</article-title> <source>Pacific Insects </source> <volume>24</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>114</fpage>-<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<source> An introduction to the Spiders of South East Asia with notes on all the genera.</source> <publisher-name>Malaysian Nature Society, Kuala Lumpur</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Malaysia</publisher-loc>, <lpage>625</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> Additional information concerning the spider family Psechridae.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British Arachnological Society </source> <volume>7</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> <italic>The world spider catalog, version 11.5</italic>.American Museum of Natural History. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://research.amnh.org/entomology/spiders/catalog/" xlink:type="simple">http://research.amnh.org/entomology/spiders/catalog/</ext-link> (accessed: 01 March 2011)
</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrunkevitch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1928</year>)<article-title> Systema Aranearum.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>270</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1899</year>)<article-title> Diagnoses of some new Indian Arachnida.</article-title> <source>Journal of the Bombay Natural History Society </source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>744</fpage>-<lpage>753</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1900</year>)<source> The fauna of British India, including Ceylon and Burma.</source> <publisher-name>Taylor and Francis</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>279</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rainbow</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1913</year>)<article-title> Arachnida from the Solomon Islands.</article-title> <source>Records of the Australian Museum </source> <volume>10</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3853/j.0067-1975.10.1913.893" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.3853/j.0067-1975.10.1913.893</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Reimoser</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1929</year>)<article-title> Spolia Mentawiensia. Araneae.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the Raffles Museum Singapore </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>-<lpage>133</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Reimoser</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1936</year>)<source> Fauna Buruana. Arachnoidea. Treubia 7(Suppl.): 405–413.
</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lubin</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> Specialists and generalists: The ecology and behaviour of some web-building spiders from Papua New Guinea. II. <italic>Psechrus argentatus</italic> and <italic>Fecenia sp.</italic> (Araneae: Psechridae).</article-title> <source>Pacific Insects </source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>-<lpage>164</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sebastian</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<source> Spiders of India.</source> <publisher-name>Universities Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Hyderabad</publisher-loc>, <lpage>614</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sethi</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tikader</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> Studies on some giant crab spiders of the family Heteropodidae from India. Records of the Zoological Survey of India.</article-title> <source>Miscellaneous publication occasional paper </source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sierwald</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Revision der Gattung <italic>Thalassius</italic> (Arachnida, Araneae, Pisauridae).</article-title> <source>Verhandlungen des Naturwissenschaftlichen Vereins in Hamburg </source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sierwald</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Morphology and ontogeny of female copulatory organs in American Pisauridae, with special reference to homologous features (Arachnida: Araneae).</article-title> <source>Smithsonian Contributions to Zoology </source> <volume>484</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>24</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5479/si.00810282.484" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.5479/si.00810282.484</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B40"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1885</year>)<article-title> Matériaux pour servir à la faune arachnologique de l'Asie méridionale. III. Arachnides recueillis en 1884 dans la presqu'ile de Malacca par M. J. de Morgan.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Societe zoologique de France </source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B41"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1887</year>)<source> Observation sur divers arachnides: synonymies et descriptions. Annales de la Societe Entomologique de France (6)7(Bull.): 193–195.
</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B42"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1892</year>)<article-title> Histoire naturelle des araignées.</article-title> <source>Librairie Encyclopédique de Roret, Paris, </source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>256</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B43"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1906</year>)<article-title> Etude sur les araignées de la section des cribellates.</article-title> <source>Extrait des Annales de la Societe Entomologique de Belgique </source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>284</fpage>-<lpage>308</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B44"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>DX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen,</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> The Spiders of China.</source> <publisher-name>Hebei Science and Technology Publishing House</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Shijiazhuang</publisher-loc>, <lpage>640</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B45"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>DX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> A checklist of spiders from Singapore (Arachnida: Araneae).</article-title> <source>The Raffles Bulletin of Zoology </source> <volume>50</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>359</fpage>-<lpage>388</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B46"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stagl</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> Carl Ludwig Doleschall – Arzt, Forscher und Sammler.</article-title> <source>Quadrifina </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>-<lpage>203</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B47"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Strand</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1906</year>)<article-title> Studien über Bau und Entwicklung der Spinnen. I-III.</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift für wissenschaftliche Zoologie </source> <volume>80</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>515</fpage>-<lpage>543</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B48"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Strand</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1915</year>)<article-title> Wissenschaftliche Ergebnisse der Hanseatischen Südsee-Expedition 1909. III. Indoaustralische, papuanische und polynesische Spinnen des Senckenbergischen Museums, gesammelt von Dr E. Wolf, Dr J. Elbert u. a.</article-title> <source>Abhandlungen der Senckenbergischen Naturforschenden Gesellschaft </source> <volume>36</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>274</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B49"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1878</year>)<article-title> Studi sui ragni Malesi e Papuani. II. Ragni di Amboina raccolti dal Prof. O. Beccari.</article-title> <source>Annali del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale Giacomo Doria, Genova </source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>317</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B50"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1881</year>)<article-title> Studi sui Ragni Malesi e Papuani. III. Ragni dell‘Austro Malesia e del Capo York, conservati nel Museo civico di storia naturale di Genova.</article-title> <source>Annali del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale di Genova </source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>727</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B51"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1891</year>)<article-title> Spindlar från Nikobarerna och andra delar af södra Asien. Kongl.</article-title> <source>Svenska Vetenskaps-Academiens Handlingar </source> <volume>24</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B52"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><!--PageBreak--><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1895</year>)<source> Descriptive catalogue of the spiders of Burma.</source> <publisher-name>Longmans &amp; Co., British Museum of Natural History, and others</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>406</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B53"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1897</year>)<source> Viaggio di Leonardo Fea in Birmania e regioni vicine (LXXIII). Secondo saggio sui Ragni birmani. I. Parallelodontes. Tubitelariae. Annali del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale Giacomo Doria, Genova (2) 17[=37]: 161–267.
</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B54"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tikader</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>)<article-title> Studies on spider fauna of Andaman and Nicobar islands, Indian Ocean.</article-title> <source>Records of the Zoological Survey of India </source> <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>-<lpage>212</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B55"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>)<article-title> A new species of psechrid spider from China (Araneae: Psechridae).</article-title> <source>Acta Scientiarum Naturalium Universitatis Normalis Hunanensis </source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>-<lpage>258</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B56"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> A review of the Chinese Psechridae (Araneae).</article-title> <source>The Journal of Arachnology </source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>330</fpage>-<lpage>344</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1636/0161-8202(2001)029[0330:AROTCP]2.0.CO;2" xlink:type="simple">doi: 10.1636/0161-8202(2001)029[0330:AROTCP]2.0.CO;2</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B57"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<source> The role of juvenile hormone (JH) and its analogs (JHA) in <italic>Nephila clavipes</italic> development. Biology 198, Senior Research Project, Burlington, Vermont, USA: The University of Vermont. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.webberdigital.com/web/uploads/seniorresearch.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.webberdigital.com/web/uploads/seniorresearch.pdf</ext-link>
</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B58"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wigglesworth</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1952</year>)<article-title> Hormone balance and the control of metamorphosis in <italic>Rhodnius prolixus</italic> (Hemiptera).</article-title> <source>Journal of Experimental Biology </source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>620</fpage>-<lpage>631</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B59"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> A newly recorded of the spider genus <italic>Fecenia</italic> (Araneae: Psechridae) from China.</article-title> <source>Acta arachnologica sinica </source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B60"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>)<article-title> Phenology and life-cycle regulation of the fishing spider <italic>Dolomedes triton</italic> Walckenaer (Araneae, Pisauridae) in central Alberta.</article-title> <source>Canadian Journal of Zoology </source> <volume>76</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>309</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>