<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.185.2909</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>New species and records of Hydroptilidae (Trichoptera) from Venezuela</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Thomson</surname>
                        <given-names>Robin E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:0BF22276-86CB-46FD-9251-045A24C10962</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Holzenthal</surname>
                        <given-names>Ralph W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:C27A1C49-F372-4232-A49C-B8B5F753CC70</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Entomology, University of Minnesota, 219 Hodson Hall, 1980 Folwell Avenue, St. Paul, Minnesota, 55108, USA
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Department of Entomology, National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, DC 20013, USA
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Robin E. Thomson (<email xlink:type="simple">thom1514@umn.edu</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Christy Geraci</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>23</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>185</issue>
            <fpage>19</fpage>
            <lpage>39</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>10</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>17</day>
                    <month>4</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Robin E. Thomson, Ralph W. Holzenthal</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:6302D0EF-A872-4DAC-BCBC-D1B3D328F6EE</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Eight new species of <tp:taxon-name>Hydroptilidae</tp:taxon-name> (<tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>) from Venezuela are described: <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acostatrichia digitata</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hydroptila cressae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metrichia botrychion</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ochrotrichia spira</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira bettyae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira quiramae</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira redunca</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhyacopsyche shorti</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold>New country records for Venezuela of 2 additional species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotrichia feolai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Santos &amp; Nessimian, 2009 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira picita</tp:taxon-name></italic> Harris &amp; Davenport, 1999, are also provided. Illustrations of male genitalia are provided with each description.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Trichoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>caddisflies</kwd>
                <kwd>Hydroptilidae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic><tp:taxon-name>Anchitrichia</tp:taxon-name></italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hydroptila</tp:taxon-name></italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic><tp:taxon-name>Metrichia</tp:taxon-name></italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotrichia</tp:taxon-name></italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ochrotrichia</tp:taxon-name></italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira</tp:taxon-name></italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhyacopsyche</tp:taxon-name></italic></kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
                <kwd>Neotropical</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Caddisflies, or <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>, are a diverse order of insects with ~15,000 described species and 100s of new species awaiting description (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Holzenthal et al. 2011</xref>). <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name> faunal diversity is particularly impressive in the Neotropical biogeographical region, <!--PageBreak-->where recent inventories have revealed up to 75% of collected species to be undescribed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Holzenthal et al. 2007</xref>) <tp:taxon-name>Hydroptilidae</tp:taxon-name> is the largest family in the order, including 75 genera, ~2,000 described species found all over the world, and a high number of undescribed species. As their common name, microcaddisflies, suggests, hydroptilids are minute with few larger than 5 mm. The aquatic larvae construct portable or fixed silken purse-like cases in the final instar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Wiggins 2004</xref>). The larvae of many species feed on algae, while some feed on moss microphylls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Wiggins 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Carins and Wells 2008</xref>). Some have been known to be predatory, while others are parasitoids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Wells 1985</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">2005</xref>).</p>
            <p>In this paper, we describe 8 new hydroptilid species in 6 genera from Venezuela.We also provide new country records for Venezuela for 2 species, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotrichia feolai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Santos &amp; Nessimian, 2009 and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira picita</tp:taxon-name></italic> Harris &amp; Davenport, 1999. The material was collected as part of a project under the direction of Dr. Andrew Short, University of Kansas, USA, to inventory the aquatic <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name> and other aquatic insect orders of Venezuela. In June, 2010, a team of 4 American and 4 Venezuelan entomologists collected aquatic insects in the southern half of Venezuela, including the <italic>llanos</italic> of Guárico state, the southern tributaries of the upper to middle Orinoco River basin, and the <italic>Gran Sabana</italic> of Bolívar state, and, in northern Venezuela, the Turimiquire Mountains of Monagas state. About 90 species of <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name> were collected, including about 25 new species of which the new <tp:taxon-name>Hydroptilidae</tp:taxon-name> are described here.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Materials and methods">
            <title>Materials and methods</title>
            <p>Morphological terminology used for male genitalia of specimens in the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira</tp:taxon-name></italic> follows that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Kelley (1984)</xref>, for the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metrichia</tp:taxon-name></italic> that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Flint (1972)</xref>, and for the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhyacopsyche</tp:taxon-name></italic> that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Wasmund and Holzenthal (2007)</xref>. All others follow the terminology of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Marshall (1979)</xref>. For simplicity, paired structures are discussed in the singular. Procedures for specimen preparation followed those explained in detail by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Blahnik et al. (2007)</xref>. For specimen examination and illustration, cleared genitalia were placed in a watch glass with glycerin and small glass beads. The glass beads held the genitalia in place and allowed structures to be viewed in precise lateral, dorsal, and ventral positions. Genitalia were examined with an Olympus BX41 compound microscope at 250–500 × magnification. Structures were traced in pencil with the use of a <italic>camera lucida</italic> (drawing tube) mounted on the microscope. Pencil sketches were then scanned (Fujitsu ScanSnap S1500M scanner), edited in Adobe Photoshop (v. 9.0.2, Adobe Systems Inc.), and used as a template in Adobe Illustrator (v. 13.0.2, Adobe Systems Inc.) to be digitally inked. Electronic “drawing” was completed with the aid of a graphics tablet (Bamboo Fun, Wacom Company, Limited). Species descriptions were constructed using the program DELTA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Dallwitz et al. 1999</xref>) and specimen management followed the procedures outlined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Holzenthal and Andersen (2004)</xref>. Each pinned specimen examined during the study was affixed with a barcode label (4 mil polyester, 8 × 14 mm, code 49) bearing a unique alphanumeric sequence begi<!--PageBreak-->nning with the prefix UMSP. Specimens in alcohol were given a single barcode label to represent all those in a single vial. The prefix is not meant to imply ownership by the University of Minnesota Insect Collection (UMSP), but only to indicate that the specimen was databased at that collection. Types of species described and other material examined are deposited in the University of Minnesota Insect Collection, St. Paul, Minnesota (UMSP), the National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C. (NMNH), and the Museo del Instituto de Zoología Agrícola, Maracay, Venezuela (MIZA).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Acostatrichia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">digitata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:85981ECC-3397-4968-ACBC-B6EE2098DA5B</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Acostatrichia_digitata</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Thomson &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acostatrichia fimbriata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Flint, 1974 but can be distinguished by a mesoventral process on abdominal segment VII with an apex that is truncate and rugose, not pointed. The posterolateral process of abdominal segment VIII bears digitate projections apically, unlike the spines on <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acostatrichia fimbriata</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Additionally, the subgenital appendage of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Acostatrichia digitatus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is pointed apically instead of rounded.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Male</italic>. Length of forewing 2.7 mm (n=1). Head unmodified, with 3 ocelli; antennae unmodified. Tibial spur count 1, 3, 4. Dorsum of head dark brown with pale yellow setae; thorax dark brown with pale yellow setae dorsally, light brown ventrally; leg segments with light brown setae. Forewings covered with fine yellow setae and small scattered patches of dark brown setae. <italic>Genitalia</italic>. Abdominal sternum VII with long mesoventral process, apex truncate, rugose. Segment VIII anterolateral margin straight, posterolateral margin greatly elongate into narrow structure bearing digitate apical projections; ventrally posterior margin concave, mildly crenulated. Segment IX anterolateral margin acute, posterolateral margin broadly convex; with mesolateral quadrate structure bearing prominent setae (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>); dorsally with posterior margin straight. Subgenital appendage paired, broadly rounded with apicoventral point, dorsally with rounded emargination on inner edge. Inferior appendage setose, narrow, rod-like, fused latero-ventrally with subgenital appendage, in ventral view with semiquadrate apical emargination (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>). Tergum X membranous, triangular in dorsal view. Phallus tubular basally with median complex bearing basal loop and pair of circular “windows”, apex with pair of elliptic plates, strongly sclerotized mesolaterally.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 1.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Acostatrichia digitata</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> segments IX–X, lateral (base of phallus crosshatched) <bold>B</bold> segments VII–VIII and segment IX anterolateral margin, lateral <bold>C</bold> segments IX–X, dorsal  <bold>D</bold> segments VII–IX, ventral <bold>E</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>F</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-185-019-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype male:</bold> <bold>VENEZUELA: Bolívar:</bold> E Tumeremo, W Bochinche, Río Botonamo, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">07°25.462'N, 61°14.318'W</named-content>, 150 m, 13.vii.2010, UV light, Holzenthal, Thomson, Cressa (UMSP000095201) (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The Latin word <italic>digitatus</italic> meaning “having fingers”,referring to the digitate projections on the posterolateral process of the VIIIth segment.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Hydroptila</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">cressae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:22765A69-4EE1-4DA6-BB78-E100D0C6EF33</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Hydroptila_cressae</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Thomson &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hydroptila denza</tp:taxon-name></italic> Ross, 1948, but differs in the shape of the projection on the posterolateral margin of abdominal segment IX. This projection is more pointed and is curved downward, or decurved, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hydroptila cressae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, while it is straight and more blunt in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hydroptila denza</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The triangular subgenital process seen in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hydroptila denza</tp:taxon-name></italic> is not apparent in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hydroptila cressae</tp:taxon-name></italic>.Additionally, tergum X of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hydroptila cressae</tp:taxon-name></italic> contains an internal apodeme that is not apparent in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Hydroptila denza</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Male</italic>. Length of forewing 2.0 mm (n=1). Head unmodified, without ocelli; antennae unmodified. Tibial spur count 0, 2, 4. Dorsum of head brown with pale yellow setae; thorax brown with light brown setae dorsally, light brown ventrally; leg segments with light brown setae. Forewings covered with fine light brown setae with small dark brown patch of setae at apex. <italic>Genitalia</italic>. Abdominal sternum VII with simple, slender, pointed mesoventral process. Segment VIII unmodified. Segment IX anterolateral margin convex, posterolateral margin with pointed projection, curving slightly ventrad; dorsally with posterior margin convex. Inferior appendage setose, with narrow base, apex truncate with pair of dark points on internal face. Tergum X membranous, extending past inferior appendage, containing internal sclerotized apodeme (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Phallus narrow, elongate; apex membranous, ovate, with elongate, slender spines extending past membranous region.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Hydroptila cressae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> segments VII–X, lateral (base of phallus crosshatched) <bold>B</bold> segments VIII-X, dorsal <bold>C</bold> segments VII–IX, ventral <bold>D</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>E</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-185-019-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotypemale:</bold> <bold>VENEZUELA: Bolívar:</bold> Gran Sabana, E. Pauji, “Río Curvita”, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">04°31.237'N, 61°31.591'W</named-content>, 869 m, 15–16.vii.2010, UV light, Holzenthal, Thomson, Cressa (UMSP000095196) (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named in honor of Dr. Claudia Cressa, an aquatic ecologist at the Universidad Central de Venezuela and friend and colleague of the authors.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Metrichia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">bostrychion</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:13F7C864-63DB-4360-92FA-D3CB3331DBA3</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Metrichia_bostrychion</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Thomson &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metrichia anisoscola</tp:taxon-name></italic> (Flint, 1991), but differs in the shape of the inferior appendage, which is less elongate in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metrichia bostrychion</tp:taxon-name></italic> and more suborbicular. The dorsolateral hook in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metrichia bostrychion</tp:taxon-name></italic> is also stouter than that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metrichia anisoscola</tp:taxon-name></italic>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Metrichia bostrychion</tp:taxon-name></italic> can also be distinguished by the 3rd spine on the phallus which spirals dorsally.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Male</italic>. Length of forewing 1.8 mm (n=1). Head unmodified, with 3 ocelli; antennae unmodified. Tibial spur count 1, 3, 4. Dorsum of head dark brown with white setae; thorax dark brown with white and dark brown setae dorsally, brow<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->n ventrally; leg segments with brown setae. Forewings covered with fine dark brown setae with small patch of light brown setae at apex. Abdomen with internal sacs between segments IV–V. Dorsolateral setal brushes on segments IV and V. <italic>Genitalia</italic>. Abdominal sternum VII with short, pointed mesoventral process. Segment VIII unmodified. Segment IX anterolateral margin very elongate, narrowing, withdrawn into segments VII–VIII, posterolateral margin convex; dorsally with posterior margin membranous, flat. Preanal appendage (cercus) short, rounded. Dorsolateral hook stout, strongly decurved (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Inferior appendage suborbicular with shallow posterolateral emargination, extends as high as segment IX. Tergum X membranous, apex subdeltoid in dorsal view. Phallus widest at base, narrowing to median constriction, membranous apex with 3 spines, 1st and 3rd slender, elongate, 2nd spiraling dorsad.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 3.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Metrichia bostrychion</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> segments VII–X, lateral (base of phallus crosshatched) <bold>B</bold> segments IX–X, dorsal <bold>C</bold> segments VII–IX, ventral <bold>D</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>E</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-185-019-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype male:</bold> <bold>VENEZUELA: Monagas:</bold> Guachero Cave National Park at La Paila waterfall, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">10°10.322'N, 63°33.315'W</named-content>, 1110 m, 20–21.vii.2010, sweep net, Holzenthal, Thomson (UMSP000095197) (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratype">
                    <title>Paratype.</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 1 female (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The diminutive of the Greek word <italic>bostrychos</italic> meaning “curl”, referring to the small spiral in the second apical spine on the phallus.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Neotrichia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">feolai</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Neotrichia_feolai</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Santos &amp; Nessimian, 2009</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">redescription and new country record</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Neotrichia feolai</tp:taxon-name><comment> Santos &amp; Nessimian, 2009: 766 [Type locality: Brazil, Amazonas, Rio Preto da Eva (tributary to Rio Preto da Eva); INPA; male].</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotrichia feolai</tp:taxon-name></italic> was previously only known from the male holotype collected from Brazil, Amazonas. Eight males were collected for the first time from Venezuela, representing a new record in this study for the country. Original illustrations did not include the distinctive subgenital appendage, but specimens from Venezuela match all other characteristics of the Brazilian species perfectly. Some of our specimens are dry, while the holotype was collected in alcohol, allowing us to to describe coloration. We have also described and illustrated the subgenital plate not seen in the original illustration.</p>
                    <p>According to the original authors, this species is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotrichia biuncifera</tp:taxon-name></italic> Flint, 1974. The shapes and lengths of the bracteole and inferior appendage are similar, but <italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotrichia feolai</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished by having only a single spine at the apex of the phallus.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Redescription">
                    <title>Redescription.</title>
                    <p><italic>Male</italic>. Length of forewing 1.6–1.9 mm (n=8). Head unmodified, with 3 ocelli; antennae unmodified. Tibial spur count 0, 2, 3. Dorsum of head brown with light brown setae; thorax brown with light brown setae dorsally, light brown ventrally; leg segments with light brown setae. Forewings covered with fine light brown setae with small patches of dark brown setae. <italic>Genitalia</italic>. Abdominal sternum VII with<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->out mesoventral process. Segment VIII unmodified. Segment IX anterolateral margin strongly narrowing, withdrawn into segment VIII, posterolateral margin fused dorsally with tergum X (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Subgenital plate fused, diamond-shaped with pair of apico-ventral setae, posterior margin bearing paired row of sclerotized spines within membranous layer (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs. 4A, 4C</xref>). Bracteole spatulate, extended evenly with inferior appendage. Inferior appendage setose, laterally narrow and rod-like, fused latero-ventrally with subgenital appendages, ventrally with semiquadrate apical emargination. Tergum X membranous, bearing minute dorsal setae, with deep emargination both laterally and dorsally, dorsal lobe with sclerotized apex. Phallus with wide tubular base narrowing to median constriction, membranous apex with spiral process and slender apical spines.</p>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 4.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Neotrichia feolai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Santos &amp; Nessimian, 2009. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> segments VIII–X, lateral (base of phallus crosshatched) <bold>B</bold> segments IX–X, dorsal <bold>C</bold> segment IX, ventral <bold>D</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>E</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-185-019-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>VENEZUELA: Guárico:</bold> Santa Rita, Morichal de los Becerros, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">08°09.044’N, 62°35.149’W</named-content>, 66 m, 6.vii.2010, UV light, Holzenthal, Thomson, 8 males (5 in alcohol) (UMSP, NMNH, MIZA).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Ochrotrichia</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">spira</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:83832CD2-268B-4AA3-A5EC-F6FAB463D9F6</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Ochrotrichia_spira</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Thomson &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ochrotrichia raposa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Bueno-Soria &amp; Santiago-Fragoso, 1992. Both have a simple, threadlike phallus and the large inferior appendage bears patches of black pegs on its internal face. The inferior appendage of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ochrotrichia spiralis</tp:taxon-name></italic>, however, is parallel-sided with a truncate apex. Also, the sclerotized processes extending from tergum X of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ochrotrichia spiralis</tp:taxon-name></italic> are easily distinguishable from those of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ochrotrichia raposa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, in particular the large, spiral process.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Male</italic>. Length of forewing 2.6–2.7 mm (n=3). Head unmodified, with 3 ocelli; antennae unmodified. Tibial spur count 0, 3, 4. Dorsum of head dark brown with pale yellow setae; thorax light brown with light brown setae dorsally, light brown ventrally; leg segments with light brown setae and patches of dark brown. Forewings covered with fine brown setae with small patches of dark brown setae near apex. <italic>Genitalia</italic>. Abdominal sternum VII with short, rounded mesoventral process. Segment VIII unmodified. Segment IX anterolateral margin concave, posterolateral margin fused dorsally with tergum X. Inferior appendage setose, 3 times longer than wide, parallel-sided, apex truncate, inner surface bearing many short, stout spines distributed as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs. 5A, 5C</xref>. Tergum X sclerotized, highly developed with 3 processes: 1st simple, slender pointed; 2nd with heavily sclerotized edge, large subapical point, small apical point; 3rd strongly spiraled, extended past other processes. Phallus tubular, elongate, threadlike.</p>
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 5.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Ochrotrichia spira</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> segments VII-X, lateral (base of phallus crosshatched) <bold>B</bold> segments VIII–X, dorsal <bold>C</bold> segments VII–IX, ventral <bold>D</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>E</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-185-019-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotypemale:</bold> <bold>VENEZUELA: Monagas:</bold> Guachero Cave National Park, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">10°10.322'N, 63°33.315'W</named-content>, 1110 m, 20–21.vii.2010, UV light, Holzenthal, Thomson, Cressa (UMSP000095193) (UMSP)<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes">
                    <title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 2 males (UMSP, NMNH).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The Latin word <italic>spiralis</italic> meaing “spiral”, referring to the strongly spiraled process extending from tergum X.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Oxyethira</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        (<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subgenus">Tanytrichia</tp:taxon-name-part>)
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">bettyae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:9B85F4D2-070A-4192-BD8D-E4DF432D19AA</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Oxyethira_bettyae</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Thomson &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is placed in the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tanytrichia</tp:taxon-name></italic> according to the characters given by Kelley (1985): segment VIII venter excised to anterior margin, segment IX elongate and extending into segment VI, the absence of segment IX dorsum, and a phallus bearing two long lateral processes originating at the midlength. This species is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira longissima</tp:taxon-name></italic> Flint, 1974. The phallus is very similar, bearing long paired processes sharply bent back anteriorly. However, the subgenital process of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira longissima</tp:taxon-name></italic> is more strongly arched and much more slender in lateral view than that of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira bettyae</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Also, when viewed ventrally, the bilobed process of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira bettyae</tp:taxon-name></italic> is wider basally than <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira longissima</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Male</italic>. Length of forewing 2.0–2.2 mm (n=6). Head unmodified, with 3 ocelli; antennae unmodified. Tibial spur count 0, 3, 4. Dorsum of head dark brown with pale yellow setae; thorax brown with light brown setae dorsally; leg segments with light brown setae. Forewings covered with fine light brown setae and small scattered patches of dark brown setae and golden brown setae. <italic>Genitalia</italic>. Abdominal sternum VII with simple, pointed mesoventral process with small patch of stout pegs basally. Segment VIII anterolateral margin straight, posterolateral margin pointed; dorsally posterior margin with rounded emargination; ventrally posterior margin with deeply divided. Segment IX anterolateral margin very narrow and very elongate, withdrawn into segments VI–VIII, posterolateral margin straight, not extended posteriorly past segment VIII. Subgenital process fused, apex with small rounded emargination (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>). Bilobed process slender, extending posteriad. Inferior appendage fused with deep apical emargination, sparsely setose, heavily sclerotized, apex acute, upturned in lateral view. Tergum X membranous, quadrate dorsally, oblong ventrally. Phallus with tubular basal half, apical half membranous; 2 long, lateral processes beginning at midlength, very sharply curved backward, or recurved.</p>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 6.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira bettyae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> segments VI–X, lateral (base of phallus crosshatched) <bold>B</bold> segments VI–X, dorsal <bold>C</bold> segments VI–IX, ventral <bold>D</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>E</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-185-019-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotypemale:</bold> <bold>VENEZUELA: Guárico:</bold> UCV San Nicolasito Field Station, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">08°8.296'N, 66°24.459'W</named-content>, 62 m, 5.vii.2010, UV light, Holzenthal, Thomson (UMSP000095178) (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes">
                    <title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 1 male (UMSP); <bold>Venezuela: Bolívar:</bold> Los Pijiguaos at rock outcrop, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">6°35.617'N, 66°49.238'W</named-content>, 80 m, 7–8.vii.2010, UV light trap, Holzenthal, Thomson, 5 males (in alcohol) (UMSP, NMNH, MIZA).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named in honor of the first author’s grandmother, Betty Welter, who passed away while this work was in progress.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Oxyethira</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">picita</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Oxyethira_picita</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Harris &amp; Davenport, 1999</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">new country record</tp:taxon-status>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira picita</tp:taxon-name><comment> Harris &amp; Davenport, 1999: 35 [Type locality: Peru, Loreto, edge of Rio Sucusari backwater, adjoining Explorama lodge; NMNH; male]. - Santos et al. 2009: 36, 43 [distribution].</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira picita</tp:taxon-name></italic> was previously known only from the male holotype collected from Peru, Loreto. A single male was collected at a later date from Brazil, Amazonas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Santos et al. 2009</xref>). Five males were now collected for the first time from Venezuela, representing a new record for the country. All five males were collected in alcohol.</p>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira picita</tp:taxon-name></italic> was placed in the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tanytrichia</tp:taxon-name></italic> by Harris &amp; Davenport (1999), although it was suggested that it also displayed some similarity to the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Loxotrichia</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The original description and illustration of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira picita</tp:taxon-name></italic> are detailed and well done; further description or illustration was not thought necessary.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>VENEZUELA: Bolívar:</bold> Campamento Río Aro, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">07°37.443'N, 64°08.324'W</named-content>, 90 m, 10–11.vii.2010, UV light, Holzenthal, Thomson, 4 males (in alcohol) (UMSP, MIZA). <bold>VENEZUELA: Bolívar:</bold> 30 km S Upata, roadside marsh, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">07°22.239'N, 61°44.233'W</named-content>, 163 m, 12.viii.2010, Short, Tellez, Camacho, 1 male (in alcohol) (NMNH).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Oxyethira</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        (<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subgenus">Dactylotrichia</tp:taxon-name-part>)
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">quiramae</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6C447B87-EA39-4D06-A28A-0702345D2930</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Oxyethira_quiramae</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Thomson &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is placed in the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Dactylotrichia</tp:taxon-name></italic> according to the characters given by Kelley (1985): segment VIII venter excised nearly to the anterior margin and segment IX venter extending anteriorly through segments VIII–VI. This species is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira hozosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Harris &amp; Davenport, 1999. Both species have short, blunt, ventrally triangular inferior appendages and a phallus with a distal curved process and an ejaculatory duct enclosed within the membranous apex. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira quiramae</tp:taxon-name></italic> can be distinguished by a subgenital plate that is not as strongly decurved and lacks an acute apex in lateral view. Also, in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira quiramae</tp:taxon-name></italic>, segment IX extends anteriorly past the posterior margin of abdominal segment VI.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Male</italic>. Length of forewing 1.8–1.9 mm (n=3). Head unmodified, with 3 ocelli; antennae unmodified. Tibial spur count 0, 3, 4. Dorsum of head brown with light brown setae; thorax brown with light brown setae dorsally, light brown ventrally; leg segments with light brown setae. Forewings covered with fine brown setae with small scattered patches of light brown setae and small patches of dark brown setae near margins and apex. <italic>Genitalia</italic>. Abdominal sternum VII with simple, digitat<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->e mesoventral process with large patch of stout pegs basally. Segment VIII anterolateral margin straight, posterolateral margin convex with small mesal emargination; dorsally posterior margin with rounded emargination; ventrally deeply excised. Segment IX anterolateral margin narrow and elongate, withdrawn into segments VI–VIII, posterolateral margin straight, not extended posteriorly past segment VIII. Subgenital process fused distomesally, apex with shallow emargination, curving ventrad (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7C</xref>). Bilobed process slender, curved, not extending posteriorly past segment VIII. Inferior appendage reduced, triangular, heavily sclerotized (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7C</xref>). Tergum X not apparent. Phallus with tubular basal half, apical half membranous; apex elongate, slender, pointed, curving dorsad and sharply recurved.</p>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 7.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira quiramae</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> segments VI–IX, lateral (base of phallus crosshatched) <bold>B</bold> segments VII–IX, dorsal <bold>C</bold> segments VII–IX, ventral <bold>D</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>E</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-185-019-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype male:</bold> <bold>VENEZUELA: Guárico:</bold> UCV San Nicolasito Field Station, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">08°8.296'N, 66°24.459'W</named-content>, 62 m, 5.vii.2010, UV light, Holzenthal, Thomson (UMSP000095179) (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes">
                    <title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 2 males (NMNH, MIZA).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named in honor of Gina Quiram, a friend and colleague of the first author, for all her help in the field.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Oxyethira</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">redunca</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:C8A428D1-6558-479C-8AF8-8857D6E2A5FB</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Oxyethira_redunca</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Thomson &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>We have been unable to assign this species to a subgenus. The deep ventral excision of abdominal segment VIII and the extension of segment IX anteriorly into segment VII make it somewhat similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Loxotrichia</tp:taxon-name></italic>. However, the absence of a subgenital process precludes it from being placed with certainty in any of the current subgenera and distinguishes it from all other species.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Male</italic>. Length of forewing 2.4 mm (n=1). Head unmodified, with 3 ocelli; antennae unmodified. Tibial spur count 0, 3, 4. Dorsum of head brown with pale yellow setae; thorax brown with pale yellow setae dorsally, pale yellow ventrally; leg segments with brown setae. Forewings covered with fine brown setae and elongate patches of light brown setae and small patches of dark brown setae near margins and apex. <italic>Genitalia</italic>. Abdominal sternum VII with spatulate mesoventral process. Segment VIII anterolateral margin straight, posterolateral margin acutely convex; dorsally posterior margin with deep acute emargination; ventrally posterior margin with deep rounded emargination. Segment IX anterolateral margin very elongate, narrowing, withdrawn into segments VII–VIII, posterolateral margin acute, not extending past segment VIII; dorsally bearing paired, elongate, slender processes, basal half extending posteriorly, apical half strongly bent anteriad. Subgenital process not apparent. Bilobed process not apparent. Inferior appendage setose, laterally narrow and rod-like, fused latero-ventrally with subgenital appendages, ventrally with semiquadrate apical emargination. Tergum X <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->membranous, large, bearing elliptic patch of minute setae dorsally (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8B</xref>). Phallus with tubular basal half, apical half membranous, convex ventrally, apex curving dorsad.</p>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 8.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Oxyethira redunca</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> segments VII–X, lateral (base of phallus crosshatched) <bold>B</bold> segments VII–X, dorsal <bold>C</bold> segments VII–X, ventral <bold>D</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>E</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-185-019-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype male:</bold> <bold>VENEZUELA: Bolívar:</bold> Gran Sabana, E. Pauji, “Río Curvita”, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">4°31.237'N, 61°31.591'W</named-content>, 869 m, 15–16.vii.2010, UV light, Holzenthal, Thomson, Cressa (UMSP000095176) (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The Latin word <italic>reduncus</italic> meaning “bent backward”, referring to the sharply bent dorsal processes of segment IX.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Rhyacopsyche</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">shorti</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:56EB1974-52AA-4EE1-9F95-357CD2AC3A4A</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Rhyacopsyche_shorti</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Thomson &amp; Holzenthal</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>This species is most similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhyacopsyche otarosa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Wasmund &amp; Holzenthal, 2007. Both species display an inferior appendage with a bifid apex bearing a large rounded dorsal lobe. However, the ventral lobe is broadly pointed in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhyacopsyche shorti</tp:taxon-name></italic> and truncate in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhyacopsyche otarosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Additionally, when seen dorsally, the dorsolateral lobes of segment IX are rounded in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhyacopsyche shorti</tp:taxon-name></italic>, not acicular as in <italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhyacopsyche otarosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p><italic>Male</italic>. Length of forewing 2.6–2.7 mm (n=2). Head unmodified, with 3 ocelli; antennae unmodified. Tibial spur count 1, 3, 4. Dorsum of head brown with dark brown setae and light brown patch between antennae; thorax brown with light brown setae dorsally, light brown ventrally; leg segments with dark brown setae. Forewings covered with golden brown setae with small patches of dark brown setae at margins and apex. <italic>Genitalia</italic>. Abdominal sternum VII without mesoventral process. Segment VIII unmodified. Segment IX anterolateral margin very elongate, narrowing, withdrawn into segments VII–VIII, posterolateral margin with rounded setae-bearing dorsolateral lobe and truncate mesolateral lobe. Inferior appendage with rounded mesodorsal projection bearing setae, setae directed anteriad; apex heavily sclerotized, curving dorsad, acute. Tergum X membranous, round in dorsal view, contracted inside dorsolateral lobes of segment IX. Phallus basally tubular, elongate, narrow, apex membranous and with thickened spines.</p>
                    <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 9.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Rhyacopsyche shorti</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. Male genitalia: <bold>A</bold> segments IX–X, lateral (base of phallus crosshatched) <bold>B</bold> segments IX–X, dorsal <bold>C</bold> inferior appendages, ventral <bold>D</bold> phallus, lateral <bold>E</bold> phallus, dorsal.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-185-019-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p><bold>Holotype male:</bold> <bold>VENEZUELA: Bolívar:</bold> Gran Sabana, E. Pauji, “Río Curvita”, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">04°31.237'N, 61°31.591'W</named-content>, 869 m, 15–16.vii.2010, UV light, Holzenthal, Thomson, Cressa (UMSP000095199) (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratype">
                    <title>Paratype.</title>
                    <p>same data as holotype, 1 male (UMSP).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>Named in honor of Dr. Andrew Short, an entomologist at the University of Kansas and friend and colleague of the authors<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>We are grateful to Dr. Andrew Short, University of Kansas, for giving us the opportunity to collect fresh material in Venezuela and for his expertise as expedition leader. For assistance in the field, we would like to thank Dr. Claudia Cressa, Jesús Camacho, Monica Tellez, Sergio Pacheco, and Quintin Arias. Special thanks are extended to Dr. José Clavijo, MIZA, for administrative and logistic support and for his hospitality. Dr. OS Flint, Jr., Smithsonian Institution, provided invaluable comments on the identity and placement of these new species. This material is based on work supported by the National Science Foundation under Grant Nos. DEB 0816904 to AEZ Short and KB Miller and 0816865 to KM Kjer and RW Holzenthal. RE Thomson was supported also by a CIC Smithsonian Institution Fellowship. This support is gratefully acknowledged.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blahnik</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prather</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> The lactic acid method for clearing Trichoptera genitalia.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bueno-Soria</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barba-Alvarez</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armitage</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>). <issue-title>Proceedings of the XIIth International Symposium on Trichoptera.</issue-title> <source>The Caddis Press, Columbus, Ohio</source>: <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bueno-Soria</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santiago-Fragoso</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Studies in aquatic insects, XI: seven new species of the genus <italic>Ochrotrichia (Ochrotrichia)</italic> from South America (Trichoptera: Hydroptilidae).</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington </source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>-<lpage>446</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dallwitz</surname> <given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paine</surname> <given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zurcher</surname> <given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> User’s guide to the DELTA Editor. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://delta-intkey.com/" xlink:type="simple">http://delta-intkey.com/</ext-link> [accessed 6 February 2012]</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Carins</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Contrasting modes of handling moss for feeding and case-building by the caddisfly <italic>Scelotrichia willcarinsi</italic> (Insecta: Trichoptera).</article-title> <source>Journal of Natural History </source> <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>2609</fpage>-<lpage>2615</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00222930802354308" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/00222930802354308</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flint</surname> <given-names>OS Jr</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Studies of Neotropical caddisflies, XIV: on a collection from northern Argentina.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Biological Society of Washington </source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>-<lpage>248</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flint</surname> <given-names>OS Jr</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<article-title> Studies of Neotropical caddisflies, XV: the Trichoptera of Surinam.</article-title> <source>Studies on the Fauna of Suriname and other Guianas </source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>151</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Flint</surname> <given-names>OS Jr</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>)<article-title> Studies of Neotropical caddisfliesm XLV: the taxonomy, phenology, and faunistics of the Trichoptera of Antioquia, Colombia.</article-title> <source>Smithsonian Contributions to Zoology </source> <volume>520</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>113</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5479/si.00810282.520" xlink:type="simple">10.5479/si.00810282.520</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davenport</surname> <given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<article-title> New species of Hydroptilidae (Trichoptera) from the Amazon region of northeastern Peru.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington  </source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> The caddisfly genus <italic>Triaenodes</italic> in the Neotropics (Trichoptera: Leptoceridae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>511</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blahnik</surname> <given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prather</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjer</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Order Trichoptera Kirby, 1813 (Insecta), Caddisflies.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1668</volume>: <fpage>639</fpage>-<lpage>698</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morse</surname> <given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjer</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Order Trichoptera Kirby, 1813.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>ZQ</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title> Animal biodiversity: an outline of higher-level classification and survey of taxonomic richness.</issue-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>3148</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelley</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> Phylogeny, morphology and classification of the micro-caddisfly genus <italic>Oxyethira</italic> Eaton (Trichoptera: Hydroptilidae).</article-title> <source>Transactions of the American Entomological Society </source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>435</fpage>-<lpage>463</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname> <given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>)<article-title> A review of the genera of the Hydroptilidae (Trichoptera).</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History) Entomology Series </source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>-<lpage>239</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname> <given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1948</year>)<article-title> Notes and descriptions of Nearctic Hydroptilidae (Trichoptera).</article-title> <source>Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences </source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>-<lpage>206</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname> <given-names>APM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henriques-Oliveira</surname> <given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nessimian</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> New species and records of <italic>Oxyethira</italic> Eaton (Trichoptera: Hydroptilidae) from Amazonas State, Brazil.</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>2169</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname> <given-names>APM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nessimian</surname> <given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> New species and records of <italic>Neotrichia</italic> (Trichoptera: Hydroptilidae) from Central Amazonia, Brazil.</article-title> <source>Zoologia </source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>758</fpage>-<lpage>768</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wasmund</surname> <given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzenthal</surname> <given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> A revision of the Neotropical caddisfly genus <italic>Rhyacopsyche</italic>, with the description of 13 new species (Trichoptera: Hydroptilidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1634</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<article-title> Larvae and pupae of Australian Hydroptilidae (Trichoptera), with observations on general bilogy and relationships.</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Zoology, Supplementary Series </source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>69</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/AJZS113" xlink:type="simple">10.1071/AJZS113</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Parasitism by hydroptilid caddisflies (Trichoptera) and seven new species of Hydroptilidae from northern Queensland.</article-title> <source>Australian Journal of Entomology </source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>-<lpage>391</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1440-6055.2005.00492.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1440-6055.2005.00492.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiggins</surname> <given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<source> Caddisflies: The Underwater Architects.</source> <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc>, <lpage>292</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>