<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.75.884</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    A new species of Amblyodus Westwood, 1878 (Coleoptera, Melolonthidae, Dynastinae) from South America
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Grossi</surname>
                        <given-names>Paschoal Coelho</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:5347A9A1-F9DD-44E8-ABB8-2542E8EDF1FB</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Grossi</surname>
                        <given-names>Everardo José</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:479A0E54-0EC5-45AE-992A-63782C258105</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>Universidade Federal do Paraná, Centro Politécnico, Departamento de Zoologia, Caixa Postal 19007, CEP 81531-980, Curitiba, Paraná, Brazil</label></aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>Caixa Postal 96887, CEP 28610-974, Nova Friburgo, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding authors: Paschoal Coelho Grossi (<email xlink:type="simple">paschoal.grossi@gmail.com</email>), Everardo José Grossi (<email xlink:type="simple">everardogrossi@globo.com</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Andrey Frolov</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>12</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>75</issue>
            <fpage>21</fpage>
            <lpage>28</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>2</day>
                    <month>9</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>21</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Paschoal Coelho Grossi, Everardo José Grossi</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:6F1882C4-FF17-4B9A-B600-6B3EAD37F987</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>A second species of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name> Westwood, 1878, <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus castroi</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, is described from the northern South America based on 12 specimens from Brazil and Peru (Amazonian subregion). The new species is here compared with the type species of the genus, <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus taurus</tp:taxon-name> Westwood, 1878 and both species and their male genitalia are illustrated. Diagnostic characters for the genus are discussed, especially the metatibial teeth. A distribution map including the type species and the new species is provided. The genus <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name> is recorded for the first time from Peru and from Brazil states of Pará and Rondônia.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Amazonian subregion</kwd>
                <kwd>Phileurini</kwd>
                <kwd>South America</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name> was described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Westwood (1878)</xref> and until now was known only by the type species, <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus taurus</tp:taxon-name> Westwood, restricted to some Central American countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Blackwelder 1944</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Endrödi 1977</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Lachaume 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Ratcliffe 2003</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Ratcliffe and Cave 2006</xref>). In a recently published paper, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Gasca and Aguiar (2008)</xref> <!--PageBreak-->recorded the genus for the first time from South America (Brazilian Amazon) based on six specimens collected between the Juruá and Purus rivers. However, they wrongly identified the species as <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus taurus</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p>After studying these specimens and additional six specimens, three from Peru and three from Brazil, we concluded that all these material belong to a new species of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name> which is here described and compared with the type species of the genus. The diagnostic characters are discussed. A distribution map is provided, including a new country locality from Peru.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>The specimens were examined under a dissecting stereomicroscope at magnification of 0.8–50×. Description of external morphological features and conventions follow in part <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Endrödi (1985)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Ratcliffe and Cave (2006)</xref>. Images of specimens were captured with a digital camera and assembled in the Automontage software. Label data were separated by single slash “/” for the type material.</p>
            <p>The phylogenetic species concept of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Wheeler and Platnick (2000)</xref> was used in this work: “A species is the smallest aggregation of (sexual) populations or (asexual) lineages diagnosable by a unique combination of characters states.”</p>
            <p>Specimens examined for this work were provided by seven institutions and private collections. Acronyms for institutions are mostly taken from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Samuelson et al. (2001)</xref>, as follows:</p>
            <p><bold>CEMT</bold>	Coleção Entomológica da Universidade Federal do Mato Grosso, Cuiabá, MT, Brazil (F. Z. Vaz-de-Mello)</p>
            <p><bold>EPGC</bold>	 Everardo and Paschoal Grossi Private Collection, Nova Friburgo, RJ, Brazil (E. J. Grossi)</p>
            <p><bold>JSC</bold>	Jochen P. Saltin Private Collection, Niedernhausen/Taunus, Germany (J. P. Saltin)</p>
            <p><bold>IOC</bold>	Instituto Oswaldo Cruz, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil (J. M. Costa)</p>
            <p><bold>MIIS</bold>	Museo Insectarium Internacional de Santiago, Sanriago, Chile (S. Castro)</p>
            <p><bold>UFAM</bold>	Universidade Federal do Amazonas, Manaus, AM, Brazil (N. O. Aguiar)</p>
            <p><bold>MIUP</bold>	Museo de Invertebrados G. B. Fairchild, Universidade de Panamá, Panamá (R. A. Cambra T.)</p>
            <sec sec-type="Key to the Amblyodus species"><title>Key to the Amblyodus species</title>
                <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                    <table>
                        <tbody>
														
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frontal horns distinctly divergent. Pronotal disc weakly declivous, almost horizontal, punctures predominantly C-shaped; lateral carina not high. Internal margin of parameres almost parallel; apical external carina of parameres in lateral view complete</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus taurus</tp:taxon-name> Westwood</td>
                            </tr>
                            <!--PageBreak-->
														
                            <tr>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frontal horns not distinctly divergent, instead parallel. Pronotal disc more declivous, with punctures predominantly reticulated, not C-shaped; lateral carina high. Internal margin of parameres concave; apical external carina of parameres in lateral view incomplete</td>
                                <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus castroi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">castroi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:37121595-32A5-4339-93DD-BC7F1AE006B9</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Grossi &amp; Grossi</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–8</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">13, 14</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p> Holotype male, dissected, labeled: a) “male symbol label”; b) “Brasil, Amazonas, <tp:taxon-name>Uarini</tp:taxon-name>,/ 03°02'57"S, 65°41'42"W,/ 22/VII-03/VIII/1995, P./ Bührnhein, N.Aguiar &amp; al.”; c) handwritten label “NO ALBURNO DE/ TRONCO CAÍDO/ 01/VIII/1995” (UFAM).</p>
                    <p><bold>Paratypes</bold>, 4 males and 7 females labeled: 1 female a) “female symbol label”, b) “Brasil, Amazonas, <tp:taxon-name>Uarini</tp:taxon-name>,/ 03°02'57"S, 65°41'42"W,/ 22/VII-03/VIII/1995, P./ Bührnhein, N.Aguiar &amp; al.”; c) handwritten label “NO ALBURNO DE/ TRONCO CAÍDO/ 01/VIII/1995” (CEMT). 3 females labeled “Brasil, Amazonas, Coari,/ Duto <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->Urucu/Porto Terminal,/ 04°50'16"S, 65°20'36"W,/ 16/VI/1996, Buhmheim (<italic>sic</italic>),/ PF, Aguiar, NO, Arruda,/ AMR &amp; Gualberto, TL col.” (UFAM). 1 male labeled a) “Brasil, Amazonas, Coari,/ Duto Urucu/Porto Terminal,/ 04°50'16"S, 65°20'36"W,/ 16/VI/1996, Bühmheim (<italic>sic</italic>),/ P.F. &amp; Aguiar, N.O. col.”; b) handwritten label “Em tronco/ caído” (EPGC). 1 female labeled “PERU, Junin, Puerto/ Ocopa, I-2007, 600m/ 11°07'50"S, 74°17'46"W/ S.Castro col.” (EPGC). 1 female a) “BRASIL: Rondônia: Porto/ Velho, margem direita/ do Rio Madeira, IX-2004” (EPCG). 1 male labeled “PERU, Ucayali, Via/ Puerto Ocopa-Ucayali,/ XII-2009, 1200m,/ 11°03'51"S, 74°15'39"W/ S. Castro col.” (MIIS); 1 male labeled “PERU, Junin,Huerto/ Eden c.a, near Puerto/ Prado XII-2009/ 1800m, local collector” (JSC). 1 male labeled a) “BR 14, Km 92/ Pará, Brasil/ E. Lobato XII. 60” (IOC). 1 female labeled a) handwritten label “S. Paulo de/ Olivença/ Solimões/ VIII. – Fassl”, b) “Coleção/ J. F. Zikan” (IOC). All paratypes additionally labeled, yellow label, “<tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus castroi</tp:taxon-name>/ PARATYPE/ Grossi &amp; Grossi.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Head with frontal horns less divergent, being almost parallel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 3</xref>). Pronotal disc more declivous than in <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus taurus</tp:taxon-name> with lateral carinae distinctly higher in males majors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 4</xref>), posterior furrow deeply excavated as opposed to a less excavated furrow in <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus taurus</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9 and 10</xref>). Aedeagus with internal margin of parameres concave, not parallel; external margin less constricted than in <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus taurus</tp:taxon-name> where internal margin is almost parallel, and external margin abruptly constricted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 11 and 12</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Holotype description"><title>Holotype description</title>
                    <p> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1 and 2</xref>). Total body length 20 mm. Total pronotal width 9.2 mm. Body elongated, about 2 times longer than wide, color dark brown dorsally and reddish brown ventrally; dorsal surface glabrous, with sterna being setose. <italic>Head</italic>: Surface smooth and glabrous with sparse micropunctures; in frontal view with two lateral, concave areas with scattered C-shaped puntures. Clypeus subtriangular, laterally bordered and slightly upturned, convex and with acute apex. Canthi intruding upon eyes just before first third. Frons with two erect, diverging, posteriorly recurving horns. Interocular width equals 3.3 mm. Mandibles tridentate with inner tooth more acute; teeth upturned. Antennae 10 segmented with scape as long as the 6 next segments; club with segments subequal in length. <italic>Pronotum:</italic> Shape trapezoidal, narrower than both elytra together; discal area with C-shaped punctures combined with reticulated areas, flat and declivous; anterior border incomplete. Lateral and posterior sides of pronotal depression strongly carinated, anterior carina more pronounced, higher, being convex and wider posteriorly; carina at base weakly emarginate; carina posteriorly interrupted at middle by a longitudinal furrow, internally weakly angulate; furrow about 4.5 times narrower than head width. Anterior angles acute, posterior angles rounded. Outer side and lateral posterior side of pronotal surface punctate; punctures ocellate, sometimes coalescent, posteriorly larger. <italic>Elytra:</italic> Discal area with 5 rows of large ocellate punctures, rows weakly impressed. Interstriae slightly convex, with scattered small punctures. Lateral edges with 5 similar rows of ocellate punctures, instead of by some ocellate punctures between third and fourth rows. <italic>Pygidium:</italic> Shape convex in lateral view; surface densely punctate; punctures ocellate, moderately sized, elongate near dorsal margin. Sixth ventrite sinuous at middle. <italic>Legs:</italic> Protibiae quadridentate, proximal tooth smaller, distal ones bigger. Metatibiae with 5 apical teeth. <italic>Parameres:<!--PageBreak--></italic> Shape symmetrical, narrower at apex; apex dilated, laterally roundly angulated, apically rounded, triangle shaped; internal side of each paramera concave, not parallel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 5</xref>). In lateral view shaft constricted, with a post-anterior concavity; dorso-ventral carina incomplete, not reaching ventral margin; with a flat, truncate tooth near base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 6</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 1–2.</label>
                        <caption><p>Habitus of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus castroi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>1</bold> Dorsal view <bold>2</bold> Lateral view.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-075-021-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <p>Female paratypes. Similar to male in general aspects except for the following characters: <italic>Head:</italic> Frontal horns less developed and never reaching pronotal middle. <italic>Pronotum:</italic> Pronotal depression narrower, near anterior margin smooth, not punctate; lateral carina smaller with a weak acute projection before first third (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7 and 8</xref>); pronotal furrow longer, ending just before posterior margin. <italic>Pygidium:</italic> Shape wider laterally and shorter, with punctures smaller. Sixth ventrite not sinuous at middle.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figures 3–14.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name> spp. <bold>3–4</bold> Head and pronotum of a male major of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus castroi</tp:taxon-name> in dorsal and lateral views respectively <bold>5–6</bold> Parameres of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus castroi</tp:taxon-name> in caudal and lateral views respectively <bold>7–8</bold> Head and pronotum of a female of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus castroi</tp:taxon-name> in dorsal and lateral views respectively <bold>9–10</bold> Head and pronotum of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus taurus</tp:taxon-name> in dorsal and lateral views respectively <bold>11–12</bold> Parameres of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus taurus</tp:taxon-name> in caudal and lateral views respectively <bold>13–14</bold> Head and pronotum of a male minor of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus castroi</tp:taxon-name> in dorsal and lateral views respectively. Arrows indicate apical lateral carina, <bold>6</bold> (incomplete) and <bold>12</bold> (complete).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-075-021-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Variation of male paratypes"><title>Variation of male paratypes.</title>
                    <p> Smaller males possess less developed and less posteriorly recurving frontal horns. Pronotal carina very weakly pronounced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 13 and 14</xref>).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology. </title>
                    <p>The species is named <italic>castroi</italic> in homage of Sergio Castro who provided us with part of the paratypes from Peru.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p>When recording the new occurrence of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus taurus</tp:taxon-name> for South America, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Gasca and Aguiar (2008)</xref> misapplied the name <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus taurus</tp:taxon-name> to the material they had on hand. Actually both species of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name> are similar in appearance, which is common in <tp:taxon-name>Phileurini</tp:taxon-name>. The authors also stated that the only two genera of the tribe that possess elongate frontal horns were <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Oryctophileurus</tp:taxon-name> Kolbe, 1910. However, <tp:taxon-name>Ceratophileurus</tp:taxon-name> Ohaus, 1911 also possess this character in both sexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Gillett et al. 2010</xref>).</p>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Oryctophileurus</tp:taxon-name> share the lateral pronotal carina and pronotal shape: elongate, widely flattened, depressed with discal depression totally wrinkled. Additionally, both genera have almost no external sexual dimorphism, as females also possess a well-developed frontal horn, a feature that makes the distinction between genders difficult, being the shape of the last sternite the better way to determine gender in these cases. Moreover parameres have almost the same shape, and the shape of prosternal process is also shared between <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Oryctophileurus</tp:taxon-name>, namely flat ventrally and with a spine-like process posteriorly. Based on several morphological characters, there is a possibility that <tp:taxon-name>Oryctophileurus</tp:taxon-name> could be a synonym of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name> because the unique feature to distinguishing both genera is the number of frontal horns, one or two, which is not a good character within <tp:taxon-name>Dynastinae</tp:taxon-name> as some genera are usually extremely allometric. Only with the examination of the type species of <tp:taxon-name>Oryctophileurus</tp:taxon-name>, will it be possible to affirm if they are congeneric or not.</p>
                    <p>The holotype male is an incomplete specimen and it was apparently damaged by an axe during collecting inside dead logs. It is the same male specimen illustrated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Gasca and Aguiar (2008, figure 1, male in lateral view)</xref>.</p>
                    <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name> is recorded for the first time from Peru and from Brazil states of Pará and Rondônia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 15</xref>). It is possible that <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus castroi</tp:taxon-name> occurs in all the Amazonian subregion.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
        	
                        <label>Figure 15.</label>
                        <caption><p>Known distribution map of <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus</tp:taxon-name> species. <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus taurus</tp:taxon-name> (circles) and <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus castroi</tp:taxon-name> (squares).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00003/ZooKeys-075-021-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <p>Characters used to diagnose the genus by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Ratcliffe (2003)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Ratcliffe and Cave (2006)</xref> are confirmed with the new species described here, except for the presence of six teeth on the apex of the metatibiae. In <tp:taxon-name>Amblyodus castroi</tp:taxon-name>, that is a variable character, as the number of teeth may be five or six.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We are grateful to the following colleagues for the loaned specimens used here in this publication: Dr. Nair O. Aguiar from UFAM, Dr. Jane M. Costa from IOC, Mr. Sergio Castro from MIIS, Dr. Roberto A. Cambra T. from MIUP and Dr. Fernando Z. Vaz-de-Mello from CEMT. We would like to thank Vitor Antonio Nardino and Taxon Line Project – Network of Biological Collections from Paraná State for helping with the automontage images. We also thank Dr. Cristiano Lopes-Andrade for comments and suggestions that helped to improve an earlier version of the manuscript. We would like to thank Dr. David Miller for the English corrections and suggestions to the manuscript and also Mrs. Andressa Paladini for the help with the map here included. PCG is supported by a grant from CNPq (Ministério da Ciência e Tecnologia, Brazil). This is the contribution number 1816 of the Departamento de Zoologia, Universidade Federal do Paraná</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwelder</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1944</year>)<article-title> Checklist of the coleopterous Insects of Mexico, Central America, West Indies and South America. U. S.</article-title> <source>National Museum Bulletin</source> <volume>185</volume>:<fpage>220</fpage>-<lpage>265</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Endrödi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>)<article-title> Monographie der Dynastinae. 8. Tribus: Phileurini, amerikanische Arten I (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>Folia Entomologica Hungarica</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Endrödi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>)<source> The Dynastinae of the World</source>. <publisher-name>Dr. W. Junk</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Dordrecht, Netherlands</publisher-loc>, <lpage>800</lpage> pp., 46 plates.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasca Alvarez</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguiar Otaviano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Primer Registro de Amblyodus taurus Westwood, 1878 (Scarabaeidae: Dynastinae: Phileurini) em Brasil.</article-title> <source>Acta Zoologica Mexicana (nueva serie)</source> <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>224</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillett</surname><given-names>CPDT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drumont</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ponchel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> The rare rhinoceros beetle, <italic>Ceratophileurus lemouti</italic> Ohaus, 1911, in French Guiana and Suriname (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Dynastinae, Phileurini).</article-title> <source>ZooKeys</source> <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>198</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lachaume</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>)<article-title> Dynastidae Américains. Cyclocephalini-Agaocephalini-Pentodontini-Oryctini-Phileurini</article-title>. <source>Les Coléoptères du Monde 14</source>. <publisher-name>Sciences Nat</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Venette, France</publisher-loc>. <fpage>56</fpage>, 83–<lpage>89</lpage>, plates 1–11.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratcliffe</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<source> The Dynastine Scarab Beetles of Costa Rica and Panama (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Dynastinae).</source> <publisher-name>Bulletin of the University of the Nebraska State Museum 16:</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>1–50</publisher-loc> <lpage>6</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratcliffe</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cave</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<source> The Dynastine Scarab Beetles of Honduras, Nicaragua and El Salvador (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Dynastinae).</source> <publisher-name>Bulletin of the University of the Nebraska State Museum 21:</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>1–42</publisher-loc> <lpage>4</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuelson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evenhuis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<source> The Insect and Spider Collections of the World Web Site</source>. <publisher-name>Bishop Museum</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Honolulu, HI</publisher-loc>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hbs.bishopmuseum.org/coden/codensearch.html" xlink:type="simple">http://hbs.bishopmuseum.org/coden/codensearch.html</ext-link> [accessed: March 2010].</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>QD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> The phylogenetic species concept</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>QD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Species concepts and phylogenetic theory</source>. <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>; <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>, <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Westwood</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1878</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of some exotic lamellicorn beetles</article-title>. <source>The Transactions of the Entomological Society of London</source>, viii: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>, plates 1–2.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>