<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.78.800</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                    On the identity of the fossil aquatic beetles from the Tertiary localities in the southern part of the Upper Rhine Graben (Coleoptera, Hydrophilidae, Dytiscidae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Martin</surname>
                        <given-names>Fikáček</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Hájek</surname>
                        <given-names>Jiří</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Schmied</surname>
                        <given-names>Heiko</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1"><label>Department of Entomology, National Museum, Kunratice 1, CZ-148 00 Praha 2, Czech Republic</label></aff>
            <aff id="A2"><label>Department of Zoology, Faculty of Science, Charles University in Prague, Viničná 7, CZ-128 44 Praha 2, Czech Republic</label></aff>
            <aff id="A3"><label>Steinmann Insitute of Geology, Mineralogy and Palaeontology, University of Bonn, Nußalle 8, 53115 Bonn, Germany</label></aff>
            <aff id="A4"><label>Institute of Crop Science and Resource Conservation, Animal Ecology, University of Bonn, Melbweg 42, 53127 Bonn, Germany</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Martin Fikáček (<email xlink:type="simple">mfikacek@gmail.com</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Jes Rust</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>28</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>78</issue>
            <fpage>15</fpage>
            <lpage>25</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>12</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>25</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Martin Fikáček, Jiří Hájek, Heiko Schmie</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>This study focuses on the fossil beetles assigned previously to the family <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophilidae</tp:taxon-name> described from the localities in the southern part of the Upper Rhine Graben: Brunstatt (France, Alsace) and Kleinkems (Germany, Baden-Württemberg) (both dated ca. to Eocene-Oligocene boundary, 34 Ma). The identity of <tp:taxon-name>Escheria convexa</tp:taxon-name> Förster, 1891 is fixed by the designation of its neotype, the species is redescribed, illustrated, transferred from the hydrophilid genus <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius</tp:taxon-name> Leach, 1815 to the genus <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus</tp:taxon-name> Erichson, 1832 (<tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Adephaga</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Dytiscidae</tp:taxon-name>) and compared with other fossil representatives of <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus</tp:taxon-name>. The identity of the remaining three species, <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius crassipunctatus</tp:taxon-name> (Förster, 1891), <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius dimidiatus</tp:taxon-name> (Förster, 1891) and <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius punctulatus</tp:taxon-name> (Förster, 1891),is briefly evaluated on the basis of the original descriptions and illustrations only, because their types were lost or destroyed during World War II; all three species are removed from the fossil record of the <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name> and placed into <tp:taxon-name>Polyphaga</tp:taxon-name> <italic>incertae sedis</italic>. The geology and stratigraphy of Brunnstatt and Kleinkems are discussed briefly.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Dytiscidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Hydrophilidae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Copelatus</italic></kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Hydrobius</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>fossils</kwd>
                <kwd>Eocene-Oligocene boundary</kwd>
                <kwd>Brunstatt</kwd>
                <kwd>Kleinkems</kwd>
                <kwd>neotype designation</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>In his study of the insects from the Tertiary outcrop of Brunstatt (Alsace, France), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref> described four species of the family <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophilidae</tp:taxon-name>, assigning all of them to the fossil genus <tp:taxon-name>Escheria</tp:taxon-name> Heer, 1847. Later, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald (1937)</xref> recorded two of these species from the locality of Kleinkems (spelled incorrectly as ‘Kleinkembs’ by the latter author), which is situated 16 km from Brunstatt and is believed to be of the same age and origin (see below for details). Based on the preserved characters, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald (1937)</xref> transferred all four of Förster’s (1891) species to the recent hydrophilid genus <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius</tp:taxon-name> Leach, 1815. After 1937, the specimens were never re-examined and their identity remained unclear. Unfortunately, the Förster collection was either lost or destroyed during World War II (see Material and methods for details), which further complicates research.</p>
            <p>For this study, we have re-examined the specimens from the locality of Kleinkems studied previously by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald (1937)</xref>. In order to resolve the complicated situation concerning the four hydrophilid taxa, a neotype is designated for <tp:taxon-name>Escheria convexa</tp:taxon-name> Förster, 1891 and its taxonomic position is thus illuminated. The remaining fossils are excluded from the <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name> due to the absence of any hydrophiloid apomorphy. Hence, our study supports the opinion by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Fikáček et al. (2010)</xref> that various middle-sized Tertiary beetles were assigned into the hydrophilid genus <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius</tp:taxon-name> irrespectively to their real taxonomic position.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Geology and stratigraphy of the fossil sites"><title>Geology and stratigraphy of the fossil sites</title>
            <p>The Tertiary outcrops of Brunstatt and Kleinkems were located in the south-west of central Europe and no longer exist today. Brunstatt was situated south of the city of Mulhouse in France (47°41'N, 7°31'E); Kleinkems was situated in Germany (47°43'N, 7°19'E) northwest of the city of Basel (Switzerland), about 16 km from Brunstatt. Several hundred fossils in total were collected at these localities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Wappler et al. 2005</xref>).</p>
            <p>According to the reconstruction of the sedimentation history, the limnic sediments of Brunstatt and Kleinkems were deposited on the shore of a very large shallow saline lake (with an area of several hundred square kilometres) with episodical intrusion of fresh water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Lutz 1997</xref>). The landscape in this area originated during the formation of the Upper Rhine Graben (URG) which forms the central part of the Cenozoic Central European Rift System. Increased rifting during the late Middle Eocene to Early Oligocene led to the formation of the Mulhouse Potash Salt Basin (also called Potash Basin or Potassic Basin) which is located in the narrowest part of the graben and flanked by the highest of the Vosges Mountains and Black Forest Mountains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Hinsken et al. 2007</xref>)<!--PageBreak-->. A detailed overview of the development of the URG and the Potash Basin is provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Berger et al. (2005 a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">b</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Hinsken et al. (2007)</xref>.</p>
            <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Lutz (1997)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Mai (1995)</xref> assign the age of Brunstatt and Kleinkems to the Lower Oligocene, but <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Mai (1995)</xref> also allocated Brunstatt to the Mammal Reference Level MP20 which corresponds to the Priabonian (37.2–33.9 Ma) in the latest part of the Eocene. Thus, the stratigraphical position of Brunstatt and Kleinkems seems to be close to the Eocene-Oligocene boundary, as is the case of the similar fossil site of Altkirch in France (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Wappler et al. 2005</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Mai (1995)</xref> [based on <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Lakowitz (1895)</xref>], the palaeoclimate of Brunstatt was characterised by an average annual temperature of 18°C and abundant rainfall.</p>
            <p>It seems very likely that the sediments of Brunstatt and nearby Kleinkems are nearly identical in age and genesis. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Lutz (1995)</xref> even combined both localities in his study reconstructing their paleoenvironment, and according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Mai (1995)</xref>, plant fossils from Brunstatt and Kleinkems are both deposited in the same layers of laminated clay (‘plattiger Steinmergel’).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods"><title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Only the fossils from the locality of Kleinkems mentioned by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald (1937)</xref> deposited currently in the Naturhistorisches Museum in Basel, Switzerland (NHMB) were studied for this paper. The material originally examined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref> was deposited at the ‘Service de la Carte Geologique de Strasbourg’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald 1937</xref>) and is considered to have been lost or destroyed during World War II on the basis of information we received from Jean Claude Horrenberger (École et Observatoire de la Terre, Strasbourg, France) as well as two letters sent to Volker Püthz, a specialist on <tp:taxon-name>Staphylinidae</tp:taxon-name>, by Marguerite Wolf (Université Louis Pasteur, Institut de Géologie, Strasbourg, France) in July 1967 and September 1971 (Püthz, pers. comm. 2010). The identity of species missing from the Kleinkems material is only discussed briefly on the basis of the original drawings by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref>.</p>
            <p>Fossils were examined using the Olympus SZ61 binocular microscope. Photographs were taken using the Canon MP-E 65 mm macro lens attached to the Canon EOS 550D camera. Drawings were traced from photographs. Abbreviations used in descriptions are: <bold>EL</bold> – length of the elytron; <bold>TL</bold> – total length, a single measurement of length from front of head to apex of elytra; <bold>TL-h</bold> – total length minus head length, length of body from anterior margin of pronotum to apex of elytra; <bold>TW</bold> – maximum width of body measured at right angles to TL.</p>
            <p>Fossils whose family placement and hence also generic placement remains unclear are cited using the original combination of the name, placing the respective genus name in  quotation marks.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy"><title>Taxonomy</title>
            <sec sec-type="Coleoptera: Adephaga  Family Dytiscidae"><title><tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Adephaga</tp:taxon-name>  Family <tp:taxon-name>Dytiscidae</tp:taxon-name></title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Copelatus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">convexus</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>(Förster, 1891)</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">comb. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–4</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Escheria convexa</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster 1891</xref>: 359, plate XI, Figs 9a,b (original description from Brunstatt); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Handlirsch 1908</xref>: 767 (catalogue).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius convexus</tp:taxon-name><comment>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald 1937</xref>: 168, plate XII, Fig. 29 (transferred to <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius</tp:taxon-name>, recorded from Kleinkems); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Hansen (1999</xref>: 319, catalogue).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="WWW site on Wikispecies"><title>WWW site on Wikispecies.</title>
                        <p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://species.wikimedia.org/wiki/Copelatus_convexus" xlink:type="simple">http://species.wikimedia.org/wiki/Copelatus_convexus</ext-link></p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Neotype, by present designation (NHMB): R91 (imprint) + R74 (counter-imprint) from the locality of Kleinkems (SW Germany, ca. Eocene-Oligocene boundary): fossil of the whole beetle in dorsal view, head, pronotum and elytra almost completely preserved; appendages missing.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Redescription"><title>Redescription.</title>
                        <p>Body oblong-oval, broadest in basal third of elytra. Head relatively broad; compound eyes large, not exceeding body outline; clypeus rounded. Pronotum broadest between posterior angles, lateral margins regularly, moderately curved. Mesoscutellar shield well preserved, broadly triangular. Base of elytra as broad as pronotal base; lateral margins of elytra moderately curved. Only mesocoxae, part of metathoracic anepisternum, and probably part of apical abdominal ventrite perceptible from ventral part of body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1–4</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Surface sculpture. Pronotum with distinct longitudinal median impression, and poorly perceptible short longitudinal striolae on disc. Elytra with 12 moderately impressed longitudinal striae.</p>
                        <p>Measurements. TL: 6.3 mm, TL-h: 5.6 mm, TW: 3.2 mm. EL: 5.2 mm.</p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 1–6.</label>
                            <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus convexus</tp:taxon-name> (Förster, 1891). <bold>1–4</bold> neotype (<bold>1, 3</bold> NHMB R91; <bold>2, 4</bold> NHMB R74) <bold>5</bold> original illustrations of the holotype by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref> <bold>6</bold> drawing of the specimen NHMB R91 by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald (1937)</xref>.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00002/ZooKeys-078-000-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Notes on the type material"><title>Notes on the type material.</title>
                        <p>Theneotype corresponds well with the original description and drawings by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref> in the following characters: (i) general body shape; (ii) shape of the pronotum with projecting anterior angles; (iii) elytra with large number of longitudinal striae [preserved only in posterior portion of elytra in the holotype and their number is therefore estimated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref> to be at least 10; 12 striae are present in the specimen from Kleinkems]; (iv) shape and proportion of the scutellar shield [much wider than long]; (v) body size [TL = 6.5 mm, EL = 4.3 mm, TW = 3.8 mm for the specimen from Brunstatt according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref>]. The body proportions differ slightly between both specimens (the specimen from Brunstatt is relatively wider), but this may easily have been caused by deformation during the fossilization process or by the inaccuracy of the drawings by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref> which is quite usual for historic authors (e.g., compare the drawings by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald (1937)</xref> in Figs 6 and 12 with the actual appearance of the respective fossils)<!--PageBreak-->. Moreover, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref> mentioned that his fossil resembles the dytiscid genus <tp:taxon-name>Agabus</tp:taxon-name> in most characters and did not assign it to the <tp:taxon-name>Dytiscidae</tp:taxon-name> merely because of its ventral morphology which was reconstructed by him as resembling that of <tp:taxon-name>Polyphaga</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 5</xref>). It seems that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald (1937)</xref> examined Förster’s types as he mentioned certain details which are absent in Förster’s (1891) original publication, <!--PageBreak-->and his opinion about the conspecificity therefore also has to be considered as a strong argument.</p>
                        <p>The reasons provided above together with the same age, geological origin and geographical proximity of both outcrops (Brunnstatt and Kleinkems) provide strong support for the conspecificity of both specimens mentioned by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald (1937)</xref>. As the specimen from Brunstatt (i.e., the holotype) is lost, we consider it adequate to designate the specimen from Kleinkems as the neotype.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Generic attribution"><title>Generic attribution.</title>
                        <p>The preserved characters of the ventral morphology, i.e. the narrow metathoracic anepisternum arising from the median coxal cavity and the anepisterno-metaventral suture directed lateroposteriad correspond closely with the ventral morphology of the <tp:taxon-name>Dytiscidae</tp:taxon-name> (see, e.g., Fig. 7.6.1 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Balke (2005)</xref>). The hydrodynamic body shape, large eyes, broad mesoscutellar shield, medium body size and distinct elytral striae enable us to classify the specimen without any doubt as belonging to the genus <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus</tp:taxon-name> Erichson, 1832 of the family <tp:taxon-name>Dytiscidae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                        <p><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus</tp:taxon-name> is currently pantropical in its distribution and contains more than 400 described species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Nilsson 2001</xref>). Most species of <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus</tp:taxon-name> are characterised by longitudinal elytral striae whose number has been used to group the species into species groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Sharp 1882</xref>); only a few species have smooth elytra (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Hájek et al. 2010</xref>). Although the presence and number of elytral striae provides only limited evidence of phylogeny (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Balke et al. 2004</xref>), the species groups delimited by number and position of elytral striae are frequently used as a tool for better orientation within the genus (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Guignot 1961</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Guéorguiev 1968</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Nilsson et al. 1997</xref>). The European species previously classified in <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus</tp:taxon-name> have elytra without striae and have been transferred to the genus <tp:taxon-name>Liopterus</tp:taxon-name> Dejean,1833 by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Balke et al. (2004)</xref>; they are not closely related to the fossil dealt with in this study.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Comparison with other Copelatus species"><title>Comparison with other Copelatus species.</title>
                        <p>Altogether five species of fossil <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus</tp:taxon-name> species are known: <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus aphroditae</tp:taxon-name> Balke, 2003 from Baltic amber (Eocene), <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus predaveterus</tp:taxon-name> Miller, 2003 from Dominican amber (Miocene) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Miller and Balke 2003</xref>), and <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus fossilis</tp:taxon-name> Říha, 1974, <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus ponomarenkoi</tp:taxon-name> Říha, 1974 and <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus stavropolitanus</tp:taxon-name> Říha, 1974 from the Miocene deposit of Stavropol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Říha 1974</xref>). The differences between all known species are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
                        <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Table 1.</label>
                            <caption><p>List of fossil species of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus</tp:taxon-name>, their basic morphological characteristics and their age. Body measurements in italics are estimated from usual TL/EL ratio in <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus</tp:taxon-name>.</p></caption>
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th>
                                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Period</th>
                                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length</th>
                                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of elytral striae</th>
                                        <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Nilsson 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Miller and Balke 2003</xref>)</th>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus aphroditae</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eocene</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 mm</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 discal</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus aphroditae</tp:taxon-name>-group</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus convexus</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eocene- Oligocene boundary</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3–6.5 mm</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 discal</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus convexus</tp:taxon-name>-group</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus fossilis</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miocene</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1–6.5 mm</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 discal + 1 submarginal</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus erichsoni</tp:taxon-name>-group</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus ponomarenkoi</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miocene</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5–5.6 mm</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 discal + 1 submarginal</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus irinus</tp:taxon-name>-group</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus predaveterus</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miocene</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8–4.4 mm</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 discal + 1 submarginal</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus trilobatus</tp:taxon-name>-group</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus stavropolitanus</tp:taxon-name></td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miocene</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 mm</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 discal</td>
                                        <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus nigrolineatus</tp:taxon-name>-group</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </table-wrap>
                        <p><tp:taxon-name>Copelatus convexus</tp:taxon-name> differs from all known fossil and extant species of the genus in the presence of 12 longitudinal striae on each elytron. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Sharp (1882)</xref> erected a group characterized by 12 discal striae (group 7) for a single species <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus interruptus</tp:taxon-name> Sharp, 1882 which is, however, currently classified in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Exocelina</tp:taxon-name> Broun, 1886 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Nilsson 2007</xref>). In contrast to the fossil <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus convexus</tp:taxon-name>, this recent species has elytra with numerous short striolae rather than ‘true’ striae, see, e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Wewalka et al. (2010)</xref>. Therefore, <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus convexus</tp:taxon-name> might be provisionally classified in a separate <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus convexus</tp:taxon-name>-group. However, it is necessary to point out that the counting of the precise number of lateral elytral striae is problematic in compressed fossils as the imprint of the submarginal stria may coincide with the lateral margin of the body or with the epipleuron. Therefore, we cannot rule out that a short submarginal stria was present in <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus convexus</tp:taxon-name> although it is not perceptible in the fossil. In this case, <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus convexus</tp:taxon-name> would belong to the <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus simoni</tp:taxon-name>-group sensu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Nilsson (2001)</xref>.</p>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Coleoptera: Polyphaga  Family incertae sedis"><title><tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Polyphaga</tp:taxon-name>  Family incertae sedis</title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <!-- ‘ ’ -->
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Escheria</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">crassipunctata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Förster, 1891</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 7</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Escheria crassipunctata</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster 1891</xref>: 364, plate XI, Fig. 11 (original description from Brunstatt); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Handlirsch 1908</xref>: 767 (catalogue).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius crassipunctatus</tp:taxon-name><comment>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald 1937</xref>: 169, plate II, Fig. 28 (transferred to <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius</tp:taxon-name>, referred from Kleinkems); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Hansen 1999</xref>: 319 (catalogue).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Taxonomic notes"><title>Taxonomic notes.</title>
                        <p>As in the case of <tp:taxon-name>Copelatus convexus</tp:taxon-name>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald (1937)</xref> transferred <tp:taxon-name>Escheria crassipunctata</tp:taxon-name> to the hydrophilid genus <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius</tp:taxon-name> and assigned fossil specimen no. R 707 from the locality of Kleinkems (deposited in NHMB) to this species. We have examined the specimen from Kleinkems for this study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 10–11</xref>) but we cannot confirm that it is conspecific with <tp:taxon-name>Escheria crassipunctata</tp:taxon-name> for the following reasons: (i) the elytra are slightly constricted sub-basally in the specimen from Kleinkems, but evenly rounded laterally in <tp:taxon-name>Escheria crassipunctata</tp:taxon-name>; (ii) the body outline is distinctly interrupted between the pronotum and the elytra, but it is uninterrupted in <tp:taxon-name>Escheria crassipunctata</tp:taxon-name>, (iii) eyes are large and globular in the specimen from Kleinkems, but relatively small in <tp:taxon-name>Escheria crassipunctata</tp:taxon-name>. A more detailed comparison is impossible as the holotype of <tp:taxon-name>Escheria crassipunctata</tp:taxon-name> is lost and was moreover preserved in dorsal view based on the drawing by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref>, whereas the specimen from Kleinkems is preserved in ventral view.</p>
                        <p>Based on the original drawing by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref>, <tp:taxon-name>Escheria crassipunctata</tp:taxon-name> does not bear any synapomorphy of the <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name>. For this reason, the species is removed from the fossil record of the <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name> and is placed in <tp:taxon-name>Polyphaga</tp:taxon-name> <italic>incertae sedis</italic>.</p>
                        <!--PageBreak-->
                        <p>Specimen no. R707 from Kleinkems does not bear any synapomorphy of the <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name>, and moreover bears a combination of characters which excludes its assignment to the <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name>: (i) prosternal process wide, (ii) mesocoxal cavities rather wide apart, and (iii) eyes large and globular. The preserved characters of this specimen do not allow an unambiguous family assignment (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Lawrence et al. 1999</xref>).</p>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figures 7–12.</label><!-- ‘ -->
                            <caption><p><bold>7</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Escheria crassipunctata</tp:taxon-name> Förster, 1891, original illustration of the holotype <bold>8</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Escheria dimidiata</tp:taxon-name> Förster, 1891, original illustration of the holotype <bold>9</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Escheria punctulata</tp:taxon-name> Förster, 1891, original illustration of the holotype <bold>10–12</bold> specimen NHMB R707 (<bold>10</bold> photograph <bold>11</bold> drawing <bold>12</bold> original drawing by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald (1937)</xref>).</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/00002/ZooKeys-078-000-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Escheria</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">dimidiata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Förster, 1891</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 8</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Escheria dimidiata</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster 1891</xref>: 363, plate XI, Figs 10a,b (original description from Brunstatt); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Handlirsch 1908</xref>: 767 (catalogue)</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius dimidiatus</tp:taxon-name><comment>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald 1937</xref>: 169 (transferred to <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius</tp:taxon-name>); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Hansen 1999</xref>: 319 (catalogue).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Taxonomic note"><title>Taxonomic note.</title>
                        <p>Based on the original drawing by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref>, the morphology of <tp:taxon-name>Escheria dimidiata</tp:taxon-name> agrees with that of <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophilidae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophilinae</tp:taxon-name> in many aspects: (i) mesocoxal cavities transverse, narrowly isolated from each other, (ii) metanepisternum rather narrow, (iii) epipleuron narrow but reaching elytral apex, and (iv) elytron with 10 longitudinal punctural series. None of these characters or their combination is, however, unique for the <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name> and may be found in other beetle families as well (see e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Lawrence et al. 1999</xref>). Moreover, the medium body size (EL: 9 mm according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref>) would indicate that the fossil should belong to the subtribes <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobiusina</tp:taxon-name> or <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophilina</tp:taxon-name>, whose representatives are characterized by a relatively large and well developed triangular mesoscutellar shield; in contrast, the scutellar shield is very small or reduced in <tp:taxon-name>Escheria dimidiata</tp:taxon-name>. Moreover, the re-examination of the fossil is impossible as the holotype was lost or destroyed. For all these reasons, <tp:taxon-name>Escheria dimidiata</tp:taxon-name> is removed from the fossil record of the <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name> and is placed in <tp:taxon-name>Polyphaga</tp:taxon-name> <italic>incertae sedis</italic>.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Escheria</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">punctulata</tp:taxon-name-part> 
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Förster, 1891</tp:taxon-authority>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 9</xref>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Escheria punctulata</tp:taxon-name> <comment><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster 1891</xref>: 361; plate XI, Figs 8a,b (original description from Brunstatt); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Handlirsch 1908</xref>: 767 (catalogue).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                            <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius punctulatus</tp:taxon-name><comment>: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Théobald 1937</xref>: 169 (transferred to <tp:taxon-name>Hydrobius</tp:taxon-name>); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Hansen 1999</xref>: 319 (catalogue).</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Taxonomic note"><title>Taxonomic note.</title>
                        <p>Based on the drawing by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Förster (1891)</xref>, the ventral morphology of this species agrees with that of <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophilidae</tp:taxon-name>: <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophilinae</tp:taxon-name> in many characters: (i) mesocoxae transverse and very narrowly separated, (ii) mesepimeron well separated, triangular, (iii) metanepisternum rather narrow; (iv) abdomen with five ventrites.<!--PageBreak--> However, none of these characters or their combination is unique for the <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name> and may be found in other beetle families as well (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Lawrence et al. 1999</xref>). Moreover, two characters illustrated on the drawing and/or mentioned in the original description exclude the placement of <tp:taxon-name>Escheria punctulata</tp:taxon-name> in the <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name>: (i) elytra bear only 6 deeply impressed striae [9–11 striae are present in all <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name> with striate elytra, only rarely is the number of series higher but in such cases they are never impressed to striae]; (ii) mesoventrite fused with mesepisternal (i.e. not separated from them by sutures) [in <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name>, the mesoventrite is fused to mesepisterna only in derived groups of the <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeridiinae</tp:taxon-name> which are characterized by a highly elevated median portion of the mesoventrite; the elevated median elevation is missing from the fossil]. For these reasons, <tp:taxon-name>Escheria punctulata</tp:taxon-name> is removed from the fossil record of <!--PageBreak-->the <tp:taxon-name>Hydrophiloidea</tp:taxon-name> and is placed into <tp:taxon-name>Polyphaga</tp:taxon-name> <italic>incertae sedis</italic>; its family placement remains unclear.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We are indebted to W. Etter (Naturhistorisches Museum, Basel) for the opportunity to re-examine the specimens studied by Théobald (1937), to J. C. Horrenberger (École et Observatoire de la Terre, Strasbourg) and V. Püthz (Max-Planck-Institut für Limnologie, Schlitz/Hessen) for information about the type specimens by Förster (1891), to T. Wappler (University of Bonn) for help with geological and paleontological literature, and to M. Lambertz and C. Carrington for proof reading the English text.</p>
            <p>The study was supported by grant KJB301110901 from the Czech Academy of Sciences (GAAV), grant MK 00002327201 from the Ministry of Culture of the Czech Republic and grant MSM 0021620828 from the Ministry of Education of the Czech Republic.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Balke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> Dytiscidae Leach, 1915</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Beutel</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leschen</surname><given-names>RAB</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Handbook of zoology. A natural history of the phyla of the animal kingdom. Volume IV. Arthropoda: Insecta. Part 38. Coleoptera, Beetles. Volume 1: Morphology and systematics (Archostemata, Adephaga, Myxophaga, Polyphaga partim.)</source>. <publisher-name>Walter de Gruyter</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Berlin-New York</publisher-loc>, <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Balke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribera</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> MtDNA phylogeny and biogeography of Copelatinae, a highly diverse group of tropical diving beetles (Dytiscidae).</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>866</fpage>-<lpage>880</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reichenbacher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Picot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Storni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirkenseer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005a</year>)<article-title> Paleogeography of the Upper Rhine Graben (URG) and the Swiss Molasse Basin (SMB) from Eocene to Pliocene.</article-title> <source>International Journal of Earth Sciences</source> <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>697</fpage>-<lpage>710</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reichenbacher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Picot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Storni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirkenseer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005b</year>)<article-title> Eocene-Pliocene time scale and stratigraphy of the Upper Rhine Graben (URG) and the Swiss Molasse Basin (SMB).</article-title> <source>International Journal of Earth Sciences</source> <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>711</fpage>-<lpage>731</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fikáček</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prokop</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Fossil water scavenger beetles of the subtribe Hydrobiusina (Coleoptera: Hydrophilidae) from the Late Oligocene locality of Aix-en-Provence (France).</article-title> <source>Acta Entomologica Musei Nationalis Pragae</source> <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>-<lpage>458</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Förster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1891</year>)<article-title> Die Insekten des „Plattigen Steinmergels“ von Brunnstatt</article-title>. <source>Abhandlungen zur geologischen Spezialkarte von Elsass-Lothringen</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>–<lpage>594</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guéorguiev</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> Essai de classification des coléoptères Dytiscidae. I. Tribus Copelatini (Colymbetinae).</article-title> <source>Izvestiya na Zoologicheskiya Institut s Muzey(Sofia)</source> <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guignot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>)<article-title> Revision des hydrocanthares d’Afrique (Coleoptera Dytiscoidea). 3.</article-title> <source>Annales du Musée Royal du Congo Belge, Série 8vo (Sciences Zoologiques)</source> <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>659</fpage>-<lpage>995</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hájek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendrich</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawlitschek</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Copelatus sibelaemontis sp. nov. from the Moluccas, delineated based on morphology and DNA sequence data (Coleoptera: Dytiscidae).</article-title> <source>Acta Entomologica Musei Nationalis Pragae</source> <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>-<lpage>443</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Handlirsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1908</year>)<article-title> Die fossilen Insekten und die Phylogenie der rezenten Formen</article-title>. <source>Ein Handbuch für Paläontologen und Zoologen</source>. <publisher-name>Wilhelm Engelmann</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Leipzig</publisher-loc>, <lpage>1430</lpage> pp. + 51 plates.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> World Catalogue of Insects. Volume 2. Hydrophiloidea (s.str.) (Coleoptera)</source>. <publisher-name>Apollo Books</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Stenstrup</publisher-loc>, <lpage>416</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinsken</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ustaszewski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wetzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Graben width controlling syn-rift sedimentation: the Palaeogene southern Upper Rhine Graben as an example.</article-title> <source>International Journal of Earth Sciences</source> <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>979</fpage>-<lpage>1002</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakowitz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1895</year>)<article-title> Die Oligozänflora der Umgebung von Mühlhausen im Elsatz</article-title>. <source>Abhandlungen zur geologischen Spezialkarte von Elsass-Lothringen</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>180</fpage>–<lpage>360</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dallwitz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paine</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> Beetles of the world. A key and  information system for families and subfamilies. CD-ROM, Version 1.0 for MS-Windows</source>, <publisher-loc>Melbourne</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>CSIRO Publishing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Taphozönosen terrestrischer Insekten in aquatischen Sedimenten – ein Beitrag zur Rekonstruktion des Paläoenvironments.</article-title> <source>Neues Jahrbuch für Geologie und Paläontologie, Abhandlungen</source> <volume>203</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>-<lpage>210</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>)<source> Tertiäre Vegetationsgeschichte Europas</source>. <publisher-name>Fischer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Jena</publisher-loc>, <lpage>691</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> The unusual occurrence of aquatic beetles in amber, <italic>Copelatus aphroditae</italic> Balke, n. sp. and <italic>C. predaveterus</italic> Miller, n. sp., (Coleoptera: Dytiscidae: Copelatinae)</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>809</fpage>–<lpage>815</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<article-title> Dytiscidae (Coleoptera).</article-title> <source>World Catalogue of Insects</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>395</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> ExocelinaBroun, 1886 is the valid name of PapuadytesBalke, 1998.</article-title> <source>Latissimus</source> <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bilardo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> A check list of Copelatus Erichson 1832 species (Coleoptera Dytiscidae) from Afrotropical and Madagascan regions with a review of published penis drawings.</article-title> <source>Tropical Zoology</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Říha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<article-title> Neue fossile Schwimmkäfer aus dem Tertiär Europas und Westsibiriens (Coleoptera, Dytiscidae)</article-title>. <source>Acta Entomologica Bohemoslovaca</source> <source>71</source>: <fpage>398</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1882</year>)<article-title> On aquatic carnivorous Coleoptera or Dytiscidae</article-title>. <source>Scientific Transactions of the Royal Dublin Society, Series 2</source> ,<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>1003</lpage> + pls. 7–18.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Théobald</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1937</year>)<source> Les insectes fossiles des terrains oligocènes de France</source>. <publisher-name>G. Thomas</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Nancy</publisher-loc>, <lpage>473</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wappler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinsken</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brocks</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wetzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>)<article-title> A fossil sawfly of the genus <italic>Athalia</italic> (Hymenoptera: Tenthredinidae) from the Eocene–Oligocene boundary of Altkirch, France.</article-title> <source>Comptes Rendus Palevol</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wewalka</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendrich</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Dytiscidae: Copelatinae (Coleoptera)</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jäch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Water beetles of New Caledonia, part 1. Monographs on Coleoptera</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>128</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>