<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.84.1189</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
                Notes on the Nazeris fauna of Yunnan Province, China (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Paederinae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Hu</surname>
                        <given-names>Jia-Yao</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7DDE2164-18DE-4D55-A5AB-FEB0F9388A38</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Li</surname>
                        <given-names>Li-Zhen</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:BBACC7AE-9B70-4536-ABBE-54183D2ABD45</uri></contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Zhao</surname> 
                        <given-names>Yun-long</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:ED604F1A-C78B-4AAC-916C-A73AB0A2EC7D</uri></contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>Department of Biology, East China Normal University, 3663 North Zhongshan Road, Shanghai, 200062 P. R. China</label></aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>Department of Biology, Shanghai Normal University, 100 Guilin Road, Shanghai, 200234 P. R. China</label></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Yun-long Zhao (<email xlink:type="simple">ylzhao@bio.ecnu.edu.cn</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Volker Assing</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>1</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>84</issue>
            <fpage>13</fpage>
            <lpage>21</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>9</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>12</day>
                    <month>1</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Jia-Yao Hu, Li-Zhen Li, Yun-long Zhao</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:E27D8AB1-223C-4246-B208-400014DDDF7E</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Two new species of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris</tp:taxon-name> Fauvel collected from Nabanhe Nature Reserve, Yunnan Province, are described under the names of <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nabanhensis</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold> and <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris caoi</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold> The male sexual characters are described and illustrated. A key to the <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris</tp:taxon-name> species of Yunnan is provided. A map of the collecting sites is given.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Coleoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Staphylinidae</kwd>
                <kwd>Paederinae</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Nazeris</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>key</kwd>
                <kwd>Yunnan</kwd>
                <kwd>China</kwd>
                <kwd>new species</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The genus <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris</tp:taxon-name> Fauvel (1873: 298) can be readily distinguished from other <tp:taxon-name>Paederinae</tp:taxon-name> by the labrum having four teeth at the front margin and the bi-lobed 4th tarsal segments. Up to the present, 51 species and subspecies of <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris</tp:taxon-name> have been recorded from China. Yunnan is a mountainous province located in Southwest China, from <!--PageBreak-->which nine species of <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris</tp:taxon-name> have been described: <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris zhangi</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao (1993: 130) from “Yu’an-shan near Kunming City”, <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris giganteus</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao (1997:2) and <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris daliensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao (1997: 7) from “Diancang shan Mts., Dali shi”, <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris alpinus</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao (1997: 5) from “Mt. Yulongxue shan, Lijiang County”, <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris jizushanensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao (1997: 9) from “Mt. Jizu Shan, Binchuan County”, <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris baihuaensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao (2000: 312), <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris ishiianus</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao (2000: 319) and <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nomurai</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao (2000: 316) from “Gaoligong Shan Mts., Baoshan area”, <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris huanxipoensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao (2000: 318) from “Huanxipo, Tengchong Xian”. Only two species have become known from the three countries adjacent to Yunnan (Myanmar, Laos and Vietnam): <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris coomani</tp:taxon-name> Jarrige (1948: 40) (redescribed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Rougemont 1988</xref>: 775) from “du mont Bavi, Tonkin” (Vietnam) and <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris odzisan</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe (1996: 1) from “Mt. Tam Dao, Vinh Phu Prov.” (Vietnam).</p>
            <p>The specimens from Yunnan Province contained another two undescribed species, <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nabanhensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. and <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris caoi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. The male sexual characters of the two new species are described and illustrated. A map (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 13</xref>) of the collecting sites of <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris</tp:taxon-name> species in Yunnan and a key to the Yunnan species are provided.</p>
            <p>The types are deposited in the Insect Collections of Department of Biology, Shanghai Normal University, Shanghai, P. R. China (SHNUC).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
            <p>The specimens were collected from decaying leaf litter of forest floors by hand sifting. They were killed with ethyl acetate and dried. To examine the male genitalia, the last four abdominal segments were detached from the body after softening in hot water. The aedeagi and sternites were mounted in Euparal on plastic slides. Drawings were made using an Olympus SZ61 microscope. Photos were taken with an Olympus E420 camera mounted on an Olympus SZX12 stereoscope. Material of other Yunnanese <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris</tp:taxon-name> species was not examined. The characters used in comparative remarks and keys are according to descriptions of (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Watanabe and Xiao (1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">2000</xref>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Watanabe (1996)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Jarrige (1948)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Rougemont (1988)</xref>.</p>
            <sec sec-type="Measurements"><title>Measurements</title>
                <p>Body length: measured from anterior margin of labrum to end of abdomen;</p>
                <p>Forebody length: measured from anterior margin of labrum to elytral apices;</p>
                <p>Eye length: longitudinal length of eye in dorsal view;</p>
                <p>Postocular length: length of postocular portion in dorsal view;</p>
                <p>Head width: width of head across eyes;</p>
                <p>Pronotum width: width of pronotum across the widest part;</p>
                <p>Elytra width: width of elytra across the widest part;</p>
                <p>Head length: measured from front margin of head to its posterior margin;<!--PageBreak--></p>
                <p>Pronotum length: measured from front margin of pronotum to its posterior margin;</p>
                <p>Elytra length: measured from humeral angle to apicolateral angle.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Descriptions"><title>Descriptions</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Nazeris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">nabanhensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:7B0F8A68-2EEE-412E-9090-9F1CE8EBA8ED</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">3–7</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                    <p> CHINA: Holotype: Yunnan Prov.: male, Jinghong City, Nabanhe Nature Reserve, Benggangxinzhai, 1,750m, 16. XI. 2008, Hu Jia-Yao &amp; Tang Liang leg. Paratypes: 2 females, Jinghong City, Nabanhe Nature Reserve, Bengganghani, Nanmugahe, 1,700m, 11. XI. 2008, Hu Jia-Yao &amp; Tang Liang leg.; 1 female, Jinghong City, Nabanhe Nature Reserve, Bengganghani, 1,800m, 14. XI. 2008, Hu Jia-Yao &amp; Tang Liang leg.; 5 males, 8 females, same locality as holotype, 3. V. 2009, Hu Jia-Yao &amp; Yin Zi-Wei leg.; 1 female, Jinghong City, Nabanhe Nature Reserve, Bengganghani, Nanmugahe, 1,700m, 27. IV. 2009, Hu Jia-Yao &amp; Yin Zi-Wei leg.; 3 females, Jinghong City, Nabanhe Nature Reserve, Bengganghani, Chuguohe, 1,700m, 28. IV. 2009, Hu Jia-Yao &amp; Yin Zi-Wei leg.; 1 male, 1 female, Jinghong City, Nabanhe Nature Reserve, Bengganghani, 1,650m, 29. IV. 2009, Hu Jia-Yao &amp; Yin Zi-Wei leg.; 1 male, Jinghong City, Nabanhe Nature Reserve, Bengganghani, Nanmugahe, 1700m, 30. IV. 2009, Hu Jia-Yao &amp; Yin Zi-Wei leg.; 4 females, Jinghong City, Nabanhe Nature Reserve, Bengganghani, 1,650m, 30. IV. 2009, Hu Jia-Yao &amp; Yin Zi-Wei leg. SHNUC.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 1–2.</label>
                        <caption><p>Habitus of <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris</tp:taxon-name>. <bold>1</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nabanhensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <bold>2</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris caoi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Scale bars 1 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-084-013-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body length: 5.8–6.4 mm; forebody length: 3.3–3.5 mm.</p>
                    <p><italic>Male</italic>. Body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) elongate, dark brown, with labrum, coxae, and basal antennomeres reddish yellow, the remaining antennomeres, maxillary palpi and legs yellow, with exception for coxae.</p>
                    <p>Head suborbicular, longer than wide (length/width = 1.18); postocular portion 1.96 times as long as eye length; punctation coarse, dense, and umbilicate; interstices reduced to narrow ridges. Antennae slender; relative length of each segment from 1 to 11: 42.0 : 15.0 : 29.0 : 23.0 : 22.5 : 22.0 : 19.0 : 17.0 : 15.5 : 14.0 : 20.0; relative width of each segment from 1 to 11: 12.0 : 7.5 : 6.0 : 6.0 : 6.0 : 6.0 : 6.0 : 6.0 : 6.0 :7.5 : 7.5.</p>
                    <p>Pronotum convex, oval, longer than wide (length/width = 1.20), narrower (pronotum/head = 0.93) and shorter (pronotum/head = 0.94) than head; prosternum with strong longitudinal median carina, which disappears behind anterior margin. Elytra shorter than wide (length/width = 0.91), distinctly shorter (elytra/pronotum = 0.74) and slightly narrower (elytra/pronotum = 0.97) than pronotum.</p>
                    <p>Abdomen elongate, tergites without any microsculpture. Seventh sternite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 3</xref>) trapezoidally emarginated in middle of posterior margin and distinctly depressed in front of emargination; 8th sternite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 4</xref>) V-shaped deeply excised in middle of posterior margin. Aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs. 5, 6 and 7</xref>) well sclerotized; apical part of me<!--PageBreak-->dian lobe in dorsal view tri-lobed, median part cone-shaped, two outer parts acute at apices, with little agnail in each outer side near apex; dorso-lateral apophyses slightly curved inward, distinctly widened near apex, extending beyond apices of median lobe.</p>
                    <p><italic>Female</italic>. Seventh and 8th sternites simple. The other characters are similar to those of male.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 3–7.</label>
                        <caption><p>Details of <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nabanhensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <bold>3</bold> male 7th sternite <bold>4</bold> male 8th sternite <bold>5</bold> aedeagus, in dorsal view <bold>6</bold> aedeagus, in lateral view <bold>7</bold> aedeagus, in ventral view. Scale bar: 0.5 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-084-013-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p> The new species is similar to <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris daliensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe (1997: 7) from Yunnan Province in appearance, but it can be distinguished from the latter by the following characters: elytra slightly narrower than pronotum (in <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris daliensis</tp:taxon-name> nearly as wide as, or slightly broader than pronotum); depth of excision of male 8th sternite nearly half of middle length of sternite (in <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris daliensis</tp:taxon-name> much shallower, nearly 1/3 of middle length of 8th sternite); apical part of median lobe of aedeagus in dorsal view tri-lobed (in <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris daliensis</tp:taxon-name> not lobed). The new species can be distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris coomani</tp:taxon-name> Jarrige (1948: 40) from Vietnam by head with umbilicate punctation (in <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris coomani</tp:taxon-name><!--PageBreak--> punctation of head simple) and distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris odzisan</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe (1996: 1) from Vietnam by elytra shorter than wide (in <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris odzisan</tp:taxon-name> elytra longer than wide); dorso-lateral apophyses of aedeagus extending beyond apices of median lobe (in <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris odzisan</tp:taxon-name> not extending to apices of median lobe).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The specific name is derived from the name of the type locality: Nabanhe Nature Reserve.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Nazeris</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">caoi</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:3B251645-1B6B-4388-ACEC-4E5B42C4A858</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">8–12</xref>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                    <p> CHINA: Holotype: Yunnan Prov.: male, Jinghong City, Nabanhe Nature Reserve, Bengganghani, 1,930m, 14. XI. 2008, Hu Jia-Yao &amp; Tang Liang leg. <!--PageBreak-->Paratypes 1 male, same data as holotype; 1 female, Jinghong City, Nabanhe Nature Reserve, Bengganghani, 1,900m, 1. V. 2009, Hu Jia-Yao &amp; Yin Zi-Wei leg. SHNUC.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Body length: 6.1–6.4 mm; forebody length: 3.3–3.6 mm.</p>
                    <p><italic>Male</italic>. Body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 2</xref>) elongate, dark brown, with labrum, coxae, and basal two antennomeres reddish yellow, the remaining antennomeres, maxillary palpi and legs yellow, with exception for coxae.</p>
                    <p>Head suborbicular, slightly longer than wide (length/width = 1.07); postocular portion 2.14 times as long as eye length; punctation coarse, dense, and umbilicate; interstices reduced to narrow ridges. Antennae slender; relative length of each segment from 1 to 11: 42.0 : 13.5 : 30.0 : 23.0 : 21.0 : 21.0 : 19.0 : 18.0 : 18.0 : 16.0 : 22.0; relative width of each segment from 1 to 11: 10.5 : 7.0 : 6.5 : 6.0 : 5.5 : 6.0 : 5.5 : 5.5 : 6.0 :6.5 : 7.0.</p>
                    <p>Pronotum convex, oval, longer than wide (length/width = 1.19), narrower (pronotum/head = 0.88) and shorter (pronotum/head = 0.98) than head; prosternum with<!--PageBreak--> strong longitudinal median carina, which disappears behind anterior margin. Elytra slightly shorter than wide (length/width = 0.97), distinctly shorter (elytra/pronotum = 0.80) and slightly narrower (elytra/pronotum = 0.97) than pronotum.</p>
                    <p>Abdomen elongate, tergites without any microsculpture; densely and coarsely punctate. Seventh sternite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 8</xref>) distinctly emarginated in middle of posterior margin; 8th sternite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 9</xref>) with little short protrusion in middle, deeply excised in middle of posterior margin. Aedeagus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 10, 11 and 12</xref>) well sclerotized; median lobe bi-lobed in dorsal view, curved ventrad in apical 1/3 in lateral view; dorso-lateral apophyses very thin, slightly curved ventrad, not extending to apices of median lobe.</p>
                    <p><italic>Female</italic>. Seventh and 8th sternites simple. The other characters are similar to those of male.</p>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 8–12.</label>
                        <caption><p>Details of <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris caoi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <bold>8</bold> male 7th sternite <bold>9</bold> male 8th sternite <bold>10</bold> aedeagus, in dorsal view <bold>11</bold> aedeagus, in lateral view <bold>12</bold> aedeagus, in ventral view. Scale bar: 0.5 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-084-013-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p> The present new species is similar in appearance to <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nabanhensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. from the same locality, but can be distinguished from the latter by the following <!--PageBreak-->characters: postocular part more than twice as long as longitudinal diameter of each eye (in <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nabanhensis</tp:taxon-name> less than twice as long as longitudinal diameter of each eye); median lobe of aedeagus in dorsal view bi-lobed (in <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nabanhensis</tp:taxon-name> tri-lobed); dorso-lateral apophyses of aedeagus not extending to apices of median lobe (in <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nabanhensis</tp:taxon-name> extending beyond apices of median lobe). The new species can be distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris coomani</tp:taxon-name> Jarrige (1948: 40) from Vietnam by head with umbilicate punctation (in <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris coomani</tp:taxon-name> punctation of head simple), and distinguished from <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris odzisan</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe (1996: 1) from Vietnam by elytra shorter than wide (in <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris odzisan</tp:taxon-name> elytra longer than wide); median lobe of aedeagus in dorsal view bi-lobed (in <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris odzisan</tp:taxon-name> not lobed).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The species is named in honor of Mr. Guanghong Cao of Nabanhe Nature Reserve, who helped us a lot during field work.</p>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figures 13.</label>
                        <caption><p>Map showing the collecting sites of the <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris</tp:taxon-name> in Yunnan Prov.; <bold>1</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nabanhensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <bold>2</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris caoi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <bold>3</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris zhangi</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao <bold>4</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris giganteus</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao <bold>5</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris daliensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao <bold>6</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris alpinus</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao <bold>7</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris jizushanensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao <bold>8</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris baihuaensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao <bold>9</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris ishiianus</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao <bold>10</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nomurai</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao <bold>11</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Nazeris huanxipoensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="export.php_files/ZooKeys-084-013-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Key to species of Nazeris from Yunnan Province, China"><title>Key to species of Nazeris from Yunnan Province, China</title>
                    <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor" orientation="portrait">
                        <table>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length less than 4.5 mm; posterior margin of male 7th sternite not emarginate</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Nazeris zhangi</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body length at least 5.0 mm; posterior margin of male 7th sternite emarginate</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male 8th sternite with short protrusion in middle, median lobe of aedeagus bi-lobed in dorsal view</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Nazeris caoi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male 8th sternite without protrusion in middle, median lobe of aedeagus not bi-lobed in dorsal view</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median lobe of aedeagus tri-lobed in dorsal view</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nabanhensis</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median lobe of aedeagus not tri-lobed in dorsal view</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorso-lateral apophyses of aedeagus extending beyond apex of median lobe</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorso-lateral apophyses of aedeagus not extending to apex of median lobe</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorso-lateral apophyses of aedeagus dilated in apical part and markedly curved ventrad in apical half</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Nazeris nomurai</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorso-lateral apophyses of aedeagus not dilated in apical part and not markedly curved ventrad in apical half</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median lobe of aedeagus subtriangular in apical third and curved dorsad near apex in lateral view, dorso-lateral apophyses curved ventrad near apex in lateral view</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Nazeris huanxipoensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median lobe of aedeagus not subtriangular in posterior third, not curved dorsad near apex in lateral view, dorso-lateral apophyses nearly straight in lateral view</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorso-lateral apophyses of aedeagus dilated at middle; median lobe of aedeagus without wing-shaped process</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Nazeris baihuaensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorso-lateral apophyses of aedeagus not dilated at middle; median lobe of aedeagus with a wing-shaped process on each side near middle</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postocular part less than twice as long as eye length; depth of excision of posterior margin of male 8th sternite more than twice its width</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Nazeris jizushanensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao    <!--PageBreak--></td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postocular part more than twice as long as eye length; depth of excision of posterior margin of male 8th sternite nearly the same its width</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Nazeris daliensis</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median lobe of aedeagus semicircularly emarginate at apex</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Nazeris ishiianus</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median lobe of aedeagus not emarginate at apex</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median lobe of aedeagus tongue-shaped; dorso-lateral apophyses of aedeagus very narrow and near straight in dorsal view</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Nazeris alpinus</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median lobe of aedeagus not tongue-shaped, distinctly narrowed in apical 1/4 in dorsal view; dorso-lateral apophyses of aedeagus markedly curved inward in dorsal view</td>
                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Nazeris giganteus</tp:taxon-name> Watanabe &amp; Xiao</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </table-wrap>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We thank Mr. Guanghong Cao and Mr. Maoxing Tian (Nabanhe Nature Reserve) for their help during field work. We thank Dr. Liang Tang and Mr. Ziwei Yin (Shanghai Normal University) for their collecting the specimens and continuous help in many ways. We thank Dr. Ales Smetana (Agriculture and Agri-Food Canada) for revision our paper. This study is supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 30870323) and by Shanghai Normal University (No. SK200833 and SK200834).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fauvel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1873</year>)<source> Faune Gallo-Rhénane ou species des insectes qui habitent la France, la Belgique, la Hollande, le Luxembourg, la prusse Rhénane, la Nassau et la Valais avec tableaux synoptiques et planches gravées. Tome 3</source>. <publisher-name>Livraison 4. Caen: Le Blanc-Hardel</publisher-name>, <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>390</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarrige</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1948</year>)<article-title> Staphylinides nouveaux d’Asie orientale.</article-title> <source>Notes d’Entomologie Chinoise, Musée Heude</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rougemont</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> Un <italic>Nazeris</italic> nouveau de Thaïlande (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Paederinae).</article-title> <source>Revue Suisse de Zoologie</source> <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>773</fpage>-<lpage>777</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> A new <italic>Nazeris</italic> (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae) from northern Vietnam.</article-title> <source>Species Diversity</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> A new species of the genus <italic>Nazeris</italic> (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae) from Yunnan Province, Southwest China.</article-title> <source>Elytra, Tokyo</source> <volume>21</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>129</fpage>-<lpage>133</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Four new <italic>Nazeris</italic> (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae) from Yunnan Province, Southwest China</article-title>. <source>Edaphologia</source> (<volume>58</volume>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>)<article-title> Four new species of the genus <italic>Nazeris</italic> (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae) from the Gaoligong Shan Mountains in Yunnan, Southwest China.</article-title> <source>Elytra, Tokyo</source> <volume>28</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>311</fpage>-<lpage>321</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>