<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.303.4808</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Two new species of the genera 
                    <italic>Mysmena</italic> and 
                    <italic>Trogloneta</italic> (Mysmenidae, Araneae) from Southwestern China</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Lin</surname>
                        <given-names>Yucheng</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:A514B4E7-2F9F-42B5-82E9-60713ACE9943</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Li</surname>
                        <given-names>Shuqiang</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:773E9385-8857-4D9E-B344-E836B1BDA2E8</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Key Laboratory of Bio-resources and Eco-environment (Ministry of Education), College of Life Sciences, Sichuan University, Chengdu, Sichuan 610064, China
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100101, China
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Shuqiang Li (<email xlink:type="simple">lisq@ioz.ac.cn</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Jeremy Miller</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>21</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2013</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>303</issue>
            <fpage>33</fpage>
            <lpage>51</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>2</month>
                    <year>2013</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>8</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2013</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Yucheng Lin, Shuqiang Li</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:3B8E5947-27BC-4038-8DB0-FF9FED584BDD</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Two new spider species of the family <tp:taxon-name>Mysmenidae</tp:taxon-name> Petrunkevitch, 1928 are reported from Southwestern China, i.e., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena wawuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> (male and female) from Sichuan and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta yuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> <bold>sp. n.</bold> (male) from Chongqing. Diagnoses and illustrations of the new species are provided.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>diagnosis</kwd>
                <kwd>description</kwd>
                <kwd>forest</kwd>
                <kwd>etymology</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Mysmenidae</tp:taxon-name> is a small family of minute araneoid spiders. Although the family <tp:taxon-name>Mysmenidae</tp:taxon-name> is distributed worldwide, it is one of the least-studied family-level groups among orb-weaving spiders, and its diversity is grossly undersampled due to their small size (0.7–3 mm) and cryptic life style (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Lopardo et al. 2011</xref>). Mysmenids mainly occur in leaf litter and other cryptic places in very humid habitats <!--PageBreak-->(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Lopardo &amp; Coddington 2005</xref>), and even in caves. Their distribution ranges throughout the tropical or subtropical regions of Eurasia, America and Africa. According to the latest records, a total of 123 species and 23 genera were reported in the family <tp:taxon-name>Mysmenidae</tp:taxon-name> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Platnick 2013</xref>). Up to present, 30 species placed in 9 genera have been described in China (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Yin et al. 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Ono 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Lin and Li 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Miller et al. 2009</xref>).</p>
            <p>The genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena</tp:taxon-name></italic> was erected by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Simon in 1894</xref> initially as a genus of the family <tp:taxon-name>Theridiidae</tp:taxon-name> with the type species <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridion leycoplagiatum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Simon, 1879; later transferred to the <tp:taxon-name>Symphytognathidae</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Forster (1959)</xref>, and then to the family <tp:taxon-name>Mysmenidae</tp:taxon-name> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Forster and Platnick (1977)</xref>. To date, 23 <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena</tp:taxon-name></italic> species have been reported worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Platnick 2013</xref>), including 12 species from China which is about a half of all species of the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Ono 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Lin and Li 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Miller et al. 2009</xref>).</p>
            <p>The genus  <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta</tp:taxon-name></italic> was established and placed in the family <tp:taxon-name>Theridiidae</tp:taxon-name> by Simon in 1922 for a minute spider from caves in France, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta granulum</tp:taxon-name></italic> (“<italic>Troglonata”</italic> was misspelled in the original description, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Simon 1926</xref>: 313) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Brescovit &amp; Lopardo 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Gertsch (1960)</xref> transferred this genus to the family <tp:taxon-name>Symphytognathidae</tp:taxon-name>, and then <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Forster &amp; Platnick (1977)</xref> put it in the family <tp:taxon-name>Mysmenidae</tp:taxon-name>. Until now there is no consistent diagnosis for <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Brescovit and Lopardo (2008)</xref> proposed that this genus can be distinguished from other mysmenids by the following combination of features: AME smaller than ALE; one femoral spot on leg I on both males and females; one male clasping spine on metatarsus I; males with highly elevated and conical carapace, and male pedipalp very large. Additional diagnostic characters may include the clustering of eyes around the apex of the carapace in males (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A–B</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Lin &amp; Li 2008</xref>: figs 16A–B, 19A–B) and the abdomen usually pointed dorsal-posteriorly (the exception is <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta denticocleari</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lin &amp; Li, 2008, which has a globose abdomen).</p>
            <p>At present, 9 <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta</tp:taxon-name></italic> species are known from America, Europe, Asia and some Atlantic islands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Platnick 2013</xref>), including two species reported from China (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Lin &amp; Li 2008</xref>): one found in caves from the Yunnan-Guizhou Plateau, another found at the canopy of Xishuangbanna tropical rainforest.</p>
            <p>In this paper we described two new species of genera <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Wawu Mt., Sichuan and Jinyun Mt., Chongqing of Southwestern China, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena wawuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta yuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Specimens were examined and measured under an Olympus SZX7 stereomicroscope. Further details were studied under an Olympus BX43 compound microscope. All drawings were made using a drawing tube attached to Olympus BX43 compound microscope, and then inked on ink jet plotter paper. Photos were taken with a Canon EOS 60D wide zoom digital camera (8.5 megapixels). The images were montaged using Helicon Focus 3.10 software. Male pedipalpi and female genitalia were examined and illustrated after they were dissected and detached from the spiders’ bodies. Vulvae were removed and treated in lactic acid before illustration. To reveal the course of spermatic <!--PageBreak-->duct, the pedipalpal bulb was also treated in lactic acid and mounted in Hoyer’s Solution. Left pedipalp of male spiders was illustrated. All specimens are preserved in 85% ethanol solution.</p>
            <p>All measurements are in millimeters. Leg measurements are given as: total length (femur, patella, tibia, metatarsus, and tarsus). The terminology mostly follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Lopardo et al. (2011)</xref>. The abbreviations used in text including: AER – anterior eye row; ALE – anterior lateral eye; AME – anterior median eye; PER – posterior eye row; PLE – posterior lateral eye; PME – posterior median eye. All specimens are deposited in the Zoological Department of the School of Life Science, Sichuan University Museum (SCUM) in Chengdu.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <sec sec-type="Mysmena Simon, 1894">
                <title><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena</tp:taxon-name></italic> Simon, 1894</title>
                <p><bold>Type species.</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Theridion leycoplagiatum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Simon, 1879</p>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Mysmena</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">wawuensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FF5B96D7-39D7-4F3E-816D-521A57F1413C</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Mysmena_wawuensis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">–7</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">, 13</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: CHINA, Sichuan: Hongya County, Wawu Mt. National Forest Park, Gufuping, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">29°40.114'N, 102°57.515'E</named-content>, elevation ca 1929 m, 27 June 2012, by hand collection, Yucheng Lin leg., male (SCUM).</p>
                        <p>Paratypes: [same data as holotype] (SCUM), 2 females.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific name is taken from the type locality; adjective.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>This new species is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena goudao</tp:taxon-name></italic> Miller, Griswold &amp; Yin, 2009 (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Miller et al. 2009</xref>: 39, figs 21F–G, 27A–E, 28A–B, 29A–F) in male pedipalpal shape and female genital configuration. Male differs from the latter by the presence of a subdistal cymbial process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3D–E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6E</xref>), a subdistal-ventral marcoseta on the pedipalpal femur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A–B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A–B</xref>), the absence of cymbial groove (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3D–E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D–E</xref>). Female by a small, weakly sclerotized scape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4B–C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B–C</xref>), a paired rugose accessory bursae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref>) and twisted course of spermathecae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><bold>Male</bold> (holotype). Somatic characters see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A–C</xref>. Coloration: Prosoma brown centrally, dark marginally. Sternum black. Opisthosoma black, with tiny yellow speckles.</p>
                        <p>Measurement: Total length 0.60. Prosoma 0.36 long, 0.35 wide, 0.32 high. Opisthosoma 0.36 long, 0.32 wide, 0.39 high. Clypeus 0.12 high. Sternum 0.25 long, 0.21 wide. Length of legs [total length (femur + patella + tibia + metatarsus + tarsus)]: I 1.14 (0.36, 0.14, 0.25, 0.18, 0.21); II 0.97 (0.30, 0.13, 0.21, 0.14, 0.19); III 0.76 (0.21, 0.11, 0.13, 0.13, 0.18); IV 0.93 (0.29, 0.13, 0.20, 0.14, 0.17).</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->Prosoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A, C</xref>): Carapace near round. Cephalic pars elevated, sharply vertical forward and slope backward. Ocular area at apex, dark. Eight eyes in two rows. AME black, others white. ALE and PLE contiguous. AME smallest, ALE largest. ARE slightly procurved, PRE straight. Chelicerae yellow, small, as long as endites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>).</p>
                        <p>Legs: Femora pale yellow, other segments yellow proximally, gray distally. Leg formula: I-II-IV-III. Leg I with a distal metatarsal clasping macroseta prolaterally on 1/3 position. Leg I and II with a subdistal sclerotized femoral spot ventrally. Patellae I–IV with a dorsal seta distally. Tibiae I–IV with a dorsal seta proximally, and with 3 trichobothria. Metatarsi I–IV with only one trichobothrium.</p>
                        <p>Opisthosoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A–C</xref>): Globular dorsally. Spinnerets dark, the anteriors larger than the posteriors. Colulus indistinct. Anal tubercle grey.</p>
                        <p>Pedipalp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>): Femur long, with a subdistal macroseta ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2A–B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A–B</xref>). Patella short, with a few setae. Tibia swollen, bowl-shaped, covered with long setae on distal margin ventrally and dorsally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3D–E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D–E</xref>). Cymbium membranous, wide, arisen from tibial margin ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6E</xref>), paracymbium attached with long setae along prolateral margin, a sclerotized cymbial process subdistally, a row of setae on cymbial fold subdistally and a primary cymbial conductor distally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3D–E</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D–E</xref>). Tegulum rugose, translucent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A–C</xref>). Spermatic duct visible through subtegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3A–C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A–C</xref>). Embolus long, thin and <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->sparal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>), coiling into four loops. Embolic end exceeded apex of cymbium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A–C</xref>).</p>
                        <p><bold>Female</bold> (one of paratypes). Somatic characters see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D–F</xref>. Coloration: Same as in male.</p>
                        <p>Measurement: Total length 0.75. Prosoma 0.36 long, 0.32 wide, 0.30 high. Opisthosoma as in male, 0.54 long, 0.50 wide, 0.61 high. Clypeus 0.05 high, distinctly lower than in male. Sternum 0.23 long, 0.21 wide. Length of legs [total length (femur + patella + tibia + metatarsus + tarsus)]: I 1.05 (0.34, 0.14, 0.21, 0.16, 0.20); II 0.93 (0.29, 0.13, 0.18, 0.14, 0.19); III 0.77 (0.23, 0.11, 0.13, 0.13, 0.17); IV 0.99 (0.30, 0.13, 0.20, 0.16, 0.20).</p>
                        <p>Prosoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D, F</xref>): Carapace near pear-shaped. Cephalic part lower than in male. Eyes arrangement, chelicerae and endites as in male.</p>
                        <p>Legs: Color, number of trichobothria same as in male, except for leg I without distal metatarsal clasping macroseta prolaterally. Sclerotized femoral spot present at leg I and II as in male. Leg formula: I-IV-II-III.</p>
                        <p>Opisthosoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D–F</xref>): Globose dorsally. Spinnerets grey, the anteriors larger than the posteriors. Colulus small, pale.</p>
                        <p>Epigynum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>): Large, weakly sclerotized, darkish. Epigynal area covered with short setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). A small, sclerotized scape stands on epigynal posteromargin <!--PageBreak-->mesially (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B–C</xref>). Spermathecae short clubbed, weakly sclerotized, twisted, attached with membranous, rugose accessory bursae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref>). Fertilization ducts short, connected with spermathecae and accessory bursa. Copulatory ducts long, curved, weekly sclerotized, derives from inner side of spermathecae ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Known only from the type locality (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13</xref>).</p>
                        <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 1.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena wawuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype (<bold>A–C</bold>) and female paratype (<bold>D–F</bold>). <bold>A–F</bold> Habitus. <bold>A, D</bold> dorsal view <bold>B, E</bold> ventral view <bold>C, F</bold> lateral view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 2.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena wawuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A–C</bold> Left pedipalp. <bold>A</bold> prolateral view <bold>B</bold> retrolateral view <bold>C</bold> dorsal view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 3.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmma wawuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A–C</bold> Pedipalpal bulb <bold>D–E</bold> Cymbium. <bold>A</bold> ventral view <bold>B</bold> dorsal view <bold>C</bold> apical view <bold>D</bold> ventral view <bold>E</bold> dorsal view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 4.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena wawuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female paratype. <bold>A</bold> Epigynum, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Epigynum (lactic acid-treated), ventral view <bold>C</bold> Vulva (cleared), dorsal view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 5.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena wawuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A–C</bold> Left pedipalp. <bold>A</bold> prolateral view <bold>B</bold> retrolateral view <bold>C</bold> dorsal view. Abbrs.: <bold>CyP</bold> cymbial process; <bold>E</bold> embolus; <bold>Pa</bold> patella; <bold>T</bold> tegulum; <bold>Ti</bold> tibia.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 6.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena wawuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A–C</bold> Pedipalpal bulb, <bold>D–E</bold> Cymbium. <bold>A</bold> ventral view <bold>B</bold> dorsal view <bold>C</bold> apical view <bold>D</bold> ventral view <bold>E</bold> dorsal view. Abbrs.: <bold>Cy</bold> cymbium; <bold>CyC</bold> cymbial conductor; <bold>CyF</bold> cymbial fold; <bold>CyFs</bold> setae on cymbial fold; <bold>CyP</bold> cymbial process; <bold>E</bold> embolus; <bold>SD</bold> spermatic duct; <bold>Ti</bold> tibia.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 7.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Mysmena wawuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., female paratype. <bold>A</bold> Epigynum, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Epigynum (lactic acid-treated), ventral view <bold>C</bold> Vulva (cleared), dorsal view. Abbrs.: <bold>AB</bold> accessory bursa; <bold>CD</bold> copulatory duct; <bold>FD</bold> fertilization duct; <bold>S</bold> spermatheca; <bold>Sp</bold> scape.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Trogloneta Simon, 1922">
                <title><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta</tp:taxon-name></italic> Simon, 1922</title>
                <p><bold>Type species.</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta granulum</tp:taxon-name></italic> Simon, 1922</p>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Trogloneta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">yuensis</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:47B062D1-CCC8-4C2B-978B-6ABF9B135CDF</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Trogloneta_yuensis</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figs 8</xref>
                        <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">–13</xref>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                        <title>Material examined.</title>
                        <p>Holotype: CHINA, Chongqing: Beibei District, Jinyun Mt., Guankou, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">29°50.261'N, 106°23.811'E</named-content>, elevation ca 531 m, 5 April 2010, by sieving, Zhisheng Zhang leg., male (SCUM).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                        <title>Etymology.</title>
                        <p>The specific name is taken from the type locality; adjective. Yu is short name for Chongqing.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                        <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p>This new species has the following combinations of typical generic features: AME dark, smaller ALE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8B</xref>); eyes at the apex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A</xref>); male leg I with a femoral spot and a metatarsal clasping spine; highly elevated and conical carapace (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A</xref>); male pedipalp large (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8B–C</xref>). All indicating that this species belongs to the genus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta</tp:taxon-name></italic>. This new species is similar to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta denticocleari</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lin &amp; Li, 2008 (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Lin and Li 2008</xref>: 513, figs 16A–E, 17A–C) in habitus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A</xref>), eyes arrangement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8B</xref>), pedipalp shape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9A–B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11A–B</xref>), cymbial configuration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12E</xref>) and a trichobothrium present at pedipalpal tibia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11A–B</xref>), but distinguished from the latter by a long, distally hooked embolus attaching accessory membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10A–B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12A–B</xref>), a long fingerlike median apophysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10C–D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12C–D</xref>), a laminar cymbial conductor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12E</xref>), a distally aquiline, basally constricted cymbial process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10E–F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12E</xref>) and a dorsal-posterior opisthosomal tubercle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A, D–E</xref>).</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                        <title>Description.</title>
                        <p><bold>Male</bold> (holotype). Somatic characters see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A–E</xref>. Coloration: Prosoma yellow centrally, dark marginally. Clypeus black. Sternum yellow, with a pair of shoulder dark speckles. Opisthosoma yellow, with irregular dark spots.</p>
                        <p>Measurement: Total length 1.01. Prosoma 0.45 long, 0.45 wide, 0.59 high. Opisthosoma 0.54 long, 0.55 wide, 0.95 high. Clypeus 0.32 high. Sternum 0.31 long, 0.29 wide. Length of legs [total length (femur + patella + tibia + metatarsus + tarsus)]: I 1.42 (0.43, 0.17, 0.32, 0.29, 0.21); II 1.15 (0.38, 0.16, 0.23, 0.22, 0.16); III 0.96 (0.29, 0.13, 0.20, 0.18, 0.16); IV 1.15 (0.36, 0.14, 0.26, 0.22, 0.17).</p>
                        <p><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->Prosoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A–C</xref>): Carapace near round. Cephalic pars sharply elevated, slope forward and backward. Ocular area at apex. Eight eyes in two rows. AME black, others white. AME smallest, ALE largest. ALE&gt;PLE&gt;PME&gt;AME. ALE, PME and PLE contiguous. ARE procurved, PRE strongly procurved. Chelicerae pale, small, shorter than endites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A</xref>), fang furrow with 2 promaiginal and 1 retromarginal teeth.</p>
                        <p>Legs: Femora and other segments pale yellow mesially, but grey proximally and distally. Leg formula: I-II-IV-III. Leg I with a subdistal sclerotized femoral spot ventrally and a submesial metatarsal clasping macroseta prolaterally. Patellae I–IV with a dorsal seta distally. Tibiae I–IV with a dorsal seta proximally. Tibiae I, II and IV with 3 trichobothria, but 4 on tibia III. Metatarsi I–IV lack trichobothrium.</p>
                        <p>Opisthosoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8A, D–E</xref>): elliptic dorsally, fusiform posteriorly, triangular laterally, with a tubercle at rear. Spinnerets grey, the anteriors larger than the posteriors. Colulus small, tongue-shaped. Anal tubercle pale.</p>
                        <p>Pedipalp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref>): Large, strongly sclerotized. Femur as 2.5 times long as patella (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9A, B</xref>). Patella short, with a few setae. Tibia wider than long, nearly cup-<!--PageBreak-->shaped, covered with a dorsal trichobothrium and a few marginal long setae ventrally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figs 11A–B</xref>). Cymbium large (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10E–F</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12E</xref>), membranous, paracymbium flattened, covered with dense long setae. A long cymbial process (aquiline distally, constricted proximally) arisen from inner side subdistal margin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12E</xref>). Cymbial fold distinctly, with long setae. Distal primary cymbial conductor membranous, translucent, attaching with a cluster of setae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12E</xref>). Tegulum smooth, sclerotized (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10C–D</xref>). Spermatic duct long, visible through subtegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11C–D</xref>). A long, fingerlike median apophysis starts at the junction between tegulum and subtegulum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figs 10D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11D</xref>). Embolus long, arched, strongly sclerotized, gradually diminishing from base to end (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12A–B</xref>). Embolic end unciform, with accessory membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12A–B</xref>), hidden behind cymbial conductor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figs 9B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11B</xref>).</p>
                        <p><bold>Female</bold>. Unknown.</p>
                        <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 8.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta yuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Habitus, lateral view <bold>B</bold> Prosoma, dorsal view <bold>C</bold> Ditto,ventral view <bold>D</bold> Opisthosoma, dorsal view <bold>E</bold> Ditto, posterior view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 9.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta yuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Left pedipalp, retrolateral view <bold>B</bold> Ditto, prolateral view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 10.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta yuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Embolus, ventral view <bold>B</bold> Ditto, dorsal view <bold>C</bold> Pedipalpal bulb (excluding embolus), ventral view <bold>D</bold> Ditto, dorsal view <bold>E</bold> Cymbium, dorsal view <bold>F</bold> Ditto, ventral view.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F11" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 11.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta yuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A</bold> Left pedipalp, retrolateral view <bold>B</bold> Ditto, prolateral view. Abbrs.: <bold>Cy</bold> cymbium; <bold>CyC</bold> cymbial conductor; <bold>CyF</bold> cymbial fold; <bold>CyFs</bold> setae on cymbial fold; <bold>CyP</bold> cymbial process; <bold>E</bold> embolus; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>Pa</bold> patella; <bold>PC</bold> paracymbium; <bold>SD</bold> spermatic duct; <bold>T</bold> tegulum; <bold>Ti</bold> tibia.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                        <fig id="F12" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 12.</label>
                            <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Trogloneta yuensis</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., male holotype. <bold>A–B</bold> Embolus. <bold>A</bold> ventral view <bold>B</bold> dorsal view <bold>C–D</bold> Pedipalpal bulb (excluding embolus) <bold>C</bold> ventral view <bold>D</bold> dorsal view <bold>E</bold> Cymbium, dorsal view. Abbrs.: <bold>Cy</bold> cymbium; <bold>CyC</bold> cymbial conductor; <bold>CyF</bold> cymbial fold; <bold>CyFs</bold> setae on cymbial fold; <bold>CyP</bold> cymbial process; <bold>E</bold> embolus; <bold>MA</bold> median apophysis; <bold>Pa</bold> patella; <bold>PC</bold> paracymbium; <bold>SD</bold> spermatic duct; <bold>ST</bold> subtegulum; <bold>T</bold> tegulum.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g012.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                        <title>Distribution.</title>
                        <p>Known only from the type locality (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13</xref>).</p>
                        <fig id="F13" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                            <label>Figure 13.</label>
                            <caption><p>Distributional records of two new mysmenid species from China.</p></caption>
                            <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-303-033-g013.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                        </fig>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>The manuscript benefited greatly from comments by Jeremy Miller (Naturalis Biodiversity Center, the Netherlands) and one anonymous reviewer. This study was supported by the National Natural Sciences Foundation of China (China National Funds for Distinguished Young Scientists-31025023 and NSFC-30870271, 31000946, 31272280), and by New Teacher Fund for Doctor Station of Ministry of Education of China (20100181120049).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brescovit</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopardo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The first record on the spider genus <italic>Trogloneta</italic> Simon in the southern hemisphere (Araneae, Mysmenidae), with descriptions of three new species from Brazil and remarks on the morphology.</article-title> <source>Acta Zoologica (Stockholm)</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1463-6395.2007.00296.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1463-6395.2007.00296.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>) <article-title>The spiders of the family Symphytognathidae.</article-title> <source>Transactions and Proceedings of the Royal Society of New Zealand</source> <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>329</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname> <given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname> <given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>A review of the spider family Symphytognathidae (Arachnida, Araneae).</article-title> <source>American Museum Novitates</source> <volume>2619</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gertsch</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1960</year>) <article-title>Descriptions of American spiders of the family Symphytognathidae.</article-title> <source>American Museum Novitates</source> <volume>1981</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopardo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coddington</surname> <given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Mysmenidae. In Ubick D, Paquin P, Cushing CE, Roth V (Ed) Spiders of North America: An Identification Manual. American Arachnological Society, 377.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopardo</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giribet</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hormiga</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Morphology to the rescue: molecular data and the signal of morphological characters in combined phylogenetic analyses–a case study from mysmenid spiders (Araneae, Mysmenidae), with comments on the evolution of web architecture.</article-title> <source>Cladistics</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>278</fpage>-<lpage>330</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-0031.2010.00332.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1096-0031.2010.00332.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mysmenid spiders of China (Araneae: Mysmenidae).</article-title> <source>Annales Zoologici</source> <volume>58</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>487</fpage>-<lpage>520</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3161/000345408X364337" xlink:type="simple">10.3161/000345408X364337</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griswold</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The symphytognathoid spiders of the Gaoligongshan, Yunnan, China (Araneae: Araneoidea): Systematics and diversity of micro-orbweavers.</article-title> <source>ZooKeys</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>195</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.11.160-app.C.dt" xlink:type="simple">10.3897/zookeys.11.160-app.C.dt</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ono</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Eight new species of the families Hahniidae, Theridiidae, Linyphiidae and Anapidae (Arachida, Araneae) from Japan.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the National Museum of Nature and Science,Tokyo (A)</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Platnick</surname> <given-names>NI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <source>The world spider catalog, version 13.5. American Museum of Natural History. Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://research.amnh.org/entomology/spiders/catalog/" xlink:type="simple">http://research.amnh.org/entomology/spiders/catalog/</ext-link> (accessed 2 May 2013).</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1926</year>) <article-title>Les arachnides de France. Synopsis générale et catalogue des espèces françaises de l’ordre des Araneae; 2e partie.</article-title> <source>Paris</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>-<lpage>532</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1922</year>) <article-title>Description de deux arachnides cavernicoles du midi de la France.</article-title> <source>Bulletin de la Société entomologique de France</source> <volume>1922</volume>: <fpage>199</fpage>-<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1894</year>) <article-title>Histoire naturelle des araignées.</article-title> <source>Paris</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>489</fpage>-<lpage>760</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname> <given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname> <given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A new species of the genus <italic>Mysmenella</italic> from China (Araneae, Mysmenidae).</article-title> <source>Acta Zootaxonomica Sinica</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>80</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>