<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.89.825</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title><italic>Stylobates birtlesi</italic> sp. n., a new species of carcinoecium-forming sea anemone (Cnidaria, Actiniaria, Actiniidae) from eastern Australia</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Crowther</surname>
                        <given-names>Andrea L.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:D014F6D4-6BDD-4012-9189-A1F30DC25452</uri></contrib>           
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Fautin</surname>
                        <given-names>Daphne G.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:55D84D7A-40A1-454D-8A7F-755C8958E1D9</uri></contrib>           
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Wallace</surname>
                        <given-names>Carden C.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:78F6BEE6-F495-4151-A1D0-7C301F4F92B3</uri></contrib>           
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>1</label><italic>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, and Natural History Museum and Biodiversity Institute, University of Kansas, 1200 Sunnyside Ave., Lawrence, Kansas 66045–7534 USA</italic></aff>
                    <aff id="A2"><label>2</label><italic>Museum of Tropical Queensland, 70–102 Flinders St., Townsville, Queensland 4810 Australia</italic></aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Andrea L. Crowther (<email xlink:type="simple">andreac@ku.edu</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Leen van Ofwegen</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>11</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>89</issue>
            <fpage>33</fpage>
            <lpage>48</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>20</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>7</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Andrea L. Crowther, Daphne G. Fautin, Carden C. Wallace</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:054D5B51-29BA-4349-8B0A-70DDEA289DC9</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>We describe a new species of carcinoecium-forming sea anemone, <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold>, from sites 590–964 m deep in the Coral Sea, off the coast of Queensland, Australia. An anemone of this genus settles on a gastropod shell inhabited by a hermit crab, then covers and extends the shell to produce a chitinous structure termed a carcinoecium. <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> <bold>sp. n.</bold> is symbiotic with the hermit crab <tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus trispinosus </tp:taxon-name>(Balss, 1911). The nature of marginal sphincter muscle and nematocyst size and distribution distinguish <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi </tp:taxon-name><bold>sp. n.</bold> from other species in the genus. The four known species of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates </tp:taxon-name>are allopatric, each inhabiting a separate ocean basin of the Indo-West Pacific. We also extend the known range of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name> in the Indian Ocean off the coast of Western Australia.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Anthozoa</kwd>
                <kwd>Hexacorallia</kwd>
                <kwd>deep sea</kwd>
                <kwd>symbiosis</kwd>
                <kwd>hermit crab</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name> Dall, 1903, of family <tp:taxon-name>Actiniidae</tp:taxon-name> Rafinesque, 1815, is an exclusively deep-water genus of sea anemones in which three species are known: <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> Dall, 1903, from Hawai’i and Guam in the Pacific Ocean, <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name> (Carlgren, 1928a), from the Indian Ocean off Africa, and <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name> Fautin, 1987, from the Indian Ocean off Western Australia. We describe <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi </tp:taxon-name>sp. n. from specimens collected in the Coral Sea off the northeastern coast of Australia. In addition, we report previously unpublished localities for <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            <p>A distinctive feature of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name> is the chitinous carcinoecium it produces; a carcinoecium is a shell-like structure inhabited by a hermit crab. Carcinoecia are produced by bryozoans (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Vermeij 1993</xref>) as well as many species of cnidarians (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Williams and McDermott 2004</xref>), including hydrozoans (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Millard 1975</xref>), zoanthids (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Muirhead et al. 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Ates 2003</xref>) and sea anemones (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Carlgren 1928a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Ross 1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Dunn and Liberman 1983</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Daly et al. 2004</xref>). Of anemones that attach to gastropod shells inhabited by hermit crabs, animals of some species (e.g. those belonging to <tp:taxon-name>Calliactis</tp:taxon-name>) form a thin layer of chitin over the shell. Those of other species (e.g. those belonging to <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates </tp:taxon-name>and <italic>Paracalliactis</italic>) not only cover but extend the shell, producing a carcinoecium. The ability to form a carcinoecium is a convergent attribute of anemones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Gusmão and Daly 2010</xref>); anemones possessing this ability belong to four families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Daly et al. 2004</xref>).</p>
            <p>The genus and species <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> were described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Dall (1903, p. 61)</xref>, who was initially under the impression that the shell of “flexible, horny consistency,” which was inhabited by a hermit crab and covered by a sea anemone, was that of a gastropod. He later corrected his mistake, recognizing that “These specimens were secretions from the bases of the Actinias” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">(Dall 1919, p. 80)</xref>. Nonetheless, the holotype of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> Dall, 1903, consisting only of the carcinoecium, is still housed in the mollusc collection of the United States National Museum of Natural History (USNM). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Carlgren (1928a)</xref> described <tp:taxon-name>Isadamsia cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name> as a new genus and species of carcinoecium-forming anemone, making no reference to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Dall (1903)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Dunn et al. (1981)</xref> synonymized the genera <tp:taxon-name>Isadamsia</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name>. According to International Code of Zoological Nomenclature Article 12.2.8 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature 1999</xref>), having been published before 1931, the name <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus </tp:taxon-name>is available for the anemone because it is a “description of the work of an organism.”</p>
            <p>The allopatric distribution that we found for the four species of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name> is similar to that of other deep-sea invertebrates in the tropical Indo-West Pacific, such as scleractinian corals and squat lobsters.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title>
            <p>The holotype and five paratypes of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. were trawled by ORV <tp:taxon-name>Franklin</tp:taxon-name> during the Cidaris I expedition on the northeastern continental slope of Queensland<!--PageBreak--> in 1986 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Anonymous 1986</xref>). The holotype was photographed live (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a, b</xref>) within a few minutes of being brought on deck. Four paratypes were trawled by RV <italic>Soela</italic> off the northeast coast of Queensland and one voucher was trawled by FRV <italic>Iron Summer</italic> off the southeast coast of Queensland. All specimens were preserved in 70% ethanol. Specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisettae</tp:taxon-name> were collected on the RV <italic>Southern Surveyor</italic> expedition to the northwestern coast of Australia in 2007.</p>
            <p>Cnida preparations were made from the tentacles, mesenterial filaments, actinopharynx, and column by smashing tissue with water under a coverslip. Preparations were examined using differential interference (Nomarski) optics at 1000×. For each tissue type, the length and width were measured for each type of cnida. Representative cnidae were photographed using an Olympus digital camera. Histological sections were stained with Gomori trichrome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Menzies 1959</xref>).</p>
            <p>The holotype, four paratype lots, and one voucher of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. are deposited at Museum of Tropical Queensland, Townsville [MTQ], and one paratype lot is deposited at the Division of Invertebrate Zoology collection of the University of Kansas Biodiversity Institute, Lawrence [KUDIZ]. New records for <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name> are based on specimens in the Western Australian Museum, Perth [WAM]. Separated hermit crab specimens are deposited at Queensland Museum South Bank, Brisbane [QM].</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Results"><title>Results</title>
            <p><bold>Family <tp:taxon-name>Actiniidae</tp:taxon-name> Rafinesque, 1815</bold></p>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature><label>Genus</label>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Stylobates</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Dall, 1903</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name><comment> Dall, 1903: p. 62</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Isadamsia</tp:taxon-name><comment> Carlgren, 1928a: p. 167</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="General"><title>General</title>
		                <p>Because <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Dall (1903)</xref> had been under the impression that the carcinoecium upon which he based his description was that of a gastropod, the first description of the anemone was by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Carlgren (1928a)</xref> for <tp:taxon-name>Isadamsia cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name> from the east coast of Africa. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Carlgren (1928a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">1949)</xref> is the only person to have defined the genus, and his definition was based on the single species he knew. We update the definition of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name> to incorporate information from all four known species.</p>
		                <p>Deep-sea <tp:taxon-name>Actiniidae</tp:taxon-name> with very wide pedal disc that covers a gastropod shell inhabited by a hermit crab. Anemone pedal disc secretes carcinoecium. Column smooth, thin-walled. Marginal sphincter muscle endodermal, circumscribed, palmate or pinnate. Tentacles hexamerously arranged; fewer than mesenteries at base. Longitudinal muscles of tentacles and radial muscles of oral disc ectodermal. Mesenteries of 5–6 orders; those of lowest orders complete and sterile, those of highest orders incomplete and fertile. Retractor muscles weak, diffuse; parietobasilar and basilar muscles distinct.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species (by monotipy)"><title>Type species (by monotypy):</title>
		                <p><tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> Dall, 1903.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
		        <sec sec-type="Species description"><title>Species description</title>
		            <tp:taxon-treatment>
		                <tp:nomenclature>
		                    <tp:taxon-name>
		                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Stylobates</tp:taxon-name-part>
		                    	<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">birtlesi</tp:taxon-name-part>
		                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:6B1BF135-854D-4495-BC5D-0D5FAE79EF7D</object-id>
		                    </tp:taxon-name>
		                    <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
		                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>
		                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2"/>
		                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"/>
		                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4"/>
		                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>
		                </tp:nomenclature>
		                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined"><title>Material examined.</title>
		                    <p><bold>Holotype:</bold></p>
		                    <p>MTQ G57579 (one specimen) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
		                    <p>Type locality: <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">17°45.99'S, 148°39.09'E</named-content>, 958–964 m; Coral Sea, off Tully, Queensland, Australia (FRV Franklin, Cidaris I expedition, Station 15–4). Bottom temperature 5.5°C, rocks/mud sediment. Collected 9 May 1986, by RA Birtles and P Arnold. Hermit crab present.</p>
		                    <p><bold>Paratypes:</bold></p>
		                    <p>MTQ G57580 (one specimen).</p>
		                    <p>Locality: <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">17°52'S, 147°08'E</named-content>, 680–740 m; Coral Sea, off Tully, Queensland, Australia (FRV Franklin, Cidaris I expedition, Station 48–3). Bottom temperature 8.2°C, mud sediment. Collected 17 May 1986, by RA Birtles and P Arnold. Hermit crab separated from carcinoecium, registered as QM W16502 (crustacean collection).</p>
		                    <p>MTQ G57581 (two specimens).</p>
		                    <p>Locality: <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">17°51.71'S, 147°09.93'E</named-content>, 881–920 m; Coral Sea, off Tully, Queensland, Australia (FRV Franklin, Cidaris I expedition, Station 49–3). Bottom temperature 6.1°C, rocks/shell debris/sticky mud sediment. Collected 17 May 1986, by RA Birtles and P Arnold.</p>
		                    <p>MTQ G57582 (one specimen).</p>
		                    <p>Locality: <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">18°01.69'S, 147°20.53'E</named-content>, 899–918 m; Coral Sea, off Tully, Queensland, Australia (FRV Franklin, Cidaris I expedition, Station 50–3). Bottom temperature 6.2°C, mud sediment. Collected 17 May 1986, by RA Birtles and P Arnold. Hermit crab separated from carcinoecium, registered as QM W16499 (crustacean collection).</p>
		                    <p>KUDIZ 003352 (one specimen).</p>
		                    <p>Locality: <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">18°01.69'S, 147°20.53'E</named-content>, 899–918 m; Coral Sea, off Tully, Queensland, Australia (FRV Franklin, Cidaris I expedition, Station 50–3). Bottom temperature 6.2°C, mud sediment. Collected 17 May 1986, by RA Birtles and P Arnold. Hermit crab separated from carcinoecium, registered as QM W16499 (crustacean collection).</p>
		                    <p>MTQ G64680 (four specimens).</p>
		                    <p>Locality: <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">16°55'S, 151°34'E, 880 m</named-content>; Coral Sea, northeast Queensland, Australia (RV Soela, Station CO685A78). Collected 6 December 1985, by P Davie. Hermit crabs separated from carcinoecia, registered as QM W16514 (crustacean collection).</p>
		                    <p><bold>Voucher:</bold></p>
		                    <p>MTQ G58760 (one specimen).<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
		                    <p>Locality: <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">27°59.37'S, 154°00.12'E</named-content>, 590 m; off coast of southeast Queensland, Australia (FRV Iron Summer, Shot 2). Collected 31 March 1983, by R Morton.</p>
		                </tp:treatment-sec>
		                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
		                    <p><italic><underline>Base</underline></italic>: Pedal disc concave, attached to carcinoecium. Base of anemone covers most of carcinoecium, except part directly under hermit crab, presumably where hermit crab’s chelipeds frequently contact carcinoecium (arrow, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1f</xref>).</p>
		                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
		                    	<label>Figure 1.</label>
		                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. holotype MTQ G57579 <bold>a, b</bold> soon after collection (photo: RA Birtles) <bold>c, d</bold> preserved specimen with <tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus trispinosus</tp:taxon-name> showing position of oral disc of anemone <bold>e</bold> preserved specimen: shortest tentacles beside longest ones (on right side of oral disc in this view); tentacles grade in length between longest and shortest around other side of oral disc (dashed line indicates directive axis) <bold>f</bold> preserved specimen without hermit crab showing aperture and part of carcinoecium not covered by anemone (arrow). Scale bars 20 mm.</p></caption>
		                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-033-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
		                    </fig>
		                    <p><italic><underline>Column</underline></italic>: Not cylindrical: wraps around gastropod shell so column much longer on one side than on diametrically opposite side. Smallest specimen with shortest side 4 mm, longest side 50 mm. Largest specimen with shortest side 15 mm, longest side 90 mm. Smooth, thin. Fosse shallow. Live specimens light pink, body wall translucent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a, b</xref>); preserved specimens beige. Mesenterial insertions visible through body wall; white in live specimens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref>) and preserved specimens.</p>
		                    <p><italic><underline>Oral disc</underline></italic>: Oriented toward substrate in life, over umbilicus area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1c, d</xref>). Disc and mouth circular (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1e</xref>); disc exposed and mouth agape in all specimens examined. Ectodermal musculature radial.</p>
		                    <p><italic><underline>Orientation</underline></italic>: Directive axis in line with spire of shell, parallel to parietal wall of aperture (dotted red line, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1e</xref>).</p>
		                    <p><italic><underline>Tentacles</underline></italic>: Beige, slightly darker than column, no pattern. Relatively narrow, tip terete.96 to more than 200 in largest specimens; at margin, in 3 or 4 cycles. Not of uniform length: shortest ones (1–4 mm) on directive axis, at end of one siphonoglyph, beside longest ones (3–9 mm); tentacle length grades between them around oral disc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1e</xref>). Ectodermal musculature longitudinal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>).</p>
		                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
		                    	<label>Figure 2.</label>
		                        <caption><p>Longitudinal section through tentacle of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. paratype MTQ G57580.</p></caption>
		                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-033-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
		                    </fig>
		                    <p><italic><underline>Marginal sphincter muscle</underline></italic>: Well developed, circumscribed, palmate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3a, b</xref>).</p>
		                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
		                    	<label>Figure 3.</label>
		                        <caption><p>Endodermal circumscribed marginal sphincter muscles of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name> spp. <bold>a, b</bold> Palmate marginal sphincter muscle of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. <bold>a</bold> paratype MTQ G57581 <bold>b</bold> paratype KUDIZ 003352 <bold>c-e</bold> Pinnate marginal sphincter muscles. <bold>c</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> (from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Dunn et al. 1981</xref>) <bold>d</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name> (from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Carlgren 1928a</xref>) <bold>e</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name> (from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Fautin 1987</xref>).</p></caption>
		                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-033-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
		                    </fig>
		                    <p><italic><underline>Mesenteries and internal anatomy</underline></italic>: Two siphonoglyphs visible in most specimens; actinopharynx ribbed, darker beige than column. Mesenteries to five orders (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4a</xref>); <!--PageBreak-->thin, each with oral but no marginal stoma. Retractor muscles diffuse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b</xref>). Parietobasilar muscle with short free penon. Sexes presumably separate: three females, one male examined. First three orders complete and sterile, rest incomplete and fertile (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4a</xref>).</p>
		                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
		                    	<label>Figure 4.</label>
		                        <caption><p>Mesenterial musculature and fertility of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. holotype MTQ G57579 <bold>a </bold>mesenterial arrangement, orders indicated with Roman numerals; column wall at base of image <bold>b</bold> diffuse retractor muscle; column wall at base of image. Scale bar 1 mm.</p></caption>
		                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-033-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
		                    </fig>
		                    <p><italic><underline>Carcinoecium</underline></italic>: Shape similar to that of dextral, trochoid gastropod shell. Aperture with simple arced elliptical outer lip, fairly straight parietal wall along what would be termed the columella in a gastropod. Bronze color, becomes chalky out of liquid.</p>
		                    <p><italic><underline>Cnidae</underline></italic>: Cnidom: Spirocysts, basitrichs, microbasic <italic>p</italic>-mastigophores. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> lists distribution and size of cnidae; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> depicts each cnida type. The largest specimen (MTQ G57580) possessed small basitrichs (<italic>e</italic>)and(<italic>f</italic>) in the actinopharynx, and small basitrichs (<italic>h</italic>) in the column that were not found in other specimens.</p>
		                    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
		                    	<label>Table 1.</label>
		                        <caption><p>Cnidae of all four species of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name>, given as range in length X width of undischarged capsules in µm (outlier measurements in parentheses). n = number of capsules measured, N = ratio of number of animals in which that type of cnida was found to the number of animals examined (where data are available). Frequency of cnida type indicated by the following: ++ very common, + common, - sporadic. Letters in parentheses correspond to images in Figure 5 for <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</p></caption>
		                        <table>
		                            <tbody>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</th>
		                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name></th>
		                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stylobates cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name></th>
		                                    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name></th>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tentacles</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basitrich (<italic>a</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6-38.8 X 2.6-4.6 n=63 N=6/6 [++]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.9-36.1 X 3.1-3.9 n=43</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.1-30.3 X 2.5-3.3 n=11</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8-39.7 X 2.5-3.7 n=70 N=6/6</td>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basitrich (<italic>b</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(11.9) 14.2-19.9 X 2.6-3.4 n=12 N=5/6 [ – ]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9-16.1 X 1.6-2.5 n=11 N=3/6</td>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spirocyst (<italic>c</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9-39.8 (46.3) X 2.2-4.6 n=51 N=7/7 [+]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(25.4) 28.7-44.3 X 2.9-4.1 (4.9) n=40</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.8-39.4 X 2.7-3.3 n=10</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1-55.8 X 2.5-3.7 n=63 N=6/6</td>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actinopharynx</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basitrich (<italic>d</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.8-37.1 X 2.9-4.3 n=61 N=6/6 [++]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(26.2) 29.5-37.7 X 2.9-4.1 n= 38</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.1-31.2 X 2.5-3.3 n=10</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.0-37.2 X 2.5-3.7 n=59 N=5/5</td>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basitrich (<italic>e</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9-21.2 X 3.3 n=9 N=1/6 [ – ]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2-21.3 X 2.5-3.1 n=9</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basitrich (<italic>f</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4-11.2 X 1.9-2.8  n=20 N=1/6 [ – ]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Column</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basitrich (<italic>g</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9-30.5 X 2.6-4.1 n=65 N=7/7 [++]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5-36.1 X 2.9-3.5 n=24</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0-28.7 X 2.7-3.3 n=12</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1-33.5 X 2.5-3.7 n=46 N=5/5</td>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basitrich (<italic>h</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3-9.2 X 1.9-3.6 n=10 N=1/6 [ – ]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesenterial Filaments</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basitrich (<italic>i</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5-37.1 X 4.4-6.7 n=25 N=6/6 [++]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(25.4) 27.9-32.8 X 4.1-5.5 n=14</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5-37.2 X 4.7-6.0 n=34 N=5/7</td>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basitrich (<italic>j</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5-33.2 X 2.8-3.8 n=18 N=5/6 [ – ]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5-36.1 X 2.5-3.9 n=21</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5-37.2 X 2.5-3.5 n=11 N=3/7</td>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basitrich (<italic>k</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9-21.4 X 2.1-3.1 n=51 N=6/6 [++]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6-23.0 X 2.1-3.3 n=58</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8-18.0 X 2.1-2.5 n=8</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4-16.1 X 1.9-3.1 n=10 N=4/7</td>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basitrich (<italic>l</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9-11.9 X 1.9-2.9 n=21 N=3/6 [+]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microbasic <italic>p</italic>-mastigophore (<italic>m</italic>)</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2-30.0 X 4.4-7.9 n=45 N=5/6 [++]</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3-29.5 X 3.9-5.7 n=27</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9-23.0 X 4.1-5.7 n=12</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.6-32.2 X 3.5-6.2 n=50 N=7/7</td>
		                                </tr>
		                                <tr>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source:</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Dunn et al. 1981</xref></td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Dunn et al. 1981</xref></td>
		                                    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Fautin 1987</xref></td>
		                                </tr>
		                            </tbody>
		                        </table>
		                    </table-wrap>
		                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
		                    	<label>Figure 5.</label>
		                        <caption><p>Cnidae of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Refer to Table 1 for list of cnida types and distribution.</p></caption>
		                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-033-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
		                    </fig>
		                    <p><italic><underline>Habitat</underline></italic>: Mud and rocks, 590–694 m.</p>
		                    <p><italic><underline>Distribution</underline></italic>: From Coral Sea of northern Queensland to southern Queensland coast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
		                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
		                    	<label>Figure 6.</label>
		                        <caption><p>Distribution of species of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name>.</p></caption>
		                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-089-033-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
		                    </fig>
		                    <p><italic><underline>Symbiont</underline></italic>: Hermit crab <tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus trispinosus</tp:taxon-name> (Balss, 1911), identified by Dr. Rafael Lemaitre (Curator of <tp:taxon-name>Crustacea</tp:taxon-name>, Department of Invertebrate Zoology, USNM).</p>
		                </tp:treatment-sec>
		                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
		                    <p>This species is named for R Alastair Birtles of James Cook University, Townsville, who, with the late P Arnold (MTQ) and M Pichon (Australian Institute of Marine Science), collected this species and photographed it alive.</p>
		                </tp:treatment-sec>
		            </tp:taxon-treatment>
		        </sec>
		        <sec sec-type="New records of Stylobates loisetteae Fautin, 1987"><title>New records of Stylobates loisetteae Fautin, 1987</title>
		            <p>WAM Z50046 (one specimen).</p>
		            <p>Locality: <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">12.1814°S, 123.4177°E</named-content>, 400 m; Ashmore, Western Australia, Australia (FRV <tp:taxon-name>Southern Surveyor</tp:taxon-name>, Station SS0507/189, Beam Trawl). Collected 6 July 2007, by MP Salotti.</p>
		            <p>WAM Z50047 (one specimen).</p>
		            <p>Locality: <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">13.2247°S, 123.3957°E</named-content>, 400 m; Kulumburu, Western Australia, Australia (FRV <tp:taxon-name>Southern Surveyor</tp:taxon-name>, Station SS0507/176, Sherman Sled). Collected 5 July 2007, by MP Salotti.</p>
		            <p>WAM Z50049 (one specimen).</p>
		            <p>Locality: <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">13.2650°S, 123.3741°E</named-content>, 400 m; Kulumburu, Western Australia, Australia (FRV <tp:taxon-name>Southern Surveyor</tp:taxon-name>, Station SS0507/180, Beam Trawl). Collected 6 July 2007, by MP Salotti.</p>
		            <p>WAM Z50050 (two specimens).</p>
		            <p>Locality: <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">15.6102°S, 120.8076°E</named-content>, 400 m; Lacepede, Western Australia, Australia (FRV <tp:taxon-name>Southern Surveyor</tp:taxon-name>, Station SS0507/130, Beam Trawl). Collected 1 July 2007, by MP Salotti.</p>
		            <p>WAM Z50058 (two specimens).</p>
		            <p>Locality: <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates">12.5295°S, 123.4273°E</named-content>, 400 m; Ashmore, Western Australia, Australia (FRV <tp:taxon-name>Southern Surveyor</tp:taxon-name>, Station SS0507/192, Beam Trawl). Collected 6 July 2007, by MP Salotti.<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--></p>
		        </sec>
		        <sec sec-type="Differential diagnosis"><title>Differential diagnosis</title>
		            <p><xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> present the major attributes of the four known species of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name>. <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. differs from the others in size and distribution of some of its nematocysts (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), and the nature of the marginal sphincter muscle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3a, b</xref>). Compared to <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name> do not possess basitrichs (<italic>b</italic>) in the tentacles nor basitrichs (<italic>l</italic>) in the mesenterial filaments; <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> lacks basitrichs (<italic>i</italic>) and <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name> lacks basitrichs (<italic>j</italic>) in the mesenterial filaments. The clearest distinguishing feature of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is the possession of an endodermal circumscribed marginal sphincter muscle in which the lamellae are arranged in a palmate fashion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3a, b</xref>). This is clearly different to the other three species, which all possess an endodermal circumscribed marginal sphincter muscle in which the lamellae are arranged in a pinnate fashion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3c–e</xref>).</p>
		            <table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
		            	<label>Table 2.</label>
		                <caption><p>Morphological, biogeographic, and ecological attributes of all four species of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name>.</p></caption>
		                <table>
		                    <tbody>
		                        <tr>
		                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
		                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.</th>
		                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name></th>
		                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stylobates cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name></th>
		                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name></th>
		                        </tr>
		                        <tr>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Marginal sphincter muscle</italic></td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">endodermal, circumscribed, palmate</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">endodermal, circumscribed, pinnate</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">endodermal, circumscribed, pinnate</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">endodermal, circumscribed, pinnate</td>
		                        </tr>
		                        <tr>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tentacle lengths</italic></td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">differ around oral disc</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">differ aroundoral disc</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">differ around oral disc</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">marginal greater than oral</td>
		                        </tr>
		                        <tr>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Maximum oral disc diameter (mm)</italic></td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15-40</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">~20</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15-30</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">to 55</td>
		                        </tr>
		                        <tr>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Locality</italic></td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE Australia</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guam and Hawai’i</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E Africa</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW Australia</td>
		                        </tr>
		                        <tr>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Depth (m)</italic></td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">590–964</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">402–797</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">818</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">320–508</td>
		                        </tr>
		                        <tr>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Substrate</italic></td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mud, rock</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">sand</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">not recorded</td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mud</td>
		                        </tr>
		                        <tr>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hermit crab symbiont</italic></td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus trispinosus</tp:taxon-name></td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus dofleini</tp:taxon-name></td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus trispinosus</tp:taxon-name></td>
		                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus brevipes</tp:taxon-name></td>
		                        </tr>
		                    </tbody>
		                </table>
		            </table-wrap>
		            <p>Gross morphology of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name>sp. n. is similar to that of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name> in position and size of oral disc, and size and arrangement of tentacles. Tentacles of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (maximum length 9 mm) are shorter than those of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name> (maximum length 20 mm). The tentacles of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name>, in contrast to those of other species, are more or less the same length around the oral disc, and the marginal tentacles are longer than the discal ones. The tentacles of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name> are arranged like those of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n.<bold>,</bold> the longest and shortest ones beside each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1e</xref>). Diameter of the oral disc of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. (15-40 mm) is similar to that of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name>,but less than that of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name> (to 55 mm). The position of the oral disc of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. is near the aperture of carcinoecium, like in <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name>, whereas that of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name> is on the side of the ultimate whorl of the carcinoecium, away from the aperture.</p>
		        </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
            <p>The four species of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name> are distributed allopatrically (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>), in what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Cairns (2007)</xref> identified as separate biogeographical regions based on distributions of deep-water scleractinian corals. <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. occurs in the Coral Sea off the Queensland coast of Australia (southwestern Pacific region); <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> is known from Hawai’i and Guam (central Pacific region); <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name> occurs in the Indian Ocean off the northwest coast of Australia (southeastern Indian Ocean region); and <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name> is known from the Indian Ocean off east Africa (southwestern<!--PageBreak--> Indian Ocean region). Congeneric species of squat lobsters of the genus <tp:taxon-name>Paramunida</tp:taxon-name> have a similar allopatric distribution in the central and the southwestern regions of the Pacific (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Baba et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
            <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Uchida and Soyama (2001)</xref> reported <tp:taxon-name>Isadamsia</tp:taxon-name> sp. J from Japan; that locality is consistent with the distribution of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Doumenc (1975)</xref> reported <tp:taxon-name>Isadamsia cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name> in the North Atlantic at 3360–3600 m. We are dubious about this identification (and do not include the record in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>) because all records for the occurrence of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name> are from the Indo-West Pacific and at shallower depths.</p>
            <p>Carcinoecium-forming anemones of genera characterized by a mesogleal sphincter muscle are known from the Atlantic: for example, <tp:taxon-name>Paracalliactis consors</tp:taxon-name> (Verrill, 1882) occurs off the northeast coast of the United States at depths of 2085–2665 m, and <!--PageBreak--><tp:taxon-name>Adamsia obvolva</tp:taxon-name> Daly et al., 2004, occurs in the Gulf of Mexico at depths of 405–719 m. A specimen of an anemone symbiotic with a hermit crab in the Invertebrate Zoology collection of the California Academy of Sciences (catalog number 35119)from 2630–2660 m off the Pacific coast of Mexico is not <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name>, as it is labelled, based on its mesogleal sphincter muscle.</p>
            <p>A specimen in the Invertebrate Zoology collection of WAM (catalog number Z31227) of an anemone that laid down some chitinous material on the gastropod shell to which it is attached is from the same region and depth as <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name> off the coast of Western Australia,andhas an endodermal sphincter, but does not belong to <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name>, either. This anemone differs from <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name> in that its pedal disc does not cover the whole shell; the chitinous material does not form a carcinoecium; the column is more or less cylindrical and is much thicker than that of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name>; and the contracted oral disc creates a collar at the margin.</p>
            <p>Hermit crabs form symbioses with about 100 species of cnidarians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Williams and McDermott 2004</xref>). They occur shallow and deep, in tropical and temperate seas. The hermit crab is thought to be protected by its cnidarian symbiont (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Ross 1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">McLean and Mariscal 1973</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Bach and Herrnkind 1980</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Brooks 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Brooks and Gwaltney 1993</xref>); possible benefits to the cnidarian include transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Balss 1924</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Ross 1974</xref>), a firm substrate for attachment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Brooks and Mariscal 1986</xref>), and access to food collected by the hermit crab (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Ross 1984</xref>).</p>
            <p>Many carcineocium-forming species occur in the deep sea, where calcium carbonate (the mineral of mollusc shells) is highly soluble (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Correns 1955</xref>), resulting in a limited supply of shells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Balss 1924</xref>) and rarity of large shells. A hermit crab living in a chitinous carcinoecium need not change shells as it grows, nor will the carcinoecium dissolve (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Dunn et al. 1981</xref>). In symbioses not involving a carcinoecium, more than one anemone may be attached to a gastropod shell inhabited by a hermit crab, whereas in the <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name>/<tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus</tp:taxon-name> system, one anemone is associated with one hermit crab. In the most thorough account of this association, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Dunn et al.(1981)</xref> considered it to be<!--PageBreak--> obligate for the anemone (which receives food, transport, and substrate) and facultative for the hermit crab.</p>
            <p>Each species of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name> is associated with hermit crabs of one species, all belonging to <tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus</tp:taxon-name>. <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates aeneus</tp:taxon-name> occurs with <tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus dofleini</tp:taxon-name> (Balss, 1912), <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates cancrisocia</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. both occur with <tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus trispinosus</tp:taxon-name> (Balss, 1911) and the hermit crab associated with the newly recorded specimens from the Southern Surveyor cruise of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates loisetteae</tp:taxon-name> occur with <tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus brevipes</tp:taxon-name> (de Saint Laurent, 1972) (A McCallum, Museum Victoria, pers. comm.); hermit crabs of this species are “frequently associated with actinian-secreted carcinoecium similar to that of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name>” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">McLaughlin et al. 2007, p. 299</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title>
            <p>We describe <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n., a new species of deep-sea anemone associated with the hermit crab <tp:taxon-name>Sympagurus trispinosus</tp:taxon-name> (Balss, 1911), from specimens collected in the Coral Sea off the Queensland coast of Australia. <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates birtlesi</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. differs from the other three known species of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name> in some aspects of its nematocysts, and in having a palmate marginal sphincter muscle (in the others it is pinnate). The four species of <tp:taxon-name>Stylobates</tp:taxon-name> are allopatrically distributed in the deep Indo-West Pacific Ocean, a pattern similar to those of deep-sea scleractinian corals and squat lobsters.</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>We thank Alastair Birtles and the late Peter Arnold for collecting specimens, Paul Muir and Susan Curnock for assistance in the preparation of this manuscript, and James Cook University Histology Laboratory for use of the facilities. We thank Jane Fromont <!--PageBreak-->and Mark Salotti from WAM and Steve Coles and Holly Bolick from the Bishop Museum, Hawai’i for specimen loans. This research was made possible with funding from ABRS to CCW and DGF (grant 284–83).</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name><surname>Anonymous</surname></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> ORV Franklin Cruise 3/86 Cidaris I (05 May-18 May 1986)</article-title>. <source>Report from the Benthic Research Unit, Department of Marine Biology</source>, <publisher-name>James Cook University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Townsville</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ates</surname><given-names>RML</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>)<article-title> A preliminary review of zoanthid-hermit crab symbioses (Cnidaria; Zoantharia/Crustacea, Paguridea).</article-title> <source>Zoologische Verhandelingen (Leiden)</source> <volume>345</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macpherson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poore</surname><given-names>GCB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahyong</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bermudez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabezas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nizinski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schnabel</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Catalogue of squat lobsters of the world (Crustacea: Decapoda: Anomura—families Chirostylidae, Galatheidae and Kiwaidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>1905</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrnkind</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> Effects of predation pressure on the mutualistic interaction between the hermit crab, Pagurus pollicari Say, 1817, and the sea anemone, Calliactis tricolor (LeSueur, 1817).</article-title> <source>Crustaceana</source> <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Balss</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1911</year>)<article-title> Neue Paguriden aus den Ausbeuten der deutschen Tiefsee-Expedition “Valdivia” und der japanischen Expedition Prof. Dofleins</article-title>. <source>Zoologischer Anzeiger</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Balss</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>)<source> Paguriden. Wissenschaftliche Ergebnisse der deutschen Tiefsee-Expedition auf dem Dampfer “Valdivia” 1898–1899</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>124</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Balss</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1924</year>)<article-title> Über Anpassungen und Symbiose der Paguriden: eine zusammenfassende Übersicht</article-title>. <source>Zeitschrift für Morphologie und Okologie der Tiere</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>752</fpage>–<lpage>792</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>)<article-title> The influence of the location and abundance of the sea anemone Calliactis tricolor (Le Sueur) in protecting hermit crabs from octopus predators.</article-title> <source>Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology</source> <volume>116</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>)<article-title> Hermit crabs alter sea anemone placement patterns for shell balance and reduced predation.</article-title> <source>Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology</source> <volume>132</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>-<lpage>121</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gwaltney</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<article-title> Protection of symbiotic cnidarians by their hermit-crab hosts: evidence for mutualism.</article-title> <source>Symbiosis</source> <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariscal</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> Population variation and behavioral changes in two pagurids in association with the sea anemone Calliactis tricolor (Lesueur).</article-title> <source>Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology</source> <volume>103</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>-<lpage>289</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Deep-water corals: an overview with special reference to diversity and distribution of deep-water scleractinian corals.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of Marine Science</source> <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>-<lpage>322</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlgren</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1928a</year>)<article-title> Actiniaria der Deutschen Tiefsee-Expedition.</article-title> <source>Wissenschaftliche Ergebnisse der Deutschen Tiefsee-Expedition auf dem Dampfer “Valdivia” 1898–1899</source> <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>-<lpage>266</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlgren</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1928b</year>)<article-title> Zur symbiose swischen Actinien und Paguriden.</article-title> <source>Zeitschrift für Morphologie und Ökologie der Tiere</source> <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlgren</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1949</year>)<article-title> A survey of the Ptychodactiaria, Corallimorpharia and Actiniaria.</article-title> <source>Kungliga Svenska Vetenskapsakademiens Handlingar, series 4,</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>121</lpage>.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Correns</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1955</year>)<article-title> Pelagic sediments of the North Atlantic Ocean.</article-title> <source>Society for Economic Paleontologists and Mineralogists Special Publication</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>395</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dall</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1903</year>)<article-title> A new genus of Trochidae.</article-title> <source>Nautilus</source> <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dall</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1919</year>)<article-title> Stylobates, a warning.</article-title> <source>Nautilus</source> <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ardelean</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>H-R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fautin</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> A new species, Adamsia obvolva (Cnidaria: Anthozoa: Actiniaria), from the Gulf of Mexico, and a discussion of the taxonomy of carcinoecium-forming sea anemones.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of Marine Science</source> <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>-<lpage>399</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Doumenc</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>)<article-title> Actinies bathyales et abyssales de l’océan Atlantique nord. Familles des Hormathiidae (genres Paracalliactis et Phelliactis) et des Actinostolidae (genres Actinoscyphia et Sicyonis).</article-title> <source>Bulletin du Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle</source> <volume>197</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>-<lpage>206</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devaney</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>, for 1980) <article-title>Stylobates: a shell-forming sea anemone (Coelenterata, Anthozoa, Actiniidae)</article-title>. <source>Pacific Science</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liberman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title> Chitin in anemone shells.</article-title> <source>Science</source> <volume>221</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fautin</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>)<article-title> Stylobates loisetteae, a new species of shell-forming sea anemone (Coelenterata: Actiniidae) from Western Australia.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences</source> <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gusmão</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Evolution of sea anemones (Cnidaria: Actiniaria: Hormathiidae) symbiotic with hermit crabs.</article-title> <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source> <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>868</fpage>-<lpage>877</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature</surname></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> International code of zoological nomenclature. Fourth Edition. London: The International Trust for Zoological Nomenclature</source>, <lpage>306</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahayu</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Komai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>T-Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> A catalog of the hermit crabs (Paguroidea) of Taiwan</source>. <publisher-name>National Taiwan Ocean University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Keelung</publisher-loc>, <lpage>376</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariscal</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>)<article-title> Protection of a hermit crab by its symbiotic sea anemone Calliactis tricolor.</article-title> <source>Experientia</source> <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>-<lpage>130</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Menzies</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1959</year>)<article-title> Picro-Gomori method.</article-title> <source>Journal of Stain Technology</source> <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>294</fpage>-<lpage>295</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Millard</surname><given-names>NAH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>)<article-title> Monograph of the Hydroida of southern Africa.</article-title> <source>Annals of the South African Museum</source> <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>513</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Muirhead</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thurston</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>)<article-title> Reproductive biology and growth of the genus Epizoanthus (Zoanthidea) from the north-east Atlantic.</article-title> <source>Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom</source> <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>-<lpage>143</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafinesque</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1815</year>)<source> Analyse de la Nature ou Tableau de l’Univers et des Corps Organisés</source>. <publisher-name>CS Rafinesque</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Palerme</publisher-loc>, <lpage>224</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>)<article-title> Protection of hermit crabs (Dardanus spp.) from octopus by commensal sea anemones (<italic>Calliactis</italic> spp.).</article-title> <source>Nature</source> <volume>230</volume>:<fpage>401</fpage>-<lpage>402</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>)<article-title> Behavior patterns in associations and interactions with other animals</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Muscatine</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenhoff</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Coelenterate Biology: Reviews and New Perspectives</source>. <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>)<article-title> The symbiosis between the cloak anemone Adamsia carciniopados (Otto) (Anthozoa-Actiniaria) and Pagurus prideauxi Leach (Decapoda-Anomura).</article-title> <source>Bolletino di Zoologia</source> <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>413</fpage>-<lpage>421</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Saint Laurent</surname><given-names>M de</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>)<article-title> Sur la famille des Parapaguridae Smith, 1882. Description de Typhlopagurus foresti gen. nov., et de quinze espèces ou sous- espèces nouvelles de <italic>Parapagurus</italic> Smith (Crustacea, Decapoda).</article-title> <source>Bijdragen tot de Dierkunde</source> <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>-<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soyama</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>)<source> Sea anemones in Japanese waters</source>. <publisher-name>TBS</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Japan</publisher-loc>, <lpage>157</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B37"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeij</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>)<source> A Natural History of Shells</source>. <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey</publisher-loc>, <lpage>207</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B38"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Verrill</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1882</year>)<article-title> Notice of the remarkable marine fauna occupying the outer banks off the southern coast of New England, No. 4.</article-title> <source>American Journal of Science and Arts</source> <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>-<lpage>225</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B39"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>)<article-title> Hermit crab biocoenoses: a worldwide review of the diversity and natural history of hermit crab associates.</article-title> <source>Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology</source> <volume>305</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>128</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>