<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title xml:lang="en">ZooKeys</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.192.2364</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Description and DNA barcoding of 
                    <italic>Tipula</italic> (
                    <italic>Pterelachisus</italic>)
                    <italic>recondita</italic> sp. n. from the Palaearctic region (Diptera, Tipulidae)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Pilipenko</surname>
                        <given-names>Valentin E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:7D4B4321-A9F7-47C4-9133-46C65781B4FE</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Salmela</surname>
                        <given-names>Jukka</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:D5635C89-AB14-438A-82C8-94E8683A903A</uri>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Vesterinen</surname>
                        <given-names>Eero J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:595D74DB-122A-44BD-B193-0A28DDBD934C</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="A1">
                <label>1</label>Department of Entomology, Faculty of Biology, Moscow State University, 119899 Moscow, Russia
            </aff>
            <aff id="A2">
                <label>2</label>Zoological Museum, Department of Biology, FI-20014 University of Turku, Finland
            </aff>
            <aff id="A3">
                <label>3</label>Section of Ecology, Department of Biology, FI-20014 University of Turku, Finland
            </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Jukka Salmela (<email xlink:type="simple">jueesal@utu.fi</email>)</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: V. Blagoderov</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>8</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2012</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>192</issue>
            <fpage>51</fpage>
            <lpage>65</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>5</day>
                    <month>11</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>4</day>
                    <month>5</month>
                    <year>2012</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Valentin E. Pilipenko, Jukka Salmela, Eero J. Vesterinen</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0 (CC-BY), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:651AB2AE-DC5E-4CE5-B748-60410402E5B2</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pilipenko &amp; Salmela, <bold>sp. n.</bold> is described. The new species is collected from two localities: Finland, Kittilä (North boreal ecoregion) and Russia, Primorski kray (Zone of temperate broadleaf and mixed forests). Although variation in the structure of male hypopygium between the Finnish and Russian populations is observed, DNA barcode sequences differ only by three nucleotides (0.2 % K2P distance), supporting presence of one widespread species. K2P minimum distances between the new species and 17 other species of the subgenus range from 5.3 to 15.8 % (mean 8.8 %). The new species is forest-dwelling, known from an old-growth herb-rich forest (Finland) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Quercus mongolica</tp:taxon-name></italic> forest (Russia). The new species is perhaps closest to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) imitator</tp:taxon-name></italic> Alexander and in lesser extent to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) pauli</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mannheims; the inner gonostylus of both species are illustrated.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd>Crane flies</kwd>
                <kwd>Tipulinae</kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>Finland</kwd>
                <kwd>Russia</kwd>
                <kwd>COI</kwd>
                <!--PageBreak-->
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Tipulidae (<tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Nematocera</tp:taxon-name>), or long-palped crane flies, are medium to large sized true flies. Globally, 4269 tipulid species and subspecies are known, of these 1322 occupying the Palaearctic region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Oosterbroek 2011</xref>). In general, northwest European tipulid fauna is rather well known (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Salmela 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">2011</xref>). The majority of the species have large European or Palaearctic ranges, only a few species are known from Fennoscandia or Russian Karelia alone. On the other hand, certain species have disjunct occurrences in northern Fennoscandia and the East Palaearctic region (viz. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula kaisilai</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mannheims, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula subexcisa</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lundström, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula tchukchi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Alexander).</p>
            <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) Rondani is a northern hemisphere subgenus, totaling over 200 species and subspecies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Oosterbroek 2011</xref>). Despite taxonomic monographs covering Russia (former USSR, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Savchenko 1964</xref>) and Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Theowald 1980</xref>), the Palaearctic fauna of the subgenus includes several elusive species, known from the type locality or female specimens only. Finnish <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) species were reviewed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Salmela (2009)</xref> and those of the Central European territory of Russia were listed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Pilipenko (2009)</xref>. The subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name></italic> is closely allied to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lunatipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> Edwards and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Savtshenkia</tp:taxon-name></italic> Alexander, but is diagnosable due to the bare squama, grayish coloration, patterned wings and structure of male hypopygium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Theowald 1980</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Savchenko (1964)</xref>, dealing with the fauna of former USSR, recognized 11 species groups and two mixed groups within <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Geotipula</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Oreomyza</tp:taxon-name></italic>). These subgenera were synonymized to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name></italic> by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Alexander (1965)</xref> and later <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Theowald (1980)</xref> named 18 species groups from the West Palaearctic region. These species groups are mainly based on differences in the structure of male hypopygium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Theowald 1980</xref>), but no cladistic analysis or phylogeny of the species groups was provided by Theowald or authors after him.</p>
            <p>DNA barcoding is a molecular-based method used in the identification and delimitation of species, having usually considerable congruence with morphology-based identifications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Ward et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Hausmann et al. 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Park et al. 2011</xref>). Furthermore, barcoding has revealed cryptic diversity within a morphospecies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Smith et al. 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Huemer and Hebert 2011</xref>) or indicated a presence of one species despite morphological variation within studied specimens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Memon et al. 2006</xref>). DNA barcoding has its disadvantages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Meier 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Skevington et al. 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Taylor and Harris 2012</xref>), but it may be used as an additional, and apparently very powerful, method in taxonomy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Schlick-Steiner et al. 2010</xref>). Despite the wide use of DNA barcodes in the current taxonomy and biodiversity studies, the method has been only rarely used in taxonomic studies of crane flies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Ujvárosi et al. 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Ujvárosi and Bálint 2012</xref>).</p>
            <p>In the present article we provide a description of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pilipenko &amp; Salmelasp. n. collected from Europe (Finland) and Asia (Russian Far East). Both sexes of the new species are richly illustrated. In addition, mtDNA sequences (COI) were used to assess (i) the conspecific status of disjunct Finnish and Russian populations and (ii) genetic divergence between the new species and 17 consubgeneric species.<!--PageBreak--></p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Material and methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Total DNA of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pilipenko &amp; Salmela sp. n. specimens was extracted using a modified non-destructive salt extraction method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Aljanabi and Martinez 1997</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Gilbert et al. 2007</xref>). Whole holotype (JES-20110034) and one paratype (JES-20110035) adult specimens and one leg from a paratype (JES-20110036) were placed on 250 μl 96-plate wells. Ethanol-stored samples were briefly dried at 60 °C. First 118 μl of sterile salt homogenizing buffer (0.4 M NaCl, 10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 2 Mm EDTA pH 8.0 and 2% SDS) containing 8 μl of 20 mg/ml proteinase K (400 μg/ml final concentration) was added into each well. The samples were incubated overnight in the buffer at 55–65 °C. After the incubation, the intact samples were removed from the buffer and placed into 99.5% ethanol to stop further digestion. Type specimens JES-20110034 and JES-20110035 were finally preserved in 70 % ethanol. Then 80 μl of 6 M NaCl (NaCl saturated H<sub>2</sub>O, pH 8) was added to each well. Samples were vortexed for 1 min at maximum speed, and centrifuged for 20 minutes at 4000 rpm. Thereafter 100 μl of supernatant was transferred to wells on a new plate. An equal volume (100 μl) of isopropanol was added to each sample and the plate was briefly vortexed. Then the plate was placed into freezer (-20 °C) for 1 hour. After freezing, the samples were centrifuged for 20 minutes at 4000 rpm. The supernatant was discarded and the pellet was washed by adding 150 μl of ice-cold 70% ethanol and centrifuging for 20 min at 4000 rpm. The ethanol was then carefully pipetted out and the pellet was dried for overnight at room temperature. The next day, DNA pellet was dissolved in 50 μl of previously warmed ultrapure water.</p>
            <p>The DNA barcode region (<italic>cythocrome oxidase subunit I</italic>) was amplified and sequenced from all specimens using universal primers LCO1490: 5’-GGGTCAACAAATCATAAAGATATTGG-3’ and HCO2198: 5’-TAAACTTCAGGGTGACCAAAAAATCA-3’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Folmer et al. 1994</xref>). All PCR reactions were performed in a 20 μl volume containing 1 μl of DNA extract, 12.5 µl ddH<sub>2</sub>O, 2.0 µl 10x buffer, 2.0 µl MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.0 µl primer1 (LCO), 1.0 µl Primer 2 (HCO), 0.4 µl dNTPs, and 0.1 µl AmpliTaq Gold polymerase. The cycling profile was 95°C for 5 min, 40 cycles of 94 °C for 30 sec, 50 °C for 30 sec, 72°C for 1 min 30 sec and a final extension period of 72 °C for 10 min. Sterile water samples were used as controls in each PCR batch. All of the controls were negative. Successful PCR products were purified and sequenced by Macrogen  Incorporated (South Korea).</p>
            <p>For other species (totaling 17 species and 26 specimens, Table 1) DNA barcodes were obtained at the Canadian Centre for DNA Barcoding. Legs or 2–3 abdominal segments of the specimens were placed in 96% ethanol in a 96-well lysis microplate and dispatched to the Biodiversity Institute of Ontario where DNA was extracted and sequenced using standard protocols and primers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">deWaard et al. 2008</xref>). Resultant sequence data were placed into a project (HOLPT) on BOLD (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.boldsystems.org" xlink:type="simple">http://www.boldsystems.org</ext-link>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Ratnasingham and Hebert 2007</xref>). These sequence records are now publically available on both BOLD and on GenBank.</p>
            <table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
								<label>Table 1.</label>
                <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) specimens used in DNA barcoding (COI). Species and associated BOLD Sample ID are according to HOLPT project, available in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.boldsystems.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.boldsystems.org/</ext-link>. Co-ordinates are given in WGS84 decimal format.</p></caption>
                <table>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sample ID, species</bold></th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Year</bold></th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Country</bold></th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Locality</bold></th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>N</bold></th>
                            <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>E</bold></th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110456|Tipula_cinereocincta</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2005</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heinävesi</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.419</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.596</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20120024|Tipula_cinereocincta</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Savonranta</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.251</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.877</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20120065|Tipula_angulata</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2006</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ontario</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.483</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-76.081</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20120064|Tipula_entomophthorae</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2003</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manitoba</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.9</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-101.43</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20120004|Tipula_jutlandica</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parikkala</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.565</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.559</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110501|Tipula_laetibasis</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tuupovaara</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.442</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.606</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110497|Tipula_luridorostris</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2006</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taivalkoski</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.785</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.321</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20120011|Tipula_mats._pseudohortensis</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inkoo</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.018</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.822</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110475|Tipula_mats._pseudohortensis</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Siuntio</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.213</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.135</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110092|Tipula_mutila</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enontekiö</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.639</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.552</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110204|Tipula_mutila</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kiuruvesi</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.52</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.69</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20120095|Tipula_mutila</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kittilä</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.33</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.64</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20120014|Tipula_octomaculata</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lieksa</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.217</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.218</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20120031|Tipula_octomaculata</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2006</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taivalkoski</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.693</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.32</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110494|Tipula_pauli</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primorski kray</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.94</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137.72</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110495|Tipula_pauli</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1995</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moscow region</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.02</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.11</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110502|Tipula_pseudovariipennis</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2006</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latvia</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tukums</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.998</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.003</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110035|Tipula_recondita_sp._n</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kittilä</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.634</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.416</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110034|Tipula_recondita_sp._n</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kittilä</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.634</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.416</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110036|Tipula_recondita_sp._n</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2006</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russia</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primorski kray</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.125</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20120038|Tipula_stenostyla</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kittilä</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.634</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.416</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110408|Tipula_submarmorata</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jyväskylä</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.236</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.679</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20120041|Tipula_truncorum</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enontekiö</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.183</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.521</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110345|Tipula_varipennis</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ranua</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.017</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.852</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20120032|Tipula_varipennis</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2005</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jyväskylä</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.213</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.793</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110401|Tipula_varipennis</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jyväskylä</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.236</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.679</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110222|Tipula_wahlgreni</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kiuruvesi</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.52</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.69</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20110450|Tipula_winthemi</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lammi</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.091</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.002</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JES-20120026|Tipula_winthemi</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Finland</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Virolahti</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.465</td>
                            <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.426</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <p>In order to assess the COI divergence between the new species and 17 Holarctic <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) species, we calculated Kimura two-parameter (K2P) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kimura 1980</xref>) distances between all sequenced specimens. Based on K2P distances we also produced Neighbor-Joining (NJ) tree to visualize similarity of the <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name></italic> species. We also inferred relatedness of the species with character based Maximum Likelihood (ML) method (GTR + gamma as evolutionary model, 1000 Bootstrapping replicates). However, because the NJ and ML trees were practically identical, only ML tree is presented (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). K2P distances, NJ and ML were produced by using MEGA5 program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Tamura et al. 2011</xref>). Because one gene is far too little for reasonable phylogenetic analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Gatesy et al. 2007</xref>), the ML tree presented here do not reliably illustrate evolutionary relationships among the sequenced taxa.</p>
            <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <label>Figure 1.</label>
                <caption><p>Maximum Likelihood tree based on COI sequences (mtDNA) of 17 <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) species. Numerical values denote to Bootstrap values after 1000 replications. In the tree Bootstrap value 26 refers to the clade including <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula jutlandica</tp:taxon-name></italic> and value 11 refers to the clade including <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n., <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula jutlandica</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula stenostyla</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula matsumuriana psedohortensis</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Scale bar: nucleotide substitutions per site.</p></caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-192-051-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
            </fig>
            <p>The morphological terminology used here mainly follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Alexander and Byers (1981)</xref>. Terminology of some special parts of male genitalia was taken from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Frommer (1963)</xref>. If not otherwise stated, measurements are given in μm. The following acr<!--PageBreak-->onyms for museums and collections are used in the text: ZMKU – Zoological Museum of National Museum of Natural History, National Academy of Science of Ukraine, Kiev, Ukraine; NCBN – Netherlands Centre for Biodiversity Naturalis, Leiden, the <!--PageBreak-->Netherlands; ZMUM – Zoological Museum, Moscow State University, Moscow, Russia; ZMUT – Zoological Museum, University of Turku, Turku, Finland; ZISP – Zoological Institute Russian Academy of Sciences, St. Petersburg, Russia; VPM – Private collection of Valentin Pilipenko, Moscow, Russia.</p>
            <p>Specimens were studied with a Zoom Stereo Microscope. Photographs were taken  with a Canon PowerShot A640 camera and processed using Combine ZP software.  All drawings were prepared from photographs.</p>
            <p>[Comparative morphological material examined. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) imitator</tp:taxon-name></italic> Alexander: Russia, Shikotan Island, Kray Sveta cape, 25.VII.1965, V. Ermolenko, 1 male (ZMKU); Russia, Iturup Island (Kuril Is), Kurilsk env., 5.VII.1963; Krilov &amp; Krivolutskaya, 1 male (ZISP). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) pauli</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mannheims: Russia, Moscow region, Chashnikovo, 29.V.1995, V. Pilipenko, 1 male (VPM).]</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Taxonomy">
            <title>Taxonomy</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Tipula</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        (<tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="subgenus">Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name-part>)
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">recondita</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:CFBAD0A0-AC21-4067-88E4-C15BCA35CC56</object-id>
								<object-id xlink:type="simple">http://species-id.net/wiki/Tipula_recondita</object-id>
								</tp:taxon-name>
								<tp:taxon-authority>Pilipenko &amp; Salmela</tp:taxon-authority>
								<tp:taxon-status xlink:type="simple">sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Material examined">
                    <title>Material examined.</title>
                    <p>Holotype: Male, in alcohol (NCBN). “Finland, Lkoc: Kittilä, Iso Mustavaara, old-growth herb-rich forest, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">67.6340°N, 25.4160°E</named-content>, 30.V.–1.VII. 2009, J. Salmela leg.” (white label, printed) “<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> sp. n./ Pilipenko &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Salmela 2011</xref>/ HOLOTYPE” (white label, printed) “BOLD sample ID JES-20110034” (white label, printed). Both wings are detached. Only one leg is present, other legs are missing. Tip of abdomen is detached and, including separate sperm pump, preserved in a microvial. This microvial is in the same tube as are wings and rest of the specimen. DNA barcode (524 bp) of holotype (coded JES-20110034|FINTI034-11|<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic>):</p>
                    <p>ATGCTTTTATTATAATTTTTTTTATAGTTATACCTATTATAATTGGAGGATTTGGAAATTGATTAGTACCTTTAATATTAGGTGCCCCTGATATAGCCTTTCCTCGAATAAATAATATAAGTTTTTGAATATTACCTCCTTCACTTACTCTTTTATTAGCTAGTAGTATAGTCGAAAACGGTGCGGGGACTGGATGAACCGTTTATCCCCCACTCTCATCTAGAATTGCCCATACAGGAGCTTCAGTTGATTTAGCCATTTTTTCTCTTCATTTAGCTGGAATTTCTTCAATTTTAGGAGCAGTAAATTTTATTACTACAGTAATTAATATACGATCAAGAGGAATTACTTTAGACCGAATACCTTTATTTGTTTGATCGGTAGTAATTACTGCAGTATTATTACTACTCTCTTTACCTGTATTAGCGGGAGCTATTACTATACTTTTAACTGATCGAAATTTAAATACATCATTTTTTGATCCTGCAGGAGGTGGAGATCCAATTCTTTACCAACATTTATTT</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Paratypes">
                    <title>Paratypes.</title>
                    <p>Finland, Lkoc: Kittilä, Iso Mustavaara Nature reserve, herb-rich old-growth forest, <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">67.6340°N, 25.4160°E</named-content>, 30.V.–1.VII. 2009, Malaise trap, J. Salmela leg.,<!--PageBreak--> 2 males (ZMUT, in alcohol [BOLD sample ID JES-20110035] and a pinned specimen). DNA barcode (524 bp) of paratype (JES-20110035|FINTI035-11) is identical to the holotype sequence. Russia, Far East, Primorski kray, Kedrovaya Pad’, oak forest (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Quercus mongolica</tp:taxon-name></italic>), <named-content content-type="dwc:verbatimCoordinates" xlink:type="simple">43.1301°N, 131.5041°E</named-content>, 7.VII. 2006 V. Pilipenko leg., 3 males and 3 females, deposited in ZSIP (BOLD sample ID JES-20110036), ZMUM, VPM. DNA barcode (524 bp) of paratype male (JES-20110036|FINTI036-11) differs from holotype at three positions (212=C, 473=T, and 515=G). In other words, intraspecific K2P distance between Finnish and Russian specimens was 0.2 %.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis">
                    <title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Rather small yellowish brown <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> species (body length: 11 mm male, 12.3 mm female; wing length 11–12.6 mm male, 12.5–13.5 mm female). Scape, pedicel and base of 1<sup>st</sup> flagellomere yellowish, other flagellomeres brown. Caudal margin of male 9<sup>th</sup> tergite with a median notch, bearing no tooth or other elevated structures. Outer gonostylus narrow, about as long as inner gonostylus, slightly bent sub-basally. Lower beak of inner gonostylus apically rounded, black. Outer basal lobe of inner gonostylus with 3–4 stout black spines.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description">
                    <title>Description.</title>
                    <p>Male. Head gray pruinose, sparsely covered with dark hairs. Base of rostrum gray pruinose, otherwise dark brown, shining. Nasus distinct, tip with light bristles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Palpi brownish. Lengths of palpal segments (n=2): p1 128-147, p2 307-309, p3 317-365, p4 309-333 and p5 1207-1359. Scape, pedicel and base of 1<sup>st</sup> flagellomere yellowish, other flagellomeres brown. Scape cylindrical (length 442–466, width 119–120, n=2). Pedicel globular (length 132–134, width 134–135, n=2). Flagellar segments cylindrical, covered with silvery, erect and thick pubescence. Verticils black, shorter than respective segments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Lengths of flagellomeres (n=2): f1 371–398, f2 312–314, f3 298–316, f4 289–326, f5 297–324, f6 296–325, f7 291, f8 270–289, f9 257–261, f10 227–230 and f11 100. Thorax. General coloration dark brown, with gray pruinosity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). Pronotum with light hairs. Prescutum with four longitudinal brown bands; lateral bands short, median bands distinctly separated. Anepisternum, katepisternum and anepimeron with dense, gray pruinosity. Scutum, scutellum, laterotergite and mediotergite unicolorous, dark brown. Coxae brown, with light hairs. Trochanters yellowish, with light hairs. Proximal part (ca. two thirds) of femora yellowish, turning dark brown toward tips. Tibiae and tarsi dark brown, spur formula 1:2:2. Tarsal claws smooth. Legs covered with dark brown – black bristles. Stem of halter yellowish, knobs infuscated. Wings with marmorate pattern, length (n= 5) 11.9 mm (11–12.6 mm), venation as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>. R<sub>1+2</sub> is variable, reach or not reach Costa. Wing cells c and sc yellowish, other cells brown tinged (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs. 2b, 2c</xref>). Pterostigma distinct. Abdomen yellowish brown, with a narrow dorsal stripe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). Hypopygium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>) dark brown. Caudal margin of 9<sup>th</sup> tergite with a median notch, bearing no tooth or other elevated structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3g–h</xref>). Caudal margin of 9<sup>th</sup> tergite oblique (Finnish specimens) or almost horizontal, truncated (Russian specimens) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3g–h</xref>). Outer gonostylus narrow, about as long as inner gonostylus, slightly bent sub-basally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3b, d</xref>). Lower beak of inner gonostylus apically rounded, black. Beak of inner gonostylus rather narrow and elongated in lateral view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3b, d</xref>), tip roundish and proximal margin oblique, notched in posterior view (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>). Outer basal lobe of inner <!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->gonostylus with 3–4 stout black spines. Aedeagal guide as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3e–f</xref>. Sperm pump hairy between posterior immovable apodemes, apex of aedeagus pointed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3i–j</xref>).</p>
                    <p>Female. Wing length (n=3) 12.8 mm (12.5–13.5 mm), body length (n=3) 12.3 mm (12–13 mm). Generally similar to male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>). Antenna short (2.4 mm), not extending to wing base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>). The wing’s marmorate pattern more intensive than in male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>). Ovipositor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs. 4a, b</xref>) elongate, similar to that of most other tipulines; 8<sup>th</sup> tergite dark brown, 9th tergite narrow dull dark brown, 10<sup>th</sup> tergite shining chestnut brown. 8<sup>th</sup> sternite dull dark brown anteriorly, grading to shining yellow posteriorly. Cerci narrow, yellow, slightly longer than 10<sup>th</sup> tergite. Hypogynial valves yellow, reaching mid-length of cerci, relatively wide, gradually narrowing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref>).</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 2.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pilipenko &amp; Salmela, sp. n. <bold>a</bold> Holotype male, head, lateral view (Finland) <bold>b</bold> paratype male, habitus, lateral view (Russia) <bold>c</bold> paratype male, wing (Russia) <bold>d</bold> paratype female, head, dorso-lateral view (Russia) <bold>e</bold> paratype female, habitus, lateral view (Russia) <bold>f</bold> paratype female, wing (Russia). Scale bars: <bold>a, d</bold> 1 mm; <bold>c, f</bold> 2.5 mm; <bold>b, e</bold> 5 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-192-051-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 3.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pilipenko &amp; Salmela, sp. n., paratype males <bold>a</bold> hypopygium, lateral view (Russia) <bold>b</bold> outer and inner gonostylus, lateral view (Finland) <bold>c</bold> outer and inner gonostylus, posterior view (Finland) <bold>d</bold> outer and inner gonostylus, lateral view (Russia) <bold>e</bold> aedeagal guide, lateral view (Finland) <bold>f</bold> aedeagal guide, lateral view (Russia) <bold>g</bold> 9<sup>th</sup> tergite, dorsal view (Finland) <bold>h</bold> 9<sup>th</sup> tergite, dorsal view (Russia) <bold>i</bold> sperm pump and aedeagus, ventro-lateral view (Finland) <bold>j</bold> sperm pump and aedeagus, ventro-lateral view (Russia). Scale bars: 0.5 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-192-051-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                        <label>Figure 4.</label>
                        <caption><p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pilipenko &amp; Salmela sp. n., paratype female (Russia)  <bold>a–c</bold> <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) pauli</tp:taxon-name></italic> Mannheims <bold>d</bold> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) imitator</tp:taxon-name></italic> Alexander (<bold>e, f, g, h, i</bold>). <bold>a</bold> female terminal abdominal segments and cerci, dorsal view <bold>b</bold> female terminal abdominal segments, cerci and hypovalva, lateral view <bold>c</bold> female hypovalva and 8<sup>th</sup> sternite, dorsal view <bold>d–e</bold> male inner gonostylus, lateral view <bold>f</bold> outer and inner gonostylus, posterior view <bold>g</bold> 9<sup>th</sup> tergite, dorsal view <bold>h</bold> aedeagal guide, lateral view <bold>i</bold> sperm pump and aedeagus, ventro-lateral view. Scale bars: 0.5 mm.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="ZooKeys-192-051-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"></graphic>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology">
                    <title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p>The species epithet is from reconditus (Latin, adjective) meaning hidden, concealed. This word refers to the rarity and apparent low detectability of the new species, so far known only from two sites in the Palaearctic region.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Distribution">
                    <title>Distribution and ecology.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pilipenko &amp; Salmela, sp. n. is known from North Europe (Finland) and Asia, Russian Far East. The Finnish collecting site in Kittilä, Iso Mustavaara, is a state-owned Nature Reserve (Lehtojensuojelualue), included in the Natura2000 network of conservation areas. It is part of the biogeographical province of Lkoc (<italic>Lapponia kemensis pars occidentalis</italic>) and lies in the North boreal vegetation zone. The collecting site is an old-growth mixed forest, dominated by birch (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Betula pubescens</tp:taxon-name></italic>), goat willow (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Salix caprea</tp:taxon-name></italic>) and Norway spruce (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Picea abies</tp:taxon-name></italic>), with scattered aspen (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Populus tremula</tp:taxon-name></italic>) trees. Lower vegetation is characterized by herbs and shrubs such as <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calypso bulbosa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Daphne mezereum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Actaea erythrocarpa</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Ribes spicatum</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Filipendula ulmaria</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Geranium sylvaticum</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Decaying trees, especially goat willow and birch, are abundant in the site. The Russian collecting site is located in the Kedrovaya Pad’ Nature Reserve, within the temperate broadleaf and mixed forest zone, in an oak forest (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Quercus mongolica</tp:taxon-name></italic>) growing on limestone outcrops on the southern slope of a mountain range. Lower vegetation is characterized by <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lespedeza bicolor</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Spodiopogon sibirieus</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Astra ageratoides</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Carex siderosticta</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Artemisia keiskeana</tp:taxon-name></italic>, <italic><tp:taxon-name>Lathyrus davidii</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Calamagrostis brachytricha</tp:taxon-name></italic>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion">
                    <title>Discussion.</title>
                    <p><italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pilipenko &amp; Salmela, sp. n. is rather easily distinguished from other Holarctic <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) species. The new species is distinctive in characters of the male hypopygium, especially that of the 9<sup>th</sup> tergite. There are several <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachsus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) species with a U-shaped median notch or an emargination in the caudal margin of the tergite, but usually having a tooth or other elevated structures at the mid-point (e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) angulata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Loew [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Alexander 1919</xref>, p. 984, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Salmela and Autio 2007</xref>, p. 55], <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) varipennis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Meigen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Savchenko 1964</xref>, p. 56], <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) imitator</tp:taxon-name></italic> Alexander [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Alexander 1953</xref>, Plate 1], <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) resupina</tp:taxon-name></italic> Alexander [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Alexander 1935</xref>, Plate 2]); the new species is peculiar having no such structures in the 9<sup>th</sup> tergite.</p>
                    <p>Morphologically the new species is perhaps the closest to two Palaearctic species, namely <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) imitator</tp:taxon-name></italic> and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) pauli</tp:taxon-name></italic>. The former species has a median notch in 9<sup>th</sup> tergite, but also a distinct tooth at the midpoint (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4g</xref>); the outer basal lobe of inner gonostylus bears one conspicuous black spine, not 3–4 smaller ones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4e</xref>). For other differences, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4f, h, i</xref>. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula pauli</tp:taxon-name></italic> also has a median notch in 9<sup>th</sup> tergi<!--PageBreak--><!--PageBreak-->te and a small but discernible tooth in the midpoint; the lower beak of inner gonostylus is roundish and black, but the outer basal lobe bears no stout, black spines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) imitator</tp:taxon-name></italic> is known from Japan and Kuril Islands and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) pauli</tp:taxon-name></italic> from Europe, Altay and Russian Far East (Oosterbroek 2012, V. Pilipenko pers. obs.).</p>
                    <p>Based on COI divergence, the new species is apparently rather isolated from the members of the subgenus <italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Among the other species vs. the new species, interspecific distances varied from 5.3 % (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula winthemi</tp:taxon-name></italic> Lackschewitz) to 16.1 % (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula laetibasis</tp:taxon-name></italic> Alexander). Mean of the minimum interspecific distances was 8.8 %. According to K2P divergence, the new species is closest to <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula winthemi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (5.3 %), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula jutlandica</tp:taxon-name></italic> Nielsen (5.5 %), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula stenostyla</tp:taxon-name></italic> Savchenko (6.6 %) and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula pauli</tp:taxon-name></italic> (6.8 %); distances between the other species range from 7.4 to 16.1 %. In other words, no very close relatives were present in the pair-wise comparisons of COI sequences. For example, much shorter interspecific K2P distances were found between <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula varipennis</tp:taxon-name></italic>/<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula pseudovariipennis</tp:taxon-name></italic> (1.5 %), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula mutila</tp:taxon-name></italic>/<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula wahlgreni</tp:taxon-name></italic> (2.2 %), <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula stenostyla</tp:taxon-name></italic>/<italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula winthemi</tp:taxon-name></italic> (3.7 %). However, it must be emphasized that <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula imitator</tp:taxon-name></italic> was not included in COI analysis, due to the lack of fresh material. Given to the morphological similarity of the new species and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula imitator</tp:taxon-name></italic>, it is likely that their barcoding distances would be similar to those three comparisons given above.</p>
                    <p>There are some morphological differences (9<sup>th</sup> tergite, inner gonostylus) between Finnish and Russian specimens, perhaps due to the long distance and lack of gene flow between the populations. These differences, however, are here considered to be intraspecific variation. Very small K2P divergence of COI gene (0.2 %) between Finnish and Russian specimens also substantiates the presence of one widespread, but disjunct, species. In rare cases (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Burns et al. 2007</xref>) differences of only one to three nucleotides may be observed between otherwise (for example morphologically and ecologically) distinct species. However, in this case we were able to produce 524 bp of high quality sequence, instead of &lt;400 as in the problematic cases of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Burns et al. (2007)</xref>. Moreover, the known biologies of the Finnish and Russian individuals seem alike. To say more of the COI variation, it would be essential to collect more individuals which is rather difficult, given the rarity of the species.</p>
                    <p>The new species is most probably a very rare tipulid. Despite the rather long tradition of crane fly taxonomy and faunistics in North Europe, this species has hitherto remained unnoticed. One of the authors (JS) has within 12 years identified some 70 000 crane flies from a Finnish Malaise trapping material consisting of 476 sampling sites and ca. 1670 Malaise trapping months. Thus, despite this relatively large sampling effort, only three specimens from a single locality have been caught. The true range of the species is Palaearctic, whether disjunct or not remains to be seen. In Northwestern Europe the species is likely to occur in the north boreal zone (for further information on boreal ecoregions or vegetation zones, see e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Ahti et al. 1968</xref>). <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pilipenko &amp; Salmela, sp. n. may be confined to old-growth forests, and its rarity is perhaps due to the narrow habitat niche. On the other hand, the new species may be hard to collect using traditional methods. Larval associations of this species are unknown, but some <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) species are saproxylic, i.e. dependent on decaying trees. Such species are e.g. <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) pseudoirrorata</tp:taxon-name></italic> Goetghebuer and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) stenostyla</tp:taxon-name></italic> Savchenko (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Salmela 2009</xref>), both of them also encountered in the type locality.</p>
                    <p><!--PageBreak-->To our regret we were not able to examine the holotype male of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula imitator</tp:taxon-name></italic> (D. Furth, pers. comm.). Description of that species was based on a single male specimen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Alexander 1953</xref>). We have however examined other material (two male specimens, see above) that very likely represents <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula imitator</tp:taxon-name></italic>. Despite morphological similarity of <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula (Pterelachisus) recondita</tp:taxon-name></italic> Pilipenko &amp; Salmela, sp. n. and <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula imitator</tp:taxon-name></italic>, we are confident that these are separate taxa, due to the differences in the structure of male hypopygium.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p>Special thanks to Pjotr Oosterbroek (Amsterdam) for his help with the vast <italic><tp:taxon-name>Tipula</tp:taxon-name></italic> (<italic><tp:taxon-name>Pterelachisus</tp:taxon-name></italic>) literature. It would have been much more laborious for us to resolve the status of the new species without Pjotr’s help. Metsähallitus, Lapin luontopalvelut (Finnish Natural Heritage Services) provided a permission to collect insects in Iso Mustavaara Nature Reserve. Comments by John Kramer (Leicester), Fenja Brodo (Ottawa), anonymous referee and Vladimir Blagoderov (London) improved manuscript. Aleksanteri Hihnavaara (Ponku) is thanked for such a cheerful field company. Barcode sequences were obtained at the Canadian Centre for DNA Barcoding based in the Biodiversity Institute of Ontario at the University of Guelph. Their work was supported by funding from the Government of Canada through Genome Canada and the Ontario Genomics Institute in support of the International Barcode of Life Project. Finnish Barcode of Life (FinBOL) is also thanked for a help in the barcoding process. JS was financially supported by Finnish Cultural Foundation, Oskar Öflunds Stiftelse and Societas pro Fauna et Flora Fennica and EJV by Betty Väänäsen Rahasto.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahti</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hämet-Ahti</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jalas</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>)<article-title> Vegetation zones and their sections in northwestern Europe.</article-title> <source>Annales Botanici Fennici</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>-<lpage>211</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1919</year>)<article-title> The crane-flies of New York. Part I. Distribution and taxonomy of the adult flies.</article-title> <source>Memoirs, Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station </source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>767</fpage>-<lpage>993</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1935</year>)<article-title> New or little-known Tipulidae from eastern Asia (Diptera). XXIV.</article-title> <source>Philippine Journal of Science </source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>525</fpage>-<lpage>562</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1953</year>)<article-title> Records and descriptions of Japanese Tipulidae (Diptera). Part I. The crane-flies of Shikoku. I.</article-title> <source>Philippine Journal of Science </source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1965</year>)<article-title> New subgenera and species of crane-flies from California (Diptera: Tipulidae).</article-title> <source>Pacific Insects </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>333</fpage>-<lpage>386</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname> <given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byers</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>)<source> Tipulidae 7. In: McAlpine JF, Peterson BV, Shewell GE, Teskey HJ, Vockeroth JR, Wood DM (Eds) Manual of Nearctic Diptera 1. Monograph No. 27, Biosystematic Research Institute, Ottawa, Ontario, 153–190. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esc-sec.ca/aafcmonographs/manual_of_nearctic_diptera_vol_1.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.esc-sec.ca/aafcmonographs/manual_of_nearctic_diptera_vol_1.pdf</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Aljanabi</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>)<article-title> Universal and rapid salt-extraction of high quality genomic DNA for PCR- based techniques.</article-title> <source>Nucleic Acids Research</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>4692</fpage>-<lpage>4693</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/25.22.4692" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/nar/25.22.4692</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname> <given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> DNA barcodes of closely related (but morphologically and ecologically distinct) species of skipper butterflies (Hesperiidae) can differ by only one to three nucleotides.</article-title> <source>Journal of the Lepidopterists’ Society </source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>138</fpage>-<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Folmer</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeh</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrijenhoek</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>)<article-title> DNA primers for amplification of mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit I from diverse metazoan invertebrates.</article-title> <source>Molecular Marine Biology and Biotechnology </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>294</fpage>-<lpage>299</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Frommer</surname> <given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>)<article-title> Gross morphological studies of the reproductive system in representative North American crane flies (Diptera: Tipulidae).</article-title> <source>Kansas University Science Bulletin  </source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>535</fpage>-<lpage>625</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gatesy</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeSalle</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahlberg</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> How Many Genes Should a Systematist Sample? Conflicting Insights from a Phylogenomic Matrix Characterized by Replicated Incongruence.</article-title> <source>Systematic Biology </source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>363</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10635150701294733" xlink:type="simple">10.1080/10635150701294733</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname> <given-names>MTP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melchior</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Worobey</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<source> DNA Extraction from Dry Museum Beetles without Conferring External Morphological Damage. PLoS ONE 2: e272. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0000272" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0000272</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hausmann</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haszprunar</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> DNA Barcoding the Geometrid Fauna of Bavaria (Lepidoptera): Success, Surprises, and Questions. PLoS ONE 6: e17134. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.137/journal.pone.0017134" xlink:type="simple">10.137/journal.pone.0017134</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Huemer</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Cryptic diversity and phylogeography of high alpine <italic>Sattleria</italic> – a case study combining DNA barcodes and morphology (Lepidoptera: Gelechiidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>2981</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> A simple method for estimating evolutionary rate of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequences.</article-title> <source>Journal of Molecular Evolution  </source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>120</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF01731581" xlink:type="simple">10.1007/BF01731581</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Meier</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<source> DNA Sequences in Taxonomy: Opportunities and Challenges. In Wheeler QD (Ed), The New Taxonomy. Systematics Association Special Volume, CRC Press, 95–128.</source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Memon</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meier</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mannan</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su Feng-Yi</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> On the use of DNA sequences for determining the species limits of a polymorphic new species in the stink bug genus <italic>Halys</italic> (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae) from Pakistan.</article-title> <source>Systematic Entomology </source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>703</fpage>-<lpage>710</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365–3113.2006.00350.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1365–3113.2006.00350.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oosterbroek</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> Catalogue of the Craneflies of the World (Diptera, Tipuloidea: Pediciidae, Limoniidae, Cylindrotomidae, Tipulidae) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nlbif.eti.uva.nl/ccw/index.php" xlink:type="simple">http://nlbif.eti.uva.nl/ccw/index.php</ext-link></source></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>D-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foottit</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maw</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<source> Barcoding Bugs: DNA-Based Identification of the True Bugs (Insecta: Hemiptera: Heteroptera). PLoS ONE 6(4): e18749. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0018749" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pone.0018749</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pilipenko</surname> <given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> A check list of craneflies (Diptera, Tipulidae) of the Central European territory of Russia.</article-title> <source>Zoosymposia </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>-<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnasingham</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> BOLD: The Barcode of Life Data System (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.barcodinglife.org" xlink:type="simple">www.barcodinglife.org</ext-link>).</article-title> <source>Molecular Ecology Notes </source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>-<lpage>364</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1471-8286.2006.01678.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1471-8286.2006.01678.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmela</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> The subgenus Tipula (Pterelachisus) in Finland (Diptera, Tipulidae) – species and biogeographic analysis.</article-title> <source>Zoosymposia </source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>-<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmela</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Cranefly (Diptera, Tipuloidea &amp; Ptychopteridae) fauna of Limhamn limestone quarry (Sweden, Malmo). Diversity and faunistics viewed from a NW European perspective.</article-title> <source>Norwegian Journal of Entomology </source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>135</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmela</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> Annotated list of Finnish crane flies (Diptera: Limoniidae, Tipulidae, Pediciidae &amp; Cylindrotomidae).</article-title> <source>Entomologica Fennica </source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>242</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmela</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Autio</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title> Redescription of <italic>Tipula octomaculata</italic> Savchenko, with notes on related Holarctic species (Diptera, Tipulidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1527</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Savchenko</surname> <given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1964</year>)<source> Crane-flies (Diptera, Tipulidae), Subfam. Tipulinae, Genus Tipula L., 2. Fauna USSR, N.S. 89, Nasekomye Dvukrylye [Diptera], 2(4): 1–503 </source>[in Russian].</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlick-Steiner</surname> <given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiner</surname> <given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifert</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stauffer</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christian</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crozier</surname> <given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Integrative taxonomy: a multisource approach to exploring biodiversity.</article-title> <source>Annual Review of Entomology </source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>-<lpage>438</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev-ento-112408-085432" xlink:type="simple">10.1146/annurev-ento-112408-085432</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Skevington</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kehlmaier</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ståhls</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>)<article-title>DNA Barcoding: Mixed results for big-headed flies (Diptera: Pipunculidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>1423</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname> <given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodley</surname> <given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janzen</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallwachs</surname> <given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> DNA barcodes reveal cryptic hostspecificity within the presumed polyphagous members of a genus of parasitoid flies (Diptera: Tachinidae).</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America </source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>3657</fpage>-<lpage>3662</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0511318103" xlink:type="simple">10.1073/pnas.0511318103</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname> <given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>)<article-title> MEGA5: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis using Maximum Likelihood, Evolutionary Distance, and Maximum Parsimony Methods.</article-title> <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution </source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>2731</fpage>-<lpage>2739</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msr121" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/molbev/msr121</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname> <given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname> <given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<source> Am emergent science on the brink of irrelevance: a review of the past 8 years of DNA barcoding. Molecular Ecology Resources. </source>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1755–0998.2012.03119.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1755–0998.2012.03119.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Theowald</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>)<article-title> 15. Tipulidae.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. (Ed.), <issue-title>Die Fliegen der palaearktischen Region</issue-title>, 3(5)1, Lief. <volume>324</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>-<lpage>538</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B33"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ujvárosi</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bálint</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meszaros</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Popescu</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>)<article-title> Genetic diversity with morphological imprints among Pedicia (Amalopis) occulta (Meigen, 1830) (Diptera, Pediciidae) populations in the Carpathian area: Preliminary results.</article-title> <source>Lauterbornia </source> <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B34"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ujvárosi</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bálint</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>)<article-title> Discovery of the second European Amalopis species: an integrative survey of the widespread <italic>Pedicia (Amalopis) occulta</italic> (Meigen, 1830) (Insecta, Diptera, Pediciidae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa </source> <volume>3189</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B35"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>deWaard</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanova</surname> <given-names>NV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibabaei</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>)<article-title> Assembling DNA Barcodes: Analytical Protocols.</article-title> In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname> <given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Ed</role>). <issue-title>Methods in Molecular Biology: Environmental Genetics; Humana Press Inc.</issue-title> <source>, Totowa, USA</source>: <fpage>275</fpage>-<lpage>293</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B36"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname> <given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zemlak</surname> <given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Innes</surname> <given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Last</surname> <given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname> <given-names>PDN</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>)<article-title> DNA barcoding Australia’s fish species.</article-title> <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B </source> <volume>360</volume>: <fpage>1847</fpage>-<lpage>1857</lpage>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2005.1716" xlink:type="simple">10.1098/rstb.2005.1716</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
    </back>
</article>