<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//TaxonX//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v0 20100105//EN" "tax-treatment-NS0.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ZooKeys</journal-id>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">1313-2989</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">1313-2970</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Pensoft Publishers</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.71.789</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>
               A revision of the genus Antepione Packard with description of the new genus Pionenta Ferris (Lepidoptera, Geometridae, Ennominae)
                </article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Ferris</surname>
                        <given-names>Clifford D.</given-names>
                    </name>
										<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
                    <uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:80047B1E-99C4-4227-B92B-5C430A916BEA</uri>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
                    <aff id="A1"><label>5405 Bill Nye Ave., R.R. 3, Laramie, WY 82070, USA, cdferris@uwyo.edu. Research Associate: McGuire Center for Lepidoptera and Biodiversity, Florida Museum of Natural History, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL; C. P. Gillette Museum of Arthropod Diversity, Colorado State University, Ft. Collins, CO; Florida State Collection of Arthropods, Gainesville, FL</label>
                    </aff>
            <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="corresp">
                    <p>Corresponding author: Clifford D. Ferris (<email xlink:type="simple">cdferris@uwyo.edu</email>).</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="edited-by">
                    <p>Academic editor: Axel Hausmann</p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>14</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2010</year>
            </pub-date>
            <issue>71</issue>
            <fpage>49</fpage>
            <lpage>70</lpage>
            <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>14</day>
                    <month>10</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>8</day>
                    <month>12</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
            </history>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Clifford D. Ferris</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="creative-commons-attribution" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0" xlink:type="simple">
                    <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri content-type="lsid" xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:F37C9B51-6084-4939-A86E-E374848FECA7</self-uri>
            <abstract>
                <label>Abstract</label>
                <p>Based on genitalic studies, the new genus <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta</tp:taxon-name> is established for two taxa formerly placed under <tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name>. The taxa <italic>hewesata</italic> and <italic>ochreata</italic> (and previously associated synonyms) are now synonomized as <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta ochreata</tp:taxon-name>. Three species of <tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name> are now recognized: <tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Antepione tiselaaria</tp:taxon-name> with the taxa <italic>comstocki</italic>, <italic>constans</italic>, and <italic>indiscretata</italic> synonomized under <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name>. No new species are described. Adults and genitalia are illustrated, including type specimens.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <label>Keywords</label>
                <kwd><italic>Antepione</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>Arizona</kwd>
                <kwd>Colorado</kwd>
                <kwd>Costa Rica</kwd>
                <kwd>Ennominae</kwd>
                <kwd>Geometridae</kwd>
                <kwd>Guatemala</kwd>
                <kwd>Lepidoptera</kwd>
                <kwd>Mexico</kwd>
                <kwd>New Mexico</kwd>
                <kwd>nomenclature</kwd>
                <kwd>North America</kwd>
                <kwd><italic>Pionenta</italic></kwd>
                <kwd>taxonomy</kwd>
                <kwd>Texas</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
            <p>A genitalic study of the eight species recognized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Parsons et al. (1999)</xref> associated with genus <tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name> uncovered two distinct and quite different forms in both the male and female genitalia. This situation was alluded to by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Pitkin (2002: 283)</xref>, who excluded <tp:taxon-name>Antepione ochreata</tp:taxon-name> (Hulst) in her treatment of the genus. In <tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name>, as restricted herein, the <!--PageBreak-->male genitalia lack a furca, and the female genitalia lack a signum. I recognize three species of <tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name>. <tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name> (Guenée) is widely distributed in eastern North America with additional records for Mexico, Guatemala and Costa Rica. <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name> occurs in the southwestern United States from Texas to Arizona. <tp:taxon-name>Antepione tiselaaria</tp:taxon-name> (Dyar) ranges from central Mexico to Costa Rica. In the genus <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta</tp:taxon-name>, as subsequently described, I recognize only one species, <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta ochreata</tp:taxon-name>. The male genitalia have a stubby robust furca, and the female genitalia a single large stellate signum. The species assigned to both genera are sexually dimorphic and extremely polyphenic, which, lacking genitalic examination, historically apparently led to the descriptions of multiple taxa. My field collections of multiple specimens in ultraviolet light traps at single sites and subsequent genitalic dissections allowed me to assess variation. The range of <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta</tp:taxon-name> is southwestern New Mexico and southeastern Arizona. It most likely occurs in contiguous northern Mexico, but I have found no records.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title>
            <sec sec-type="Repository abbreviations"><title>Repository abbreviations</title>
                <p><abbrev>AMNH<def><p> American Museum of Natural History, New York, NY, USA.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>ANSP<def><p> Academy of Natural Sciences, Philadelphia, PA, USA.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>BMNH<def><p> The Natural History Museum (formerly British Museum [Natural History]), London, UK.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>CDF<def><p> Personal collection of Clifford D. Ferris, Laramie, WY, USA.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>CMNH<def><p> Carnegie Museum of Natural History, Pittsburgh, PA, USA.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>CNC<def><p> Canadian National Collection of Insects, Arachnids, and Nematodes, Ottawa, Ontario, Canada.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>EME<def><p> Essig Museum of Entomology, University of California, Berkeley, CA, USA.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>FMNH<def><p> Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago, IL, USA.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>MCZ<def><p> Museum of Comparative Zoology, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, USA.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>MNHN<def><p> Museum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris, France.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>SEM<def><p> Snow Entomological Museum Collection, University of Kansas, Lawrence, KS, USA.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>USNM<def><p> 	National Museum of Natural History [formerly United States National Museum], Washington, District of Columbia, USA.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Methods and general terminology"><title>Methods and general terminology.</title>
                <p> Terms for genital structures and wing markings follow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Ferris and Schmidt (2010)</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="Description abbreviations"><title>Description abbreviations</title>
                
                <p><abbrev>AML<def><p> Antemedial line.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>DFW<def><p> Dorsal forewing.<!--PageBreak--></p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>DHW<def><p> Dorsal hindwing.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>FWL<def><p> Forewing length, measured along costa from base to apex.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>MB<def><p> medial band = area between DFW AML and PML.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>PML<def><p> Postmedial line.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
                <p><abbrev>TL<def><p> Type locality.</p></def> </abbrev></p>
            </sec>
		        <sec sec-type="Key to genera"><title>Key to genera</title>
		            <p>(based on DFW pattern and genitalia)</p>
		            <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor">
		                <table>
		                    <tbody>
		                        <tr><td>1</td><td>DFW triangular costal dark patch present; male genitalia lack furca; female genitalia lack colliculum and signum</td><td><tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name></td></tr>
														<tr><td>–</td><td>DFW triangular costal dark patch absent; male genitalia with robust stubby furca; female genitalia with colliculum and signum</td><td><tp:taxon-name>Pionenta ochreata</tp:taxon-name></td></tr>
		                    </tbody>
		                </table>
		            </table-wrap>
		        </sec>
		        <sec sec-type="Key to Antepione species"><title>Key to Antepione species</title>
		            <p>(based on genitalia)</p>
		        <table-wrap content-type="key" position="anchor">
		                <table>
		                    <tbody>
													<tr><td>1</td><td>Male genitalia: apical region of valva lacks spines. Female genitalia: corpus bursa oblong and initially swollen with membranous anterior sac</td><td><tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name></td></tr>
													<tr><td>–</td><td>Not as above</td><td><bold>2</bold></td></tr>
													<tr><td>2</td><td>Male genitalia: valva rounded at apex with 3 long robust spines and additional fine setae. Female genitalia: corpus bursae long and cylindrical with membranous anterior sac</td><td><tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name></td></tr>
													<tr><td>–</td><td>Not as above</td><td><bold>3</bold></td></tr>
													<tr><td>3</td><td>Male genitalia: valva rounded at apex with multiple short slender translucent spines over most of surface excepting toward base. Female genitalia unknown to author</td><td><tp:taxon-name>Antepione tiselaaria</tp:taxon-name></td></tr>
		                    </tbody>
		                </table>
		        </table-wrap>
		        </sec>        
            <sec sec-type=" "><title> </title>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Antepione</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Packard, 1876: 459, 483</tp:taxon-authority>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species:</title>
                        <p> <tp:taxon-name>Epione depontanata</tp:taxon-name> Grote, 1864. Location of type unknown; originally placed in ANSP. Described from Maryland, USA.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:taxon-treatment>
                    <tp:nomenclature>
                        <tp:taxon-name>
                            <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Mimogonodes</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-authority>Warren, 1895</tp:taxon-authority>
                    </tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species:</title>
                        <p> <tp:taxon-name>Mimogonodes constricta</tp:taxon-name> Warren, 1895 [BMNH].</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                        <p> <bold>Adults.</bold> Medium sized (FWL 13–21 mm) basically ochreous-colored moths with variable markings on DFW. DFW outer margin angulate at vein M3. Separation from similar genera is by the combination of characters: filiform antennae; male genitalia with stout tapered decurved uncus, valvae with even outer margins lacking projections, absence of furca; female genitalia without colliculum and signum.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                        <p> <bold>Adults.</bold> Sexually dimorphic and sexes polyphenic; FWL 13–21 mm. Antenna simple, more slender in females. <italic>Head</italic> – Dark ochreous speckled with darker scales, concolorous collar; labial palpi broad, barely extending beyond frons, ochreous speckled with darker scales. <italic>Thorax, abdomen, legs</italic> – Ochreous or pale tan as in wings with widely scattered small brown scales. <italic>Wings</italic> – FW outer margin arcuate at vein M3 and HW; DFW apex acute to falcate. Usually obscure narrow dark DFW submarginal band; small dark discal spots both wings. <bold>Males.</bold> Dorsal color varies from gray, medium ochreous to medium brown. DFW AML and PML variable from pronounced and dark to broken and indistinct; medial band concolorous with remainder of wing, or paler and yellowish; a dark triangular patch with blunted or acute apex, with or without pale oblong spot, located along costa distad of PML. DHW with dark narrow medial band varying individually from dark to indistinct. Ventrally paler with dorsal maculation repeated, usually with less intensity. <bold>Females</bold>. Dorsal color varies from yellow through pale ochreous to medium ochreous and gray. Crosslines usually indistinct. DFW triangular patch as in males, PML above inner margin expanded into two large oblong brown spots. Ventrally paler with dorsal maculation repeated, usually with less intensity. <italic>Male genitalia</italic> – Uncus stout, slightly decurved, tapering to a rounded tip; medial gnathos with a few small teeth; valva rounded at apex; anellus with small spines; aedeagus truncate with one large oblong cornutus near base of vesica. <italic>Female genitalia</italic> – Apophyses long, slender; posterior apophyses ca. 1.8 × anterior apophyses; colliculum absent; ductus bursae ridged, short, partially sclerotized at posterior end; corpus <!--PageBreak-->bursae without signum, oblong with membranous anterior sac; ductus seminalis originates at top of ductus bursae.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                    <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                        <p> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">McDunnough (1938)</xref> treated <tp:taxon-name>Epione depontanata</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Heterolocha sulphurata</tp:taxon-name> Packard, 1876 as synonyms of <tp:taxon-name>Hyperythra arcasaria</tp:taxon-name> Walker, 1860. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Forbes (1948: 108)</xref> placed <tp:taxon-name>Hyperythra arcasaria</tp:taxon-name> as a synonym of <tp:taxon-name>Heterolocha thisoaria</tp:taxon-name> (Guenée, 1858), which he then placed as <tp:taxon-name>Sabulodes thisoaria</tp:taxon-name>, and lumped several genera, including <tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name>, under <tp:taxon-name>Sabulodes</tp:taxon-name> Guenée (1858). Subsequent authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Ferguson 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Covell 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">McGuffin 1987</xref>) restored <tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name> as a separate genus. Ferguson recognized the species: <italic>comstocki</italic> Sperry; <italic>hewesata</italic> Sperry; <italic>imitata</italic>, H. Edwards.; <italic>indiscretata</italic>, (H. Edwards); <italic>ochreata</italic> (Hulst); <italic>thisoaria</italic> (Guenée); <italic>tiselaaria</italic> (Dyar). The geographic range of the genus includes eastern North America, the southwestern United States, portions of Mexico, Costa Rica and Guatemala.</p>
                    </tp:treatment-sec>
                </tp:taxon-treatment>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="Systematics"><title>Systematics</title>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Antepione</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">thisoaria</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Guenée, 1857 [1858])</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 1</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">11–19</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">59</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Antepione sulphurata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Packard 1876</xref>: 484</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Epione depontanata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Grote 1864</xref>: 90</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Eutrapela furciferata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Packard 1876</xref>: 559</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Gonopteryx rhomboidaria</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Oberthür 1912</xref>: 246, pl. 148, f. 1401</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Heterolocha sulphurata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Packard 1873</xref>: 79</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Heterolocha thisoaria</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Guenée 1857 [1858]</xref>: 106.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Hyperythra arcasaria</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Walker 1860</xref>: 131</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Mimogonodes constricta</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Warren 1895</xref>: 149</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Sabulodes thisoaria</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Forbes 1948</xref>: 108</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Tetracis azonax</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Druce 1892</xref>: 54, pl. 46, f. 8</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Tetracis rivulata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Warren 1897</xref>: 506</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                    <p> Female HT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), country of origin not stated [MNHN].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Fixation of type locality"><title>Fixation of type locality.</title>
                    <p> The Central American taxa were not recognized and described until 1892 (<italic>azonax</italic>) and 1912 (<italic>rhomboidaria</italic>). On this basis, I infer that specimens from this region were not available to Guenée in 1857 when he described <italic>thisoaria</italic>, and that the holotype was collected in eastern North America. In habitus, the HT matches exactly female specimens of the <italic>sulphuraria/sulphurata</italic> form. The HT was most probably collected in the Middle Atlantic region. I hereby fix the type locality as eastern North America. Based on my research, it appears that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Forbes (1948)</xref> was the first to use the name <italic>thisoaria</italic> in the North American fauna.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined"><title>Other material examined.</title>
                    <p> 84 specimens (a few by photograph) from Alabama, Indiana, Kentucky, Mexico, Michigan, New Jersey, New York, Nova Scotia, Pennsylvania, Quebec, Tennessee, Virginia. Additional distribution records were obtained<!--PageBreak--> from individuals and several museums, including 439 from the Carnegie Museum of Natural History, Pittsburgh, PA.</p>
                    <fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    	
                        <label>Figures 1–4.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name> species. <bold>1</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name> HT (dorsal and ventral) with pin labels (MNHN photo) <bold>2</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name> HT with pin labels (SEMC photo) <bold>3</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Antepione (Tetracis) indiscretata</tp:taxon-name> HT with pin labels (SEMC photo) <bold>4</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Antepione (Eugonobapta) constans</tp:taxon-name> HT, adult, pin labels (AMNH photo) and male genitalia. The balsam embedding medium has fogged with age producing the apparent lack of focus in the genitalia photo.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/621/supp/ZooKeys-071-049-g001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Antepione thisoaria is most easily separated from <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name> based on geography. It does not occur west of the 95th parallel, while <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name> extends eastward<!--PageBreak--> only to west Texas, and is not recorded from Central America. In the male genitalia, the apical region of the valva lacks spines, which are present in the valva of <italic>imitata</italic>. In the female genitalia, the corpus bursae is initially swollen while not so in <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <bold>Adults.</bold> As described above for the genus. <bold>Genitalia.</bold> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 17–19</xref>. Two dissections (male and female) by author; illustrations in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">McGuffin (1987, Figs 242g, 245e)</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Pitkin (2002, Figs 202, 460)</xref>.  Uncus stout, slightly decurved, tapering to a rounded tip; gnathos with unjoined slender arms, medial gnathos with a few small teeth; valva rounded at apex without spines<italic>Male genitalia</italic> –, produced ventral ridge forming two short projections; anellus with two sclerotized spinose lobes; aedeagus truncate with one large narrow elliptical cornutus near base of vesica. <italic>Female genitalia</italic> – Apophyses long, slender; posterior apophyses ca. 1.8 × anterior apophyses; ductus bursae ridged, moderately short, partially sclerotized at posterior; corpus bursae without signum, corpus bursae without signum, oblong and initially swollen with membranous anterior sac; ductus seminalis originates at top of ductus bursae.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology and distribution"><title>Biology and distribution</title>
                    <p> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 59</xref>)<bold>.</bold> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">McGuffin (1987: 88–89)</xref> described the early stages and cited three specific larval hosts: <tp:taxon-name>Alnus rugosa</tp:taxon-name> (Du Roi) Spreng; <tp:taxon-name>Physocarpus opulifolius</tp:taxon-name> (L.) Maxim; <tp:taxon-name>Prunus serotina</tp:taxon-name> Ehrh. Various additional larval hosts are reported in the literature in the families <tp:taxon-name>Aceraceae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Betulaceae</tp:taxon-name>, <tp:taxon-name>Ebenaceae</tp:taxon-name>, and <tp:taxon-name>Rosaceae</tp:taxon-name>. The last instar larva was illustrated by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Wagner et al. (2001, p. 155)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Wagner (2005, p. 195)</xref>. Adults fly April–May with an occasional mid-March and mid-June record, July–August with occasional September to mid-October records. There is one generation in Canada, and at least two southward. The distribution map (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 59</xref>) represents the data that I was able to locate. The heavy distribution in Pennsylvania reflects intensive collecting in that state by CMNH personnel and volunteers. Undoubtedly similar efforts in neighboring areas should produce additional records. The overall range of this species is: in <bold>CANADA</bold> from Nova Scotia to Manitoba; in the <bold>UNITED</bold> <bold>STATES</bold> (county records in parentheses) then south and west to the Gulf states to the 95th parallel, including <bold>Alabama</bold> (Bibb, DeKalb, Jackson, Madison, Monroe), <bold>Arkansas</bold> (Logan, Montgomery, Polk, Scott, Washington), <bold>Connecticut</bold> (Fairfield, Hartford, New Haven, New London, Tolland, Windham), <bold>Georgia</bold> (Cherokee, Rabun), <bold>Illinois</bold> (Cook, Macon), <bold>Indiana</bold> (Elkhart, Jackson, Jasper, Lagrange, Laporte, Monroe,  Newton, Perry, Pulaski, St. Joseph), <bold>Iowa</bold> (Johnson, Monroe), <bold>Kansas</bold> (Crawford), <bold>Kentucky</bold> (Bell, Boone, Bracken, Bulitt, Calloway, Carter, Fayette, Graves, Harlan, Jefferson, Madison, McCracken, Meade, Menifee, Metcalfe, Morgan, Muhlenberg, Oldham, Owsley, Powell, Rowan, Russell, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Covell 1999</xref>), <bold>Louisiana</bold> (Feliciana Parish), <bold>Maine</bold> (Aroostook, Franklin, Oxford, Penobscot, Piscataquis), <bold>Maryland</bold> (Allegheny, Anne Arundel, Baltimore, Cecil, Garrett, Harford, Howard, Washington, Worcester), <bold>Massachusetts</bold> (Berkshire, Dukes, Essex, Middlesex, Nantucket), <bold>Michigan</bold> (Berrien, Cass, Otsego), <bold>Minnesota</bold> (Houston), <bold>Mississippi</bold> (Franklin, George, Grenada, Harrison, Kemper, Lee, Marshall, Oktibbeha, Pike, Pontotoc, Tishomingo, Union, Warren, Webster, Winston), <bold>Missouri</bold> (Barry, Benton, Camden, Cape Girardeau, Carter, Greene, Jasper, Lafayette, Lewis, Madison, Morgan, Newton, Stoddard, Warren, Wayne), <bold>Nebraska</bold> (Cass), <bold>New Jersey</bold> (Burlington, Essex, Gloucester, Morris, Passaic,<!--PageBreak--> Sussex, Union, Warren), <bold>New Hampshire</bold> (Rockingham), <bold>New York</bold> (Albany, Kings, Queens, Nassau, Suffolk, Westchester), <bold>North Carolina</bold> (Allegheny, Ashe, Avery, Stokes, Swain, Transylvania), <bold>Ohio</bold> (Adams, Ashland, Ross, Wayne), <bold>Oklahoma</bold> (Cherokee, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Nelson 2010</xref>), <bold>Pennsylvania</bold> (Adams, Allegheny, Armstrong, Beaver, Bedford, Berks, Blair, Bucks, Butler, Centre, Chester, Clearfield, Crawford, Dauphin, Fulton, Greene, Huntingdon, Lawrence, Northumberland, Perry, Somerset, Washington, Westmoreland, York), <bold>Rhode Island</bold> (Washington), <bold>South Carolin</bold>a (Greenville), <bold>Tennessee</bold> (Louden, Wilson), <bold>Virginia</bold> (Augusta, Carroll, Giles), <bold>West Virginia</bold> (Cabell, Grant, Greenbrier, Hampshire, Mason, Monongalia, Monroe, Pendleton, Randolph, Roane, Wyoming); <bold>MEXICO</bold> (Michoacan state); <bold>CENTRAL AMERICA</bold> in Costa Rica and Guatemala <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">(Pitkin et al. 1996)</xref>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Covell (1984)</xref> stated the westward range of the species to Texas. I have been unable to confirm Texas from museum records. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Forbes (1948)</xref> stated: “. . . varieties in Colorado, Texas, and Arizona.” His “varieties” are assumed to be <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name>. Although the distribution map (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 59</xref>) suggests occurrence of <italic>thisoaria</italic> in Florida, Vermont and Wisconsin, no records were found.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p> The gray spring form of the moth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 11, 15</xref>) was described by Packard as the species <italic>furciferata</italic>. The male (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 14</xref>) represents the summer form <italic>arcasaria</italic>, and the female (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 16</xref>) represents the summer form <italic>sulphuraria</italic> = <italic>sulphurata</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Packard (1876)</xref> redescribed <tp:taxon-name>Heterolocha sulphuraria</tp:taxon-name> Packard, 1873 as <tp:taxon-name>Antepione sulphurata</tp:taxon-name>. Once barcoding data are available, the disjunct distributions of Mexican and Central American populations may ultimately prove to be separate species, in which case the name <italic>azonax</italic> Druce, 1892 (Costa Rica, Guatemala) is available and has date priority over <italic>rhomboidaria</italic> Oberthür, 1912 (Costa Rica) and <italic>rivulata</italic> Warren, 1897 (Costa Rica). The two female specimens in the CNC from Tuxpan, Michoacan, Mexico are exact matches for the <italic>sulphuraria</italic>/<italic>sulphurata</italic> phenotype and were collected in early August, 1959.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Antepione</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">imitata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Edwards, 1884</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 2</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">5</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">20–33</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">59</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Antepione comstocki</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Sperry 1939</xref>, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Antepione costinotata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Taylor 1905</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Eugonobapta constans</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Hulst 1898</xref>, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Metanema vanusaria</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">Strecker 1899</xref>: 6, syn. rev.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Tetracis indiscretata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Edwards 1884</xref>: 48, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                    <p> Female HT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>), New Mexico, [San Miguel Co.], Las Vegas, July, 1882. [SEMC].</p>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione comstocki</tp:taxon-name> male HT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 5</xref>), Arizona, [Pima Co.], Baboquivari Mts., 26 April, 1938 [CNC]. <tp:taxon-name>Tetracis indiscretata</tp:taxon-name> female HT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 3</xref>), New Mexico, [San Miguel Co.], Las Vegas, August, 1882 [SEMC]. <tp:taxon-name>Eugonobapta constans</tp:taxon-name> male HT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 4</xref>), Arizona, [Yavapai Co.], Prescott, August, 1896 [AMNH].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined"><title>Other material examined.</title>
                    <p> 145 specimens in [CDF] from Arizona, Colorado and New Mexico; additional material (some by photographs) from Arizona (including a reared series), Colorado, New Mexico, Texas, Mexico.</p>
                    <fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    	
                        <label>Figures 5–10.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name> species. <bold>5</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Antepione comstocki</tp:taxon-name> HT with pin labels (CNC photo) <bold>6–10</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Antepione tiselaaria</tp:taxon-name>. <bold>6</bold> HT with pin labels (USNM photo) <bold>7–8</bold> adult males <bold>9</bold> male genitalic capsule, aedeagus removed <bold>10</bold> aedeagus with vesica everted.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/621/supp/ZooKeys-071-049-g002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Antepione imitata is most easily separated from <tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name> based on geography. It does not occur east of west Texas and is not recorded from Central Ame<!--PageBreak-->rica, while <tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name> extends west only to the 95th parallel. In the male genitalia, the apical region of the valva exhibits 3 long robust spines and additional fine setae, which are not present in the valva of <italic>thisoaria</italic>. In the female genitalia, the corpus bursae is not initially swollen as in <tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <bold>Adults.</bold> As described above for the genus. <bold>Genitalia.</bold> <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">31–33</xref>. Dissections 8m, 2f comprising full range of phenotypes). <italic>Male genitalia</italic> – Uncus stout, slightly decurved, tapering to a rounded tip; gnathos with unjoined slender arms, medial gnathos with a few small teeth; valva rounded at apex with 3 long robust spines and additional fine setae, produced ventral ridge forming two short projections; anellus with two sclerotized spinose lobes; aedeagus truncate with one large oblong cornutus near base of vesica. <italic>Female genitalia</italic> – Apophyses long, slender; posterior apophyses ca. 1.8 × anterior apophyses; ductus bursae ridged, short, partially sclerotized at posterior; corpus bursae without signum, long and cylindrical with membranous anterior sac; ductus seminalis originates at top of ductus bursae.</p>
										
                    <fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
											
                        <label>Figures 11–19.</label>
        						    
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name>. <bold>11–14</bold> adult males <bold>15–16</bold> adult females <bold>17</bold> male genitalic capsule, aedeagus removed <bold>18</bold> aedeagus with vesica everted <bold>19</bold> female genitalia.</p></caption>
        						    
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/621/supp/ZooKeys-071-049-g003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
        						
                    </fig>
										
                    <fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
											
                        <label>Figures 20–30.</label>
        						    
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name> adults. <bold>20–25</bold> males <bold>26–30</bold> females.</p></caption>
        						    
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/621/supp/ZooKeys-071-049-g004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
        						
                    </fig>
 										
                    <fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 											
                        <label>Figures 31–33.</label>
        						    
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name> genitalia. <bold>31</bold> male genitalic capsule, aedeagus removed <bold>32</bold> aedeagus with vesica everted <bold>33</bold> female genitalia.</p></caption>
        						    
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/621/supp/ZooKeys-071-049-g005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
        						
                    </fig>
                    <p><bold>Remarks.</bold> One male specimen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 25</xref>) of the <italic>comstocki</italic> phenotype examined from Las Animas Co., Colorado lacks the characteristic DFW costal triangular patch, causing it to resemble superficially the <italic>ligata</italic> form of <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta ochreata</tp:taxon-name>. The male genitalia, however, are typical of <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology and distribution"><title>Biology and distribution</title>
                    <p> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 59</xref>)<bold>.</bold> Noel McFarland (Hereford, AZ) reared the species on <tp:taxon-name>Ribes aureum</tp:taxon-name> Push. from ova from an adult female of the nearly uniformly brownish-ochreous April–May generation; adults emerged June–July. The resulting adults are of the form with yellow females and males in which the DFW medial band has a yellow flush. Based on my field studies over many years in southeastern Arizona and southwestern New Mexico and McFarland’s reared material, there appear to be three generations in southeastern Arizona and Southwestern New Mexico. There is a strong early flight starting in April and early May, with a weaker flight in late June into July, and another strong flight beginning in mid-August after the monsoonal rains with a few individuals into early October. This species ranges from west <bold>Texas</bold> (Brewster, Culberson, Jeff Davis), <bold>Colorado</bold> (Delta, La Plata, Las Animas), <bold>New Mexico</bold> (Grant, Harding, Hidalgo, San Miguel), to southern <bold>Arizona</bold> (Cochise, Gila, Pima, Santa Cruz). A typical male specimen was examined [CMNH] with the collection data: <bold>Mexico:</bold> Coahuila, Sierra La Madera, upper Canada Desiderio, 15–17 March 1985, 27–08N, 102–31W, 1810m, J. Rawlins, S. Thompson. This locality is essentially due south of the western Texas records, and one might anticipate that with further collecting <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name> will prove to be widespread in northern Mexico. It is generally associated with riparian canyons up to 6000’ (1830m).</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion.</title>
                    <p> As is also the case with <tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name>, most spring individuals of <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name> are rather drab in appearance with lightly maculated brownish males (the <italic>comstocki</italic> phenotype) and pale creamy colored or ochreous females. The strongly maculated males and yellow females appear in the later generations in company with the rather drab early-season phenotypes. In his original descriptions of <italic>imitata</italic> and <italic>indiscretata</italic>, Edwards provided no insight as to why he assigned <italic>imitata</italic> <!--PageBreak-->to <tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name> and <italic>indiscretata</italic> to <tp:taxon-name>Tetracis</tp:taxon-name>. Both taxa are described on the same page with the description of <italic>imitata</italic> preceding that of <italic>indiscretata</italic>. He characterized the color of <italic>imitata</italic> as similar to the yellow <italic>sulphurata</italic> phenotype of <italic>thisoaria</italic>, and <italic>indiscretata</italic> as “Ochraceus drab.” Over the years the type specimens have faded to some extent so that they now appear nearly identical in color, the only difference being the extent of the dark maculation. The name <italic>constans</italic> appears to have been applied to the heavily maculated male phenotype, as best can be determined from the poor condition of the HT.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Antepione</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">tiselaaria</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>(Dyar, 1912)</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 6–10</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Paragonia tiselaaria</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Dyar 1912</xref></comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                    <p> Male HT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 6</xref>), Mexico, Minerale de Zacualpan, January, 1911 [USNM]. Comment: <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Dyar (1912: 87)</xref> stated the type locality only as “Zacualpan” and not “Minerale de Zacualpan” as shown on the specimen label. I interpret the label to mean the Zacualpan mining region located in the state of Morelos south of Mexico City, today still an active silver mining district.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined"><title>Other material examined</title>
                    <p>(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 7–10</xref>). MEXICO. Puebla, 2 mi. SW Tehuacan, 5300’, 4.x.1975, Powell (1m, dissected); same, 5.x.1975, J. Powell (1m) [EME].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Females not known to the author. Mexican specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Antepione tiselaaria</tp:taxon-name> males are most easily separated from <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name> based on geography, since the latter species does not penetrate south to central Mexico. In Costa Rica, where <tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name> is also reported, <tp:taxon-name>Antepione tiselaaria</tp:taxon-name> manifests a more orange-brown overall color than the drab ochreous-gray form of <italic>thisoaria</italic>. In the male genitalia, the apical region of the valva is covered with multiple short slender translucent spines over most of the surface except toward the base; spines are absent in the valva of <tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name>, and 3 long robust spines occur in <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <bold>Adults.</bold> Only males were available for examination. As described above for the genus, other than the wings. FWL 17–18 mm. <italic>Wings</italic> – FW outer margin arcuate (roundly produced about) vein M3 and HW; DFW apex sightly acute, not falcate. Dorsal color pale orange-brown-ochreous with darker maculation. AML a narrow band centrally with a few paler scales, PML an interrupted band with irregular edges and centrally paler, widening substantially approaching inner margin; MB not clearly defined with splotchy brown maculation over paler ground color; a dark triangular patch with blunted or acute apex, with or without pale oblong spot, located along costa distad of PML; small dark discal spots FW and HW. Ventrally paler with dorsal maculation repeated with slightly less intensity. <bold>Male genitalia</bold>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs 9–10</xref>. Dissection 1m. Uncus stout, slightly decurved, tapering to a rounded tip; gnathos with unjoined<!--PageBreak--> slender arms, medial gnathos with a few very small dark teeth; valva rounded at apex with multiple short slender translucent spines over most of the surface excepting toward the base, produced ventral ridge forming one large and one short projection; anellus with two sclerotized spinose lobes; aedeagus truncate with one large (equal to diameter of aedeagus shaft) oblong triangular cornutus near base of vesica; fully everted vesica initially spherical becoming a tapered tube.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology and distribution"><title>Biology and distribution.</title>
                    <p> Early stages unknown. Current distribution records are for the Mexican states of Morelos and Puebla, and Costa Rica.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Pionenta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    <object-id xlink:type="simple">urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:95BF80CA-F55F-40D9-B877-A25252635770</object-id>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Ferris</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <tp:taxon-status>gen. n.</tp:taxon-status>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type species"><title>Type species:</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Antepione ochreata</tp:taxon-name> Hulst, 1898.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Etymology"><title>Etymology.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta</tp:taxon-name> is a masculine anagram of <tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p>Pionenta ochreata lacks the DFW triangular costal patch found in all species of <tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name>. The well-developed DFW AML and PML form a wedge-shaped<!--PageBreak--> medial band absent in <tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name>. The robust centered furca in the male genitalia and large stellate signum in the female genitalia of <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta</tp:taxon-name> are absent in <tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> <bold>Adults.</bold> Sexually dimorphic and both sexes are polyphenic; FWL 14–19 mm. Antenna simple. <italic>Head</italic> – Uniformly ochreous, collar concolorous; labial palpi relatively narrow, slightly upcurved, ochreous, barely extending beyond frons. <italic>Thorax, abdomen, legs</italic> – Uniformly colored as in ground color of wings with a few widely scattered small brown scales on legs. <italic>Wings –</italic> Outer margin arcuate FW (about M3) and HW; DFW apex normally sightly falcate. Wing color variable from pale creamy white to ochreous tan. AML and PML narrow and brown (occasionally reddish-brown), PML continues on DHW as medial line; AML with narrow pale shading basad, PML with narrow pale shading distad. MB trapezoidal tapering inward from costa to inner margin. Small dark discal spots present FW and HW. Scattered dark patches may be present basally and submarginally on DFW, and submarginally on DWH. Ventrally paler with dorsal maculation only weakly repeated. <italic>Male genitalia</italic> (7 dissections by author, additional museum slides examined) – Uncus stout, slightly decurved, tapering at apex to a rounded tip; gnathos v-shaped with well-sclerotized edges, medially a sharp upcurved tip with numerous very small teeth; valva rounded at apex, but with blunt triangular projection at end of sclerotized costa; anellus membranous without spines or setae, with central robust cylindrical furca covered by numerous short spines on rounded apex; aedeagus truncate with two long sclerotized pointed extensions from apical margin and a variable patch of apparently deciduous dark setae near base of otherwise membranous short cylindrical vesica. <italic>Female genitalia</italic> (6 dissections) – Posterior apophyses short, anterior apophyses much reduced ca. 0.4 × posterior apophyses; sterigma well sclerotized; posterior margin of lamella antevaginalis rounded at ends with central depression; well-defined colliculum; partially ridged short ductus bursae opens into ovoid membranous corpus bursae; one large centrally located oval stellate signum; ductus seminalis originates immediately below colliculum.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
                <tp:nomenclature>
                    <tp:taxon-name>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="genus">Pionenta</tp:taxon-name-part>
                        <tp:taxon-name-part taxon-name-part-type="species">ochreata</tp:taxon-name-part>
                    </tp:taxon-name>
                    <tp:taxon-authority>Hulst, 1898</tp:taxon-authority>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 34–58</xref>
                    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">60</xref>
                    <tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                        <tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Antepione hewesata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Sperry 1948</xref>, syn. n.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Sabulodes arizonata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Taylor 1905</xref>, syn. rev.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Sabulodes dyari</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Grossbeck 1908</xref>, syn. rev.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
												<tp:nomenclature-citation><tp:taxon-name>Sabulodes ligata</tp:taxon-name><comment> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">Grossbeck 1908</xref>, syn. rev.</comment></tp:nomenclature-citation>
                    </tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
                </tp:nomenclature>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type material"><title>Type material.</title>
                    <p> Male HT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 34</xref>), Arizona, Senator [probably Senator Mine, Yavapai Co.] [AMNH].</p>
                    <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione hewesata</tp:taxon-name> female HT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 35</xref>), Arizona [Coconino Co.], Oak Creek Canyon, Todd’s Lodge, [AMNH]. <tp:taxon-name>Sabulodes arizonata</tp:taxon-name> male HT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 38</xref>), Arizona [Cochise Co.], Huachuca Mts. [USNM]. <tp:taxon-name>Sabulodes dyari</tp:taxon-name> male HT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 39</xref>), Arizona <!--PageBreak-->[Cochise Co.], Huachuca Mts. [USNM]. <tp:taxon-name>Sabulodes ligata</tp:taxon-name> male HT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 36–37</xref>), Arizona [Cochise Co.], Huachuca Mts. [USNM].</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Other material examined"><title>Other material examined.</title>
                    <p> 135 specimens in [CDF] from Arizona and New Mexico; 61 additional specimens (some by photographs) from Arizona.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Diagnosis"><title>Diagnosis.</title>
                    <p> As for genus.<!--PageBreak--></p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Description"><title>Description.</title>
                    <p> General description as for genus.</p>
                    <fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    	
                        <label>Figures 34–39.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Pionenta ochreata</tp:taxon-name>. <bold>34</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta ochreata</tp:taxon-name> HT with pin labels (AMNH photo) <bold>35</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta (Antepione) hewesata</tp:taxon-name> HT with pin labels (AMNH photo) <bold>36–37</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta (Sabulodes) ligata</tp:taxon-name> <bold>36</bold> HT with pin labels <bold>37</bold> genitalia <bold>38</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta (Sabulodes) arizonata</tp:taxon-name> HT with pin labels <bold>39</bold> <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta (Sabulodes) dyari</tp:taxon-name> HT with pin labels. (36–39 USNM photos).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/621/supp/ZooKeys-071-049-g006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    	
                        <label>Figures 40–53.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Pionenta ochreata</tp:taxon-name> adults. <bold>40–48</bold> males <bold>49–53</bold> females.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/621/supp/ZooKeys-071-049-g007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    	
                        <label>Figures 54–58.</label>
                        <caption><p><tp:taxon-name>Pionenta ochreata</tp:taxon-name> genitalia. <bold>54–57</bold> male genitalic capsules, adeagii removed and adeagii with vesicas everted (arrows point to deciduous setae) <bold>58</bold> female genitalia.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/621/supp/ZooKeys-071-049-g008.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Remarks"><title>Remarks.</title>
                    <p> <tp:taxon-name>Antepione ochreata</tp:taxon-name> has two distinct phenotypes. The male form with pale ochreous wing color and varying numbers of multiple dark patches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 34</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">40–43</xref>) was described as <italic>ochreata</italic>. The female described as <italic>hewesata</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 35</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">44</xref>) is intermediate between typical <italic>ochreata</italic> and the brownish-tan phenotype without dark patches described as <!--PageBreak--><italic>ligata</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 36</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">46, 50–53</xref>) which is the usual female form based on my field experience and examination of museum material. Regarding the taxa <italic>arizonata</italic> and <italic>dyari</italic>, apparently some years ago an accident occurred with a drawer containing type specimens and they were badly damaged. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs 38</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">39</xref> illustrate what remains of these two specimens. Their associated genitalia slides were not damaged and the preparations agree with Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">54–57</xref>.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Biology and distribution"><title>Biology and distribution</title>
                    <p> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 60</xref>). Early stages unknown. Adults from mid-May to August in riparian canyons and dry coniferous forest to 8400’ (2560m); probably more than one generation. Collection records include <bold>Arizona</bold> (Cochise, Coconino, Pima, Santa. Cruz, Yavapai), <bold>New Mexico</bold> (Grant).</p>
                    <fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    	
                        <label>Figure 59.</label>
                        <caption><p>Partial distribution map for <tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name>.</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/621/supp/ZooKeys-071-049-g009.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                    <fig id="F10" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                    	
                        <label>Figure 60.</label>
                        <caption><p>Distribution map for <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta ochreata</tp:taxon-name> (counties only).</p></caption>
                        <graphic xlink:href="http://pensoftonline.net/zookeys-files/journals/1/articles/621/supp/ZooKeys-071-049-g010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple"/>
                    </fig>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
                <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Discussion"><title>Discussion.</title>
                    <p>Based on the male and female genitalia, <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta</tp:taxon-name> is closely related to <tp:taxon-name>Tetracis</tp:taxon-name>. The male genitalia of both genera possess a well defined central furca. The female genitalia of both genera possess a well defined colliculum and prominent single signum. The gnathos in <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta</tp:taxon-name> does not have a quadrate dorso-caudal margin with two to four (occasionally five) widely separated, dorsally projecting teeth as found in <tp:taxon-name>Tetracis</tp:taxon-name> (Ferris &amp; Schmidt, 2010). Once barcoding of the North America geometrid genera has been completed, the relationship of <tp:taxon-name>Pionenta</tp:taxon-name> can be established.</p>
                </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <title>Acknowledgments</title>
            <p>Special thanks to my friends for permitting me to camp and run light traps on their properties: in Cochise Co., Arizona, Karen Coreg, Noel and Dienie McFarland, Todd Hoyer and Hayley Smith, Ralph and Rosemary Snapp, Gwen B. Wright; Nate Gibson in Patagonia, Arizona; the Coles in Grant Co., NM. Photographs, locality data, and loan material were kindly provided by: James Adams, Calhoun, GA; Susan Borkin, Milwaukee, WI; Jerome Barbut (MNHN), Paris, France; Richard L. Brown, Mississippi State, MS; Charles V. Covell, Jr., Gainesville, FL; Diane M. Debinski, Ames, IA; Michael S. Engle and Jennifer C. Thomas, (SEMC), Lawrence, KS; Irving Finkelstein, Atlanta, GA; Patricia Gentili-Poole, (USNM), Washington, DC; Suzanne Rab Green (AMNH), New York, NY; Howard Grisham, Huntsville, AL; John Gruber, Wynnewood, PA; Ed Knudson, Houston, TX; Timothy McCabe, Albany, NY: Hugh McGuiness, East Hampton, NY; J.S. Nordin, Laramie, WY; Paul Opler, Ft. Collins, CO; Bob Patterson, Bowie, MD; Jerry Powell (EME), Berkeley, CA; John E. Rawlins and Vanessa Verdecia (CMNH), Pittsburgh, PA; J. A. Snyder, Greenville, SC; J. B. Sullivan, Beaufort, NC; Jim Vargo, Mishawaka, IN; David Wagner, Storrs, CT; J. B. Walsh. Tucson, AZ; Jocelyn Gill, Don Lafontaine, Chris Schmidt, (CNC), Ottawa, Ontario, Canada. Two anonymous reviewers provided useful suggestions.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="B1"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Covell CV</surname><given-names>Jr</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <source>A field guide to the moths of eastern North America</source>. <publisher-name>Houghton Mifflin Co.</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>, <lpage>496</lpage> pp.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B2"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Covell CV</surname><given-names>Jr</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The butterflies and moths (Lepidoptera) of Kentucky: an annotated checklist</article-title>. <source>Kentucky State Nature Preserves Commission Scientific and Technical Series</source> <volume>6</volume>, <lpage>220</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B3"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Druce</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1892–1900</year>) <source>Biologia Centrali-Americana. Lepidoptera – Heterocera</source>. <volume>2</volume>, <lpage>622</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B4"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dyar</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of new species and genera of Lepidoptera, chiefly from Mexico.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the United States National Museum</source> <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B5"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>)<article-title>Geometridae</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dominick</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franclemont</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munroe</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Check List of the Lepidoptera of America North of Mexico</source>, <fpage>88</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B6"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>WTM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1948</year>) <article-title>Lepidoptera of New York and neighboring states. 2</article-title>. <source>Memoirs of the Cornell Agricultural Experiment Station</source> <volume>274</volume>, <lpage>263</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B7"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1884</year>) <source>Descriptions of new species of N. Am. Heterocera Papilio</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>–19, <lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B8"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>)<article-title> Revision of the North American Genera <italic>Tetracis</italic> Guenée and Synonymization of <italic>Synaxis</italic> Hulst with Descriptions of Three New Species (Lepidoptera: Geometridae: Ennominae).</article-title> <source>Zootaxa</source> <volume>2347</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B9"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grote</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1864</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of North American Lepidoptera. No. 3.</article-title> <source>Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Philadelphia</source> <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B10"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grossbeck</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1908</year>)<article-title> Additions to the list of North American Geometridae with notes on some described species.</article-title> <source>Journal of the Entomological Society of Washington</source> <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B11"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Guenée</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1857 [1858]</year>) <article-title> Vol. 9, Uranides et Phalénites 1</article-title>. In: <person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Boisduval</surname><given-names>JBAD de</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guenée</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<role>Eds</role>) <source>Histoire Naturelle des Insectes. Species Général des Lépidoptères</source>, <publisher-name>Roret</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>, <lpage>551</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B12"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dominick</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franclemont</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munroe</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <source>Check List of the Lepidoptera of America North of Mexico</source>. <publisher-name>E. W. Classey Ltd, London and The Wedge Entomological Research Foundation</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc>, xxiv + <lpage>284</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B13"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulst</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1898</year>)<article-title> Descriptions of new genera and species of the geometrina of North America.</article-title> <source>Transactions of the American Entomological Society</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>214</fpage>-<lpage>219</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B14"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McDunnough</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1938</year>) <article-title>Check list of the Lepidoptera of Canada and the United States of America. Part 1, Macrolepidoptera</article-title>. <source>Memoirs of the Southern California Academy of Sciences</source>, vol. <volume>1</volume>, <lpage>272</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B15"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>McGuffin</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Guide to the Geometridae of Canada (Lepidoptera) II. Subfamily Ennominae 4</article-title>. <source>Memoirs of the Entomological Society of Canada</source>, No. <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>182</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B16"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Oklahoma Moth Species by County</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biosurvey,ou.edu/ok_butterfly.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.biosurvey,ou.edu/ok_butterfly.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B17"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberthür</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1912</year>) <article-title>Révision des Phalénites décrites par Guenée dans le Species général des Lépidoptères (Tome IX) – Famille II</article-title>. <source>Ennomidae, Guenée. Études de Lépidoptérologie comparée</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–307, 346–<lpage>355</lpage>, pls. 144–160.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B18"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Packard</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1873</year>) <article-title>Descriptions of new American Phalaenidae</article-title>. <source>5th Annual Report of the Trustees of the Peabody Academy of Science</source>, <fpage>52</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B19"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Packard</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1876</year>)<article-title>A monograph of the geometrid moths or Phalaenidae of the United States</article-title>. <source>Report of the United States Geological Survey of the Territories</source> <volume>10</volume>, <lpage>607</lpage> pp, iv, 13 plates.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <!--PageBreak-->
            <ref id="B20"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scoble</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Honey</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitkin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitkin</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>)<source> The Catalogue. In: MJ Scoble (Ed) Geometrid Moths of the World: a Catalogue (Lepidoptera, Geometridae). CSIRO Publishing, Collingwood. 2 vol. 1,016 pp.</source> <publisher-name>+ 129 pp. +</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>12</publisher-loc> <lpage>9</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B21"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitkin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>)<article-title> Neotropical ennomine moths: a review of the genera (Lepidoptera: Geometridae).</article-title> <source>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</source> <volume>135</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>-<lpage>401</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B22"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitkin,</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mora</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scoble</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>)<article-title> A checklist to the Ennominae (Geometridae) of Costa Rica: taxonomy for a national biodiversity inventory.</article-title> <source>Gayana Zoologia</source> <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>-<lpage>155</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B23"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sperry</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1939</year>)<article-title> Two apparently new geometrids from the Southwest.</article-title> <source>Canadian Entomologist</source> <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>262</fpage>-<lpage>263</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B24"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sperry</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1948</year>)<article-title> Southwestern geometrid notes and new species II.</article-title> <source>Bulletin of the Brooklyn Entomological Society</source> <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>88</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B25"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Strecker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1899</year>)<source> Lepidoptera, Rhopaloceres and Heteroceres, indigenous and exotic. Lep., Rhopal. and Het., Suppl.</source> <publisher-name>2:</publisher-name> <publisher-loc>1</publisher-loc> <lpage>1</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B26"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1905</year>)<article-title> Some new Geometridae from Arizona.</article-title> <source>Journal of the New York Entomological Society</source> <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>130</fpage>-<lpage>131</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B27"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Caterpillars of eastern North America</source>. <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>, <lpage>512</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B28"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reardon,</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Geometrid caterpillars of northeastern and Appalachian forests</source>. <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, publication FHTET-2001–10</publisher-name>, <lpage>237</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B29"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1860</year>) <source>List of the Specimens of Lepidopterous Insects in the Collection of the British Museum</source> <volume>20</volume>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>, <lpage>276</lpage> pp.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B30"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1894</year>)<article-title> New genera and species of Geometridae.</article-title> <source>Novitates Zoologicae</source> <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>366</fpage>-<lpage>466</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B31"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1895</year>)<article-title> New genera and species of Geometridae.</article-title> <source>Novitates Zoologicae</source> <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>-<lpage>159</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref>
            <ref id="B32"><mixed-citation xlink:type="simple"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1897</year>)<article-title> New genera and species of Geometridae.</article-title> <source>Novitates Zoologicae</source> <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>408</fpage>-<lpage>507</lpage>.<!--PageBreak--></mixed-citation></ref>
        </ref-list>
        <sec sec-type="Appendix: Annotated checklist of the taxa assigned to Antepione and Pionenta"><title>Appendix: Annotated checklist of the taxa assigned to Antepione and Pionenta</title>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione</tp:taxon-name> Packard, 1876</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione imitata</tp:taxon-name> H. Edwards, 1884, New Mexico, Las Vegas [HT female, SEMC]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione comstocki</tp:taxon-name> Sperry, 1939, <bold>syn. n.</bold>, Arizona, Baboquivari Mts. [HT male, CNC]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione constans</tp:taxon-name> (Hulst, 1898), <bold>syn. n.</bold>, Arizona, Prescott [HT male, AMNH]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione costinotata</tp:taxon-name> Taylor, 1906, Colorado, Durango [HT female, USNM] Note 1</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione indiscretata</tp:taxon-name> (H. Edwards), 1884, <bold>syn. n.</bold>, New Mexico, Las Vegas [HT female, SEMC]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione vanusaria</tp:taxon-name> (Strecker, 1899), <bold>syn. rev.</bold>, New Mexico [HT male, FMNH]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione thisoaria</tp:taxon-name> Guenée, 1857 [1858], fixed herein as eastern North America [HT female, MNHN]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione arcasaria</tp:taxon-name> (Walker, 1860), [HT female, BMNH]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione azonax</tp:taxon-name> (Druce, 1892) Guatemala, San Geronimo; Costa Rica, Volcan de Irazu [ST female, BMNH] Note 2</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione constricta</tp:taxon-name> (Warren, 1895), ? South America [HT male, BMNH] Note 2</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione depontanata</tp:taxon-name> (Grote, 1864), Maryland [HT male] Note 3</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione fuciferata</tp:taxon-name> (Packard, 1876), New York [HT male, MCZ]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione rhomboidaria</tp:taxon-name> (Oberthür, 1912), Costa Rica, San Jose [STs, BMNH] Note 2</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione rivulata</tp:taxon-name> (Warren, 1897), Costa Rica [HT female, BMNH] Note 2</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione sulphuraria</tp:taxon-name> (Packard, 1873), New York, West Farms; Middle States [HT female, MCZ]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione sulphurata</tp:taxon-name> (Packard, 1876) Note 4</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Antepione tiselaaria</tp:taxon-name> (Dyar. 1912), Mexico, Minerale de Zacualpan [HT male, USNM]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Pionenta</tp:taxon-name> Ferris, 2010, <bold>gen. n.</bold></p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Pionenta ochreata</tp:taxon-name> (Hulst, 1898), <bold>comb. n.</bold>, Arizona, Senator [HT male, AMNH]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Pionenta arizonata</tp:taxon-name> (Taylor, 1905), <bold>syn. rev.</bold>, Arizona, Cochise Co., Huachuca Mts. [HT male, USNM]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Pionenta dyari</tp:taxon-name> (Grossbeck, 1908), <bold>syn. rev.</bold>, Arizona, Huachuca Mts. [HT male, USNM]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Pionenta hewesata</tp:taxon-name> (Sperry, 1948), <bold>syn. n.</bold>, Arizona, Oak Creek Canyon, Todd’s Lodge [HT female, AMNH]</p>
            <p><tp:taxon-name>Pionenta ligata</tp:taxon-name> (Grossbeck, 1908), <bold>syn. rev.</bold>, Arizona, Huachuca Mts. [HT male, USNM]</p>
            <sec sec-type="Notes"><title>Notes:</title>
                <p>1.	Taylor stated in his original description that the HT was type number 9800 in the USNM. A recent attempt to locate the type failed, and it is presumed misplaced or lost. The TL was incorrectly stated as Prescott, Arizona in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Parsons et al. (1999)</xref>.</p>
                <p><!--PageBreak-->2.	Barcoding of these taxa may ultimately indicate species distinct from <italic>thisoaria</italic>.</p>
                <p>3.	The type was originally placed in the collection of the Entomological Society of Philadelphia and subsequently in ANSP. In the 1960s, the bulk of the ANSP <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name> collection went to CMNH. The type cannot be located in either ANSP or CMNH and is presumed lost.</p>
                <p>4.	<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Packard (1876)</xref> redescribed <tp:taxon-name>Heterolocha sulphuraria</tp:taxon-name> Packard, 1873 as <tp:taxon-name>Antepione sulphurata</tp:taxon-name>.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
    </back>
</article>